<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Beth Mardutho Ten-Year Anniversary Fund Raising</title>
            <author>
               <name/>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>January 2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.org/Vol6No1</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author/>
                  <title level="a">Beth Mardutho Ten-Year Anniversary Fund Raising</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-26-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P1"/>[1] Beth
    Mardutho is holding a fund raising raffle to celebrate its
    10-year anniversary. The proceeds will go towards the Beth
    Mardutho Endowment, and various projects. While all those who
    work for the Institute do so on voluntary basis, the Institute
    incurs many expenses.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P2"/>[2] The fund
    raising takes the form of a cash-prize Raffle: 35% of what we
    raise will be distributed as prizes. The first prize is 20% of
    the proceeds, the second prize is 10%, and the third prize is
    5%. For example, if we raise $10,000, the first prize will be
    $2,000, the second $1,000 and the third $500. Tickets can be
    purchased on <ref target="http://www.bethmardutho.org">www.bethmardutho.org</ref>.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P3"/>[3]
    “Although the uncertain economy makes it difficult
    for all of us to make new financial commitments just now,”
    said Prof. Kathleen McVey, treasurer of Beth Mardutho, “the
    same circumstance makes it vital for each of us to support the
    organizations we value. Every contribution to Beth Mardutho,
    however small, will help to promote ecumenical study of
    the Syriac heritage.”</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P4"/>[4] Our
    major accomplishments during the last 10 years include
    publishing <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> twice a
    year (since 1998), adding Syriac to the Unicode standard, the
    design of over 20 Meltho Fonts for Windows XP, digitizing over
    600 Beth Gazo melodies, and holding three international SyrCOM
    conferences on Syriac computing.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P5"/>[5]
    Currently, we are working hard to bring you <hi rend="bold">The Syriac
    Digital Library</hi> which will be the largest library of Syriac
    material in the world, accessible on the Internet. We are also
    busy producing the first encyclopedia that is totally dedicated
    to the Syriac heritage. All these activities require your
    support.<lb/>
    . <!-- #EndEditable --></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
