<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of: <hi rend="italic">Two Early Lives of Severos, Patriarch of Antioch</hi>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Pauline</forename>
                        <surname>Allen</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Australian Catholic University and University of Pretoria</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">Abigail Pearson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2014</date>
                <idno>Volume 17.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/h1n2bookreviews</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Pauline Allen</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: <hi rend="italic">Two Early Lives of Severos, Patriarch of Antioch</hi>. Translated Texts for Historians 59</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol17/h17n2prallen.pdf</idno>
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/####</idno><!-- Don't worry about this for now -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2014</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="372" to="373">372&#8211;373</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="12"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p><!-- ILeave this as is -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTranscription">
            <change when="2018-06-18">?File created by Abigail Pearson</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Sebastian Brock and Brian Fitzgerald, eds. and trans., <hi rend="italic">Two Early Lives of Severos, Patriarch of Antioch</hi>. Translated Texts for Historians 59 (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2013). Pp. 224; £16.99.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="372"/>The 1500th anniversary of the consecration of <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Severus-of-Antioch">Severos</ref> as patriarch of Antioch in 2012 has inspired a number of panels, conferences, and articles. 
					Now, in the book under review, we have translations of two of Severos’ earliest biographies, one by the patriarch’s friend Zacharias (variously called 
					‘scholastikos’, ‘rhetor’, or ‘bishop’) and another anonymous account traditionally attributed to John of Beth Aphtonia. The Syriac texts of both these works 
					were edited with a French translation in Patrologia Orientalis, vol. 2, by the Belgian scholar Marc-Antoine Kugener at the beginning of the twentieth century.
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is the great merit of the two twenty-first century translators, Brock and Fitzgerald, to have rendered these biographies into readable English 
					with helpful notes and other scholarly aids. A concise introduction, comprising an outline of Severos’ life, the main theological issues of his day, a list of 
					biographical materials for his life, and a consideration and analysis of each work, will introduce the unfamiliar reader to the life and times of the 
					patriarch, and satisfy initiates who have long been in need of a close analysis of the two biographies. Especially important is the comparison of Zacharias’ 
					work, designated by the translators as apology or polemic, with that of the anonymous biographer, who instead followed the rubrics of the hagiographical 
					genre. This comparison allows the reader to see beyond doubt that the purpose of Zacharias’ ‘biography’, which deals with Severos’ life before his 
					patriarchate, was to exonerate the bishop from accusations of having pagan parentage. The anonymous hagiography, on the other hand, covers the patriarch’s 
					entire life, and the reader will be grateful for the discussion of the history of the authorship of this text and the reasons behind its attribution to John 
					of Beth Aphtonia.
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The book contains two maps, of Palestine and Syria, and Anatolia, a chronological table, glossary, an appendix of the bishops of the five main 
					sees from the mid-fifth to the mid-sixth centuries, and another appendix on Severos’ <hi rend="italic">Cathedral Homilies</hi>. There is also an <pb n="373"/>index of 
					names, a select index of Greek words, and a biblical index.
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">This volume is a compendious, user-friendly, scholarly tool which will be much appreciated by those engaged in <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syriac-Language">Syriac</ref> studies, history, theology, 
					hagiography, and the post-Chalcedonian period, and it will be a welcome addition to the Liverpool series. These two early biographies of the pivotal 
					late-antique patriarch Severos are indeed essential translated texts for historians (and others).
				</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>