<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of:<hi rend="italic">Lexique des termes de la pharmacopée syriaque</hi>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Siam</forename>
                        <surname>Bhayro</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Exeter</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">Abigail Pearson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2014</date>
                <idno>Volume 17.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/h17n2bookreviews</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Siam Bhayro</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: <hi rend="italic">Lexique des termes de la pharmacopée syriaque</hi>, Studia Iranica 47 </title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol17/h17n2prbhayro.pdf</idno>
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/####</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2014</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="367" to="368">367-368</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="10"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p><!-- ILeave this as is -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTranscription">
            <change when="2018-06-18">?File created by Abigail Pearson</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Philippe Gignoux, <hi rend="italic">Lexique des termes de la pharmacopée syriaque</hi>, Studia Iranica 47 (Paris: Association pour l’avancement des études iraniennes, 2011). Pp. 103; €20.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="367"/>The contributions of Philippe Gignoux to the study of <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Medicine">Syriac medical literature</ref> are well known, and have been nicely summarized elsewhere by 
					Sebastian Brock.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
							<p rend="footnote text">See S. P. Brock, “The Contributions of Philippe Gignoux to Syriac Studies,” in R. Gyselen and Ch. Jullien, eds., 
							<hi rend="italic">‘Maitre pour l’Éternité’. Florilège offert à Philippe Gignoux pour son 80e anniversaire</hi> (Paris: Association pour l’avancement 
							des études iraniennes, 2011), 97–108, especially 98–102.</p>
						</note>
					Perhaps unsurprisingly, the majority of readers will probably find the most useful feature of this book to be its treatment of Iranian loanwords, a subject 
					that has featured heavily in Gignoux’s previous work.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
							<p rend="footnote text">See, for example, Ph. Gignoux, “Le traité syriaque anonyme sur les médications,” in R. Lavenant, ed., <hi rend="italic">Symposium 
							Syriacum VII: Uppsala University, Department of Asian and African Languages, 11–14 August 1996</hi>, OCA 256 (Rome: Pontifical Oriental Institute, 1998), 
							725–733.</p>
						</note>
					The other very useful aspect of this book is that it functions as a handy concordance to the pharmacological terminology present in <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Budge-Sir-Ernest-Alfred-Wallis">Budge’s</ref> edition of the 
					<hi rend="italic">Syriac Book of Medicines</hi>,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
							<p rend="footnote text">E. A. W. Budge, <hi rend="italic">Syrian Anatomy, Pathology and Therapeutics, or “The Book of Medicines,”</hi>	 2 vols. 
							(London: Oxford University Press, 1913).</p>
						</note>
					as well as in the two manuscripts subsequently identified by Gignoux: Paris Syr. 423 and Mingana Syr. 594A.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
							<p rend="footnote text">See Ph. Gignoux, “On the Syriac pharmacopoeia,” <hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 11–12 (1998–1999), 193–201.</p>
						</note>
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Gignoux’s lexicon, presented entirely in transliteration, contains circa 700 entries, from <hi rend="italic">ʾbgr</hi> “nitre, salpêtre” to 
					<hi rend="italic">twtʾ</hi> “mûres.” Each entry gives a gloss, variant forms in parentheses, and a list of references to the sources mentioned above. 
					Furthermore, if possible, Gignoux also supplies relevant authorities to consult (both ancient and modern) and etymological information with reference to 
					Greek, Middle Persian, Persian, Arabic, and Sanskrit. There is even the odd reference to Akkadian, Armenian, Bengali, Hebrew, Hindi, and Old Persian for 
					good measure!
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="368"/>One problem with this volume is that the page numbers in the indices are out of sync with the rest of the volume. With practice, however, one 
					quickly learns how to navigate around this error—the indices are usually only a couple of pages out. My impression is that the indices were compiled prior to 
					the final typesetting of the volume. This is, however, only a minor irritation.
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The present lexicon will prove to be of immense value to those of us who spend a lot of time delving into the treasures of the 
					<hi rend="italic">Syriac Book of Medicines</hi>, for whom it has long been apparent that Budge’s treatment is dated and that a systematic analysis of the 
					pharmacological terminology is very much a desideratum. For this, therefore, we shall be grateful to Gignoux for many years to come.
				</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>