<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Mary as a 'Letter'</title>
                <title type="sub">And Some Other Letter Imagery in Syriac Liturgical Texts<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> This article was
                        originally published in Polish in the periodical <hi rend="italic">Vox
                            Patrum</hi> 26 (2006), pp. 89-99, in an issue in honour of the Revd.
                        Professor Marek Starowieyski.</p></note></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                        <surname>Brock</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Oxford University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.org/h21n1brock</idno><!-- Not sure what to do about URI address -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Sebastian P. Brock</author>
                        <title level="a">Mary as a 'Letter' And Some Other Letter Imagery in Syriac Liturgical Texts</title>
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/####</idno><!-- Need to think about how to do this -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="3" to="20">3-20</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
                <language ident="it"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Mary</term>
                    <term>liturgy</term>
                    <term>letters</term>
                    <term>Hudra</term>
                    <term>Jacob of Serugh</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p xml:lang="en">Imagery surrounding the sending of letters is frequently
                    encountered in Syriac poetry. The article provides a number of examples of the
                    use of letter imagery linked to episodes in the Bible, focussing primarily on
                    the Annunciation to Mary, though attention is also drawn to other episodes, both
                    elsewhere in the Gospels, and in the Old Testament. At the end a striking modern
                    example of the use of the imagery in visual form for the Annunciation is
                    adduced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <p xml:lang="en">This article was originally published in Polish in the periodical
                    Vox Patrum 26 (2006), pp. 89-99, in an issue in honour of the Revd. Professor
                    Marek Starowieyski.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.1" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="3"/>
                <!-- Devise xml:id system for section namimg? -->
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The scribal arts have had a long association with Aramaic and
                    Syriac. A famous wall-painting from Til Barsip (Tel Ahmar) depicts two scribes,
                    one writing with a stylus in cuneiform, the other with a pen, writing (no doubt)
                    in Aramaic.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> Illustrated, for
                            example, in S.P. Brock with D.G.K. Taylor (eds),
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Hidden Pearl. The Syrian Orthodox Church and its Ancient Aramaic Heritage, </hi>I
                            (Transworld Films, Rome, 2001), p. 53. The wall paintings date from after
                            the Assyrian domination of Bit Adini in the second half of the 9<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> century B.C. </p></note>
                    Already <pb n="4"/>in the earliest Syriac documents, from the early 240s AD, Syriac scribes
                    identified themselves by name, whereas in the contemporary Greek texts from the
                    same source, the Greek scribes remain anonymous, suggesting that Syriac scribes
                    enjoyed a higher social status than their Greek counterparts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"
                        ><p rend="footnote text"> The three (dated) Syriac legal documents can most
                            conveniently be found in H.J.W. Drijvers and J.F. Healey,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Old Syriac Inscriptions of Edessa and Osrhoene </hi>(Leiden,
                            1999), Appendix 1, pp. 231-248; the Greek texts (P.Euphr.) are edited by D.
                            Feissel and J. Gascou in
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Journal des Savants </hi>65 (1995),
                            pp. 65-119, 67 (1997), pp. 3-57, and 70 (2000), pp. 157-208.</p></note> Likewise in
                    Syriac literary manuscripts the scribe frequently gives his name (sometimes
                    adding proudly that he is 'an Edessan scribe'), whereas it is much rarer for
                    Greek scribes to mention their name. Accordingly, it is not all that surprising
                    that various kinds of scribal imagery should be particularly common in Syriac
                    writers. Of course this sort of imagery is to be found elsewhere as well, and in
                    the New Testament <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1983">Paul</persName>
                    already speaks of the 'document of debt' (Col. 2:14), a theme that is
                    considerably developed in Syriac liturgical poetry. Here, however, attention
                    will be confined to the specific imagery of a letter. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Two Syriac terms for 'letter' are encountered, egarta and saqra.
                    The former is familiar from certain other Semitic languages, including Hebrew,
                    while the latter is a loan word from Latin sacra (reaching Syriac by way of
                    Greek), an official letter from a higher authority, for which 'missive' is
                    employed in the translations below.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> The
                        loanword <hi rend="italic">saqra</hi> is not attested in Syriac until the
                        late fifth century, the earliest datable authors being Narsai (d. c.500) who
                        uses it once (<hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> 40, p. 140) and
                        <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of Serugh</persName> (d.521) who uses it a considerable number of times (several
                        texts are cited below). </p></note> Although the present article is confined to the use of
                    letter imagery in connection with the Bible, in passing it should be recalled
                    that one of the earliest pieces of Syriac literature, the 'Hymn of the Pearl',
                    incorporated into the Acts of Thomas, tells how the Prince's father and mother
                    arouse him from his 'deep sleep' in Egypt by means of a letter 'that flew in the
                    likeness of an eagle ... and alighted beside [him] and became all speech' (Acts
                    of <pb n="5"/>Thomas 111, couplets 51-2). Letter imagery is also used in another early
                    text, the Odes of Solomon, where the Lord's 'thought was like letter, and his
                    will descended from on high' (Ode 23:5). This puzzling Ode still defies a fully
                    satisfactory explanation, although Harris and Mingana, who draw attention to
                    some of the letter imagery in later Syriac writers, cited below, seem to be on
                    the right path; we shall be returning briefly to this in due course.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Gabriel Bears a Letter at the Annunciation</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The context in which one encounters letter imagery most frequently
                    is the Annunciation. The term used may be either egarta, the standard term for a
                    letter, or (more frequently) saqra, a missive from a higher authority. One of
                    the anonymous madrashe on <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/624">Mary</persName> makes considerable use of the image: <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <lg>
                                <l>1. The Father wrote a letter</l>
                                <l>and sent it, at the hands of a Watcher, to Nazareth,</l>
                                <l>to a virgin, Mary, in whom He was pleased</l>
                                <l>and so chose her to become</l>
                                <l>mother to His Only-Begotten</l>
                                <l>when He descended to deliver all worlds.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg>
                                <l>... 3. God gave Gabriel the command</l>
                                <l>and he flew down amidst great commotion,</l>
                                <l>bearing that letter full of fair tidings,</l>
                                <l>to bring peace to those in a state of wrath,</l>
                                <l>seeing that reconciliation had taken place between God and the
                                    world.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <lg>
                                <l>4. The messenger learnt the secret</l>
                                <l>and fluttered down, arriving at Nazareth.</l>
                                <l>As he beheld the Virgin, he bowed down in worship,</l><pb n="6"/>
                                <l>then stretched out his hand and gave her the letter of peace</l>
                                <l>that had been sent from above.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> T.J. Lamy,
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sancti Ephraemi Hymni et Sermones, </hi>III
                                    (Malines, 1889), col. 969; the poem is also to be found in the Mosul
                                    edition of the Fenqitho (Mosul, 1886-96) [henceforth cited as FM], II,
                                    p. 89b-90a. An English translation is given in my
                                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Bride of Light. Hymns on Mary from the Syriac Churches </hi>(Moran
                                    Etho 6; Kottayam, 1994), pp. 86-87 (no. 25).</p></note></l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> This poem also features in the West Syriac Fenqitho, or Festal
                    Hymnary on the Sunday of the Annunciation to Mary (the 5th Sunday before
                    Christmas in the Syriac liturgical year), and many other examples can be found
                    in the liturgical texts for this Sunday and the accompanying weekdays. Not
                    surprisingly, it is the term saqra, 'missive' that is the most frequently used,
                    though on occasion one encounters both, as: <cit>
                        <quote>The fiery being took the letter, the missive filled with peace...
                            (Fenqitho II, p. 126a)</quote>
                    </cit> The fiery aspect of Gabriel is often emphasised in both the Eastern and
                    Western Syriac liturgical traditions. Thus, for example in the East Syriac
                    festal hymnary, the Hudra, we find:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Henceforth designated ‘H’; references are given
                        first to T. Darmo’s edition (Trichur, 1960-62) and then to P. Bedjan’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Breviarium Chaldaicum</hi> (Rome, 1938; one-volume
                        reprint with same pagination, Rome 2002), cited as ‘BC’. A concordance
                        between the two editions can be found in <hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi>
                        19 (2006), pp. 117-136.</p></note>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>A man of fire flew down from the ranks of flame, wrapped in burning
                            fire and flame; he rent the height and descended to the depth, carrying
                            a missive with its greeting... (Hudra I, p. 116, cp 153)</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In passages where the term 'missive' (saqra) is used, it was
                    natural enough to introduce imagery of royalty, as in the following: <cit>
                        <quote>The missive left the palace and a servant received it.... (There
                            follows a description of his descent through the fiery realms of
                            heaven). He passed by the city of <pb n="7"/>the heavenly beings and came forth to
                            our region; flying down from the height, he reached Mary and prostrated
                            before her: the servant saw the Mother of the King and he bowed his head
                            as he proffered her the missive full of peace for the entire world.
                            (Fenqitho II, pp, 136b-137a)</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In another passage Gabriel is no longer a 'servant', but an
                    official messenger, or even ambassador (izgadda): <cit>
                        <quote>The ambassador (izgadda) approached and handed over the missive full
                            of peace that had been written in secret, as in a mystery; and he opened
                            it before her and began to read it with his eloquence: 'Blessed are you
                            among women…' (FM II, p. 117b)</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Mary is again described as 'Mother of the King' in a text which
                    identifies the place where he finds Mary as 'the sanctuary', perhaps a
                    reflection of the traditions of her upbringing in the Temple: <cit>
                        <quote>To the midst of the sanctuary did the Watcher descend, carrying the
                            good tidings. He knelt down in veneration to the Mother of the King, and
                            gave her the missive, being a wise (servant) who had been sent from the
                            Most High as in a mystery. (FM II, p. 88a)</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In the introductory stanzas to the Dialogue between Mary and the
                    Angel<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> English
                            translation in <hi rend="italic">Bride of Light</hi>, pp.
                            111-118.</p></note> we
                    are told that the letter was 'sealed': <cit>
                        <quote>A letter did he bring, which had been sealed with the mystery that
                            was hidden from all ages. (stanza 9; also in FM II, p. 94b).</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A passage in the East Syriac Hudra describes the missive as
                    likewise being 'sealed', but this time 'with (God's) Being without a beginning': <cit>
                        <quote>(Wanting to renew his image that had become badly corrupted, the Lord
                            of all) <pb n="8"/>sent a missive from on high which was sealed with His Being
                            without a beginning, and in it was inscribed (rshim) peace to earthly
                            and heavenly beings, for they have been liberated from error. 'I am
                            Gabriel who stand ministering before that awesome Majesty: the Father
                            has sent me to proclaim to you the good tidings that give joy to the
                            entire world...' (H I, p. 114 = BC I, p. 54; 1st Sunday of the Period of
                            the Annunciation)</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The sealed character of the missive is also emphasised in a sedro
                    for the Annunciation in an early liturgical manuscript, London Add. 14,493, f.
                    29a): <cit>
                        <quote>(Gabriel was sent from the Father) with a missive full of joys and
                            exultation that had been written. He flew swiftly with spiritual wings,
                            with a missive in his hand that was securely sealed. He put into
                            commotion both heavenly and earthly beings at his descent: wonder and
                            amazement gripped them. He came to the virgin Mary, blessed among women;
                            gently and silently he opened in her presence the missive filled with
                            good tidings, and said to her, 'Greeting, modest Mary; blessed are you,
                            for my Lord is with you, O blessed among women. For from you the Lord of
                            (all) races and generations will shine forth. Greeting to you, O mother
                            of the Ancient of Days<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> For Christ (rather than the Father) as ‘Ancient of
                                Days’ (Dan. 7:13), see my ‘The Ancient of Days: the Father or the Son?’,
                                in <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Harp </hi>22 (2007), pp.
                                121-30.</p></note>... (there follows a long series of phrases
                            beginning 'Greeting to you...').</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In one passage in the Fenqitho (FM II, p. 167b) the letter is
                    specifically said to have been 'written in a mystery by the hidden Father'. The
                    letter itself is described as being 'full of life<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Or ‘salvation’: <hi
                            rend="italic">ḥayye</hi> in earlier Syriac translations regularly
                            corresponds to Greek <hi rend="italic">sotēria</hi>. </p></note> and good hope for <pb n="9"/>mortals' (H I, p. 117
                    = BC I, p. 56), or it is 'a missive of salvation for the whole race of mortals'
                    (H I, p. 129 = BC I, p. 68), or one 'full of joys' (FM II, p. 167b) or 'full of
                    peace for the entire world' (FM II, p. 137a, quoted above).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The examples cited above amply bear out the comment, made in a
                    different context by Mary Beard, that there is "a tendency to define
                    communication between humans and gods in written terms."<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> M. Beard, ‘Writing and religion’, in M. Beard and
                        others (eds),
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Literacy in the Roman World </hi>(Ann
                        Arbor, 1991), p. 52 (she is referring in particular to oracle texts in
                        Egypt). </p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mary Herself as a Letter</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">In a few passages in the West Syriac liturgical texts one
                    encounters the surprising image of Mary herself being described as a letter.
                    Thus: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>Mary was like a letter full of mysteries,</l>
                                <l>and the Word opened her and resided in her womb inexplicably;</l>
                                <l>and she conceived without marital intercourse,</l>
                                <l>and there shone forth from her the great Light for the entire
                                    world. (FM II, p. 149a)</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The first line (only) of this corresponds to a line in the
                    following passage of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of Serugh's</persName> Verse Homily on Faith,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"
                        ><p rend="footnote text"> Ed. P. Bedjan,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Homiliae Selectae Mar-Jacobi Sarugensis, </hi>III
                            (Paris/Leipzig, 1907; repr. Piscataway NJ, 2006), p .591. To Bedjan’s
                            five volumes the reprint adds a sixth which includes the Homilies which
                            Bedjan published at the end of his edition of Sahdona’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Book of Perfection</hi> (whose pagination is also
                            given).</p></note> where
                    almost in passing he refers to Mary as resembling a letter: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>It was the captivity that the Slayer of Mankind had taken captive
                                    from Paradise</l>
                                <l>that the Son of the King came down to return them from subjection
                                    to their former place.</l>
                                <l>He set forth valiantly, following the track of the Thief</l>
                            <l>and the path took Him to the ear of the virgin Eve.</l><pb n="10"/>
                                <l>Because He is the Word, it was the gate of (Mary's) ear which
                                    received Him,</l>
                                <l>and He was conceived, so as to come to birth in bodily
                                    fashion,</l>
                                <l>and Mary became like a letter full of mysteries,</l>
                                <l> being sealed in virginity in holy fashion.</l>
                                <l>The Word became embodied in her, from her, in a mysterious
                                    way,</l>
                                <l>so that He might visit the world in the revelation of His bodily
                                    form.</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> proves also to be the source of two further occurrences of
                    the imagery of Mary as a letter in West Syriac liturgical texts: In the Maronite
                    Shehimto (Weekday Office) we find: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>Mary has appeared to us as a sealed letter,</l>
                                <l>for in her were hidden the mysteries and profundities of the
                                    Son.</l>
                                <l>She was not a letter that was written and then sealed,</l>
                                <l>rather, the divinity [bet aloho] had sealed her (first) and then
                                    written. (Friday, Lilyo)</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This is in fact an abbreviated form of a Bo'uto ('Supplication') in
                    the Fenqitho for the Marian Commemoration on 15th Jan. (Our Lady of the Seeds;
                    III, p. 354), which in turn can be identified as a passage from one of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of
                    Serugh's</persName> Verse Homilies on Mary:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> VI,
                        p. 24/636. There is an English translation in M. Hansbury,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Jacob of Serugh. On the Mother of God </hi>(Crestwood
                        NY,1998), pp. 38-39. </p></note>
                    <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>Mary has appeared to us as a sealed letter:</l>
                                <l>hidden within her were the mysteries and profundities of the
                                    Son.</l>
                            <l>She gave her pure body like a clean piece of paper<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">kartisa</hi> &lt; Greek <hi rend="italic"
                                        >chartēs</hi>, writing material (‘paper’, which I use here, is of course
                                    an anachronism). It is interesting to note that a text in the Hudra
                                    denotes the metaphorical use of <hi rend="italic">saqra</hi> by calling
                                    it <hi rend="italic">la kartisaya</hi>, ‘not made of writing material’,
                                    i.e. ‘immaterial’ (H II, p. 506 = BC II, p. 372). </p></note></l>
                            <l>and on it the Word inscribed Himself in bodily form.</l><pb n="11"/>
                                <l>The Son is the Word, and she, as we have said, is the Letter</l>
                                <l>in which forgiveness has been sent to the entire world.</l>
                                <l>She was not a letter that was written and then sealed,</l>
                                <l>rather, the divinity had sealed her (first) and then written, as
                                    we have said.</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is, however, in another Verse Homily that <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> develops the
                    idea at greatest length: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                            <l> A letter too receives a word<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                                rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">mellta</hi>, ‘word’, can imply more than a single
                                word; however, I translate here as a singular because of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob’s</persName> play
                                between ‘word’ and (divine) ‘Word’.</p></note> with its written
                                    characters,</l>
                                <l> and the word resides there as if contained, yet not
                                    contained.</l>
                                <l> A hidden word is also sent within a letter,</l>
                                <l> and who can say that the entire word are not there?</l>
                                <l> The whole of it is placed (there) in the letter in the written
                                    characters.</l>
                                <l> It is also revealed and seized upon, too, by many,</l>
                                <l> (but) because it is without body, who is able to seize hold
                                    of</l>
                                <l> (p. 172) the word which came and became a body within the
                                    letter,</l>
                                <l> handing itself over to the limbs (i.e. shapes) of the
                                    characters?</l>
                                <l> Eyes beheld it and hands seized hold of the glorious Word:</l>
                                <l> the Son was in the Virgin as a word within a letter,</l>
                                <l> and He became embodied in her, like words in written
                                    characters.</l>
                                <l> He who was hidden with His Begetter came into the open</l>
                                <l> and manifested Himself to the world, for it to see and
                                    comprehend Him.</l><pb n="12"/>
                                <l> People seized hold of Him in their hands, seeing that He had
                                    become embodied from the Daughter of David,</l>
                                <l> and like a word in written characters they saw His
                                    hiddenness.</l>
                                <l> Where are you, O word? In what place can one look for you?</l>
                                <l> With your sender? With your recipient? Or in the letter
                                    itself?</l>
                                <l> You are hidden and revealed at the same time, unattainable and
                                    not to be investigated.</l>
                                <l> (p. 173) See how a word is hidden from many in a letter,</l>
                                <l> preserved under seal in secret until it is disclosed.</l>
                                <l> It depicts there an image of beauty for the Only-Begotten</l>
                                <l> who is the Word, who resided in Mary as in a letter:</l>
                                <l> she was sealed in her virginity, as with a letter,</l>
                                <l> and with the seals preserved (the Word) came forth in holy
                                    fashion.</l>
                                <l> The Son of God is the Word which cannot be interpreted;</l>
                                <l> He wafted down from the Father and resided in a womb full of
                                    sanctity.</l>
                                <l> The hidden Word entered inside the Letter, by (her) ear;</l>
                                <l> she was firmly and closely sealed.</l>
                                <l> He embodied Himself from the body of the blessed woman</l>
                            <l> and with limbs - as it were with written characters<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Compare a Sedro in FM III, p.
                                    369b: ‘On tablets of flesh did He inscribe Himself in bodily
                                    fashion’.</p></note> - </l>
                                <l> the Word who had been hidden from view came to be seen.</l>
                                <l> (p. 174) Everyone who saw Him and read Him recognised that He
                                    was God,</l><pb n="13"/>
                                <l> and in order that all who enter the world might understand the
                                    report of his journey,</l>
                                <l> the Son of Thunder stood up and revealed to all the earth that
                                    He was the Word.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> John
                                        1:1.</p></note></l>
                                <l> He showed that a word cannot be taken hold of or be seen,</l>
                                <l> it cannot be touched or confined in space,</l>
                                <l> but all of a sudden in comes and takes on a body in written
                                    characters:</l>
                                <l> for a particular purpose it embodies itself and gives itself
                                    over;</l>
                                <l> it comes so that it can be touched, and read out in speech:</l>
                                <l> everyone can see it, everyone can read it, everyone take hold of
                                    it.</l>
                                <l> It becomes confined, people take hold of it in (different)
                                    places;</l>
                                <l> they carry it about, escorting it in their hands,</l>
                                <l> and because it has come and taken on a body in the letter,</l>
                                <l> space has contained it, even though by its nature it is beyond
                                    containment.</l>
                                <l> And if it is investigated, it hides itself away from those who
                                    would investigate it,</l>
                                <l> whereas when it is read, it is totally to be found with
                                    learners.</l>
                                <l> It is entirely with the readers in the written characters, </l>
                                <l> but (at the same time) it is preserved with its writer, high up
                                    out of sight. (II, pp. 171-4).</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> then goes on to speak of another analogy involving mellta,
                    but here with a shift of sense, also possible with Greek logos, from 'word' to
                    'reason': <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                            <l> Word/Reason is in the soul, and is naturally found there:</l><pb n="14"/>
                                <l> when it is revealed, it goes forth from the soul's very
                                    essence.</l>
                                <l> From the moment of the soul's existence, reason is there with
                                    it,</l>
                                <l> neither younger nor older than the essence (of the soul);</l>
                                <l> (p.175) just as the Son is in the Father without any beginning, </l>
                                <l> so too reason is in the soul from the moment of its
                                    existence.</l>
                                <l> For this reason (John) called the Son of God 'the Word',</l>
                                <l> (John), the disciple who loved and knew Him.</l>
                                <l> The Word is too exalted for artists to depict, </l>
                                <l> so too He is too exalted for even the wise to speak about.</l>
                                <l> No one is able to establish an image of the Word in paints,</l>
                                <l> nor will any explanation of Him emerge into the open on the part
                                    of enquirers. (II, pp. 174-5).</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">If, in the light of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob's</persName> extended use of letter imagery in the
                    context of the incarnation, one the goes back to the mysterious 23rd Ode of
                    Solomon, one gets the impression that, although Harris and Mingana did not cite
                    this particular verse homily of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> in their discussion of this Ode, their
                    interpretation of the 'letter' in that Ode was along the right lines.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"> R.
                        Harris and A. Mingana,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Odes and Psalms of Solomon , </hi>II
                        (Manchester, 1920), pp. 336-340. The matter certainly deserves further
                        exploration, which would be out of place here. </p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Letters During the Life and Ministry of Christ</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Here and there one finds letter imagery introduced into certain
                    episodes in the life and ministry of Christ. At the opening of his Verse Homily
                    on the Magi <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of Serugh</persName> addresses Christ and says 'You sent a letter to the
                    Magian <pb n="15"/>religion in (the form of) the star of light, which drew it out of
                    darkness and took it out into Your illumination' (Hom. 6, on the Magi; I, p.
                    85). This is picked up a little later in the narrative: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>The King sent a missive of light to the realm of darkness,</l>
                                <l>to bring them out of the night that had engulfed them.</l>
                                <l>He wrote a letter and sent it to the region in the hands of a
                                    messenger,</l>
                                <l>(saying) that there would be peace in the land that had grown
                                    waste with Magianism.</l>
                                <l>(I, p. 88; he goes on to explain why a star, not a prophet had
                                    been sent)</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In a prose prayer composed by Shallita of Resh'aina (9th cent.) in
                    the East Syriac Hudra, John the Baptist is rather surprisingly described as a
                    'postman' (tabellara, from Latin tabellarius), but without any other specific
                    letter imagery being introduced. (H I, p. 675 = BC I, p. 443).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Likewise very much in passing, a madrasha in the Pampakuda
                    Fenqitho<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">
                        Ed. A. Konat, II (Pampakuda, 1963), p. 257 [henceforth cited as ‘FP’] .
                        The contents of this edition differ considerably from those of
                        FM.</p></note> (II, p. 257) speaks of the sinful woman of Luke 7 as carrying,
                    instead of 'wages' (from her previous paramours), 'a missive' as she goes to
                    Jesus in the house of Simeon; the image is not developed, though one might have
                    expected some expansion such as 'written in the ink of her tears (of
                    repentance)'.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">More predictably, Mary and Martha are described in the same source
                    as having 'written a letter of grief' which they sent to Jesus, informing him of
                    their brother Lazarus' death (FP II, p. 394; Saturday of Lazarus).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> A different <hi rend="italic"
                            >madrasha</hi> for the Saturday of Lazarus, to be found in the Mosul
                            Fenqitho (IV, p. 775b) has them writing
                            ‘letter<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">s </hi>full of sufferings’
                            (likewise, p. 768a).</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of Serugh</persName>, who was evidently particularly partial to letter
                    imagery, introduces it again into his Verse Homily on <pb n="16"/>Peter's Confession of
                    Christ (Homily 19; I, p. 473). <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> speaks of this as a 'revelation' sent in
                    the form of a missive in the Father's own handwriting. When asked by Christ
                    'Whom do you say that I am?' Peter prays to the Father for enlightenment, and in
                    response: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>a revelation went forth from the Father's house to that
                                    disciple;</l>
                                <l>it came down and he received it like missive from the royal
                                    palace.</l>
                                <l>He manifested the signature of the hidden Father, with the
                                    seal,</l>
                                <l>and written in it was 'You are the Christ, the Son of God'.</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit> Whereupon Peter feels himself enabled to address Christ with these
                    words.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> Matt. 16:16.
                        </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Next to the Annunciation, the Crucifixion is the episode where
                    letter imagery is particular frequent. This may be either in connection with the
                    repentant thief, or with the Descent to Sheol, though sometimes the two motifs
                    may be combined. In the delightful dramatic dialogue between the Good Thief and
                    the Cherub who guards the gate of Paradise (Gen. 3:24), the introductory
                    narrative compares Christ's words to the thief on the cross to a royal
                    missive:<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Stanza 6; ed. with English
                            translation in <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Hugoye </hi>5
                            (2002), pp. 169-193.</p></note><cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>The word of our Lord was sealed</l>
                                <l>like a missive from the palace;</l>
                            <l>it was handed over to the thief</l><pb n="17"/>
                            <l>who took it and made off for the Garden of Eden.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                                n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> Similarly Jacob in his verse homily on the
                                    Repentant Thief, Jesus tells him that ‘the ranks of fire will rejoice
                                    at your missive and will convey you on their wings’ (V, p. 669); the
                                    very next line continues ‘When the missive of Life had been written, the
                                    King who wrote it held back the Son’s signature’ until his side had been
                                    pierced, so that he could sign it with the blood that flowed from his
                                    side, the water serving as the thief’s baptism (p. 670). In Romanos’
                                    Kontakion on the Cross (ed. Maas-Trypanis, no. 23, stanzas 10-11, the
                                    Thief tells the Cherub that he as with him a <hi rend="italic"
                                        >gramma</hi>, with Christ’s seal; similarly in a Pseudo- Chrysostom
                                    homily the Thief says to the Cherub, ‘Christ has written a letter (<hi
                                        rend="italic">epistolēn</hi>) for me’ (ed. M. van Esbroeck, in <hi
                                            rend="italic">Analecta Bollandiana</hi> 101 (1983), pp. 327-362
                                    (section 8). </p></note></l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A verse text in the Fenqitho tells how, at the Descent, 'To Adam
                    and to all his children a missive has been written, (stating) that God is
                    reconciled to them and has forgiven their wrongdoing' (FM VII, p. 133a).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text"> Similarly F IV, p. 163b (1<hi
                            rend="superscript">st</hi> Friday of Lent), where the missive is
                            sent from Christ on the Cross.</p></note> The two
                    scenarios are combined in the Cave of Treasures, which states that 'Christ wrote
                    the missive (announcing) Adam's return with his own blood and sent it by the
                    hands of the thief' (52:13).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">
                        Ed. Su-Min Ri, in the Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium,
                        Scriptores Syri 207-8 (1987). </p></note> Also written in Christ's blood is the dowry which
                    Christ gives (in the form of the Sacraments) to the Church, his Bride; this set
                    of imagery, however, does not introduce any letter.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> For this theme,
                            see my ‘”The Wedding Feast of Blood”. an unusual aspect of John 19:34 in
                            Syriac tradition’,
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Harp </hi>6:2 (1993), pp.
                            121-134.</p><p rend="footnote text">and the literature cited
                                there.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Finally, at Pentecost <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> tells how God, having 'given speech and
                    sent forth the Apostles, wrote a letter in the tongues of the (different)
                    regions to inform them that he is the Master who had taught them (sc. the
                    Apostles)' (II, p. 683).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.5" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="18"/>
                <head>Some Examples Concerning Episodes in the Old Testament</head>
                <p xml:lang="en"><persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob of Serugh</persName>, whose predilection for letter imagery has already
                    become amply evident, also takes the opportunity to introduce it into various
                    episodes of Old Testament history. Thus the cry of Abel's blood (Gen. 4:10) had
                    'brought down a missive with a sentence of judgement upon the rebel (Cain)' (V,
                    p. 20), while Noah's dove (Gen. 8:11) 'entered (the Ark) to bring out the
                    missive of peace from the (heavenly) Palace' (IV, p. 49). Less expected is
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob's</persName> introduction of letter imagery into his Verse Homily on Abraham and his
                    types (no. 109).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> For this homily,
                            see R.E. McCarron, in <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> 1:1 (1998), pp.
                            57-108. </p></note> As frequently in his homilies, <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob</persName> commences with a prayer, in
                    the course of which he requests: <cit>
                        <quote><lg>
                                <l>Allow me to make the slaying of Isaac a rational missive;</l>
                                <l>I will reserve its seal for You to add Your signature. (IV, p.
                                    62)</l>
                            </lg></quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is likely that there are further examples of letter imagery of
                    this sort to be found in <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob's</persName> extensive corpus of verse homilies, many of
                    which are still unpublished, but these will suffice to give some indication of
                    <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/42">Jacob's</persName> creative powers of imagination. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h21n1brock.6" xml:lang="en">
                <head>A Striking Modern Parallel: The Annunciation in Pope John Paul II's Private
                    Chapel</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Of all the texts introduced here, it is undoubtedly those which
                    describe Mary herself as a 'letter' on which the Word 'inscribes himself', that
                    is the most striking. Remarkably, a similar idea has recently been expressed in
                    artistic form in the mosaic decoration of the Pope's private chapel in the
                    Vatican, commissioned by Pope John Paul II.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> This is superbly illustrated in M. Apa, O. Clément
                        and C. Valenziano (eds),
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">La Capella “Redemptoris Mater” del Papa Giovanni Paolo II </hi>(Vatican
                        City, 1999). For the Annunciation, see plate 48 (p. 72).</p></note> In the scene portraying <pb n="19"/>the
                    Annunciation, Gabriel is standing with his tip of his left hand touching an
                    opened scroll on which the Virgin is portrayed as kneeling. Gabriel's right hand
                    is depicted at the level of Mary's ear, pointing to the widespread motif of the
                    Word entering Mary through her ear, thus contrasting her obedient listening with
                    Eve's disobedient listening to the Serpent's counsel. The work was designed and
                    carried out by Fr. Marko Rupnik, Director of the Centro Aletti in Rome, and in
                    his notes on the iconography he had adopted he comments:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                        rend="footnote text">
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">La Capella, </hi>p. 294, note
                        48.</p></note><cit>
                        <quote xml:lang="it">Maria è in attegiamento di raccoglimento, con gli occhi
                            chiusi, non si sa se stia per sedere sulle gambi o se stia per alzarsi.
                            Appare sul rotolo del libro che l'angelo srotola ed è in atteggiamento
                            di ascolto. Efrem il Siro, riprendendo una antica tradizione, dice che
                            Maria è stata fecondata dall'orecchio. Gabriele srotola il rotolo del
                            Verbo e la sua mano destra è esattamente all'altezza dell'orecchio,
                            annuncia la Parola a Maria. Lei, con le mani sul grembo, tesse il filo
                            rosso che significa tessere la carne al Verbo. Si tratta del passaggio
                            dalla Parola all'Immagine. Il Verbo infatti è il Figlio e come tale
                            Maria lo presenta al mondo. La spiritualità mariana e proprio rendere
                            visibile la Parola di Dio.</quote>
                    </cit>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although Fr. Rupnik speaks of the scroll as a 'book', rather than a
                    'letter', the underlying concept is very similar. While he makes specific
                    mention of St Ephrem, in connection with the tradition of the divine Word
                    entering Mary through her ear,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"
                        > This of course is fairly widespread, being indicated pictorially by a
                        stream of light in several medieval western depictions of the
                        Annunciation.</p></note> it is intriguing to note that he was not at the time
                    aware of the imagery, present in the Syriac writings outline here, where either
                    Gabriel gives the message <pb n="20"/>in the form of a letter, or Mary herself is described
                    as the letter in which the Divine Word has inscribed himself.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- Templates to copy:
            <div xml:id="" xml:lang="en">
                <head/>
                <p xml:lang="en"/>
            </div>
            <ref type="noteAnchor" n="" xml:id="note#" target="#fn#">
             -->
            <div xml:id="bibliography" type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>S. P. Brock</author>
                        <author>D. G. K. Taylor</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="m">The Hidden Pearl. The Syrian Orthodox Church and its
                            Ancient Aramaic Heritage, I </title>
                        <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Transworld Films</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
