<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Jonathan Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                    Manuscript of the Syriac ‘Masora’ Dated to 899 CE; vol. 1: A Facsimile
                    Reproduction of British Library, Add. MS 12138; vol. 2: Introduction, List of Sample Texts, and Indices to Marginal Notes in
                        British Library, Additional MS 12138</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Aïm</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Tel Aviv</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n1praim</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Emmanuel Aïm</author>
                        <title level="a">Jonathan Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                            Manuscript of the Syriac ‘Masora’ Dated to 899 CE; vol. 1: A Facsimile
                            Reproduction of British Library, Add. MS 12138; vol. 2: Introduction, List of Sample Texts, and Indices to Marginal Notes in
                            British Library, Additional MS 12138</hi></title>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N1PRAim.pdf</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="317" to="322">317-322</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="8"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-02-12">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <ab type="review-title">Jonathan Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                    Manuscript of the Syriac ‘Masora’ Dated to 899</hi> CE; vol. 1: A Facsimile
                    Reproduction of British Library, Add. MS 12138; vol. 2: <hi rend="Emphasis"
                        >Introduction, List of Sample Texts, and Indices to Marginal Notes in
                        British Library, Additional MS 12138</hi> (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press,
                    2014–2015). Pp. ix + 624; $157 and pp. xi + 541; $136.</ab>
                </div>
                
                <div xml:lang="en">

                <p xml:lang="en">With respect to the advancement in manuscript editing and the
                    development of efficient tools for researchers, the monograph under review is a
                    masterful work. Its impressive apparatus is designed to meet the need of the
                    established scholar as well as that of the advanced student. It should also be
                    warmly welcomed as a direct continuation of the fundamental studies by H. Ewald,
                    A. Merx, G. Diettrich, T. Weiss, and J. B. Segal on the ‘Masoretic’ accents. In
                    this context, it is worth noting the author’s latest publication on the
                    patristic selections included in the ‘Masoretic’ West Syriac manuscripts (see
                    the reference below). In a sense, this work will complement the book under
                    review: both open new perspectives in the study of the Syriac ‘Masora’.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The monograph consists of two volumes, of which the first
                    presents a facsimile edition of manuscript BL Add. 12138. Volume 2 is an
                    introduction to Volume 1. Dated to 899 CE and written in the city of Ḥarrān, BL
                    Add. 12138 is a manuscript that aims to support accuracy in the recitation and
                    transmission of the Peshiṭta according to the tradition of the East Syriac
                    schools. It consists of sample passages from the Peshiṭta which are vocalized,
                    marked with diacritics, accentuated, and accompanied by marginal notes. Some
                    discourses on the accents, grammar, various marks, and the East Syriac schools
                    are included at the end. It is the only known East Syriac ‘Masoretic’
                    manuscript, and scholars such as P. Martin, A. Merx, and W. Wright have long
                    recognized its significance for the study of how the Peshiṭta was read and
                    interpreted in the ninth and tenth centuries. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Some parts of BL Add. 12138 were previously published by
                    G. Diettrich and T. Weiss, among others. The contribution of Volume 1 is, first,
                    to present for the first time the entire text of the manuscript. The copyist,
                    Bābai, claims that he punctuated the text according to older books of reading
                    teachers (<hi rend="italic">maqryānē</hi>). Interestingly, he also incorporates,
                    in red ink, the punctuation of another respected scribe, viz. Rāmīšoʿ. Herein
                    lies the second contribution of Volume 1. Previous publications of excerpts from
                    the manuscript were for technical reasons printed only in black and white, but
                    Loopstra’s colour reproduction allows the reader to distinguish precisely
                    between the two systems of punctuation. In addition, the high resolution of the
                    printed images (and even more so the PDF version which allows one to zoom in)
                    allows an easier reading and a more secure identification of the other reading
                    marks (vowels, diacritics, symbols indicating mistakes or revisions, etc.). The
                    third contribution of the volume is the placement of folio numbers and the range
                    of biblical passages above each image. These enable the reader easily to find
                    any passage in the manuscript. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Loopstra begins the second volume by discussing principal
                    issues pertaining to the manuscript (historical background, general overview,
                    biographical elements of the copyist, relation with the West Syriac ‘Masoretic’
                    manuscripts, and publication history). In the following seven chapters, he dives
                    into an exhaustive description of the different marks and notes of the text (the
                    collections of <seg rend="italic">šm</seg><hi rend="italic">ā</hi><seg
                        rend="italic">he</seg> and <seg rend="italic">qr</seg><hi rend="italic"
                            >ā</hi><seg rend="italic">y</seg><hi rend="italic">ā</hi><seg rend="italic"
                                >t</seg><hi rend="italic">ā</hi>, section dividers, reading marks, vowel
                    marks, phonological marks, notes on schools, and exegetical glosses). This study
                    is remarkably thorough in its treatment of the sources and the scholarship. It
                    covers various fields of research such as history, palaeography, exegesis,
                    liturgy, grammar, and even music. The author should be commended for his
                    handling of these different areas, which are so often intertwined. Worth
                    mentioning is the description of the marks and reading system of Rāmīšoʿ (pp.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">xxxiv–xxxvi</hi>): these clarifications are essential
                    for scholars who want to study the accentuation system. When needed, the
                    sections are copiously illustrated with images extracted from the manuscript. It
                    is regrettable that these extracts are in black and white, since in some cases
                    colour would have been more suitable, as for example on
                    pp.<hi rend="smallcaps" xml:space="preserve"> xxxiv–xxxvi</hi> where Rāmīšoʿ’s
                    punctuation is explained. In addition, the author could have dealt in more depth
                    with one sign, viz. the dash between two words. Loopstra discusses this sign
                    when accompanied by the gloss <hi rend="italic">ʾqp</hi> in the margin where it
                    has to be understood as a hyphen (see pp. <hi rend="smallcaps">xlii</hi>, 422).
                    However, according to El-Attar (1982) (not cited in the bibliography), the dash
                    appears in many more occurrences and corresponds to the sign <hi rend="italic"
                        >meṭappeyānā</hi> whose functions seem more varied and complex than that of
                    a mere hyphen. One must admit that the name <hi rend="italic">meṭappeyānā</hi>
                    occurs neither in the marginal notes nor in the <hi rend="italic">Tract on the
                        Accents</hi> (a text which appears at the end of the manuscript). It is thus
                    a complicated issue which needs to be clarified.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The volume’s extensive bibliography covers almost all the
                    relevant publications. On the Syriac accentuation, the author could have added
                    Avenary (1963), who places it within the broader context of the Eastern biblical
                    chant in the Early Middle Ages; Jourdan-Hemmerdinger (1979), who argues for its
                    musical signification (on the basis of similar notation found in some Greek
                    papyri); and Moberg (1906), who refutes Merx’s view on its origin and
                    development. The lack of the aforementioned study of El-Attar (1982) is of more
                    relevance since this work examines the use of two diacritical marks in BL Add
                    12138, viz. <hi rend="italic">nāgōḏā</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >meṭappeyānā</hi>. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Volume 2 concludes with a list of the biblical passages, a
                    list of the examples cited in the <seg rend="italic">Tract on Accents</seg>,
                    some grammatical notes, the translation of the material in the colophon, and the
                    index of the marginal notes. Overall, Volume 2 is very well organized. The
                    reader will appreciate the book’s apparatus and the tedious labour the author
                    has accomplished in creating useful lists of verses, citations, glosses, section
                    dividers, etc. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As well known, BL Add. 12138 is an outstanding source for
                    the study of the Syriac ‘Masoretic’ accents. Not surprisingly, Loopstra
                    dedicates the longest section of Volume 2 (33 pages) to this subject. Thus, this
                    section deserves special attention. Loopstra offers an overview of the accents
                    and the history of their study and does not enter unnecessarily into the details
                    of the long-debated question of their origin (Greek or Syriac) and possible
                    transmission to Hebrew. He is appropriately measured in his interpretation of
                    the various possible values of the accents (pausal/grammatical, intonational,
                    ekphonetic/ musical). Also, his thorough philological knowledge renders
                    persuasive his effort to draw out common accentual patterns between BL Add.
                    12138 and other non-Masoretic East Syriac manuscripts. However, he could have
                    addressed a few points better.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Firstly, he could have ranked the accents not
                    alphabetically but according to a more significant principle such as 1) the
                    linguistic function (e.g. pausal or conjunctive force, modality, expressiveness)
                    as in the descriptions by Merx and Duval; or 2) the position of the accent mark
                    related to the word (above, below, etc.) as in Segal’s study (see, however, the
                    author’s explanation on p. <hi rend="smallcaps">lxii</hi>, note 224). </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Secondly, the description of the use of the accents is
                    sometimes vague, as shown by expressions such as “may indicate,” “can also
                    occur,” “often used,” “sometimes used.” Notwithstanding the intricacies involved
                    in the process of identifying the accent signs, in order to arrive at a more
                    accurate description, one will have to proceed to an exhaustive inventory, for
                    each accent, of all its occurrences. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Thirdly, it is well known that the recitation according to
                    the accents has been lost for a long time. However, the biblical texts are still
                    recited today during offices. A few words on this subject would have been
                    appreciated (e.g., the different regional traditions, the main musical features,
                    the possible other contexts where the texts are cantillated, such private
                    study), or at least some bibliographical references. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">One cannot blame the author for these minor flaws since the
                    chapter on the accents is meant as an overview. His more recent publications
                    show that he continues to expand his research and that he is now the leading
                    authority on these matters (see the references below). Thanks to him, other
                    researchers have all the material necessary for further investigations. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is already evident that the book under review marks an
                    important step in the history of Syriac studies. Overall, it provides a wealth
                    of phonologically and lexically reliable linguistic evidence ready for further
                    reflection and analysis. Aramaists interested in Eastern Syriac pronunciation
                    and lexicology will find it indispensable. In addition, it will allow in-depth
                    study of the accents, not only among Syriac scholars but also among Hebraists
                    and Byzantinists who will find valuable information on shared features and
                    differences between the Hebrew and Greek ekphonetic notations and that of BL
                    Add. 12138. More broadly, it will also be of interest to biblical scholars
                    concerned with Syriac exegesis and the textual and oral transmission of the
                    Bible at the end of the first millennium.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="en" type="bibliography">
                    <head>Bibliography</head>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Avenary, H. <hi rend="italic">Studies in the Hebrew,
                        Syrian and Greek Liturgical Recitative.</hi> Tel Aviv: Israel Music
                        Institute, 1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>El-Attar, B. A. F. <hi rend="italic">Two Syriac
                        Masoretic Signs: nagoḏa and meṭappeyana</hi>. M.Phil. thesis, University
                        of London, School of Oriental and African Studies, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jourdan-Hemmerdinger, D. “Nouveaux fragments musicaux
                        sur papyrus (une notation antique par points).” In <hi rend="italic">Studies
                            in Eastern Chant IV</hi>, ed. M. Velimirović. London: St. Vladimir’s
                        Seminary Press, 1979, 81–111.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loopstra, J. “Exploring Patterns of Accentuation in the
                        Peshitta Bible: Perspectives and Possibilities.” In <hi rend="Emphasis"
                            >Contemporary Examinations of Classical Languages</hi> (<hi
                                rend="Emphasis">Hebrew</hi>, <hi rend="Emphasis">Aramaic</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="Emphasis">Syriac, and Greek</hi>), ed. A. Salvesen, T. Lewis, and
                        B. Turner. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2016, 139–165.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loopstra, J. “How to Read the Bible with the <hi
                        rend="Emphasis">Tahtaya da-tlata</hi>: Recovering an Ancient Biblical
                        Marker of Exclamation and Supplication.” In <hi rend="Emphasis">From Ancient
                            Manuscripts to Modern Dictionaries</hi>: <hi rend="Emphasis">Select
                                Studies in Aramaic</hi>, <hi rend="Emphasis">Hebrew, and Greek</hi>, ed.
                        T. Li and R. Taylor. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2017, 109–137. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Loopstra, J. “<ref
                        target="https://www.academia.edu/40676500/_The_Syriac_Reading_Dot_in_Transmission_Consistency_and_Confusion_"
                        >The Syriac Reading Dot in Transmission: Consistency and
                        Confusion”</ref>.
                        In<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Studies in Biblical Philology and Lexicography</hi>,<hi rend="Emphasis" xml:space="preserve"> </hi>ed.
                        D. King. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2019, 159–176.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loopstra, J. The Patristic “Masora”: A Study of
                        Patristic Collections in Syriac Handbooks from the Near East. CSCO 689.
                        Leuven: Peeters, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moberg, A. “Über den griechischen Ursprung der
                        syrischen Akzentuation.”
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Monde Oriental </hi>1 (1906), 87–
                        99.</bibl>
                   
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
