<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Yifat Monnickendam, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Law and
                    Early Christian Identity: Betrothal, Marriage, and Infidelity in the
                    Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Daniel</forename>
                        <surname>Picus</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Western Washington University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n1prpicus</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Daniel Picus</author>
                        <title level="a">Yifat Monnickendam, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Law and
                            Early Christian Identity: Betrothal, Marriage, and Infidelity in the
                            Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</hi></title>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N1PRPicus.pdf</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="335" to="338">335-338</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="11"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-02-12">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div>
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <ab type="review-title">Yifat Monnickendam, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Law and
                    Early Christian Identity: Betrothal, Marriage, and Infidelity in the
                    Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University
                    Press, 2020). Pp. xi + 332; $99.99.</ab>
                </div>
                
                
                <div xml:lang="en">
                <p xml:lang="en">It is a rare thing for a book to accomplish exactly what it
                    sets out to do, but Yifat Monnickendam has done precisely that, in her
                    erudite study of marriage laws in the writings of Ephrem. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jewish Law and Early Christian Identity: Betrothal, Marriage, and
                        Infidelity in the Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</hi> is a remarkable
                    accomplishment, and a groundbreaking contribution to a field that is
                    constantly evaluating the evidence of contact between Aramaic-speaking
                    Jewish and Christian communities in late antiquity. Monnickendam brings
                    together a considerable command of many sources (Roman law, Rabbinic
                    literature, Ephrem’s corpus) with a deep understanding of legal theory to
                    examine a complex and often disparate body of evidence.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Monnickendam’s investigation is shaped by her analysis
                    of four related concepts, with a chapter dedicated to each. These concepts
                    are organized through their temporal relationship to marriage: the first
                    chapter deals with the act of bethrothal itself, the second with questions
                    of cohabitation <hi rend="italic">during</hi> betrothal, the third with
                    marriage, and specifically, the question of whether or not rape requires
                    marriage after the fact, and the fourth with questions of infidelity and
                    fornication—the violation of a marriage. Each chapter moves fluidly through
                    sources that range temporally from the Hebrew Bible to Ephrem’s writings,
                    covering a millennium’s worth of evidence, and a dense web of interpretive
                    possibilities that Monnickendam skillfully delineates and analyzes.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Two aspects of Monnickendam’s argument stand out as
                    particularly important, and it is worth highlighting them here. I hasten to
                    add, of course, that I am only able to present them in the briefest of
                    terms: Monnickendam’s book is worth reading in its entirety for its nuanced
                    treatment of sources, and the keen critical eye with which they are
                    compared. Her close readings are both lucid and convincing. Rabbinic
                    literature especially can be difficult for the uninitiated, but
                    Monnickendam’s careful attention to detail ensures that even the absolute
                    beginner to rabbinic materials will gain something valuable from her
                    writing. The two most important aspects of Monnickendam’s book, in my view,
                    come from both the author’s background in legal studies and an extensive
                    training in rabbinic sources: only the combination of these two would be
                    able to produce such thought-provoking results. In that sense, this book is
                    truly interdisciplinary.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">First, following a growing trend in the study of
                    rabbinic literature, Monnickendam places the <hi rend="italic">halakhah</hi>
                    of the rabbinic movement onto a spectrum of law that runs from “positive” to
                    “naturalistic” and identifies Ephrem’s approach to sexual relations as
                    distinctively naturalistic (pp. 3, 37–30). Monnickendam is not the first to
                    think about rabbinic <hi rend="italic">halakhah</hi> in the context of Roman
                    law—indeed, this is a robust area of research.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> See, for example, Catherine
                            Hezser, “Roman Law and Rabbinic Legal Composition,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">The Cambridge Companion to the Talmud and Rabbinic
                                Literature</hi>, ed. C. Fonrobert and M. Jaffee (Cambridge:
                            Cambridge University Press, 2007), 144–164.</p></note> Using this
                    type of broad heuristic as a framing device, however, is a particularly
                    helpful and useful strategy on her part. “Law” and “<hi rend="italic"
                        >halakhah</hi>” are neither of them immediately self-evident categories,
                    but by placing them on a spectrum, and explaining how they relate to the
                    communities she is discussing, Monnickendam creates a highly suggestive
                    interpretive framework.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">“Positive” law, according to Monnickendam, refers to
                    legal writing and legislation that aims to <hi rend="italic">describe</hi>
                    the way people act and behave, and the way that larger structures—be they
                    political or religious—attempt to govern that behavior. “Natural” law, on
                    the other hand, is normative, attempting to derive laws of behavior from
                    principles that are either assumed or explicitly stated. Roman law falls on
                    the “positive” side of the spectrum, while <hi rend="italic">halakhah</hi>
                    is “natural,” but Monnickendam is swift to note, in several instances, that
                    neither of them is exclusively one or the other. It is this vision of a
                    sliding scale, moreover, that is so helpful, providing a vocabulary for
                    legal concepts and laws that <hi rend="italic">mostly</hi>, if not entirely,
                    fall on one side or the other.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Monnickendam’s most striking conclusion, however, and
                    the second critical aspect of this book, is an element of her overall
                    argument that Ephrem utilizes different legal traditions in different
                    contexts while largely reproducing ideas found in Palestinian rabbinic
                    sources. She points out that time and time again, when Ephrem’s legal
                    terminology and thinking is in line with opinions expressed in Palestinian
                    rabbinic sources, the opinions he follows, while <hi rend="italic"
                        >expressed</hi> in the Palestinian literature, are ultimately rejected
                    (p. 27). Palestinian rabbinic literature, for example, has notably less
                    severe penalties for premarital cohabitation than Roman legal literature and
                    Greek Christian literature. This is a line of thinking shared by Ephrem, and
                    ultimately rejected in Babylonian rabbinic literature (and, indeed,
                    discussed by those same rabbis as a uniquely Palestinian phenomenon, pp.
                    97–108).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This is a compelling observation, and if I have one
                    criticism of Monnickendam’s book, it is that she presents us with this
                    tantalizing analysis, but offers no concrete explanation for it. There is a
                    general sense that it is reasonable for Ephrem, a Syriac-speaking writer in
                    the general region of the Palestinian rabbis, to have access to this
                    material, likely through oral transmission, but the conditions on the ground
                    that might have enabled this are left undiscussed. Did Ephrem come across
                    <hi rend="italic">only</hi> these rejected traditions over the course of
                    his life? Did he have access to a wide variety of them, from which he picked
                    and chose selectively? If so, was that selection process a polemic against
                    the Jews in whose proximity he lived? Is this understanding of marriage and
                    related concepts deeply personal and idiosyncratic, or is it part of a
                    broader set of group understandings, and were these understandings
                    consciously arranged in opposition to another set of ideas? These are
                    possibilities without a way of being proven decisively, of course, but as
                    reflections of possible lived conditions, articulating them would lend
                    another angle to this fascinating book.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The absence of this type of reconstruction, it should
                    be noted, seems to come from the author’s robust commitment to clear,
                    analytic methodology, and an unwillingness to engage in speculation (pp.
                    22–27). However, it seems that evidence like this is what makes speculation
                    possible, and a little bit less “speculative,” when we engage in it as
                    readers and scholars. The general question of how Ephrem might have accessed
                    rabbinic ideas is broad and nebulous, to be sure, but the presence of
                    rejected rabbinic opinions points to a slightly more constrained arena of
                    possibilities that would, in all likelihood, be fruitful to reflect
                    upon.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In many ways, <hi rend="italic">Jewish Law and Early
                    Christian Identity</hi> is a model book. It delineates a clear project,
                    which it accomplishes with precision and finesse. Complicated rabbinic
                    texts, along with Ephrem’s own poetry and commentaries, are introduced
                    clearly and accessibly: a sign that readers unfamiliar with either are still
                    likely to gain much. Perhaps most valuable of all, though, Monnickendam
                    presents her findings in a way that raises still more productive questions.
                    These are not vague, mysterious questions whose answers forever elude the
                    scholar, however—or at least, not entirely. These are questions that promise
                    hours of research and stimulating, thoughtful answers; questions that, even
                    if they don’t immediately shed light on the lives and inner thoughts of
                    ancient figures like Ephrem, at least allow us to build lamps that might one
                    day be lit for that purpose. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
