<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Vth Syriac Symposium</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/conferenceReport/hv10n2crkitchen</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Vth Syriac Symposium</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Syriac Symposium</term>
               <term>Toronto</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
         <p>University of Toronto, Ontario, June 25-27,
    2007 </p>
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The Vth
    (North American) Syriac Symposium was held at the University of
    Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, June 25-27, 2007, for the
    first time outside the United States, adopting the theme of
    “Syriac as a Bridge Culture.”  Previous
    Symposiums were conducted at Brown University (1991), Catholic
    University of America (1995), University of Notre Dame (1999),
    and Princeton University (2003). Professor Amir Harrak
    headed the organizing committee to provide an excellent
    conference in terms of the range and quality of papers
    presented, the convenience of living and conference quarters at
    New College, University of Toronto, as well as a range of
    extra-curricular activities.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    Symposium keeps expanding with over 80 participants from at
    least 10 countries who listened to 55 papers and presentations,
    and generally spent most of their days conversing on matters
    Syriac during meals, coffee breaks and special events.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Sidney
    H. Griffith of Catholic University of America gave the opening
    lecture, “Syrian Christian Intellectuals in the World of
    Islam: Faith, the Philosophical Life, and the Quest for
    Interreligious <hi rend="italic">Convivencia</hi> in Abbasid
    Times.” Other plenary speakers were: Elisabetta
    Valgiusti of the Association ‘Salva i Monasteri’,
    Rome, who presented a lecture and film produced by her,
    “Syriac Christianity in the Iraqi Exodus: A People of
    Prophets Between Hope and Hopelessness”; John H. Corbett
    of University of Toronto-Scarborough, presented the first of a
    series of papers on the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>, “The
    Ascetic Life as Holy War: The Biblical Basis of the <hi rend="italic">Book of
    Steps</hi>”; Lucas Van Rompay of Duke University,
    presented a magisterial review of “Severus, Patriarch of
    Antioch (512-538), in the Greek, Syriac, and Coptic
    traditions”; and Craig E. Morrison of the Pontifical
    Biblical Institute, Rome, addressed directly the
    conference’s theme, “The Bridge from Judaism: The
    Jews in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the
    Diatessaron</hi>.”  The plenary papers will be
    published in the 2007 volume of the <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian
    Society of Syriac Studies</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    papers presented offered a striking range and diversity of
    topic and theme. Sessions were held on the use of the
    Bible in Syriac exegesis, focus on specific books, history of
    medieval and modern Syriac churches, hagiography and
    asceticism, textual studies of the Peshitta, Modern Syriac and
    Neo-Aramaic, studies of the Assyrian Christians in the
    20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century Near East, studies of various Syriac
    liturgies, architecture and Syriac inscriptions, the
    relationship between Syriac Christianity and Islam and
    Judaism. The Fifth International Forum on Syriac Computing
    revealed as always remarkable new developments in computer
    tools, programs, and resources for the needs of Syriac
    scholars.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5]
    Socially, the conferees were not neglected.  Gorgias Press
    and the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies co-hosted an
    evening reception at the Department of Near and Middle Eastern
    Studies a short walk away. At the close of the academic
    portion of the Symposium, conferees were transported to the
    Cathedral Church of Saint Mary for a Syriac Vespers presided by
    His Grace Mar Emmanuel, Bishop of the Assyrian Church of the
    East in Canada (and a new doctoral candidate at the University
    of Toronto, working on Johannan bar Penkaye), followed by a
    banquet in honor of the Symposium participants in the spacious
    Sharrukin Hall in the church.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] At the
    closing session, Lucas Van Rompay’s offer to host the
    VIth Syriac Symposium at Duke University, Durham, North
    Carolina, in 2011 was gratefully accepted. The steering
    committee of the Symposium - Sidney Griffith, Susan Ashbrook
    Harvey, Kathleen McVey, and George Kiraz - augmented their
    numbers to include Amir Harrak, Lucas Van Rompay, and a
    representative of the Dorushe Graduate Student Association.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    abstracts of the papers presented at the Vth Syriac Symposium
    can be accessed <ref target="HV10No2VthSyriacSymposiumAbstracts.pdf">here</ref>.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>