<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Kthobonoyo Syriac: Some Observations and Remarks</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>George A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kiraz </surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/paper/hv10n2kiraz</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>George A. Kiraz </author>
                  <title level="a">Kthobonoyo Syriac: Some Observations and Remarks</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N2Kiraz.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Kthobonoyo</term>
               <term>Modern Syriac</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>This paper gives some observations and
    preliminary remarks on Kthobonoyo, the spoken form of classical
    Syriac as used in the twentieth and twenty first centuries. It
    presents a brief history of Kthobonoyo usage, and outlines its
    linguistic and sociolinguistic features.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->

         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz3">Introduction</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Recent
    history, beginning in the early decades of the twentieth
    century, witnessed a revival in the utilization of classical
    Syriac in both written and oral forms. Written utilization was
    not primarily in the form of religious-oriented literature as
    one may expect, but in various secular genres including
    national and ethnic-oriented poetry and prose, as well as
    journalism. Oral utilization became to be centralized around
    pop poetry and lyrics set to music (although a few written
    exceptions have been noted),<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> radio broadcasting,<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> and the use of
    classical Syriac as a spoken medium of communication. While the
    written modality of this period has been studied by
    Brock,<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> Knudsen,<ref target="#FN4">4</ref> and Wardini,<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> there are no publications
    that I am aware of on the spoken modality which I shall refer
    to as Spoken Classical Syriac (SCS). What I aim to do here is
    to give some preliminary remarks on the subject. It must be
    stressed from the outset that the remarks made herein are
    entirely observational. A serious study would require a corpus
    of recorded spoken conversations which is now not
    available.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] I shall
    begin with some terminology leading to a definition of
    Kthobonoyo, the form of SCS discussed in this paper. I shall
    then describe the history of Kthobonoyo in the twentieth
    century, following it with a preliminary account of the
    characteristics and features of this form of Syriac.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz4">Terms and Definitions</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] SCS is
    referred to with the Syriac term <hi rend="italic">leshono kthobonoyo</hi>,
    somewhat a misnomer as it literally means ‘the written
    language,’ and less often with the term <hi rend="italic">leshono
    sephroyo</hi> ‘the book language.’ For instance,
    one may hear the English utterance “He is speaking
    <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi>.” It is important to note that the
    term <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi> does not usually refer to the written
    form, despite its literal meaning. The term <hi rend="italic">suryoyo</hi> is
    reserved for the written modality; e.g., “She is
    reading/writing <hi rend="italic">suryoyo</hi>.” Moreover,
    <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi> is sometimes used to distinguish SCS from
    the Turoyo and Swadaya vernaculars.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4]
    Intriguingly, none of the printed lexica assign the spoken
    modality to the term <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi>. Brockelmann<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> and
    Smith<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> explain
    ܟܬܒܢܝܐ with Latin
    <hi rend="italic">scriptus</hi> “written,” and the latter adds
    <hi rend="italic">scripto consignatus</hi> “sealed in writing.”
    Audo<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> gives
    ܕܐܬܬܫܠܡ
    ܒܟܬܝܒܬܐ “that
    which was handed down by writing.” Margoliouth<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> does not
    cite the term at all. Instead, the lexica reserve for the
    spoken modality the shorter form <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi>. Here, Smith
    gives, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, the phrase
    ܡܡܠܠܐ
    ܟܬܒܝܐ, explains it with <hi rend="italic">sermo
    qualis est in libris</hi> “talking as it is in
    books,” and cites Étienne-Marc Quatremère
    (1782-1857), <hi rend="italic">la langue écrite, le style des
    livres</hi> “[sermon like] the written language, in the
    style of books.” Audo gives ܠܫܢܐ
    ܟܬܒܝܐ and explains it with
    ܗ̇ܘ ܕܟܬܒ̈ܐ.
    ܒܗܦܟܐ
    ܕܣܘܕܝܐ “[the
    language] of the books, on the contrary of swadaya [the spoken
    colloquial]” (here Audo’s explanation implicitly
    refers to the spoken modality as he contrasts <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi>
    with Swadaya). Margoliouth cites <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi>, but is the
    only one who does not give reference to the spoken modality;
    instead, she explains it with “literary language or
    style.” Brockelmann does not cite <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] While
    there is certainly an interchangeability between the suffixes
    ܳܝܳܐ and
    ܳܢܳܝܳܐ (e.g., in
    ܣܘܕܢܝܐ and
    ܣܘܕܝܐ), <ref target="#FN10">10</ref> it is not clear
    why modern usage did not opt for
    ܟܬܒܝܐ instead of
    ܟܬܒܢܝܐ to reference the
    spoken modality as it already exists in the printed lexica. The
    term is familiar to <hi rend="italic">malphone</hi> from the first sentence
    of the Prologue of Bar ‛Ebroyo’s <hi rend="u">S</hi>em<hi rend="u">h</hi>e,
    “ܓܪܡܛܝܩܝ
    ܐܝܬܝܗ̇
    ܝܕܥܬܐ
    ܕܡܢܗ̇
    ܡܬܝܠܦܝܢ
    ܩܢܘܢ̈ܐ
    ܕܒܢܛܘܪܘܬܗܘܢ
    ܦܘܕܐ
    ܠܥܙܢܝܐ ܡܢ
    ܡܡܠܠܐ
    ܟܬܒܝܐ
    ܕܒܚܝܪ
    ܡ̇ܪܚ—Grammar is the knowledge from
    which are learned rules with whose observance the vernacular
    mistake is distinguished from the accurate <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi>
    speech.” (There is always the remote possibility that
    ܟܬܒܢܝܐ was used in earlier
    periods to denote the spoken form, but this meaning was not
    recorded in any of the lexica.)</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    definition of <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi> can be further defined along
    time and demography. While SCS was used in earlier times and
    perhaps continuously until the present, the lack of historical
    records makes it impossible to ascertain any of its linguistic
    features. For this reason alone, I opt to limit the definition
    of <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi> to twentieth and twenty-first century
    usage, and reserve the more general term, ‘SCS,’
    for earlier periods if needed.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] As for
    demography, <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi> is primarily, and probably
    exclusively, a feature known in West Syriac and more precisely
    amongst the Syrian Orthodox, with a few hundred speakers or so
    at various competence levels. This is not to deny other
    religious communities who have competent scholars that can even
    converse in it.<ref target="#FN11">11</ref> In the late 1960s and early 1970s, for
    instance, the Syriac Catholic Monastery of Sharfeh had courses
    run by Abrohom Nuro on conversational Syriac. Earlier, the
    Maronite scholar Joseph Hobaïca published a guide for
    conversational Syriac with Arabic and French
    translations.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref> As for East Syriac, the number of its speakers
    is quite small and does not form a speaking community.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref> This
    striking absence of the spoken modality amongst the modern
    Assyrians and Chaldeans is probably due to the fact that
    Swadaya, the colloquial, had raised itself to a literary
    language in the past few centuries.<ref target="#FN14">14</ref> This is echoed in the term
    used to refer to the classical language in East Syriac:
    ܠܫܢܐ
    ܥܬܝܩܐ l<hi rend="italic">eshshana
    ‛attiqa</hi> ‘the old language’, as opposed
    to the modern written language. <hi rend="u">T</hi>uroyo,
    the vernacular of the West Syriac speakers, on the other hand,
    remains a vernacular and efforts to write it down have always
    been resisted by the clergy and <hi rend="italic">malphone</hi> (though there
    are some recent attempts to use it in written form). One finds
    a similar pattern in the use of classical Syriac in written
    form. Brock<ref target="#FN15">15</ref> notes that during the twentieth century, the
    written literary production of West Syriac is by far more
    extensive than that in East Syriac. Ironically, it was East
    Syriac writers, like Touma Audo and Awgin Manna, who surpassed
    their western counterparts in producing lexical and grammatical
    works in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Because
    <hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi>, as we shall shortly see, has its own
    identity, users, style, and idiosyncrasies that distinguish it
    from the written form of classical Syriac, it qualifies to be
    considered a subtype of Syriac. Hereinafter, I shall use the
    term ‘Kthobonoyo Syriac’ or simply
    ‘Kthobonoyo’ (capitalized and unitalicized).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] To
    summarize our definition, Kthobonoyo is the spoken, not
    written, form of classical Syriac as used in the twentieth and
    twenty first centuries. (One can designate the written form by
    ‘Modern Literary Syriac’ following Knudsen and
    Wardini). The rest of this paper discusses the use of
    Kthobonoyo in the twentieth and twenty first centuries, and
    then briefly outline some of its linguistic and sociolinguistic
    characteristics and features.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz5">Use of Kthobonoyo in the Twentieth Century</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    While Kthobonoyo was just defined as a subtype of Syriac that
    belongs to the twentieth and twenty-first centuries, it was
    born from an earlier tradition of SCS. How far was SCS used and
    to what extent is hard to ascertain. The lexical definitions of
    the term <hi rend="italic">kthoboyo</hi> by Smith and Oddo are a testimony to
    its existence.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Necessity must have dictated the use of SCS at least amongst
    the clergy. In recent centuries, the linguistic background of
    the church hierarchy in the Middle East included <hi style="text-decoration: underline">T</hi>uroyo-, Arabic-,
    Armenian-, Turkish- and Kurdish-speakers. While most of the
    clergy were conversant in more than one language, there may
    have been cases where a common language was not available, in
    which case SCS would have been the only choice. This, of
    course, is a mere conjecture, and if indeed SCS was practiced,
    its use would have been quite limited.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] The
    communication between the Church hierarchy of the Middle East
    and its flock in India provides clearer evidence for the use of
    SCS in earlier periods. At least since the seventeenth century,
    visiting bishops to Malabar had no knowledge of Malayalam, the
    indigenous language of the Syriac Christians of India, and in
    reverse the local clergy knew none of the Middle Eastern
    languages apart from Classical Syriac. While sometimes Arabic
    translators were used, much of the communication relied on
    Syriac. Until this day, one finds a few Kthobonoyo speakers
    amongst the Malayalees, although the number is dwindling, being
    replaced by English. The use of SCS as a mean of communication
    continued until the Kthobonoyo age of the twentieth
    century.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Another reason that gave rise to the use of Kthobonoyo in the
    early twentieth century is national identity, which intensified
    in 1908 when the Turkish İttihat ve Terakki Cemiyeti
    (Committee of Union and Progress, CUP), or the Young Turks,
    revolted against the Ottoman sultan, and forced him to restore
    the Ottoman constitution of 1876. This gave an opportunity to
    many <hi rend="italic">millet</hi> communities to form secular organizations
    and movements that gave rise to a spirit of nationalism. Within
    the Syrian Orthodox church, the <hi rend="italic">‛irutho</hi> movement
    was formed with much enthusiasm from activists like
    Na‛‛um Faiq. Unity was the main focus, not only
    unity within the Syrian Orthodox church, but also with other
    communities that belonged to the same “nation,”
    such as the Assyrians, Chaldeans, Syrian Catholics and
    Maronites. Hence, a notion of <hi rend="italic">'umtonoyuto</hi> (belonging
    to a ‘people’ or ‘nation’) was
    developed, and in turn a movement of Syriac revival came into
    being. Proponents of Syriac revival saw in the use of SCS but
    one method with which the language can be revived. Speakers of
    Kthobonoyo in the first half of the twentieth century included
    educators such as Youhanna Dolabani (1885-1969), and later
    Kthobonoyo was promoted by Fawlos Gabriel (1912-1971),
    Abdulmasih Qarabashi (1903-1983), Abrohom Nuro (1923-), and
    others.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] In
    the second half of the twentieth century, the use of Kthobonoyo
    was enforced in the seminaries and some of the village schools
    in Tur Abdin. It was not unusual for a pupil to receive a
    punishment if heard speaking in a tongue other than Kthobonoyo.
    Even <hi rend="u">T</hi>uroyo was prohibited in schools.
    Teachers would go to the extent of assigning some pupils as
    ‘watchers’ whose duty is to report other pupils
    when they speak in a non-Kthobonoyo language. This attitude is
    echoed in a statement made in Kthobonoyo by Malphono Isa Garis,
    director of students at Mor Gabriel Monastery,
    “ܠܦܘܬ
    ܪܥܝܢܝ ܟܠ
    ܡܠܦܢܐ
    ܕܐܝܢܐ
    ܠܫܢܐ ܕܗ̣ܘ܆
    ܐܢܗܘ ܕܥܡ
    ܬܠܡܝܕܘܗܝ
    ܒܠܫܢܐ
    ܕܡ̇ܠܦ ܠܗܘܢ
    ܠܐ ܡܣܬܘܕ܆
    ܗ̇ܘ ܡܠܦܢܐ
    ܠܐ ܥ̇ܒܕ
    ܘܠܝܬܗ.
    ܘܐܦܠܐ
    ܟܫܪܐ
    ܡܠܦܢܘܬܗ—in my
    opinion, if any teacher, of whatever language, does not
    converse in the language which he is teaching, then he is not
    doing that which is right, and his training will not be
    successful.”<ref target="#FN16">16</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    Kthobonoyo was given a push after the immigration of the Syrian
    Orthodox from the Middle East to Europe in the 1960s and 1970s.
    Immigrants came from various diverse linguistic backgrounds. In
    the diaspora, they acquired English, Swedish, French, German,
    Dutch, Flemish, or Italian. Finding a common language is not
    always possible, and amongst the clergy and <hi rend="italic">malphone</hi>,
    Kthobonoyo started to serve as a mini lingua franca. I can
    report from a personal experience how I had no choice but to
    communicate in Kthobonoyo. That was during a visit to the
    Monastery of St. Ephrem in Holland in 1988, the purpose of
    which was to teach the monks how to use the then newly released
    Syriac MLS fonts.<ref target="#FN17">17</ref> The monk who was assigned to learn this
    new technology from me spoke <hi rend="u">T</hi>uroyo,
    Swedish, and a bit of Dutch, none of which I mastered. The only
    common language available to both of us was Kthobonoyo. I found
    myself struggling not only to communicate in a language that I
    have hitherto used only in a liturgical context, albeit for
    fifteen years, but also had to translate and coin, sometimes on
    the spot, computer terminology to get the lessons across. This
    experience gave rise to a number of neologisms:
    ܡܪܬܝܢܐ
    “monitor,” ܠܘܚܐ
    ܕܩܠܝ̈ܕܐ
    “keyboard,” and of course
    ܦܘܢ̈ܛܐ “fonts.”
    Instantaneous coinage of terms is one of the linguistic
    features of Kthobonoyo as we shall shortly see.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Today, Kthobonoyo has become more popular. One finds speakers
    communicating in Kthobonoyo even when their linguistic
    backgrounds give rise to another common, sometimes native
    language. Attendees of Syriac Symposia are now hearing
    Kthobonoyo more often.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz6">Characteristics and Features of Kthobonoyo
    Syriac</head>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz7">Nativeness and Aptitude</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    Kthobonoyo, as the <hi rend="italic">fu<!--<u>-->sh<!--</u>-->ā</hi> of Arabic, is
    primarily a learned, non-native language that requires formal
    training. Very few cases where Kthobonoyo is a native language
    do exist, and one such case was reported during the Syriac
    Symposium in Princeton in 2003 and this year’s Aram
    conference in Chicago.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref> In all of these cases, the
    children who acquire Kthobonoyo as a native language are
    multilingual children, speaking at least two other
    languages.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] The
    aptitude level of Kthobonoyo speakers varies tremendously,
    despite the fact that speakers tend to be clergymen and
    <hi rend="italic">malphone</hi> well versed in Classical Syriac. There are
    two main factors that affect aptitude: the level of mastering
    Classical Syriac, and the extent to which the speakers’
    social context allows them to use Kthobonoyo. Any shift in
    these factors has a direct affect on the speaker’s
    aptitude. I am happy to provide a personal example. I began
    speaking Kthobonoyo in 1988 with a low aptitude level. As I
    began reading Syriac on daily basis as part of my M.St. degree
    in Oxford in 1990-1991, my Kthobonoyo aptitude increased
    tremendously, especially that concurrently I had the
    opportunity to speak it on regular basis with two friends in
    London until 1996. After I moved back to the US in 1996, I had
    little chance to speak Kthobonoyo and my aptitude level
    decreased until I decided to speak it at home with my
    children.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz8">Male Centricity</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] A
    significant sociolinguistic feature of Kthobonoyo, one which
    sets it apart from most other languages, is its male
    centricity. Most speakers are either clergy (by definition
    male) and/or male <hi rend="italic">malphone</hi>, with very few female
    speakers. The result is an intriguing peculiarity of a language
    that is morphologically gender sensitive.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] At
    least two types of gender related ill-usage are observed in the
    use of verbal forms, even when speakers have an average
    mastering of the written language. In male-female dialogues,
    the second person verbal paradigm is misused in <hi rend="italic">both</hi>
    directions. Males often address females in a mixture of
    masculine and feminine forms. This observation was made when a
    number of speakers, including myself, addressed my
    Kthobonoyo-speaking daughter Tabetha; e.g., *ܠܐ
    ܬܐܙܠ instead of ܠܐ
    ܬܐܙܠܝܢ “do not
    go.” This often happens in imperfect forms that end in
    the suffix –<hi rend="italic">in</hi>, whereby the speaker may wrongly
    assume a silent <hi rend="italic">yudh</hi> ending. I have also observed
    adult females addressing males in a mixture of masculine and
    feminine forms; e.g., *ܐܢܬ
    ܐܡܪܐ ܐܢܬ instead of
    ܐܢܬ ܐܡܪ
    ܐܢܬ “you say.” Such ill-usage of
    verbal forms takes place when the speakers are new to each
    other. If and when the experience between the two speakers
    grows, less and less mistakes are made.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] The
    other ill-formed usage of verbs that was observed takes place
    in third feminine forms. In a dialogue I had with an adult
    <hi rend="italic">malphono</hi>, he was continuously referring to his wife in
    the masculine when constructing an ‘imperfect +
    ܕ’ form; e.g., *ܟܕ
    ܒܥܝܐ
    ܕܢܐܙܠ instead of ܟܕ
    ܒܥܝܐ
    ܕܬܐܙܠ “when she wants to
    go.” This <hi rend="italic">malphono</hi> in question was of course
    aware of the proper verbal conjugation in the written form, but
    as referring to a female is not common in Kthobonoyo, the wrong
    verbal form was used.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] This
    male dominant feature of Kthobonoyo has effects beyond
    morphology and syntax. It puts, for example, a limitation on
    the genres of dialogues that take place. While one may imagine
    gender related topics discussed, one is guaranteed that they
    are always given from a male perspective. Additionally, the
    social status of speakers puts a limitation to the range of
    topics which are usually under discussion. Matters of church
    and community are common, but dialogues on the latest in pop
    culture are probably far fetched.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz9">Code Switching</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] Code
    switching is when lexemes from another language infiltrate a
    dialogue, e.g.,<lb/>
    “interdisciplinary ܐܝܬ
    ܗܘܐ ܠܢ
    ܟܢܘܫܝܐ—we had an
    interdisciplinary meeting.”<lb/>
    Various factors affect the use of code switching; these include
    formality, subject matter of dialogue, competence of the
    speakers, and the availability or absence of another common
    language.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24]
    Formal dialogues exhibit less code switching than informal
    ones. Such dialogues take place between people who may have
    just been introduced, or between two speakers of two different
    social classes (e.g., a bishop with a lay person)—and of
    course one is trying to impress the other of one’s
    competence in Kthobonoyo! When a word is needed on the spot and
    the speaker cannot think of it, the speaker may go around by
    explaining it with a phrase to avoid code switching.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25] The
    subject matter of the dialogue is a major factor in affecting
    code switching. Mere formalities and niceties are well
    represented in Kthobonoyo that hardly any code switching is
    necessary. But discussions of current affairs, serious topics,
    or technology related matters require much code switching such
    as the “interdisciplinary” example given above.
    Sometimes even niceties demand code switching. I am not aware
    of a Kthobonoyo term that expresses the full emotions of
    missing someone. Of course, one can opt for something like
    ܠܗܩ ܠܚܙܝܐ
    ‘eager to see’. But would one really want to use it
    after not seeing one’s daughter for a month! I
    prefer<lb/>
    “ܠܟܝ ܣܓܝ
    <hi rend="italic">miss</hi> ܒܐܒܐ (Daddy misses you a
    lot).”</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26] The
    availability or absence of another common language between the
    two speakers also affects code switching. When such a language
    is available, and especially in informal and serious
    discussion, it is easy to fall back to the second language in
    order to provide for technical terms. But when no such language
    exists, one has to find a way to express oneself without code
    switching.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27] The
    more the speaker is lexically competent in literary Syriac, the
    less code switching takes place. The primary challenge here is
    that much of the lexemes that are unique to Kthobonoyo are not
    systematically recorded (e.g., ܒܝܬ
    ܛܘܣܐ ‘airport,’
    ܬܟܪܙܬܐ ‘radio,’
    ܨܘܪܩܠܐ
    ‘television’), and one has to find them by digging
    up modern dictionaries that mix Classical Syriac with
    Kthobonoyo vocabulary.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz10">The Lexicon: Neologism and Coinage</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28] The
    primary difference between Kthobonoyo and the written modality
    is in the lexicon. On the one hand, the Kthobonoyo lexicon
    employs many new additions, and gives some of the existing
    words a new meaning. On the other hand, the Kthobonoyo lexicon
    employs only a subset of the larger literary lexicon. Much of
    Kthobonoyo vocabulary can be found in recent dictionaries,
    though always mixed with Modern and Classical Literary
    Syriac.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref> The neologisms put forward by Abrohom Nuro are
    the expection.<ref target="#FN20">20</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29]
    There are instances when a new word is coined when there is in
    fact an equivalent in the written lexicon. I, for instance,
    coined ܡܝ̈ܐ
    ܕܦܐܪ̈ܐ ‘water of
    fruits’ for ‘juice’ and used it for some
    years until Abrohom Nuro pointed out
    ܬܪܝܐ.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30] In
    some cases, nominal variants of the same root are used for the
    same semantic feature by different speakers. I always used with
    my daughter ܗܒ ܠܝ
    ܢܘܫܩܬܐ ‘give me a
    kiss.’ The use of
    ܢܘܫܩܬܐ is motivated from
    the prayer of the Kiss of Peace from the Liturgy of St. James.
    Malphono Abrohom Nuru, however, opted for ܗܒ
    ܠܝ ܢܘܫܩܐ, to which
    Tabetha responded without any problem.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31]
    Kthobonoyo is rich in neologisms and coined terms, but as just
    mentioned there is no systematic recording of these terms.
    Sometimes a term is coined on the spot. For instance, when
    (then) my 3 ½ year old daughter and I were walking in an
    airport and we reached the escalator-like ‘moving
    floor’, my inquisitive daughter asked,
    “ܗܢܐ ܡܘܢ
    ܐܝܬܘܗܝ؟.” I
    instantaneously replied, “ܗܢܐ
    ܡܗܠܟ݂ܢܐ
    ܐܝܬܘܗܝ.” Others may
    coin a different word which results in an object having
    different lexical representations in Kthobonoyo.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz11">Simplified Grammar</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32]
    While the phonology and morphology of Kthobonoyo are quite
    similar to Classical Syriac, the syntax of Kthobonoyo is a
    subset of that of the classical language.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] The
    nominal absolute state is less frequent in Kthobonoyo, as well
    as the construct state (e.g., Kthobonoyo
    ܡܠܟܐ
    ܕܐܣܦܐܢܝܐ for
    Classical Syriac ܡܠܟ
    ܐܣܦܐܢܝܐ ‘the
    king of Spain’). Having said that, one finds common
    constructs such as ܪܝܫ
    ܟܪܟ݂ܘܬܐ
    ܕܠܘܣܪ ‘the mayor of
    Losser.’</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34]
    Other grammatical features are absent in Kthobonoyo. Possessive
    and object suffixes of complex verbs are avoided (e.g.,
    Kthobonoyo ܩܪܐ ܠܝ for Classical
    Syriac ܩܪܢܝ ‘he called
    me’). Active participle forms are used primarily as
    present tense verbs and hardly as nouns. The infinitive is
    quite infrequent, especially with an object (e.g., Kthobonoyo
    ܐܝܟܢܐ
    ܕܢܠܦ ܐܢܘܢ for
    Classical Syriac ܠܡܠܦܘ
    ܐܢܘܢ).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35]
    Nominal clauses with pronoun contractions are hardly heard in
    Kthobonoyo, but are quite frequent in literary Syriac. When
    Sebastian P. Brock was playing with his three-year old namesake
    Sebastian-Kenoro a game of hide-and-seek, he would use the
    literary form ܐܝܟܢܐ (i.e.,
    ܐܝܟܐ ܐܢܐ), where one
    would expect in Kthobonoyo the longer simplified form
    ܐܝܟܐ ܐܝܬܝ. The
    substitution of the ܐܝܬ-structure in place of
    contracted pronouns is quite frequent in Kthobonoyo.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P36"/>[36] Word
    order is less free in Kthobonoyo than in Classical Syriac. In
    Kthobonoyo, the verb is hardly at the end of a phrase or
    sentence, while in Classical Syriac one case place the verb in
    various positions of the sentence.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz12">Conclusion</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P37"/>[37] This
    paper gave some observations and remarks on Kthobonoyo, the
    spoken form of classical Syriac as used in the twentieth and
    twenty first centuries. We have seen that Kthobonoyo is a
    continuation of the tradition of speaking classical Syriac from
    earlier centuries, but was encouraged in our period due to
    necessity and national identity. Kthobonoyo has its own
    linguistic and sociolinguistic features such as male
    centricity, the strong use of code switching, and the lexical
    idiosyncrasies. A more thorough investigation of the topic,
    especially around syntax and usage, would ideally require a
    recorded corpus. ܫܠܡ
    ܘܠܕܘܝܐ
    ܕܟܬܒ
    ܫܘܒܩܢܐ.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz13">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> Published lyrics set to musical notation include
    Gabriel Asad’s ܡܢ
    ܡܘܣܝܩܝ
    ܕܝܠܢ ܚܕܬܐ
    (Aleppo, 1953), [Laila Haddad], ܗܫܐ
    ܙܡܪܝܢܢ:
    ܙܡܝܪ̈ܬܐ
    ܒܠܫܢܐ
    ܣܘܪܝܝܐ
    ܘܣܘܕܝܐ
    (Jönköping, 1998), <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> The first broadcasting in Classical Syriac was by
    Abrohom Nuro in Lebanon in the 1970s. Radio Qolo from Sweden
    broadcasts some interviews in Kthobonoyo, while its usual
    broadcasting is a Kthobonized form of Turoyo. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> S.P. Brock, ‘Some Observations on the Use of
    Classical Syriac in the Late Twentieth Century,’
    <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi>, XXXIV/2 (1989), 363-75.
    <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> E. E. Knudsen, ‘Lexical Innovations in Modern
    Literary Syriac’, in René Lavenant (ed.),
    <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum VII</hi>, 545-51; E. E. Knudsen,
    ‘An important step in the revival of literary Syriac:
    Abrohom Nouro’s Tawldotho’, <hi rend="italic">Oriens
    Christianus</hi> 84 (2000), 59-65. <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> E. Wardini, ‘Neologisms in MLS’,
    <hi rend="italic">Melanges de l'Universite Saint-Joseph</hi> 53:5 (1993/4),
    401-566, and 54 (1995/6), 167-324; E. Wardini, ‘Modern
    Literary Syriac: A Case of Linguistic Divorce’, in
    René Lavenant (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum VII</hi>,
    pp.517-25; E. Wardini, <hi rend="italic">Neologisms in Modern Literary
    Syriac: Some Preliminary Results</hi> (Dissertation, Oslo
    1995). <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> Karl Brockelmann, <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum</hi> (Georg
    Olms Verlag reprint, 1982). <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> Robert Payne Smith, <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus [Syriac
    Thesaurus]</hi> (Gorgias Press reprint, 2007). <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> Thomas Audo, ܣܝܡܬܐ
    ܕܠܫܢܐ
    ܣܘܪܝܝܐ (Mosul, 1897).
    <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> J. Payne Smith (Mrs. Margoliouth), <hi rend="italic">A
    Compendious Syriac Dictionary</hi> (Eisenbrauns reprint, 1998).
    <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> Brockelmann:
    ܣܘܕܝܐ alloquens;
    ܣܘܕܢܝܐ no entry. Smith:
    ܣܘܕܝܐ ad allocutionem pertinens,
    compellativus; ܣܘܕܢܝܐ
    colloquialis, ܐܡܪܝܢ
    ܒܙܢܐ
    ܣܘܕܝܐ. Margolioth:
    ܣܘܕܝܐ vocative, allocutory;
    ܣܘܕܢܝܐ colloquial,
    conversational. Audo states that both forms are synonyms and
    refer to the colloquial language. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> For instance, during the Louvain Symposium
    Syriacum, one was able to hear Alber Abbouna converse with
    Malphono Abrohom Nuro in the classical language in East Syriac
    pronunciation. Just recently, I had a very lengthy and serious
    discussion (not mere niceties and formalities) with Fr.
    Emmanuel Youkhannan who conversed with me very eloquently and
    in the Western dialect. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> Pierre Hobeïca, <hi rend="italic">Premiere Guide
    Pratique De la conversation dans la langue syriaque,
    “texte syriaque, arabe, français”, Manuel
    specialement destine</hi> (Beirut, my copy does not have the
    cover and is not dated), Part I (I do not know if a second part
    was published). <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> Malpana Daniel Benjamin, who comes from a
    family of printers and publishers, tells me that while very few
    Chaldeans and fewer Assyrians can converse in SCS, he has not
    heard it himself (e-mail communication, 7/4/03). <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> H. L. Murre-Van den Berg, <hi rend="italic">From a Spoken
    to a Written Language, The Introduction and Development of
    Literary Urmia Aramaic in the Nineteenth Century</hi> (1999).
    <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Brock, <hi rend="italic">Some Observations</hi>, p. 364.
    <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Heto [<hi style="text-decoration: underline">H</hi>e<hi rend="u">t</hi>o]</hi>, vol. 5, nos 8-9, 2003, p. 46. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> Gamma Productions, <hi rend="italic">Multi-Lingual
    Scholar, Wordprocessor User’s Manual</hi> (Santa Monica,
    1989); G. A. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Alaph Beth Font Kit User’s
    Guide</hi> (Los Angeles, 1989). <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> G. A. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tabetha Syriac</hi>
    (forthcoming). <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> Recent dictionaries containing Kthobonoyo
    terms include Issa Hanna, <hi rend="italic">Mini-Wörterbuch
    Deutsch-Assyrisch</hi> (1984); Simon Atto, <hi rend="italic">Nederlands
    Suryoyo Woordenboek</hi> (1986); Simon Atto,
    <hi rend="italic">Süryanice-Türkçe Sözlük</hi>
    (1988); Aziz Bulut, <hi rend="italic">Woordenboek Nederlands-Syrisch,
    Syrisch-Nederlands</hi> (1993); Hatune Dogan,
    <hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch Syrisch-Deutsch, Deutsch-Syrisch</hi>
    (Aleppo, 1997); Odisho Ashitha, <hi rend="italic">Hilqa de Leshana
    Assyrian-Arabic Dictionary</hi> (1977); Younan Hozaya and
    Anderios Youkhana, <hi rend="italic">Bahra Arabic-Assyrian Dictionary</hi>
    (1998); Sabo Hanno and Aziz Bulut, <hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch
    Deutsch-Aramäisch, Aramäisch-Deutsch</hi> (2000);
    Shlemon Khoshaba and Emanuel Yokhanna, <hi rend="italic">Zahreera
    Arabic-Syriac Dictionary</hi> (2000); Joseph Malke,
    ܒܪ̈ܘܠܐ
    ܣܘܪ̈ܝܝܐ
    [Syriac-Arabic, Arabic-Syriac] (2003); Gabriel Afram,
    <hi rend="italic">Svensk Assyrisk ordbok</hi> (2005). <ref target="#FNRef19"/>
            <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> Abrohom Nuro, <hi rend="italic">Tawldotho or Syriac
    Neologisms, Principles, Criteria and Examples</hi> (1997); Nuro
    also put together a word list circulated privately in Syriac,
    Arabic, English and French. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Kiraz14">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Afram, Gabriel. <hi rend="italic">Svensk Assyrisk
    ordbok</hi> (2005).</p>
         <p>Asad, Gabriel. ܡܢ
    ܡܘܣܝܩܝ
    ܕܝܠܢ ܚܕܬܐ
    (Aleppo, 1953).</p>
         <p>Ashitha, Odisho. <hi rend="italic">Hilqa de Leshana
    Assyrian-Arabic Dictionary</hi> (1977).</p>
         <p>Atto, Simon. <hi rend="italic">Nederlands Suryoyo
    Woordenboek</hi> (1986).</p>
         <p>Atto, Simon.
    <hi rend="italic">Süryanice-Türkçe Sözlük</hi>
    (1988).</p>
         <p>Audo, Thomas.
    ܣܝܡܬܐ
    ܕܠܫܢܐ
    ܣܘܪܝܝܐ (Mosul, 1897).</p>
         <p>Brock, S. P. ‘Some Observations
    on the Use of Classical Syriac in the Late Twentieth
    Century,’ <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi>, XXXIV/2
    (1989), 363-75.</p>
         <p>Brockelmann, Karl. <hi rend="italic">Lexicon
    Syriacum</hi> (Georg Olms Verlag reprint, 1982).</p>
         <p>Bulut, Aziz. <hi rend="italic">Woordenboek
    Nederlands-Syrisch, Syrisch-Nederlands</hi> (1993).</p>
         <p>Dogan, Hatune. <hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch
    Syrisch-Deutsch, Deutsch-Syrisch</hi> (Aleppo, 1997).</p>
         <p>Gamma Productions, <hi rend="italic">Multi-Lingual
    Scholar, Wordprocessor User’s Manual</hi> (Santa Monica,
    1989).</p>
         <p>Haddad, Laila. ܗܫܐ
    ܙܡܪܝܢܢ:
    ܙܡܝܪ̈ܬܐ
    ܒܠܫܢܐ
    ܣܘܪܝܝܐ
    ܘܣܘܕܝܐ
    (Jönköping, 1998).</p>
         <p>Hanna, Issa.
    <hi rend="italic">Mini-Wörterbuch Deutsch-Assyrisch</hi> (1984).</p>
         <p>Hanno, Sabo, and Bulut, Aziz
    <hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch Deutsch-Aramäisch,
    Aramäisch-Deutsch</hi> (2000).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Heto [<hi style="text-decoration: underline">H</hi>e<hi style="text-decoration: underline">t</hi>o]</hi>, vol. 5, nos 8-9,
    2003, p. 46.</p>
         <p>Hobeïca, Pierre. <hi rend="italic">Premiere
    Guide Pratique De la conversation dans la langue syriaque,
    “texte syriaque, arabe, français”, Manuel
    specialement destine</hi> (Beirut, my copy does not have the
    cover and is not dated), Part I (I do not know if a second part
    was published).</p>
         <p>Khoshaba, Shlemon, and Yokhanna,
    Emanuel. Zahreera Arabic-Syriac Dictionary (2000).</p>
         <p>Kiraz, G. A. <hi rend="italic">Alaph Beth Font Kit
    User’s Guide</hi> (Los Angeles, 1989).</p>
         <p>Kiraz, G. A. <hi rend="italic">Tabetha Syriac</hi>
    (forthcoming).</p>
         <p>Knudsen, E. E. ‘An important
    step in the revival of literary Syriac: Abrohom Nouro’s
    Tawldotho’, <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 84 (2000),
    59-65.</p>
         <p>Knudsen, E. E. ‘Lexical
    Innovations in Modern Literary Syriac’, in René
    Lavenant (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum VII</hi>, 545-51.</p>
         <p>Hozaya, Younan, and Youkhana,
    Anderios. <hi rend="italic">Bahra Arabic-Assyrian Dictionary</hi> (1998).</p>
         <p>Malke, Joseph.
    ܒܪ̈ܘܠܐ
    ܣܘܪ̈ܝܝܐ
    [Syriac-Arabic, Arabic-Syriac] (2003).</p>
         <p>Murre-Van den Berg, H. L. <hi rend="italic">From a
    Spoken to a Written Language, The Introduction and Development
    of Literary Urmia Aramaic in the Nineteenth Century</hi>
    (1999).</p>
         <p>Nuro, Abrohom. <hi rend="italic">Tawldotho or
    Syriac Neologisms, Principles, Criteria and Examples</hi>
    (1997).</p>
         <p>Smith, J. P. <hi rend="italic">A Compendious
    Syriac Dictionary</hi> (Eisenbrauns reprint, 1998).</p>
         <p>Smith, R. P. <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus
    [Syriac Thesaurus]</hi> (Gorgias Press reprint, 2007).</p>
         <p>Wardini, E. ‘Modern Literary
    Syriac: A Case of Linguistic Divorce’, in René
    Lavenant (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum VII</hi>, pp.517-25.</p>
         <p>Wardini, E. ‘Neologisms in
    MLS’, <hi rend="italic">Melanges de l'Universite Saint-Joseph</hi> 53:5
    (1993/4), 401-566, and 54 (1995/6), 167-324.</p>
         <p>Wardini, E. <hi rend="italic">Neologisms in Modern
    Literary Syriac: Some Preliminary Results</hi> (Dissertation,
    Oslo 1995).</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>