<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Syriac Language and Script in a Chinese Setting: Nestorian Inscriptions from Quanzhou, China†</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Majella</forename>
                  <surname>Franzmann</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n2franzmann</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Majella Franzmann</author>
                  <title level="a">Syriac Language and Script in a Chinese Setting: Nestorian Inscriptions from Quanzhou, China†</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N2Franzmann.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Syriac inscriptions</term>
               <term>tombstones</term>
               <term>Church of the East</term>
               <term>Nestorian</term>
               <term>Quanzhou</term>
               <term>South China</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>This article provides an overview of the
    Syriac language and script found on 14th century Nestorian
    tombstones from Quanzhou in South China. Syriac script is used
    for the most part on the tombstones for writing inscriptions in
    Turkic language. The article deals with the formation of the
    Syriac script, Syriac formulae that appear in some
    inscriptions, Syriac loan words in Turkic, the use of an extra
    letter within the Syriac script to capture a specific Turkic
    pronunciation, and the transliteration of Syriac titles into
    Chinese in the bilingual inscription for Mar Solomon, Bishop of
    South China.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>




         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->

         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] At the
    Conference of the American Oriental Society in 2001 in Toronto,
    Wassilios Klein presented an overview of the Syriac language
    and script of Central Asian tombstones from Biškek and
    Tokmak.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> In concluding the overview, he made reference to
    the Turkic-language inscriptions in Syriac script from Quanzhou
    in China, which at that stage had not been edited in full.
    While a sample of these inscriptions have been edited and
    translated since then by members of the Australian research
    team that has been working on them since 2001,<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> there is as yet
    no similar overview of the Syriac language and script from the
    inscriptions as Klein makes available for the Biškek
    area. This article proposes to fill that gap to enable a more
    comprehensive view of the extent of Syriac development across
    Central Asia and into China. It will also enable an evaluation
    of Klein’s summary statement about the Quanzhou
    inscriptions: “In any case, they are of a completely
    different character to the Central Asian
    tombstones.”<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> Only the script will be analysed. Of course
    there is a very limited amount of Syriac language as opposed to
    script, so that comparisons with Klein’s material is also
    thereby limited. The iconography of the tombstones has been the
    subject of articles by my colleague Ken Parry.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] There
    are currently nine inscribed stones in Syriac script on display
    in Quanzhou: eight are in the Quanzhou Maritime Museum (108,
    [Wu 84]; 109, [Wu 82]; 110, [Wu 79]; 111, also KJ008, [Wu
    78.1-2]; 130, also KJ006, [Wu 76.1 –2]; 131, also KJ016;
    138, also KJ007, [Wu 77.1-3]; 271, also KJ029, [Wu 108]), and
    the ninth is a new find, first viewed by the Australian
    research team in 2002 in the Quanzhou Southern-Style Historical
    Buildings Museum, and now on display in the Quanzhou City
    Museum.<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> All the inscriptions dated so far belong to the
    early to middle 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century CE, almost all within
    the dating timeframe of 1250-1342 given by Klein for the major
    finds of tombstones from Biškek and Burana under
    analysis in his overview (although the stones in Almalyk date
    up to the 1370s).<ref target="#FN6">6</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann3">Letters formed in Syriac</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Several
    features which Klein noted about the formation of Syriac
    letters in the Central Asian material hold true for the
    Quanzhou inscriptions:<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> the letters are in Estrangelo, with fairly
    consistent ligature of the <hi rend="italic">taw-alaph</hi>, and with some
    considerable variation in the formation of the <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi>.
    However, other features which Klein found are not present: the
    <hi rend="italic">rish</hi> and <hi rend="italic">daleth</hi> retain the diacritic point
    although with the weathering of the stones it is sometimes
    difficult to judge what is a diacritic mark and what a simple
    pockmark, and there is no great tendency to connect letters
    beyond what is normally found.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    variation in the formation especially of the <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi>
    even within the same inscription is quite striking. The
    <hi rend="italic">samek</hi> is also problematical, but this lies more in the
    degree to which the letter leans towards the right rather than
    the actual formation of the letter. While there is variation
    amongst all the letters in the inscriptions to some extent, as
    would only be expected with a variety of hands, the variation
    in the formation of the <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> is the most
    noticeable.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Klein
    described the Central Asian variant <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> as
    follows:</p>
         <p>The high line slanting towards the right is also common in
    other inscriptions, but the small check-mark underneath usually
    goes towards the right from the bottom of the vertical line, or
    crosses the vertical line. Here it runs upwards towards the
    left, so that the letter takes the form of a check-mark
    (√).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] Klein
    also notes that this variant as well as the usual form appear
    together. The Quanzhou inscriptions sometimes reveal the same
    feature. Inscription 108, lines 1 and 6, for example, exhibit a
    tendency to the check-mark formation of the <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> as
    described by Klein. However there is also a perfectly normally
    formed initial <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> in line 12. The greatest
    difference in formation of the initial <hi rend="italic">aleph</hi> is found
    in the bilingual inscription, 271. In this inscription, the
    second word of line 1 (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;;color:black" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܝܠܠܐܪܢܝܢܓ</hi>)
    and the first word of line 2 (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܘܘܕ</hi>) both have an intial
    <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> that appears to correspond with Klein’s
    examples, and yet the initial <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> for the seventh
    word in line 1 (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height: 150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;;color:black" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܦܝܣܩܘܦܐܢܝܢܓ</hi>)
    is normally formed.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] While
    weathering and other damage to the stones makes reading the
    Syriac script difficult, the situation is not improved by some
    inscriptions in which the Syriac letters are poorly formed
    rather than showing a variant formation. The greatest problem
    is with the variation in relative size of letters where this
    may make reading difficult: the difference between
    <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nun</hi>, or even between <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi>
    and <hi rend="italic">lamedh</hi>. The relative sizing of <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">chet</hi> does not really present a difficulty since the
    <hi rend="italic">chet</hi> is generally consistently very small and it
    appears only in the Syriac formulae, not at all in the Turkic.
    A good example of the difficulty with <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">nun</hi> is found in 108, line 8, where the <hi rend="italic">nun</hi> is
    written smaller than the <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> in the word<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܡܝܢܓ</hi>, and yet three lines
    earlier the <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> in <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܦܝܠܝܦܘܣ</hi>
    is much smaller in relation to the <hi rend="italic">lamedh</hi>. In 131,
    line 4, however, exactly the opposite occurs where the first
    <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> in the word <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܦܝܠܝܦܘܣ</hi>
    is almost as high as the following <hi rend="italic">lamedh</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] When it
    comes to the question of relative size, the formation of the
    Syriac letters may be a problem for stonemasons who have no
    knowledge of the letters. But the difficulty with the Syriac
    seems unlikely to be the problem of the (Syriac) illiteracy of
    the stonemasons themselves, as Klein suggests. That they are
    adept at their art is amply indicated by the stones with Arabic
    script in the Quanzhou Maritime Museum. It seems more probable
    that the fault lies with the poorly written script by the one
    commissioning the work from which they are copying, attesting
    to a possible loss of facility with Syriac script within the
    community.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann4">Syriac Liturgical/Prayer Formulae</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9]
    Introductory formulae on the majority of the stones are in
    Syriac language. This is the only appearance of Syriac language
    per se, apart from loan words and other items that will be
    discussed below.<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> These opening formulae are much more elaborate
    than those from Semiriče and Biškek as recorded by
    Klein.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] Of
    the seven inscriptions which include a complete opening
    section, apart from the rather official Chinese/Syro-Turkic
    bilingual, five open with a formula that shows very little
    variation:</p>
         <quote>
            <p>130</p>
            <quote>
               <p>
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="font-size:12.0pt;line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ
        ܘܒܪܐ
        ܘܪܘܚܐ
        ܕܩܘܕܫܐ</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the Father and the Son (and) the Holy
        Spirit.</p>
            </quote>
            <p>138</p>
            <quote>
               <p>
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%; font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ
        ܘܒܪܐ
        ܘܪܘܚܐ
        ܕܩܘܕܫܐ</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy
        Spirit.</p>
            </quote>
            <p>131</p>
            <quote>
               <p>
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="font-size:12.0pt;line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ
        ܘܒܪܐ
        ܘܪܘܚܐ
        ܕܩܘܕܫܐ
        ܠܥܠܡܝܢ</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the Father and the Son (and) the Holy
        Spirit forever.</p>
               <p>New piece</p>
               <p>
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ
        ܘܒܪܐ
        ܘܪܘܚܐ
        ܕܩܘܕܫܐ
        ܠܥܠܡܝܢ</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy
        Spirit, forever.</p>
            </quote>
            <p>108</p>
            <quote>
               <p>
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ
        ܘܒܪܐ
        ܘܪܘܚܐ
        ܕܩܘܕܫܐ
        ܠܥܠܡܝܢ
        ܐܡܝܢ</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the name of the Father and the Son and the Holy
        Spirit forever amen.</p>
            </quote>
         </quote>
         <p>The formulae are all correct grammatically and
    orthographically in the stones so far edited or translated.
    Perhaps if more Syriac language had been used, there may have
    been evidence of faults in this regard as Klein found on the
    Central Asian stones.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann5">Syriac Names</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] We
    have no knowledge as yet of the ethnic make-up of the
    communities in Quanzhou in the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century,
    although we know that some of the community were descendants of
    those who came from Central Asia; in 130, lines 5-9, we read of
    the deceased Usha Tasqan,<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> the son of Tutmiš Ata,
    “from the city of Chotcho”. All the names so far
    deciphered on the inscriptions are Turkic, Syrian, or biblical,
    and there is no way of knowing if any of these are names taken
    by Chinese converts to Christianity. It would not be
    unreasonable to consider that there may have been Chinese
    converts among the community. Chwolson notes the grave of a
    Chinese believer, Terim, in Semiriče.<ref target="#FN10">10</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    There are biblical names, though only for one or two of the
    deceased identified so far—in a badly damaged end of 108,
    it may be possible to read “Paulus”, and the
    bilingual is for Bishop Mar Solomon. Apart from this, the first
    name of the one who dedicates Mar Solomon’s tomb is
    Timothy. Biblical names also appear in a separate list of Old
    Testament patriarchs, Abraham, Isaac and Jacob in 109, lines
    16-17.<ref target="#FN11">11</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Names that are frequent in Klein’s material, and in
    Chwolson’s before him, are also found here. Thus in the
    new piece, line 17, we read the name of the deceased as
    Kejamtâ(<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܩܝܡܛܐ</hi> lit. = the
    resurrection). The name occurs ten times in Chwolson’s
    inscriptions.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref> Zauma is the second name of the one who
    dedicates Mar Solomon’s tomb, Zauma being another version
    of <hi rend="u">S</hi>auma (“fast”)
    (bilingual, line 2). It occurs some 15 times in
    Chwolson’s inscriptions<ref target="#FN13">13</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann6">Syriac Titles</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] The
    bilingual inscription uses the title “most reverend
    bishop”. The title of bishop
    ܐܦܝܣܩܘܦܐܢܝܢܓ
    is a loan word from the Syriac which itself is a loan word from
    the Greek (<hi style="font-family:Symbol">episkopoV</hi>).
    The term is reproduced as closely as possible in
    transliteration in the Turkic and Chinese (episqopa-nïng
    and abisiguba). The extra descriptor “most
    reverend” is again reproduced as exactly as possible in
    the Turkic and Chinese transliteration (mari <hi rend="u">h</hi>asya and Mali Haxiya). There is clearly no attempt
    to find a Turkic or Chinese equivalent for “most
    reverend”; the title of Bishop includes with it the
    further qualification “most reverend”, so that it
    is all of one piece. The use of the Syriac here is indicative
    of perhaps two things—that the bishop and his designated
    role within the Syrian region has no real equivalent either for
    the people of Central Asia or for the people of China; and/or
    that the presence of a bishop sent from the originating
    communities in Syria or from the Central Asian region has such
    status that there is no attempt to tamper with the official
    title. Klein also notes that titles are preserved “in the
    form in which the Syrians brought them”.<ref target="#FN14">14</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    Apart from the words for “bishop” and “most
    reverend”, there is only the loan word <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;;color:black" xml:lang="SYR">ܩܒܪܐ</hi>
    (“tomb”) in the inscriptions.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann7">Syriac Transcription of Turkic</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] The
    inevitable differences in Syriac spelling of Turkish words is
    noted by Klein, as well as the difficulties in using Syriac for
    the Turkic phonemes that did not all have some corresponding
    symbol in Syriac.<ref target="#FN15">15</ref> Similarities are obvious with
    Klein’s material, and one small example will suffice to
    show them—108, lines 4-11.<ref target="#FN16">16</ref> The Syriac letter
    <hi lang="AR-SA" dir="rtl" style="font-size:14.0pt;line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Simplified Arabic Fixed&#34;" xml:lang="AR-SA">ﺤ</hi> has been used here to indicate
    where an adapted letter has been used to designate the guttural
    as in the <hi rend="italic">khan</hi>, as discussed below.</p>
         <table>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܡܩܕܘܢܝܐ
        ܦܐܠܝܥ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">mqdwny’
        p’ly‘</hi>
                  <lb/>
        m(a)q(e)donya balïq</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܠܝܥ
        ܦܝܠܝܦܘܣ
        ܟܐܢ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">ly‘
        pylypws X’n</hi>
                  <lb/>
        -lïg(<hi style="font-family:Symbol">g</hi>)
        pilipos xan</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܘܥܠܝ
        ܐܠܟܣܢܕܪܘܣ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">’w‘ly
        ’lksndrws</hi>
                  <lb/>
        o<hi style="font-family:Symbol">g</hi>lï
        al(e)ks(a)ndros</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܝܠܝܓ
        ܟܐܢ
        ܣܐܟܝܫܝ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">’yly‘ X’n
        s’XyŠy</hi>
                  <lb/>
        ilig xan saqïšï</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܝܝܠ
        ܡܝܢܓ
        ܐܠܛܝ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">yyl myng
        ’lty</hi>
                  <lb/>
        yïl mïng altï</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܝܘܙ ܐܘܢ
        ܐܠܛܝ ܛܐ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">ywz ’wn
        ’lty t’</hi>
                  <lb/>
        yüz on altï-ta</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܛܐܒܥܐܨ
        ܣܐܟܝܫܝ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">t’b‘’S
        s’XYŠy</hi>
                  <lb/>
        tab<hi style="font-family:Symbol">g</hi>ac
        saqïšï</cell>
            </row>
            <row valign="top">
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</cell>
               <cell html:align="right" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܠܘܘ
        ܝܝܠ</hi>
               </cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                  <hi style="text-transform:uppercase">lww
        yylY...</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <hi rend="italic">loo</hi>  yïlï ...</cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann8">Translation</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] In
    the year 1616 of the reckoning of Alexander the Great King, son
    of King Philip from the province of Macedonia, in the Year of
    the Dragon of the Chinese reckoning...</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18]
    Similar to the inscriptions investigated by Klein, the
    <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> is used here for both i and ï, normally
    distinguished as front and back vowels; and the <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi>
    also is used for the vowel i in the word <hi rend="italic">ilig</hi>.
    <hi rend="italic">Waw</hi> is used for o as well as ü, as Klein notes
    also. <hi rend="italic">Gamal</hi> is interchangeable with
    <hi rend="italic">‘ayn</hi>, as is <hi rend="italic">beth</hi> with <hi rend="italic">pe</hi>, also
    as noted by Klein. Finally the same use of the <hi rend="italic">sadhe</hi>
    for the Turkic sound c is found in line 10.<ref target="#FN17">17</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19]
    Finally one must note the same use of the adapted letter to
    designate the guttural as used in the word <hi rend="italic">khan</hi>. Klein
    characterises it as a special symbol “created based on
    the Syriac k and supplemented by a diacritic check-mark”.
    He argues that it cannot be the Arabic <hi rend="italic">kaf</hi>, although
    it looks rather similar in its formation, which has a final
    form and is not connected as this letter is both to the left
    and the right.<ref target="#_edn18">18</ref> In fact, in the Quanzhou inscriptions
    there are no instances of the letter joining to the right.
    Chwolson had already suggested that this is a letter created by
    Syriac speakers. That it is not the Arabic is made more likely
    by the fact that the Arabic <hi lang="AR-IQ" dir="rtl" xml:lang="AR-IQ">ق</hi> generally transcribes the
    Turkic k and <hi lang="AR-SA" dir="rtl" xml:lang="AR-SA">ﮐ</hi> transcribes the Turkic K.<ref target="#_edn19">19</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20]
    Klaus Beyer notes that the Nestorian final <hi rend="italic">kaf</hi> and the
    sogdian-uigur non-final k/g look a little like a number 5 and
    he suggests that it is this <hi rend="italic">kaf</hi> that is used here as a
    symbol for a special turkic-uigur consonant or double consonant
    (e.g. <hi style="position:relative;top:-3.0pt">tk</hi>)
    which is not found in East Syriac and which is close to the
    Turkic k.<ref target="#FN20">20</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann9">Syriac Dating</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21]
    Klein comments that the Central Asian inscriptions use the
    Turkic dating system with reference to the twelve-year animal
    cycle as well as the Seleucid dating system used by Syrian
    Christians. He adds: “It is striking that only the
    Turkic-language tombstones add the information that it is the
    era of Alexander, and that the inscriptions on Chinese
    territory generally do not include this dating and the
    resulting association with Syria”.<ref target="#FN21">21</ref> However, in the
    majority of the Quanzhou inscriptions, immediately after the
    opening formula, the dating of the burial/death begins with
    just such a reference to the calendar/reckoning (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܣܐܟܝܫܝ</hi>) based
    on the reign of Alexander (111 and 130) or of Philip and
    Alexander (108, 131, and the new piece). Where the name of
    Alexander only occurs, the title of King/Khan is ascribed to
    him (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%; font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܠܟܣܢܕܪܘܣ
    ܟܐܢ</hi>111 and 130). Where the names of
    Alexander and Philip occur, Philip is given the title of King
    (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܦܝܠܝܦܘܣ
    ܟܐܢ</hi>) and Alexander is the Great King
    (<hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܐܠܟܣܢܕܪܘܣ
    ܐܝܠܝܓ
    ܟܐܢ</hi>; 108, 131, and the new piece). It
    is unusual to include Philip in the formula; his name appears
    only once in a Syro-Turkic Nestorian inscription from Central
    Asia which reads “in the year of King (Khan) Alexander,
    son of Philip of Macedonia”.<ref target="#FN22">22</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] In
    conclusion, the Syro-Turkic inscriptions from Quanzhou show
    some similarities with Klein’s material from Central
    Asia, although the former inscriptions are generally longer and
    more elaborate. Perhaps what is most surprising in the material
    presented above is the final section regarding the dating
    formulae. Together with the preservation of the Syriac forms
    for the titles of Mar Solomon, this evidences a very strong
    link with the originating Syriac communities and their
    tradition. However, despite the clear desire to keep that link
    strong, the inscriptions also attest to an inevitable and
    regrettable loss of proficiency with the Syriac script
    itself.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2Franzmann10">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef0">†</ref> An earlier version of this paper was
    presented at the 9th Symposium Syriacum in Kaslik, Lebanon in
    2004. I wish to acknowledge the teamwork that lies behind this
    paper that draws on a selection of the Syro-Turkic texts from
    Quanzhou which have been edited and translated by Prof. Sam
    Lieu, Dr. Lance Eccles and myself, with generous assistance
    from colleagues, Prof. Peter Zieme and Prof. Aloïs van
    Tongerloo. <ref target="#FNRef0">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> W. Klein, Syriac Writings and Turkic Language
    according to Central Asian Tombstone Inscriptions, in:
    <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 5/2 (2002), [
    <ref target="http://bethmardutho.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol5No2/HV5N2Klein.html">http://bethmardutho.cua.edu/Hugoye/Vol5No2/HV5N2Klein.html</ref>
    ] (accessed 20/7/2004). <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> L. Eccles, M. Franzmann, and S. Lieu, Observations
    on Select Christian Inscriptions in the Syriac Script from
    Zayton, in: <hi rend="italic">From Palmyra to Zayton: Epigraphy and
    Iconography</hi>, edited by I. Gardner, S. Lieu, and K. Parry,
    Turnhout 2005 (Silk Road Studies 10), 247-78. I wish to
    acknowledge the teamwork with my colleagues on the
    inscriptions, with generous assistance from Prof. Peter Zieme
    and Prof. Aloïs van Tongerloo, which lies behind this
    paper. See other recent work, for example, in M. Franzmann and
    S.N.C. Lieu, A New Nestorian Tombstone from Quanzhou: Z47,
    Epitaph of the Lady Kejamtâ, in: <hi rend="italic">Jingjiao. The Church
    of the East in China and Central Asia</hi>, edited by R. Malek
    and P. Hofrichter, Sankt Augustin 2006 (Institut Monumenta
    Serica), 293-302; Niu Ruji, Nestorian Inscriptions from China
    (13th – 14th Centuries), <hi rend="italic">Jingjiao</hi>, 209-242; and
    Niu Ruji, A New Syriac-Uighur Inscription from China (Quanzhou,
    Fujian Province), in: <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for
    Syriac Studies</hi> 4 (2004), 60-65. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> See K. Parry, The Iconography of the Christian
    Tombstones from Zayton, <hi rend="italic">From Palmyra to Zayton</hi>,
    229-246; <hi style="color:black">K. Parry, Angels and
    Apsaras: Christian Tombstones from Quanzhou, in: <hi rend="italic">The
    Journal of the Asian Arts Society of Australia</hi> 12/2
    (2003), 4-5; and K. Parry, Images in the Church of the East:
    The Evidence from Central Asia and China, in: <hi rend="italic">The Church of
    the East: Life and Thought</hi>, edited by J.F. Coakley and K.
    Parry, Bulletin of the John Rylands University Library of
    Manchester 78/3 (1996), 143-162. <ref target="#FNRef3">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> Klein, Syriac Writings
    and Turkic Language, #29. <ref target="#FNRef4">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> The first number
    mentioned is the current number given in the museum. Numbers in
    square brackets are taken from Wu Wenliang, <hi rend="italic">Quanzhou
    zongjiao shike (Religious Stone Inscriptions at Quanzhou)</hi>,
    Beijing 1957. Stone 131 is not found in Wu; see pl. 7, fig. 3.5
    in Wu Yuxiong, Fujian Quanzhou faxian di Yelikewen (Qingjiao)
    bei (On the Nestorian tombstone discovered in Quanzhou,
    Fujian), in: <hi rend="italic">Kaogu</hi> (1988/11), 1015-1020, pls. 7-8,
    1018. The research team is aware that many of the stones are
    well-produced replicas, and continue the search for those
    originals that have survived. <ref target="#FNRef5">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> Klein, Syriac Writings
    and Turkic Language, #2. The team’s preliminary tentative
    dating is as follows:</hi>
         </p>
         <table>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1301</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1305</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">131</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1307(?)</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1313</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">new piece</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1313</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">111</cell>
               <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1347<ref target="#FNRef6">
                     <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
                  </ref>
               </cell>
            </row>
         </table>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> See ibid., #23-28.
    <ref target="#FNRef7">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> Klein (ibid., # 9-10)
    gives a good overview of the use of Syriac language in Central
    Asia and the relative knowledge of Syriac. <ref target="#FNRef8">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> The name is uncertain,
    but is read as Tasqan in Niu Ruji, Quanzhou xuliya-weiwuer
    shuangyu jingjiaobi zai kao shi (A re-examination and
    translation of the mixed Syriac-Uighur language Inscription
    from Quanzhou), <hi rend="italic">Minzhu Yuwen</hi> (1999/3), 33. <ref target="#FNRef9">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> Inscription no. 24
    in D. Chwolson, <hi rend="italic">Syrisch-Nestorianische Grabinschriften aus
    Semiretschie</hi>, Neue Folge, St.-Pétersbourg 1897, p.
    11. <ref target="#FNRef10">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> See the similar use
    of the list of Old Testament matriarchs, Sara, Rebecca, and
    Rachel, in the Epitaph of Elizabeth of Yangzhou (a bilingual
    Syro-Turkic/Chinese inscription), line 9. A photograph of the
    rubbing of the inscription appears in Wang Qinjin, Yuan yanyou
    sinian jelishiba mubei kaoshi, in: <hi rend="italic">Kaogu</hi> (1989/6),
    553-554 and 557. <ref target="#FNRef11">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color:black">
               <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> In D. Chwolson,
    <hi rend="italic">Syrisch-Nestorianische Grabinscriften aus Semiretschie,
    Nebst einer Belage: Über das türkische Sprachmaterial
    dieser Grabinschriften von W. Radloff, mit drei phototypischen
    Tafeln und einer ebensolchen, von Julius Euting ausbeargeiteten
    Schrifttafel</hi>, St.-Pétersbourg 1890 (Mémoires
    de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de
    St.-Pétersbourg, VIIe série, Tome XXXVII, No. 8):
    inscriptions 50,2 (the girl Kejamtâ, p. 86), 50,23 (the
    believer Kejamtâ, p. 91), and 98,1 (the believer
    Kejamtâ, p. 31); in D. Chwolson (1897): inscriptions 31
    (the believer Kejamthâ, [but spelled <hi lang="SYR" dir="rtl" style="font-size:12.0pt;line-height:150%;font-family:&#34;Estrangelo Edessa&#34;" xml:lang="SYR">ܩܝܡܬܐ</hi>
    according to Chwolson], p. 12), 67 (the girl Pazak
    Kejamthâ, p. 18), 112 (the believer Kejamthâ, p.
    27), 211 (the believer Kejamthâ, p. 39), 261 (the
    believer Kejamthâ, p. 47), 264 (Kejamthâ, p. 47),
    and 294 (the little girl Kejamthâ, p. 49). <ref target="#FNRef12">
                  <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
               </ref>
            </hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> Chwolson (1890, 134) notes that the name
    occurs seven times in his data and is a frequently used Syrian
    name; see also Chwolson (1897), no. 7 (p. 7), no. 19 (p. 10),
    no. 25 (p. 11), no. 40, a woman’s name (p. 13), no. 201
    (p. 38), no. 230 (p. 42), no. 237 (p. 42), no. 243 (p. 45).
    <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> Klein, Syriac Writings and Turkic Language,
    #5. <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Ibid., #19. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> For the text in full, see Eccles, Franzmann
    and Lieu, Observations, 260-261. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> Klein, Syriac Writings and Turkic Language,
    #20. <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> Ibid., #21. <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> Chwolson (1890), 143, fn. 1. <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> Prof. Klaus Beyer, personal correspondence,
    26.6.04. Prof. Beyer also considers it highly unlikely that
    this is an Arabic letter. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef21">21</ref> Klein, Syriac Writings and Turkic Language,
    #8. <ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef22">22</ref> Cf. Č. Džumagulov, <hi rend="italic">Yazyk
    syro-tjukskix (nestorianskix) Pamjatnikov fsKirgizii</hi>,
    (Frunze, 1971), 91, text line 1. <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>