<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Isaac Armalet, Catalogue of the Syriac and Arabic Manuscripts at the Patriarchal Library of Charfet [Gorgias Press 2006; ISBN 1-59333-365-X] xii*, [iv], 15, 526, [ii], 12, 14, [vi]pp; hardcover.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>David G.K.</forename>
                  <surname>Taylor</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/bookReview/hv10n2prtaylor</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>David G.K. Taylor</author>
                  <title level="a">Isaac Armalet, Catalogue of the Syriac and Arabic Manuscripts at the Patriarchal Library of Charfet [Gorgias Press 2006; ISBN 1-59333-365-X] xii*, [iv], 15, 526, [ii], 12, 14, [vi]pp; hardcover.</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N2PRTaylor.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Isaac Armalet</term>
               <term>Manuscripts</term>
               <term>Charfet</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] This
    volume is a reprint of the very scarce 1936 Arabic catalogue of
    the Syriac and Arabic manuscripts in the Syrian Catholic
    Patriarchate of Charfet (Sharfeh), which is located in
    Dar’un-Harissa, in the hills above Jounieh, Lebanon. The
    convent was founded by Patriarch Ignatius Michael III Jarweh as
    his patriarchal see in 1786 (this volume was published to mark
    the 150th anniversary of this event), and it subsequently
    attracted wealthy donors (such as Viscount Philippe de Tarrazi)
    as well as donations from other monasteries and churches,
    enabling it to develop into one of the world’s great
    collections of Syriac and Christian Arabic manuscripts. The
    present catalogue, was produced by Chorepiscopus Isaac Armalet
    (Ishoq bar Armalto of Mardin, 1879–1954),<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> who was a
    prolific scholar<ref target="#FN1">2</ref> and an accomplished Syriac scribe,<ref target="#FN1">3</ref> and lists 586
    Syriac manuscripts (pp.1–293, 513–523)<ref target="#FN1">4</ref> and 569
    Arabic manuscripts of both Christian and Muslim origin
    (pp.295–512),<ref target="#FN1">5</ref> ranging in date from the eleventh to the
    twentieth centuries. These include biblical, exegetical,
    theological, hagiographical, liturgical, legal, philosophical,
    lexical, and scientific texts (although the sections are fairly
    randomly divided and arranged).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] As was
    noted by a contemporary reviewer, Willi Heffening, in
    1938,<ref target="#FN1">6</ref> Armalet’s work provides a useful handlist
    of the manuscripts, but the descriptions are rather brief and
    basic, and fall far short of the best cataloguing standards of
    his day. The catalogue’s usability is also reduced by the
    lack of any kind of index. In Armalet’s original Arabic
    and French prefaces (supplemented in this Gorgias Press
    re-edition by an English translation from the French) the
    author provides some background information about the history
    of the library and earlier attempts to draft catalogues, and
    calls attention to certain manuscripts which he finds
    interesting.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    prime virtue of Armalet’s work thus lies simply in the
    fact that it records the existence within the Charfet
    collection of certain named texts, and provides an approximate
    physical description and dating of the manuscripts. Before
    being too dismissive, however, we should remember that many
    European and North American collections of manuscripts are no
    better served by their catalogues, and many collections in the
    Middle East still have no reliable published catalogues of any
    kind.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] It might
    perhaps be useful to add a few further comments about
    subsequent developments in the Charfet manuscript collection.
    In 1956 Patriarch Ignatius Gabriel I Tappouni transferred the
    manuscript collection of the patriarchal residence in Beirut to
    the library at Charfet. This collection, which has been kept
    separate from the earlier manuscript holdings, then numbered
    more than 600 manuscripts, of which 305 were Syriac or Karshuni
    texts. These are obviously not included in Armalet’s 1936
    work, but a simple alphabetic table was provided by Dom
    Polycarp Sherwood in 1957.<ref target="#FN1">7</ref> In 1993 Behnam Sony published a
    large Arabic catalogue of this patriarchal collection,<ref target="#FN1">8</ref> which by
    this date had increased in size to 883 manuscripts. Again,
    descriptions of the manuscripts are kept to a bare minimum, and
    there is no citation of colophons etc., or indeed any use of
    Syriac type, but there is still far more information here than
    in Sherwood’s table. Sony introduced a new set of
    reference numbers for the manuscripts, and amongst his many
    useful indexes he also helpfully included a table
    (pp.443–448) of correspondences with the numbers cited by
    Sherwood. As it happens, the manuscripts in the Charfet
    collection are still arranged on the shelves and labelled with
    Sherwood’s numbers (inherited from an earlier unpublished
    list of Fr. Pierre Saba), rather than those of Sony.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Since
    2006 a Franco-Lebanese research group, led by Françoise
    Briquel-Chatonnet, Alain Desreumaux, and Muriel Debié of
    the CNRS, has been actively engaged in producing a new
    scientific catalogue of all of the Syriac manuscripts preserved
    in Charfet, although it is clear that this is a task that will
    take many years to complete. Once their work is published the
    earlier catalogues of Armalet and Sony will be superseded, but
    in the meantime these pioneering manuscript catalogues should
    find a place on the shelves of any library or institute with an
    interest in Middle-Eastern Christianity and its literary
    production.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2PRTaylor1">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> Also frequently listed in library catalogues as
    Ishaq Armalah. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> Cf. Rudolf Macuch, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der spät-
    und neusyrischen Literatur</hi> (Berlin 1976) 438-440. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> He copied a number of important Syriac manuscripts
    from the Charfet collection for the Benedictine monastery of
    Montserrat, in Catalonia. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> This section also includes many Karshuni
    manuscripts. <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> A further 18 manuscripts are listed in the preface
    which were transferred from Charfet to the Vatican Library
    through the agency of Cardinal Augustin Ciasca - an action
    strongly resented by Armalet and the local Syrian Catholic
    hierarchy. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> III.13 [35] (1938) 147.
    <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> ‘Le Fonds patriarcal de la
    bibliothèque manuscrite de Charfet’,
    <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien</hi> 2.1 (1957) 93-107. <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> فهرس
    المخطوطات
    البطريركية
    في دير
    الشرفة
    لبنان (Beirut, 1993) 544pp.
    <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>