<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Middle East Between Rome and Persia</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n1fcnehseminar</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">The Middle East Between Rome and Persia</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N1FCNEHSeminar.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="announcement">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
         <p>University of Notre Dame<lb/>
    June 19 - July 26, 2007 </p>
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1]
    Applications are invited for an NEH-sponsored seminar, titled
    "The Middle East Between Rome and Persia: Early Christianity on
    the Path to Islam." The six-week seminar will be held at the
    University of Notre Dame, from June 19 until July 26, 2007.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    Seminar will draw on the literature and material culture of the
    region to explore the ways in which the resurgent indigenous
    cultures there ­ Arabic, Syriac, Aramaic-speaking Jewish,
    and Armenian ­ re-emerged with the decline of local
    Hellenism to form a population that would in the seventh
    century be receptive to a new political and religious hegemony.
    For four centuries, this region was prized by western or
    Iranian empires and dominated by the imperial culture, language
    and religion of each. Despite these rival hegemonies, by the
    beginning of the seventh century the Middle East in late
    antiquity was re-emerging as a distinct zone, a fungible area
    allowing for the passage, conquest and settlement of the dar al
    Islam. Christian and Jewish cultures in the old marchlands
    between the Iranian and Roman imperia were being incorporated
    in a central Islamic territory. There they would coexist in a
    multi-religious society that only at the present moment is
    finally shattering.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] We
    intend to explore how the native Christianities and the Jewish
    communities of the region made such a conquest and enduring
    settlement possible.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] This
    seminar will be directed by Professors Joseph Amar, Professor
    of Classics (whose background is in Syriac and Arabic history),
    and Robin Darling Young, Associate Professor of Early
    Christianity (who specializes in the Greek, Syriac and Armenian
    churches).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    application, as well as a weekly curriculum and information
    about accommodations, can be found online, at: <ref target="http://www.nd.edu/~romepers/">www.nd.edu/~romepers</ref>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] If you
    have any questions, please contact Devon Smith at
    dsmith17@nd.edu.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>