<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Jacob of Sarug in English Translation</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n1fcjacobofsarug</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Jacob of Sarug in English Translation</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N1FCJacobOfSarug.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Jacob of Sarug</term>
               <term>Translation</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="announcement">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
         <p>Gorgias Press: Call for Contribution
    </p>
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Last
    year Gorgias Press published six volumes of the Syriac texts of
    the homilies of Jacob of Sarug based on the Bedjan-Brock
    edition. See the <ref target="http://www.gorgiaspress.com/bookshop/showproduct.aspx?isbn=1-59333-327-7">catalog entry</ref> for the title at Gorgias
    Press.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Gorgias
    Press will now begin publishing a bilingual edition of this
    corpus. As of today, 20% of the corpus is already translated
    into English; 33% of the homilies have been assigned to
    scholars. Gorgias Press would like to invite scholars to take
    part in this important project. Participants will be asked to
    translate texts into (idiomatic) English and provide an
    introduction for each hymn as described below.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N1FCJacobOfSarug1">Project Description</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    project aims at publishing a bilingual edition of the homilies
    of Jacob of Sarug. The Syriac will be given in vocalized Serto
    script with facing English translation. Each hymn will be
    prefaced by an introduction containing the following:</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Homily Theme: one or two sentences describing the theme
      briefly.</item>
            <item>Keywords: keywords that describe the content of the
      homily (e.g., love, Assumption, martyrs).</item>
            <item>Number of lines: the total number of lines in the
      homily.</item>
            <item>Meter: if the homily is not in the ‘Mar Jacob
      Meter’, then specify the meter.</item>
            <item>Summary of the Homily: give a brief summary of the
      homily, point out any symbolism, biblical or liturgical
      allusions, play on words, etc.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    translator will also provide the following indices (with
    references to Homily number, and line number):</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>An index of biblical quotations (or references)</item>
            <item>A subject and name index</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    translations will be published initially in fascicles as the
    translations become available. The Syriac text will be
    provided, but it will be the responsibility of the translator
    to proof the typed text against the Bedjan-Brock edition.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N1FCJacobOfSarug2">How to Contact Gorgias Press</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] If you
    are interested in contributing to the project, send an email to
    submissions@gorgiaspress.com containing the following
    information (established scholars need not send all the
    details):</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>A brief cover letter (email) indicating your interest in
      the project.</item>
            <item>Examples of previous published translations of Syriac
      texts of hymns.</item>
            <item>The homilies you are interested in translating, indicated
      by volume number and homily number of the Bedjan-Brock
      edition.</item>
            <item>If you are a graduate student with no previous
      publication record, a recommendation letter from your
      supervisor that you are capable of doing such work and that
      your supervisor is willing to oversee your work.</item>
         </list>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>