<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Syriac Studies Symposium V Syriac as a Bridge Culture</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n1fcsyriacsymposiumv</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Syriac Studies Symposium V Syriac as a Bridge Culture</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N1FCSyriacSymposiumV.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="announcement">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
         <p>Toronto, Ontario Canada.<lb/>
    June 25-27, 2007 </p>
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    (North American) Syriac Studies Symposium gathers scholars,
    researchers, graduate students, and interested public from all
    over the world for a three day conference on Syriac studies.
    Symposium V will take place in Canada for the first time,
    following four successive symposia in the United States:
    Providence RI (1991), Washington DC (1995), Notre Dame IN
    (1999), and Princeton NJ (2003).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2]
    Preference will be given to papers or sessions that directly
    deal with the main theme: The role of Syriac in bridging
    antiquity with the medieval Near East, ancient Greece with the
    Islamic civilizations, Christianity with the Far East, etc., in
    literature, translations, art, architecture and any other
    relevant field. Other proposals in the areas of Syriac
    literature, Biblical versions, history, art, archaeology, and
    theology are also welcome.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] As in
    the past conferences, the Syriac Studies Symposium will jointly
    convene with the International Forum on Syriac Computing. This
    forum aims to give those working on computational projects in
    Syriac the opportunity to share information. Papers on all
    aspects of Syriac computing are welcomed, including: databases
    (lexical, bibliographical, catalogues), word processing, fonts,
    desktop publishing, critical editions, computer aided
    learning/teaching, software and systems.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Please
    submit a title and a 250 word abstract if you wish to present a
    (20 minute) paper. The submission deadline is 28 February 2007.
    If you wish to propose a session, indicate its theme and
    participants, and enclose copies of abstracts for the papers.
    Send your abstract or proposal electronically at the following
    e-mail, csss@chass.utoronto.ca.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Address
    questions concerning papers or sessions:<lb/>
    For Syriac Symposium V to the Canadian Society for Syriac
    Studies at<lb/>
    csss@chass.utoronto.ca.<lb/>
    For the International Forum on Syriac Computing to Dr. George
    Kiraz:<lb/>
    gak@bethmardutho.org</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>