<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Literary Production of Melkites in the pre-Ottoman Era (AD 750-1516)</title>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n2fcmelkiteliterature</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">The Literary Production of Melkites in the pre-Ottoman Era (AD 750-1516)</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N2FCMelkiteLiterature.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Melkite</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
         <p>Sayyidat al-Bir (Lebanon), January
    24–26, 2008 </p>
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <head xml:id="HV10N2FCMelkiteLiterature1">The Conference</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] We have
    the honor of announcing the meeting of a conference entitled
    “The Literary Production of Melkites in the Pre-Ottoman
    Era,” organized jointly by CEDRAC (Centre de
    Documentation et de Recherches Arabes Chrétiennes
    – USJ) and l’OIB (Orient Institut – Beirut),
    from Thursday, January 24 through Saturday, January 26, at the
    Convent of Our Lady of the Well (Sayyidat al-Bir, in Matn,
    Lebanon).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] By
    Melkites we intend those who are named, in the contemporary
    Arab world, Greek Orthodox or Greek Catholic. By specifying the
    Pre-Ottoman period we intend to identify the topic at the heart
    of the conference, yet this need not absolutely exclude the
    later period. As regards subjects, we will welcome papers on
    the various contributions of Melkites, whether secular
    (science, medicine, philosophy, history, philology, art, etc.)
    or religious (Bible, theology, liturgy, canon law,
    spirituality, etc.), both original compositions and
    translations. Participants might also present studies on a
    manuscript, a work or an author, or analyze the literary
    movement of a particular period. In brief, participants are
    entirely free to specify their topic. It is expected only that
    their paper be an original scholarly contribution.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2FCMelkiteLiterature2">The Presentations</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    Participants will have 30 minutes, including 20 minutes for
    their presentation and 10 minutes for discussion. Alternatively
    participants might choose to make a brief, 10 minute
    discussion, for example to illustrate a new detail or provide a
    new report. The recommended languages of the conference are
    French and English, but other languages are not necessarily
    excluded.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] If you
    will need special technical equipment for your presentation,
    for example to project texts or slides, please inform us about
    your exact need by the beginning of January.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] All
    participants are requested to submit, before January 3, 2008,
    an abstract of about ten lines on their paper, either in French
    or in English. All of the papers will be gathered in a volume
    and published exclusively in the periodical <hi rend="italic">Parole de
    l’Orient</hi>. The published papers can be more in depth
    than the oral presentations. Be sure to have a definitive text
    by the date of the conference. Thereafter we will detail the
    guidelines of the edition. Authors will receive one copy of the
    entire volume and 25 offprints of their article.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV10N2FCMelkiteLiterature3">Organisation</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In order
    that we might prepare lodging at Our Lady of the Well and other
    organizational details, we request that you inform us of your
    participation, and provide the title of your presentation (if
    you intend to prresent) by September 15, 2007 at the latest.
    Needless to say, the earlier you can do so the better.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    organizers will cover the cost of lodging (including all meals)
    for foreign participants and meals for local participants.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Do not
    hesitate to inform any interested parties about this
    conference. And kindly respond to us at the following address:
    &lt;samirksj@hotmail.com&gt; or
    &lt;nagi.edelby@usj.edu.lb&gt;</p>
         <p>P. Samir Khalil Samir, CEDRAC, and Manfred Kropp, OIB.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>