<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Letter from the General Editor</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>George A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kiraz</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2007</date>
            <idno>Vol. 10, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv10n1issuededication</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author> </author>
                  <title level="a">Letter from the General Editor</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol10/HV10N1IssueDedication.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="10">10</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="introduction">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] It is
    with great pride that we celebrate this year the 10th
    anniversary of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi>: Journal of Syriac Studies, and
    the 15th anniversary of its parent Beth Mardutho: The Syriac
    Institute. The Institute grew from a one-man operation back in
    1992 to become an international focus for Syriac studies,
    especially online. This special issue celebrates our
    anniversaries.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Our
    recent activities at the Institute have focused on getting
    project eBethArké online, and we are pleased to launch
    it on the Institute's 15th anniversary at <ref target="http://www.bethmardutho.org/ebetharkelib">http://www.bethmardutho.org/ebetharkelib</ref>. The site
    now contains half of the catalog with a few PDF samples. This
    digital library now contains about 2,500 books, manuscripts and
    archival material most of which will become accessible through
    this web site. Additionally, plans are underway to complete the
    first volume of our encyclopedia project, hopefully within the
    next year or so.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] In this
    special issue of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> we reflect on the past,
    present and future of Syriac studies. In the first paper,
    Sebastian Brock reflects briefly on the work of Syriacists who
    have died during the last ten years. In the second paper, Lucas
    Van Rompay reflects on the present state of Syriac studies as
    well as on the opportunities and challenges of the future. He
    gives a discussion of the geographical changes in the worldwide
    presence of Syriac Christians and Syriac scholars, and then
    offers some suggestions for work to be carried out in the
    coming years. In the third paper, I give the history of Syriac
    computing in the last forty years and briefly outline the need
    for some future projects.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Efforts
    are underway to publish all back issues as well as future
    issues of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> in print—the online edition
    will remain free. For practical purposes, from this issue and
    going forward the Hugoye issues will be named Winter and Summer
    (in place of January and July).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] It is
    hoped that <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> and Beth Mardutho will continue to
    be the focal point of Syriac studies online. <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܫܢ̈ܝܐ
    ܣܓ̈ܝܐܬܐ</foreign>
         </p>
         <p>George A. Kiraz</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>