<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Marthe Mahieu-De Praetere, Kurisumala - Francis Mahieu Acharya: a Pioneer of Christian Monasticiam in India (trans.Van Winkle, Susan) Pp. xv + 394, Paperback; a) Cistercian Publications, Kalamazoo, Michigan, 2007, ISBN 978-0-87907-614-6, $79.95; b) Asian Trading Corporation, Bangalore/ Sopanam, Kottayam, India, 2008, ISBN 81-7086-470-4, IR 200.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Bernard</forename>
                  <surname>Kilroy</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>Vol. 11, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv11n2prkilroy</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Bernard Kilroy</author>
                  <title level="a">Marthe Mahieu-De Praetere, Kurisumala - Francis Mahieu Acharya: a Pioneer of Christian Monasticiam in India (trans.Van Winkle, Susan) Pp. xv + 394, Paperback; a) Cistercian Publications, Kalamazoo, Michigan, 2007, ISBN 978-0-87907-614-6, $79.95; b) Asian Trading Corporation, Bangalore/ Sopanam, Kottayam, India, 2008, ISBN 81-7086-470-4, IR 200.</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol11/HV11N2PRKilroy.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Francis Mahieu Acharya</term>
               <term>Kurisumala</term>
               <term>Biography</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The name
    of Francis Mahieu Acharya (1912-2002) is not new to
    <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi>; his work has been praised by both the Director
    of SEERI (St Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute, S
    India)<note place="foot" xml:id="FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Thekeparampil, Jacob , July
    2002. 
         </p>
                </note> and Professor Sebastian Brock<note place="foot" xml:id="FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Para. 31, 'The Contribution of Departed
    Syriacists', 1997-2006, ,
    January 2007. 
         </p>
                </note> who also noted this
    biography published in its original French in 2001 (without
    ISBN). However, the English translation now opens up its
    availability, especially because the Indian edition is at an
    Indian price.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Abbot
    Francis's main significance is to have extended the use of
    Syriac liturgical spirituality in his still living monastery of
    Kurisumala (S India), including with the first English
    translation<note place="foot" xml:id="FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">Prayer with the Harp of the Spirit: The prayer
    of the Asian Churches,</hi> Kurisumala Ashram, Vagamon, Kerala
    685 503 (Nil ISBN); Vol I [<hi rend="italic">Sh<hi rend="u">h</hi>imo</hi> - Weekday Common Prayer] (1980)
    3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Rev 1983; Vol II [Annunication to Ephipany]
    (1982) 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Rev 1999; Vol III [Fast to Resurrection]
    (1985) tbp 2008; Vol IV [season of Resurrection to Exaltation
    of the Cross] 1986. e-mail &lt;kurisumala@yahoo.com&gt;.
    
         </p>
                </note> of the West Syrian <hi rend="italic">Penqitho</hi> published
    by the Dominican Press in Mosul, Iraq 1886-96 as well as a
    later translation and commentary of the <hi rend="italic">The Ritual of the
    Clothing of Monks in the Antiochean Tradition.</hi>
            <note place="foot" xml:id="FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Trans. from <hi rend="italic">Book of Priestly Rites</hi>
    (<hi rend="italic">Ktobo d-takse kumroye</hi>) Sharfeh, Lebabon, 1952: series
    Moran Etho 13 (SEERI, Kottayam, 1999). 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Although
    the biography does not tell us more about the texts, if read
    selectively it is useful in showing how they came to be created
    and used in their present liturgical context, which appears to
    be exceptional.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Francis
    and his English Benedictine monk collaborator Fr Bede Griffiths
    began in 1956 by chanting the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Sh<hi rend="u">h</hi>imo</hi> Common Prayer (subsequently translated
    into prose by Bede and later by Francis into rhythmic chant)
    but found the 'Pampakuda' (Kerala) edition of the
    <hi rend="italic">Penqitho</hi> for Sundays and feast days too abbreviated.
    In 1961, after unproductive searches in Kerala, he set off on
    an unyielding hunt in Beirut, Aleppo, Damascus and Jerusalem,
    nowhere it seems finding the full Syriac <hi rend="italic">Penqitho</hi> in
    or out of use. He finally located it under a layer of dust in a
    store-room back in Mosul, Iraq where the new Syrian Catholic
    Bishop Benni (now Archbishop) was happy to sell him the entire
    remainder stock of seven sets of seven folio volumes, because
    (he said) there was no longer any call for it. Neither, nor the
    biographer either, apparently knew of the parallel interest by
    Chorepiscopo (later Bishop) Boutros Gemayel of the Maronite
    Church who published a selective <hi rend="italic">Penqitho</hi> translation
    in French in Beirut during (I surmise) the 1970's, which was
    translated into English and published in USA during the
    1980's<note place="foot" xml:id="FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Gemayel, Boutros (Chor-Bishop) <hi rend="italic">Prayer of the
    Faithful According to the Maronite Liturgical Year</hi>, St.
    Maron Publications, Brooklyn NY, Vol I 1982, Vol II 1983, Vol
    III 1985, trans. with adaptation from <hi rend="italic">Les Prières
    des Croyants selon l'Année Liturgique Maronite,</hi>
    Beirut, nd - collated from texts at Bkerke and 'various ancient
    monasteries'. 
         </p>
                </note>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    Kurisumala English translation is because the Kerala monks,
    whose mother tongue is Malayalam, use English as a second
    language because it is the <hi rend="italic">lingua franca</hi> of India;
    learning Syriac proved a real obstacle. Beyond the Syriac text
    the value has been its spirituality: a) being language of the
    heart; b) having a breviary not based so exclusively on the
    Judaic Psalms of the Old Covenant (as in the West) but on hymns
    and prayers which celebrate the New; c) being more integrated
    within the 'Economy of Salvation'; d) which in turn is
    reinforced by the dramatic unfolding of the Syrian Orthodox (or
    Syro-Malankara in the case of Kurisumala) liturgical
    calendar.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    systemic inter-connectedness may not emerge through the
    biography, partly because of Francis' involvement with
    Hindu-Christian theology and partly because Francis' pivotal
    but unpublished <hi rend="italic">Lectionary,</hi> which contains the adapted
    calendar, is not mentioned, though the unpublished Menology
    with its many Eastern saints is. However, there is ample
    compensation in the description of the extraordinary love
    affair which Francis had with the Eastern Fathers, especially
    the Syrians, from his first years as a novice Trappist monk in
    his native Belgium.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The most
    significant feature of the spirituality of Francis was the
    steady revelation of an Asian Christ, which displaced for him
    the classical western versions of the Greco-Roman tradition in
    which he was brought up. Even though his Asian Christ was an
    amalgam of Middle East and Indian spirituality, the
    significance lies in the vibrant originality of his monastic
    foundation through the use of the Syrian transplant.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8]
    Unfortunately the biography does not speculate why the
    influence of Kurisumala has been limited. It has not been
    imitated elsewhere and the liturgical office is not used by any
    other Community (so far as I know) although Francis
    understandably hoped it would become an adaptable model for the
    Asian Churches. Although many seminarians and Sisters are sent
    to Kurisumala for an 'ashram experience' retreat, spontaneous
    engagement is probably small, including among lay people. For
    reasons which deserve to be explored, the spirituality of
    Kurisumala has not enjoyed a fraction of the local appeal of
    charismatic retreat centres or the cult of Blessed Alphonsa or
    indeed Pentecostalism.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] There
    are other features which are mentioned only in passing and
    deserve the future interest of researchers, in particular his
    translation and use of the <hi rend="italic">Odes of Solomon</hi> as a
    devotional work. Another is an unpublished manual for monk
    novices on monasticism as a universal phenomenon, from its
    cradle in ancient India and through its apparently spontaneous
    apparition in Palestine, in parallel to Egyptian monasticism,
    and subsequent flowering in Europe.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] Some
    scholars may object to the <hi rend="italic">Penqitho</hi> translation
    because a) it is of two major Hours only (<hi rend="italic">Ramsho</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">Lilyo</hi>); b) it inserts some foreign feast days with new
    text; c) a few psalms and prayers are trimmed; d) for the sake
    of rhythm it may depart from the literal Syriac. All true. In
    addition, Volume I, the <hi rend="italic">Sh<hi rend="u">h</hi>imo</hi>,
    incorporates some Indian scriptures. Francis (and others) would
    answer that there is no such thing as an authoritative text
    because in the West Syrian tradition each monastery varied and
    adapted; what matters is the core of living and authentic
    spirituality.</p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV11N2PRKilroy1">Notes</head>
         
         
         
         
         
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>