<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Wilhelm Baum and Dietmar W. Winkler. The Church of the East: A Concise History. London and New York: RoutledgeCurzon, 2003, xii + 204 pp; hardcover. $130.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Joel</forename>
                  <surname>Walker</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>Vol. 11, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv11n2prwalker</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Joel Walker</author>
                  <title level="a">Wilhelm Baum and Dietmar W. Winkler. The Church of the East: A Concise History. London and New York: RoutledgeCurzon, 2003, xii + 204 pp; hardcover. $130.</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol11/HV11N2PRWalker.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Church of the East</term>
               <term>Historiography</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] How does
    one write a "concise" account of a Church, whose history spans
    three continents and seventeen centuries? In this learned
    little survey, Austrian scholars Wilhelm Baum and Dietmar
    Winkler make a valiant effort to provide an introductory
    overview to the entire history of the Church of the East. The
    book is an unrevised English translation of its German original
    published in 2000.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Wilhelm Baum and Dietmar Winkler, <hi rend="italic">Die
    Apostolische Kirche des Ostens: Geschichte der sogenannten
    Nestorianer</hi> (Klagenfurt, Austria: Verlag Kitab, 2000).
    Winkler is credited with authorship of chapters 1 (on the
    origins of the Church of the East) and 5 (its modern history),
    while Baum composed the central three chapters on the Church's
    history under Islamic rule. 
         </p>
                </note> As such, it fills a conspicuous hole in the
    English-language historiography, which has not seen a
    monograph-length survey of the Church of the East since
    1929.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             W. A. Wigram, <hi rend="italic">The Assyrians and their
    Neighbours</hi> (London: G. Bell and Sons, 1929; reprint:
    Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2002). The Church of the East
    does, however, receive extensive coverage in general surveys of
    Christianity in pre-modern Asia. See esp. Ian Gillman and
    Hans-Joachim Klimkeit, <hi rend="italic">Christians in Asia before 1500</hi>
    (Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press, 1999). 
         </p>
                </note> The authors composed "with a non-specialist
    audience in mind"—hence, the absence of footnotes and
    diacritical marks in transliteration. The results are mixed,
    though the book offers much of interest for advanced students
    and serious general readers.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] After a
    sensible introduction to the thorny issue of how to refer to
    the Church of the East—also known as the Nestorian, the
    East Syriac, or the Assyrian Church—chapter one explores
    the origins of Christianity in Iraq and the institutional
    development of Christianity in the Sasanian Empire (224-642).
    Winkler (sole author of this section) is perceptive on the
    development of the East-Syrian patriarchate and theology. The
    chapter concludes with his spirited defense of the orthodoxy of
    the East-Syrian creed, which was presented to the Sasanian
    court in 612 and remains valid for the "entire" Church of the
    East today.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Chapters
    two and three survey the Church of the East's history under
    Arab and then Mongol rule, emphasizing its international and
    multi-ethnic character extending across large stretches of
    Asia. Baum briefly describes the patriarchate of Ishoyabh III
    (580-658) and the East-Syrian monastic movement, which led to
    the foundation of more than one hundred forty monasteries whose
    locations have been determined in Mesopotamia, western Iran,
    and the Persian Gulf. Baum also highlights the well-documented
    role of East-Syrian doctors and philosophers in the
    intellectual accomplishments of the Abbasid translation
    movement. But his chief interest—and arguably the most
    important contribution of this book—lies in the story of
    the Church of East's vigorous expansion into Central Asia,
    China, and southern India. Baum devotes particular attention to
    the conditions that facilitated the translation of Syriac
    Christian texts into Sogdian, Uighur, and Chinese. In doing so,
    he offers valuable context for understanding the famous
    bilingual Chinese and Syriac stele erected at Xi'an in northern
    China in 781 and dedicated to a priest from Balkh
    (Afghanistan). A Buddhist document of the same decade
    describes, for instance, how an Indian scholar translated texts
    from Uighur with the help of a "Persian" Christian monk named
    King-tsing (Adam), who was already renowned for his
    translations into Chinese.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Baum's
    account juxtaposes archaeological evidence from across Asia,
    introducing documents preserved in a wide array of languages
    and formats. A page from the ninth or tenth-century Sogdian
    lectionary found at Bulayiq, north of the Turfan oasis in
    northwestern China, belongs to the detritus of the trilingual
    monastic library excavated there by the German Theodor Bartus
    in 1904. Hundreds of Syriac fragments from the same excavation
    still await publication more than a century later. Baum
    occasionally taps into documentary sources in non-Christian
    languages. In a series of copper plates inscribed in Tamil, a
    regional king of ninth-century south India guarantees the
    privileges of the Christian merchants of Kerala. But the
    relationship between these documents and the subsequent
    development of Malayalam-speaking Christianity in the same
    region remains frustratingly obscure. The contours of the
    Church become a bit clearer in the Mongol period, where Baum's
    narrative leads the reader through whole clusters of new
    literary and documentary sources in Syriac, Armenian, Latin,
    Persian, and Chinese. The wealth of information crammed into
    these chapters can be disorienting, but it also serves to
    underscore the need for new in-depth studies of particular
    segments in the pre-modern religious history of Asia.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    book's fourth chapter investigates the growing turmoil of
    East-Syrian communities under Ottoman rule, as papal emissaries
    negotiated with the two (and often three) patriarchates of the
    Church of the East based in northern Mesopotamia. The tangled
    ecclesiastical history of this period unfolds against the
    backdrop of the competing patriarchal sees at Diyarbakir, the
    monastery of Rabban Hormizd near Nineveh, and in the highlands
    of Kochanes on the upper reaches of the Great Zab River. The
    chapter has much less to say about the social and cultural
    history of the Church under Ottoman rule. The German original
    arrived too late to take advantage of David Wilmshurst's
    massive catalogue of East-Syrian colophons, the majority of
    them dating to the Ottoman period.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             David Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical
    Organization of the Church of the East, 1318-1913</hi>. CSCO
    582; Subsidia 104 (Louvain: Peeters, 2004). 
         </p>
                </note> The recent work of Heleen
    Murre-van den Berg brilliantly illustrates how such colophons
    can be used to write the social history of this period.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Heleen Murre-van den Berg, "Generous Women in the
    Church of the East between 1550 and 1850."  (January, 2004): 1-57. 
         </p>
                </note> One hopes
    that future surveys will also be able to integrate the evidence
    of later Aramaic literature by writers such as the poet Israel
    of Alqos (†1632).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    latter half of chapter four and chapter five survey the
    multi-faceted relations between the Christians of northern
    Mesopotamia and various scholars, diplomats, and missionaries
    from Europe, Russia, and America. Baum's account offers a
    refreshingly European perspective on these contacts. His list
    of characters includes: Anna Hafner Forneris, an Austrian who
    traveled from Tbilisi to Tabriz in 1830 and left a scandalized
    description of a drunken Eucharist among the "mountain
    Nestorians;" the great Orientalist Edward Sachau, who
    transported more than 250 Syriac manuscripts back to Berlin in
    1880; and the popular novelist Karl May (d. 1912), who provided
    generations of German readers with an image of the region's
    Christians as a noble but endangered people. In <hi rend="italic">Durch das
    wilde Kurdistan</hi>, published in 1892, May describes the
    region's Christians as "the remnants of the once so powerful
    Assyrian people, [who] see the sword of the Turks and the
    dagger of the Kurds hanging forever over them and have endured
    in more recent times atrocities which would make your hair
    stand on end" (131). Winkler's account of the fate of those
    "Nestorians" before, during, and in the wake of the First World
    War offers a sobering narrative of persecution, combat, flight,
    starvation, and broken diplomatic promises.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             On these same themes, see now John Joseph's <hi rend="italic">The
    Modern Assyrians of the Middle East: Encounters with Western
    Christian missions, archaeologists, and colonial powers</hi>
    (Leiden, Boston, and Cologne: Brill, 2000), 106-73. 
         </p>
                </note> The last portion of
    chapter five traces the history of the Church of the East to
    the end of the twentieth century, sketching the formation of
    the North American and European Diaspora and the growth of
    ecumenical dialogue. Chapter six gives a very brief overview of
    the Church of the East's literature preserved in Syriac and
    other languages.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] In sum,
    Baum and Winkler's survey constitutes a welcome addition to the
    growing literature on Christianity in pre-modern Asia. The text
    is probably too dense with names and details to be effective
    for the "non-specialist" readers named as its target audience.
    It is also prohibitively expensive. But research libraries
    should certainly include the title on their shelves. Sixteen
    illustrations and two maps complement and enhance the text. The
    sixteen-page bibliography, organized by chapter, provides a
    valuable guide to further reading and is particularly strong on
    German-language scholarship that is often overlooked in North
    American publications. Few bibliographies are without
    blemishes, but the book's hefty price tag should have paid for
    better copy-editing.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             I list a few examples. The bibliographic citation
    for Samuel Moffett, <hi rend="italic">A History of Christianity in Asia:
    Volume I: Beginnings to 1500</hi> (Mary Knoll, NY: Orbis Books,
    1998) has mistakes in author's name, the book's title, and its
    publication information. E. A. W. Budge translated rather than
    edited <hi rend="italic">The Monks of Kublai Khan</hi> (London: Religious
    Tract Society, 1928), although the publication includes a
    facsimile of the Syriac manuscript. Jean-Maurice Fiey attacked
    the credibility of the <hi rend="italic">Chronique d'Arbèles</hi>, and
    the volume and pagination for <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of
    Séert</hi> and several other primary texts are
    incomplete. These and other mistakes could be easily corrected
    if there is a second edition. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV11N2PRWalker1">Notes</head>
         
         
         
         
         
         
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>