<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">International Syriac Language Project Ljubljana, Slovenia. July 2007</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Terry</forename>
                  <surname>Turner</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2008</date>
            <idno>Vol. 11, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv11n1crfallaturner</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Terry Falla and Beryl Turner</author>
                  <title level="a">International Syriac Language Project Ljubljana, Slovenia. July 2007</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol11/HV11N1CRFallaTurner.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Linguistics</term>
               <term>Lexicography</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    annual meeting of the International Syriac Language Project
    (ISLP) was recently held at the XIXth Congress of IOSOT
    (International Organization for the Study of the Old Testament)
    in Ljubljana, Slovenia, where a number of the participants were
    also involved in the Bible of Edessa meetings and
    presentations.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    meetings and sessions were all held in the superbly appointed
    Faculty of Law Building. The organizers and the IOSOT
    president, Prof. Dr. Jože Krašovec, are to be
    congratulated on a splendidly well organized and resourced
    conference. Such was the efficiency that there was even a
    conference staff member present for the duration of every
    presentation and meeting to ensure that all needs were met.
    Conference delegates were generously treated to a number of
    musical entertainments and receptions in the city, including a
    welcome by the Prime Minister of Slovenia, Mayor of Ljubljana,
    and other dignitaries, and a thrilling rendition of
    Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony, performed under the stars in
    the city square.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The ISLP
    held its business meeting on the morning of Monday 16 July, and
    a dinner for any involved with Syriac and lexicography that
    evening. Papers were delivered and discussed in two sessions,
    on the Tuesday and Thursday, with Wednesday given to
    sightseeing. The next meetings will be at the Symposium
    Syriacum in Granada 2008, and the IOSOT congress in Helsinki
    2010.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    following papers were given, and will be published as
    peer-reviewed essays in a volume edited by Bas ter Haar Romeny
    and Kristian Heal in the series <hi rend="italic">Foundations for Syriac
    Lexicography</hi>, part of the ISLP series <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on
    Syriac Linguistics</hi> published by Gorgias Press.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1">Janet Dyk, “The Hebrew and Syriac
      Cognate Verbs sin, yod, mem and semkath, waw, mim in the
      Books of Kings: Similarities and Differences”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S2">David G.K. Taylor and Kristian S. Heal,
      “Towards an Electronic Corpus of Syriac
      Texts”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S3">Deryle Lonsdale, “A Computational
      Perspective on Syriac Corpus Development and
      Annotation”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S4">Michael Sokoloff, “The Translation
      and Updating of C. Brockelmann’s Lexicon Syriacum:
      Progress Report”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S5">Regina Hunziker-Rodewald, “On
      Polysemy and Homonymy”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S6">Beryl Turner, “Towards a New Syriac
      Dictionary: Lexical Reconsideration of the Term
      “kay” in the Peshitta Bible, Old Syriac Gospels,
      and Harklean Text”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S7">Reinier De Blois, “Wine to Gladden
      the Heart of Man: How to discover the meaning of different
      terms for wine”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S8">Percy van Keulen, “Feminine Nominal
      Endings in Hebrew, Aramaic and Syriac: Derivation or
      Inflection?”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S9">Wido van Peursen and Dirk Bakker,
      “Lemmatization and Grammatical Categorisation: The case
      of “haymen” in Classical Syriac”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S10">Terry C. Falla, “Towards a New
      Syriac Dictionary: Lexical Reconsideration of the Particle
      “kadh” in Classical Syriac”</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S10">Andreas Juckel, “Comparative
      features in a future lexicon of the Syriac New
      Testament”</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner1">1. Janet Dyk, Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner2">The Hebrew and Syriac Cognate Verbs sin, yod, mem and
    semkath, waw, mim in the Books of Kings: Similarities and
    Differences</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] In a
    joint effort of the Peshitta Institute of Leiden and the
    Werkgroep Informatica of the Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam, an
    electronic database has been developed in which the Masoretic
    text and the Peshitta of the Books of Kings have been analyzed
    from morpheme level up through a clause-level synopsis. On the
    basis of the synopsis, sentence constituents are matched,
    providing the basis for matching phrases within clauses, and
    for matching words within phrases. One of the products is an
    electronic translation concordance which provides the
    translation correspondences occurring within Kings. It should
    be stressed that the item that occurs at a specific point in a
    particular text is not necessarily a lexicon-based translation;
    rather, it is a “correspondence” of that item. In
    this manner, both similarities and differences are brought to
    light.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In
    Peshitta Kings the Syriac verb <hi rend="italic">semkath-waw-mim</hi> is
    found as the rendering of the Hebrew verb <hi rend="italic">sin-yod-mem</hi>
    in nearly half of the occurrences. These verbs, so similar in
    sound, shape and meaning do not overlap entirely. In an attempt
    to explain the observed data, the valence patterns of the
    Hebrew verb are compared with those of the Syriac verb. Both
    systematic tendencies and individual deviances from these are
    presented.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner3">2. David G.K. Taylor, University of Oxford, and
    Kristian S. Heal, Brigham Young University</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner4">Towards an Electronic Corpus of Syriac Texts</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    desirability of an electronic corpus of Syriac texts has long
    been recognized (most recently in Lucas Van Rompay’s
    January 2007 <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> article). Several localized and
    limited steps have been made in this direction, most
    significantly with the Peshitta, and as part of the
    Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon project. However, no coordinated
    and large scale effort has yet been attempted. This paper
    reports on a joint initiative by Oxford University and Brigham
    Young University to create a comprehensive electronic corpus of
    Syriac texts. We outline our plans for building the corpus,
    including our methodological approach. We describe the work
    that has been completed thus far, giving details of the 2.5
    million word corpus that we have already assembled. The heart
    of our current initiative is the task of preparing a
    concordance to the complete works of Ephrem. The presentation
    will conclude with a discussion of the status of this
    particular project.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner5">3. Deryle Lonsdale, Brigham Young University</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner6">A Computational Perspective on Syriac Corpus Development
    and Annotation</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] This
    paper discusses current efforts to develop the computational
    infrastructure for collecting, analyzing, annotating, and
    deploying large-scale lexical and textual resources for the
    Syriac language.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Since
    Syriac is a Semitic language, its morphological structure is
    complicated and multifaceted. We discuss our efforts to develop
    a morphological processor for Syriac word forms and compare the
    result to previous efforts by others. The presentation mentions
    development of morphology rules, encoding of lexical items, and
    generation of analysis hypotheses. Of particular interest is
    the treatment of clitics and diacritics.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    Lexical information for the morphological engine relies on an
    XML encoding of useful entries from dictionary resources for
    Syriac. We describe how we follow current best practices for
    lexical content markup, and how this information serves as a
    crucial resource for linguistic processing.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] The
    text corpus situated at the centre of this effort is based on
    Ephrem's writings and has been introduced elsewhere. In this
    presentation, though, we discuss our choice for encoding and
    marking up the content of the text, and give examples of how
    interested scholars will be able to benefit from the final
    product of our efforts.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] We
    also sketch our approach for annotating the corpus,
    particularly for part-of-speech information and morphological
    substructure. A state-of-the-art tagger is presented, and we
    discuss its use of salient features (including results from
    morphological parsing) for machine learning. An active learning
    approach allows us to maximize human annotator cost.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Finally, we discuss issues about user interface tools, data
    visualization, and other questions about deployment of the
    corpus and related lexical data to developers and to end
    users.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner7">4. Michael Sokoloff, Bar Ilan University, Ramat
    Gan</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner8">The Translation and Updating of C. Brockelmann’s
    Lexicon Syriacum: Progress Report (July 2007)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Since my report at the Philadelphia SBL Meeting, much progress
    has been accomplished and the completion of the project is now
    in sight:</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Approximately 95% of the primary references in
      <hi rend="italic">LS</hi> (ca. 86,000) have now been checked in the
      original sources. A large number of errors was found in the
      original references and most of these have now been
      corrected. A residue of errors that could not be located has
      been marked as “n. fnd.” [= not found].</item>
            <item>Complete or partial citations of the cited texts have
      been added to the dictionary for a great majority of the
      references. As a result of this, a great number of
      multivalent Latin glosses in the original have now been
      clarified.</item>
            <item>The dictionary database has been completed and refined by
      the programmer employed on the project. A demonstration of it
      will be given during this presentation.</item>
            <item>The speaker intends to begin working on the updating of
      the etymologies this summer and hopes to complete this phase
      of the project in 2008.</item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner9">5. Regina Hunziker-Rodewald, University of
    Switzerland</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner10">On Polysemy and Homonymy</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    Lexicographers of the Hebrew Bible are faced with the challenge
    of semantically categorizing a growing number of lemmas as
    homonyms and as hapax legomena. In doing so, roots need to be
    split up, which leads to some lexicons — e.g., HALOT and
    DCH – being flooded with so-called “new
    words”. This tendency may well be counteracted by using
    comparative etymology and by thus tracing polysemy. The
    presentation will exemplify how the Swiss team, working on
    KAHAL (a revision of HALAT), is proceeding with the task of
    reducing the number of homonymous roots.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner11">6. Beryl Turner, Whitley College, University of
    Melbourne</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner12">Towards a New Syriac Dictionary: Lexical Reconsideration of
    the Term “kay” in the Peshitta Bible, Old Syriac
    Gospels, and Harklean Text</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] Our
    best comprehensive Classical Syriac dictionaries are more than
    a century old. Inevitably, their lexicalization of words is
    often partial or outdated in its taxonomy, parts of speech, and
    syntactic and semantic analysis. Thus today’s reader of
    Classical Syriac often encounters in a text a word or syntagm
    with a function and/or meaning that is not cited in Syriac
    lexica, or if it is, is either misleading or generalized to the
    extent that it is difficult to know whether it is applicable to
    the instantiation in question.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] This
    paper examines the particle <hi rend="italic">kay</hi> in its contexts in the
    Peshitta Bible, Old Syriac Gospels and the Harklean text, and
    in relation to the Greek underlying it. It will be seen that
    grammatical classifications given to this term do not
    adequately define the quite distinctive ways in which it
    functions in the text. A new proposal will be offered as to how
    to define the term, and a lexical entry is presented that will
    appear in the third volume of the lexical work <hi rend="italic">A Key to the
    Peshitta Gospels</hi>, and form a basis for its reconsideration
    in other early Classical Syriac literature and subsequent
    inclusion in a future comprehensive Syriac-English lexicon.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner13">7. Reinier De Blois, United Bible Societies</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner14">Wine to Gladden the Heart of Man: How to discover the
    meaning of different terms for wine</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] Most
    modern lexicographers agree that the meaning of a lexical entry
    should be described in the form of a definition rather than a
    gloss or a set of glosses. Writing definitions, however, is an
    art in itself. What many lexicographers forget is that
    definitions should be formulated in a way that enables the user
    to compare the meanings of related words in such a way that
    s/he will be able to detect different nuances in meaning among
    the different words. This is not easy unless the compiler
    follows a clearly outlined methodology. This methodology is
    illustrated in this paper with the help of examples from the
    Semantic Dictionary of Biblical Hebrew. It focuses on the
    different terms for wine in the Hebrew Old Testament, and shows
    how this methodology helps both the dictionary compiler and its
    user to get a clear overview of all relevant aspects of the
    meaning of each individual word, including its metaphorical
    usage. This method provides the compiler with the building
    blocks on the basis of which a useful and helpful definition
    can be written.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner15">8. Percy van Keulen, Peshitta Institute Leiden</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner16">Feminine Nominal Endings in Hebrew, Aramaic and Syriac:
    Derivation or Inflection?</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] It
    is in the interest of both morphological analysis and
    lexicography to have a clear perception of the nature of
    feminine endings in the absolute state. Classic dictionaries
    and grammars often appear to be inconsistent in their treatment
    of substantives with feminine endings. Still, on the basis of a
    strict distinction between derivational and inflectional
    endings a consistent approach seems possible.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner17">9. Wido van Peursen and Dirk Bakker, Peshitta
    Institute Leiden</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner18">Lemmatization and Grammatical Categorisation: The case of
    “haymen” in Classical Syriac</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20]
    Decisions concerning grammatical categorization have a
    considerable impact on the lexicographer’s work. An
    example is the treatment of <hi rend="italic">haymen</hi> in Syriac grammars
    and dictionaries: Is it a Payel (Payne Smith), a Pael (Muraoka)
    or a Haphel (Costaz) of the verb &gt;MN? Or is it a
    denominative verb (Duval), or a Hifil borrowed from Hebrew
    (Brockelmann)? And how should we account for the He (rather
    than Alaph)? Is it part of the Hebrew loan word (Brockelmann)?
    Or is it due to strengthening (Duval) or the preservation of an
    ancient form (Nöldeke)? These questions will be addressed
    in our paper. It will appear that they are relevant also to
    other lexemes, because they touch upon the crucial interaction
    of lexicography and grammatical analysis.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner19">10. Terry C. Falla, Whitley College, University of
    Melbourne</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner20">Towards a New Syriac Dictionary: Lexical Reconsideration of
    the Particle “kadh” in Classical Syriac</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] Our
    best comprehensive Classical Syriac dictionaries are more than
    a century old. Inevitably, their lexicalization of words is
    often partial or outdated in its taxonomy, parts of speech, and
    syntactic and semantic analysis. Thus today’s reader of
    Classical Syriac often encounters in a text a word or syntagm
    with a function and/or meaning that is not cited in Syriac
    lexica, or if it is, is either misleading or generalized to the
    extent that it is difficult to know whether it is applicable to
    the occurrence in question.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] By
    way of example, this paper examines the grammatical
    classification, syntactic functions and meanings of the
    particle <hi rend="italic">kadh</hi>. It will be argued that, in the Syriac
    Gospels alone, the uses and meanings of this term goes beyond
    those recorded in existing Syriac lexica. The lexeme is
    anaylzed in its Syriac contexts and in relation to the Greek
    underlying it.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] The
    study of this term has two specific aims: its preparation as an
    entry for the third volume of the lexical work <hi rend="italic">A Key to the
    Peshitta Gospels</hi>, and as a basis for its reconsideration
    in other early Classical Syriac literature and subsequent
    inclusion in a future comprehensive Syriac-English lexicon.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner21">11. Andreas Juckel, Institute for New Testament
    Textual Research, Münster</head>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner22">Comparative features in a future lexicon of the Syriac New
    Testament<ref target="#FN1">1</ref>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] By
    their history the Syriac versions of the New Testament (Old
    Syriac, Peshitta, Philoxenian, and Harklean) are a corpus of
    texts connected by revisional development towards an
    increasingly better formal adaptation to the Greek. This
    development is set out in comparative editions which cover
    (almost) the complete Syriac New Testament. A future lexicon of
    the Syriac New Testament (based on the Peshitta) should include
    comparative information to set out those translational
    properties of the Peshitta in greater detail, which are
    “essential to the study of the Peshitta as a translation
    of the Greek and as a literary work in its own right” (T.
    Falla, <hi rend="italic">A Key to the Peshitta Gospels I, xix</hi>). These
    details refer to 1. orthography (esp. to proper nouns), 2. to
    word formation (esp. to adjectives, adverbs, and to the
    translation of Greek compounds), and 3. to semantics (esp. to
    the semantic difference existing between the Old
    Syriac/Peshitta and the Greek). The purpose of comparison is
    not to inscribe the revisional development of the Syriac NT
    corpus into the lexicon, but solely to serve the study of the
    Peshitta.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25] To
    set out the still idiomatic and non-formalized translation of
    the Peshitta as well as the linguistic restrictions of
    representing Greek word formation and semantics, the Greek
    correspondences and their Harklean calques should be given in a
    special “comparative section” (similar to the
    section of “Syriac-Greek correspondences” in T.
    Falla’s <hi rend="italic">Key</hi>). The purpose of the Harklean
    calques is to represent the “corrections” to the
    Peshitta as they actually occurred in the history of the Syriac
    NT corpus. Although these “corrections” refer to
    translation technique only and intend the reduction of Syriac
    semantics to Greek semantics, they are helpful for
    understanding the translational limits, restrictions, and
    quality of the Peshitta.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV11N1CRFallaTurner23">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> This eleventh paper, while not delivered at the
    conference, will be published in the volume with the above
    <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>