<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Andrzej Uciecha, Ascetyczna nauka w "Mowach" Afrahata [= Ascetic teaching in Aphrahat's "Expositions"], (Studia i Materialy Wydzialu Teologicznego Uniwesytetu Slaskiego w Katowicach, Nr 3), Katowice: Ksiegarnia Sw. Jacka, 2002, 192 pp.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Witold</forename>
                  <surname>Witakowski</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 11, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/bookReview/hv11n2prwitakowski</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Witold Witakowski</author>
                  <title level="a">Andrzej Uciecha, Ascetyczna nauka w "Mowach" Afrahata [= Ascetic teaching in Aphrahat's "Expositions"], (Studia i Materialy Wydzialu Teologicznego Uniwesytetu Slaskiego w Katowicach, Nr 3), Katowice: Ksiegarnia Sw. Jacka, 2002, 192 pp.</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="11">11</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Aphrahat</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    present book is a doctoral dissertation written and defended at
    the Theological Faculty of the Academy of Catholic Theology
    (now: Catholic University of Stefan Wyszynski) in Warsaw in
    2001. The author is a Catholic priest who is now working at the
    Theological Faculty of the Silesian University at Katowice in
    Southern Poland. The book is written in Polish, which is to be
    regretted, as all the potential readers in Poland would be able
    to read English, German or French, while few such readers
    abroad are able to read Polish. There is however a
    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi> in English (pp. 186-192).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Aphrahat
    (ca. 270 - ca. 345), called "The Persian Sage", is the earliest
    Syriac Church Father, which is perhaps the reason for his
    never-ceasing popularity among the Syriac scholars. His work
    "<hi rend="italic">Expositions</hi>", or "<hi rend="italic">Demonstrations</hi>" (Syr.
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">Ta&amp;wÇy%th%</hi>
            </hi>), contains
    23 homilies or treatises, of which the first 22 begin with the
    letters of the Syriac alphabet in order. U. renders the title
    in Polish with the word "<hi rend="italic">Mowy</hi>"—'speeches', which
    seems too general. 'Homilie' or 'wyklady' might have been a
    better choice.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    "<hi rend="italic">Expositions</hi>" make up one of the most famous Syriac
    compositions. They have been translated into German (twice:
    1888 by Bert, 1991 by Bruns), Latin (1894-1907, Parisot),
    English (1869 Gwynn, 1971 Neusner, both partial) and French
    (1988-89 Pierre), an honour that few Syriac compositions share.
    The popularity of the "<hi rend="italic">Expositions</hi>" is however nothing
    new, as already in Late Antiquity and Middle Ages they were
    translated (at least partially) into Armenian and Ethiopic
    (although in both languages they are attributed to Jacob of
    Nisibis), furthermore into Georgian (attr. to Hippolytus) and
    Arabic (attr. to Ephrem).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The work
    of Aphrahat bears witness to early Syriac theological thought
    at a time when it had still been little influenced by Western,
    i.e. Greek, theology (the Church of the East accepted Nicea as
    late as 410 A.D., at the synod of Catholicos Ishaq) and has
    been the object of lively discussion. In particular the
    character of the "proto-monasticism", to which the so-called
    "covenanters" devoted themselves, has attracted several
    scholars since the discovery of Aphrahat's homilies in the
    middle of the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. It is known that these
    were ascetics, but the exact kind of asceticism they were
    devoted to is uncertain. The term in question, "covenanters"
    (Syr. <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay qÇy%m%</hi>
            </hi> and
    fem. <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇn%th qÇy%m%</hi>
            </hi>;
    Uciecha neither uses <hi rend="italic">schwa</hi>, nor does he mark
    spirantization of the <hi rend="italic">beghadhkephath</hi> consonants),
    changed its meaning several times, so that that the meaning
    found in the text of the sixth century—'monks'—has
    hardly any bearing on its semantic value in Aphrahat's
    writings.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] To
    render the term <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay
    qÇy%m%</hi>
            </hi>. U. uses the expression <hi rend="italic">synowie
    przymierza</hi>—'the sons of the covenant'. This
    translation should be avoided in English as it is unnecessarily
    literal and in point of fact incomprehensible (notwithstanding
    the fact that it has been used by some scholars), just as the
    Syriac expression <hi rend="italic">bar</hi> (sing. Of <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay</hi>
            </hi>) <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">tÇl%th§n
    ¯Çn§n</hi>
            </hi>, meaning 'a person thirty
    years old', would be incomprehensible if rendered verbatim:
    'the son of thirty years'. It is however not easy to provide an
    adequate and meaningful Polish translation of the term in
    question: perhaps 'sprzymierzeniec' or 'sprzymierzony' would
    fit, despite some connotations which the Syriac term may
    lack.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In
    addition to an introduction and a conclusion U.'s book contains
    four chapters. In the introduction U. sketches the development
    of Aphrahat's studies, showing his acquaintance with the
    abundant literature on "the Persian sage". This literature is
    to a high degree coextensive with studies on the intricate
    problem of the character of the "covenanters", the topic which
    is dealt with in chapter 1, section 1. Here U. examines other
    terms which were used interchangeably with that of
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family: SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay qÇy%m%</hi>
            </hi>, an
    analysis which allows him to get a better grasp of the meaning
    of the term in question. These terms are <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family: SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">&amp;§dh%y%</hi>
            </hi>—'single',
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">qaddi¯%</hi>
            </hi>—'celibate,
    continent', <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇthºl%</hi>
            </hi>—'virgin
    (masc.)'—all of them unequivocally pointing to
    celibacy—and <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay
    ÿ7(d)tt%</hi>
            </hi>—'the children of the church',
    which poses the problem of their place within the church and of
    their relation to the regular faithful.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    chapter as a whole is devoted to the historical context of
    Aphrahat's ascetic teaching, and since this context is not
    limited to the milieu of the Christian <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">bÇnay
    qÇy%m%</hi>
            </hi>, also non-Orthodox (Markionites) and
    non-Christian (Manichaean, Gnostic, Jewish) ascetic traditions
    are presented, similar phenomena occurring in these. Aphrahat
    himself, although conscious of close parallels between his
    Christian ascetic teaching and those of the "heretics",
    dismissed any such parallels using the argument of theological
    context: it is not ascetic practice in itself which leads to
    salvation, but the context of the faith: if your belief is
    "wrong" your ascetic practice will not help you (p. 53). Of
    interest is his polemic against the Jews to whom the ideal of
    celibacy was contradictory to God's command in <hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi>
    9,18. Aphrahat first rejected the Jewish opposition, caused,
    according to him, by the lasciviousness ( <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">pa&amp;zºth%</hi>
            </hi>) and licensiousness (
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">Ëa&amp;nºth%</hi>
            </hi>) of the
    Jews (<hi rend="italic">Exp</hi>. 18,1), but went on to explain that God's
    intention was not a large quantity of progeny, but its quality,
    while the ideal of sexual abstinence was not unknown to many
    <hi rend="italic">Old Testament</hi> figures (pp. 58-59).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] In
    chapter 2, entitled "Anthropological elements in the ascetic
    teaching of Aphrahat", U. analyses a number of notions such as
    'body'(<hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">pagr%, besr%</hi>
            </hi>), 'soul' (
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">naph¯%</hi>
            </hi>), 'heart' (
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">lebb%</hi>
            </hi>) and 'spirit' (
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">rº&amp;%</hi>
            </hi>), and their role for
    ascetics. Also women are treated here: they are an impediment
    in the ascetics' path to achieving perfection or, in other
    words, the tool of the Devil. This anti-feminist attitude
    (<hi rend="italic">Exp</hi>. 6,3 is a veritable hymn of misogyny!) is only
    weakly mitigated by his providing some positive female examples
    from the <hi rend="italic">Old Testament</hi> (p. 97), which U. correctly
    does not highlight.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Chapter
    3 is devoted to the theological dimension of asceticism in the
    eyes of Aphrahat. Here the most important factors are
    Christological. For an ascetic Christ provides a model as the
    conqueror of Satan and death, as a model of humanity and as an
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">§&amp;§dh%y%</hi>
            </hi>, although
    the term as applied to Christ does not mean 'solitary' but
    '<hi rend="italic">unigenitus</hi>'. Two subsequent sections in the same
    chapter take up pneumatological and eschatological aspects.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] In
    chaper 4 U. resumes the topic of the "covenanters", this time
    taking up their ascetic ideals. He analyses notions such as
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">Ùathl7³%</hi>
            </hi>—which
    in addition to the original meaning of 'a champion' acquires in
    the context discussed the meaning of 'a spiritual athlete',
    i.e. 'an ascetic', <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">Ùakhseny%</hi>
            </hi>—i.e. keeping
    distance from the world (also known as <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">nukhr%yºth%</hi>
            </hi>—'being a stranger'
    scil. to the world), a distance involving liberation from
    things material. Other ideals of the "covenanters" are the
    <hi rend="italic">vita angelica</hi>, i.e. continuous vigilance (scil.
    against the deceits of Satan), sexual purity; and finally an
    <hi rend="italic">imitatio Christi</hi>, in prayer, in separation from the
    world, and even in suffering.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] All
    the assertions are supported by abundant text samples taken
    from the <hi rend="italic">Expositions</hi>. These are provided in as many as
    three forms: the Syriac vocalised text, a transcription (in
    footnotes), and a Polish translation. The latter wherever I
    checked is good. What is a bit odd is the presence of
    transcription and its rules. Since the Syriac text is printed
    vocalised I see no point in providing a transliteration, for it
    is a conventional rendering of the <hi rend="italic">script</hi>, not of a
    <hi rend="italic">pronunciation</hi> that U. gives here. It is the more
    surprising that the convention he uses is difficult, at least
    for the present reviewer, to accept.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Transcription of <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">§h§d%ya</hi>
            </hi>, i.e. with short last
    —<hi rend="italic">a</hi> (on p. 28 twice, p. 29 and 31) may be
    regarded as a typing error (multiplied by computer 'copy'
    function), but the use of the short <hi rend="italic">—e</hi> (without
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">Ù%laph</hi>
            </hi>) in plural ending of
    nouns is met with systematically. This is not a good
    transcription rule because Classical Syriac does not have short
    vowels in open syllables. On the other hand one finds on p. 47,
    footnote 110, <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">ne¯bºq</hi>
            </hi>, i.e. a long vowel, where
    one should have a short one (and in Classical Syriac
    —<hi rend="italic">o</hi>-, not —<hi rend="italic">u</hi>-). Traditionally in
    transcribing Semitic languages macrons are used as marks of the
    length of vowels, no matter what signs (<hi rend="italic">matres
    lectionis</hi> or vowels) are used in the original script,
    whereas in order to note the presence of <hi rend="italic">matres
    lectionis</hi> the circumflex signs are employed.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] To
    what further unfortunate consequences U.'s transliteration
    system leads can also be seen in (for example) footnote 109,
    where we find <hi rend="italic">marqyun</hi>, which renders the name
    'Markion': a simple —o- would suffice. Even more strange
    is <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">walentin%ws</hi>
            </hi> in the same footnote.
    U. follows the unfortunate vocalisation provided by Jean
    Parisot in his edition in <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Syriaca</hi>. This was
    printed in the Serto writng, whose vocalisation is far from
    adequate where texts in early Classical Syriac are concerned.
    In the ending of Valentinos' name, Parisot printed
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">zÇq%ph%</hi>
            </hi> over
    —<hi rend="italic">n</hi>- and then <hi rend="italic">waw</hi> (and
    <hi rend="italic">semkath</hi>). He almost certainly pronounced
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">zÇq%ph%</hi>
            </hi> as 'o', and thus
    this vowel sign only provided the pronunciation already
    indicated by <hi rend="italic">waw</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">mater lectionis</hi>, namely
    the vowel 'o', and not the consonant 'w'. (Incidentally, such
    vocalisation: <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">zÇq%ph%</hi>
            </hi> and <hi rend="italic">waw</hi>, would
    never be used in a real Syriac manuscript). It seems that
    Parisot used <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">zÇq%ph%</hi>
            </hi> as other editors of Syriac
    texts would use a dot over <hi rend="italic">waw</hi>, i.e. just to mark its
    being pronounced as 'o' (and not 'u'). Thus to transliterate
    the ending in question as—<hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">%ws</hi>
            </hi> is,
    to say the least, confusing.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Another example of this inadequate convention in which U.
    unfortunately follows Parisot can be found in <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">ÿidt%</hi>
            </hi> (p. 31, last two lines). This is
    a typical Western Syriac pronunciation, which does not apply in
    the case of a writer of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, who would
    have used the Classical Syriac pronunciation <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">ÿ7(d)tt%</hi>
            </hi>. On the next page, first
    line, we find <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">ÿidt%
    daÙlaha</hi>
            </hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">d-(Ù)all%h%</hi>
            </hi>. It is to be regretted
    that U. has not marked the reduplication of the consonants, a
    feature so characteristic of Classical Syriac, as opposed to
    Late Western Classical Syriac. But, again, Aphrahat lived in
    the fourth century, not in the epoch of, say, Bar'Ebroyo.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] The
    last example of an unfortunate vocalisation, although one which
    has nothing to do with Classical vs. post-Classical Syriac
    problems, is met with on p. 28, l4: <hi rend="italic">wau</hi> (the name of
    the sixth consonant in Syriac alphabet). Neither in Polish
    pronunciation nor in English (and even less so in French) makes
    such spelling any sense.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] Some
    minor lapses in other areas than transcription can be found
    too, as for instance taking Manichaeans and Valentinians for
    "heretics" (p. 41), or attributing the authorship of some
    "<hi rend="italic">Chronicles</hi>" (p. 24) to Isaac of Niniveh.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] As
    to the scholarly literarature taken into account, although this
    is quite extensive, the author missed Robert Murray's
    <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi>, Cambridge 1975, which
    deals <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> with Aphrahat and which has already
    become a classic (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed. publ. by Gorgias Press,
    Piscataway 2004). For works more directly relevant for U.'s
    topic perhaps the most conspicuous omission is the work of
    Shafiq AbouZayd, <hi rend="italic">
               <hi lang="EN-GB" style="font-family:SemiticaTms1" xml:lang="EN-GB">I&amp;idayutha</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">: a study of the life of
    singleness in the Syrian Orient: from Ignatius of Antioch to
    Chalcedon 452 A.D.</hi>, Oxford: ARAM Society for
    Syro-Mesopotamian Studies, 1993. AbouZayd devotes a whole
    chapter to "Aphrahat and the covenanters" (pp. 51-106), and
    some of his analyses are on precisely the notions dealt with by
    U. Another work of some importance for the theme of U.'s
    dissertation is Michael Breydy's, 'Les laïcs et les Bnay
    Qyomo dans l'ancienne tradition de l'Église Syrienne',
    <hi rend="italic">Kanon</hi>, 3 (1977), pp. 51-75. When referring to K.
    Brockelmann's <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum</hi> (in a footnote and in
    the bibliography) U. says "b.m.w." (Polish <hi rend="italic">sine loco</hi>).
    This is strange, since both the original edition (1928) and the
    reprint (1992), at least in my copy, provide the place of
    publication: Halis Saxonum (= Halle am Saale).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] All
    the remarks above should not however be taken as strongly
    critical of the book under review. It has the merit of
    providing an in-depth study of the intricate topic of
    Aphrahat's asceting teaching. For Polish readers U.'s book will
    make useful reading on the topic, and it is in fact the first
    of its kind in Polish. The work is a sign that Syriac studies
    in Poland have gathered momentum.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
