<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of: <hi rend="italic">Treasure-house of Mysteries: Explorations of the Sacred Text through Poetry in the Syriac Tradition</hi>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Kristian S.</forename>
                        <surname>Heal</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Brigham Young University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">Abigail Pearson</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2014</date>
                <idno>Volume 17.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv17n2prheal</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Kristian S. Heal</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: <hi rend="italic">Treasure-house of Mysteries: Explorations of the Sacred Text through Poetry in the Syriac Tradition</hi>, Popular Patristics Series 45</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol17/HV17N2PRHeal.pdf</idno>
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/####</idno><!-- Don't worry about this for now -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2014</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="17">17</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="369" to="371">369&#8211;371</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="11"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p><!-- ILeave this as is -->
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTranscription">
            <change when="2018-06-18">?File created by Abigail Pearson</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Sebastian P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">Treasure-house of Mysteries: Explorations of the Sacred Text through Poetry in the Syriac Tradition</hi>, Popular Patristics Series 45 (Yonkers, N.Y.: St. Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2012). Pp. 306; $24.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="369"/>Sebastian Brock’s editions, translations and studies of early <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Syriac-Language">Syriac</ref> poems on the Bible constitute the most important contribution to our 
					understanding of the early Syriac tradition since the publication of Robert Murray’s <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi> in 1975. This 
					unassuming volume presents in an accessible form the fruit of nearly four decades of Brock’s groundbreaking work on these texts. It is essential reading for 
					anyone interested in the reception of the Bible in late antique Syriac Christianity.
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The poems on the Old and New Testament included in this collection “take three different forms, lyric, narrative, and dialogue” (p. 13), allowing 
					for “three very different approaches to the biblical text” (p. 14). In the lyric poetry (hymns) of <ref target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Ephrem">Ephrem the Syrian</ref>, biblical characters can break free of 
					the fetters of their historical (con)text and become instead contemporary voices, speaking directly to Ephrem and his readers (p. 14). “Narrative poems 
					provide the opportunity for imaginative retellings” of biblical episodes and stories (p. 15). Because the Bible (as Auerbach puts it) is “mysterious and 
					‘fraught with background’,” leaving much of what is important unexpressed,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
							<p rend="footnote text">E. Auerbach, <hi rend="italic">Mimesis: The Representation of Reality in Western Literature</hi> (Princeton: Princeton 
							University Press, 1968), 12.</p>
						</note>
					it actively invites such dynamic, intertextual and creative retellings. Dialogue 
					poems similarly give expression to the fecundity of biblical narrative, but whereas narrative poetry is driven by story, dialogue poems most often “take 
					their starting point from a moment of tension in the biblical text” (p. 15), such as when Cain attacks Abel (Text III.4), or when Potiphar’s wife makes a grab 
					for Joseph (Text III.9). Interestingly, several episodes (e.g., Genesis 22) were treated in more than one genre.
				</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Many of the poems in the latter two genres are based on Brock’s own careful critical editions. These and other specialist publications seem to 
					have been written with just such a volume as the <hi rend="italic">Treasure-house of Mysteries</hi> in mind. This volume is, in fact, the latest in a long 
					series of publications that make the riches of Syriac liturgical poetry available to the lay reader and the contemporary Syriac<pb n="370"/> churches.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
							<p rend="footnote text">Note, for example, numerous publications in the <hi rend="italic">Eastern Churches Review, Sobornost</hi> 
							and <hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi>. See especially Brock’s publication, in Syriac, of a major collection of dramatic dialogue poems on biblical 
							themes (<hi rend="italic">Soghyatha mgabbyatha</hi>) by the Monastery of St. Ephrem (Glane, Holland, 1982), as well as the 1996 article in 
							<hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi> entitled “Syriac Liturgical Poetry: A Resource for Today.”</p>
						</note>
					Brock thus models in this collection the work of “responsible <hi rend="italic">haute vulgarisation</hi>” that he sees as being necessary “if our subject is 
					to flourish.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
							<p rend="footnote text">“Syriac Studies in the Last Three Decades: Some Reflections,” in <hi rend="italic">VI Symposium Syriacum, 1992: University of 
							Cambridge, Faculty of Divinity, 30 August – 2 September 1992</hi>, Orientalia Christiana Analecta 247, ed. René Lavenant (Roma: Pontificio Istituto 
							Orientale, 1994), 13–29, citation from 28–29.</p>
						</note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">Several major themes emerge in this collection that reflect Brock’s larger <hi rend="italic">oeuvre</hi>, above all the place of biblical women 
					in early Syriac liturgical poetry. Beginning in 1974, with the publication of “Sarah and the Akedah” (<hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi>), Brock has paid 
					particular attention to the bold and articulate biblical women portrayed in the Syriac poetic tradition, as can be seen from his further work on Sarah (1981, 
					1984, 1986, 1989, 1992, 2007, 2009), Mary (1976, 1977, 1979, 1982, 1983, 1992, 1994, 2006, 2011), the Sinful Woman of Luke 7:36–50 (1988, 1992), the Widow of 
					Sarepta (1989, 1990), Tamar (2002, 2009), and Potiphar’s Wife (2007).
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
							<p rend="footnote text">Full references can easily be found in Sergey Minov’s “Comprehensive Bibliography on Syriac Christianity,” found at: http://csc.org.il/ db/db.aspx?db=SB.</p>
						</note>
					Almost all the relevant texts are republished in this volume. Brock’s work on these biblical women is foundational, and thus meant to be built upon.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
							<p rend="footnote text">Brock’s plenary address at the 2007 Oxford Patristics Conference focused on this corpus: “Dramatic Narrative Poems on Biblical
							Topics in Syriac,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 45 (2010), 183–196.</p>
							</note>
					And the possibilities are exciting, as the work of Susan Ashbrook Harvey so brilliantly demonstrates.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
							<p rend="footnote text">For example, “Spoken Words, Voiced Silence: Biblical Women in Syriac Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian 
							Studies</hi> 9 (2001), 105–131; “On Mary’s Voice: Gendered Words in Syriac Marian Tradition,” in <hi rend="italic">The Cultural Turn in Late Ancient 
							Studies: Gender, Asceticism, and Historiography</hi>, ed. D. B. Martin and P. C. Miller (Durham / London: Duke University Press, 2005), 63–86; 
							“Impudent Women: Matthew 1:1–16 in Syriac Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 36 (2010), 65–76; <hi rend="italic">Song and Memory: 
							Biblical Women in Syriac Tradition</hi> (Milwaukee, WI: Marquette University Press, 2010).</p>
						</note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="371"/>Another major theme is Ephrem’s idea of scriptural incarnation: God revealing himself to humans through the biblical text (p. 22). This 
					self-revelation is indirect, through symbols, so as not to risk compromising human free will. But, those who respond in the right frame of mind (“thirst” and 
					“love” are the terms used in <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> 32:3) attain a purity of the inner eye of faith that enables them to see the hidden symbols 
					of the biblical text (p. 24).
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
							<p rend="footnote text">For more see, Sebastian P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision of Saint Ephrem</hi> 
							(Kalamazoo: Cistercian Publications, 1992). Ephrem’s view of salvation history is anthologized in Sebastian P. Brock and George Anton Kiraz, eds., 
							<hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian. Select Poems: Vocalized Syriac Text with English Translation, Introduction and Notes</hi>, Eastern Christian 
							Texts 2 (Provo, Utah: Brigham Young University Press, 2006).</p>
						</note>
					Brock’s introduction to “Ephrem on Reading Scripture” (p. 21–30) is a model of clear exposition, preparing the reader to 
					make the most from the texts by Ephrem in the anthology. In addition to this and the general introduction, each text has a separate introduction, often 
					several pages in length.
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">The volume ends where it should, 
					in the convergence of Bible and liturgy.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
							<p rend="footnote text">The Syriac tradition is entirely absent from Jean Danielou’s <hi rend="italic">The Bible and the Liturgy</hi> (Indiana: University of Notre Dame Press, 1956).</p>
						</note>
					The biblical poetry presented in this volume did not live outside the liturgy, unlike contemporary commentaries. Yes, exegesis is being done continually in 
					these texts,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
							<p rend="footnote text">See, for example, Susan Ashbrook Harvey, “Performance as Exegesis: Women’s Liturgical Choirs in Syriac Tradition,” in 
							<hi rend="italic">Inquiries into Eastern Christian Worship: Selected Papers of the Second International Congress of the Society of Oriental Liturgy</hi>, 
							Eastern Christian Studies 10, ed. Bert Groen, Steven Hawkes-Teeples and Stefanos Alexopoulos (Leuven: Peeters, 2010), 47–64.</p>
						</note>
					but they are not solely or even primarily exegetical in character. Syriac poetry was sung in a liturgical setting, antiphonally in the case of the dialogue poems, and with refrains in both lyric and narrative poems. 
					These poems allowed the lectionary readings to come alive, creating not just a “Bible as it Was,” to use James Kugel’s phrase, but a Bible that reaches out 
					to the congregation through drama and imagination, presenting an immanent rather than a transcendent encounter with the divine.
				</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>