<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Fourfold Gospel in the Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Matthew R.</forename>
                        <surname>Crawford</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Department of Theology and Religion, Durham University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2015</date>
                <idno>18.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv18n1crawford</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Matthew R. Crawford</author>
                        <title level="a">The Fourfold Gospel in the Writings of Ephrem the Syrian</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol18/HV18N1Crawford.pdf</idno>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available --><!-- Don't do anything here yet -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2015</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="vol" n="18">18</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="pp" from="9" to="51">9–51</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="order" n="2"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Ephrem</term>
                    <term>Diatessaron</term>
                    <term>Fourfold Gospel</term>
                    <term>Commentary on the Gospel</term>
                    <term>Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2020-05-27">File created by Joss Childs</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="9"/>
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Ephrem of Nisibis is unique among patristic authors for having
                    authored a commentary on Tatian’s gospel commonly known as the
                    “Diatessaron.” In this article I examine Ephrem’s corpus to
                    determine what evidence exists for his knowledge and use of gospel
                    versions beyond that of Tatian, most especially the fourfold, or
                    separated gospel. I point out that Ephrem, in keeping with Greek
                    and Latin authors, occasionally used poetic imagery for the fourfold
                    gospel, and, moreover, that he knew at least the Synoptic genealogies
                    and the Johannine prologue as distinct texts. It is undeniable,
                    therefore, that he knew of and to some degree used the separated,
                    fourfold gospel, even if this remained slight in comparison with his
                    reliance upon Tatian’s version. Furthermore, on six occasions
                    Ephrem refers to an unspecified “Greek” gospel version. Previous
                    scholarship has almost universally interpreted these passages as
                    references to a separated gospel in Syriac, but I argue that these are
                    best taken as references to an actual Greek version, and may well be
                    allusions to a Greek edition of Tatian’s work. Ephrem’s usage of
                    multiple gospel versions suggests that at this point in the Syriac
                    tradition, the concept of ‘gospel’ was fluid and more undefined than
                    would be the case in the fifth century when attempts were made to
                    restrict its sense to the fourfold gospel. 
                </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="introduction" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In the words of the late William Petersen, the fourth-century
                    commentary of Ephrem the Syrian “remains the premier witness to
                    the text of the Diatessaron.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p xml:lang="en">
                        1 William L. Petersen, <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron: Its Creation, Dissemination,
                            Significance, and History in Scholarship</hi>, Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae 25
                        (Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1994), 115-116. 
                    </p></note>
                    Moreover, Ephrem’s commentary
                    occupies a unique place in early Christianity as the only surviving
                    commentary on a gospel text other than the usual, fourfold gospel
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en">
                        2 Ephrem’s disciple Mar Aba also wrote a commentary on Tatian’s
                        gospel that survives in fragments. Cf. Gerrit J. Reinink, “Neue Fragmente
                        zum Diatessaronkommentar des Ephraem-schülers Aba,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                            Lovaniensia Periodica</hi> 11 (1980): 117-133. 
                    </p></note>
                    Indeed, although he was, according to the report of Sozomen the
                    historian, greatly admired by Greek-speaking Christians such as
                    Basil of Caesarea and although he, like Basil, opposed the Arians
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p xml:lang="en">
                        3 Sozomen, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 3.16.3-4.
                    </p></note>
                    his commentary on the gospel text created by the second-century
                    heretic Tatian causes him to stand out sharply against the backdrop
                    of other fourth-century authors for whom the tetraevangelium was
                    the unquestioned standard. Undoubtedly Ephrem’s usage of this
                    peculiar gospel text is related to the fact that he wrote in Syriac and
                    lived on the border of the Roman Empire, spending most of his
                    life in Nisibis, before fleeing to Edessa when the Romans ceded the
                    city to the Persians after Julian’s disastrous eastern campaign.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Thus, Ephrem’s composition of a commentary on Tatian’s
                    gospel could be taken as an indication that he stands apart from the
                    Greek patristic tradition, inhabiting a Syriac world as it existed
                    prior to the time when the Greek church imposed itself upon what
                    has been called a “genuinely Asian Christianity.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en">
                        4 Sebastian Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision of Saint
                            Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, Cistercian Studies 124 (Kalamazoo, MI: Cistercian
                        Publications, 1992), 15.
                    </p></note>
                    Indeed, in the
                    opinion of Sebastian Brock, Ephrem’s significance lies precisely in
                    the fact that he belongs to a version of Christianity that “was as yet
                    comparatively little touched by [the] process of hellenization, or as
                    we may call it, Europeanization or Westernization.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en">
                        5 <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 160.
                    </p></note>
                    On this
                    reading, we should not be surprised if Ephrem used a gospel text
                    quite unlike that current in Greek churches, since his contact with
                    the Greek world was minimal at best.
                </p>
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    However, this picture of Ephrem as untouched by the forces
                    of Hellenization has recently been subjected to significant critique
                    in the work of Ute Possekel. Through a careful reading of the
                    Syrian’s corpus, Possekel has demonstrated beyond any doubt that
                    Ephrem was actually well versed in the philosophical milieu that
                    broadly characterized the late antique Mediterranean world, and
                    that he had a particular affinity for Stoic philosophy
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p xml:lang="en">
                        6 <hi rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts in the Writings of Ephrem the
                            Syrian</hi>, CSCO 580, Subsidia 102 (Louvain: Peeters, 1999).
                    </p></note>
                    As such, he
                    can hardly be said to be ‘un-Hellenized.’ This clear evidence of
                    Ephrem’s knowledge of Greek philosophical sources forces us to
                    reconsider his idiosyncratic usage of Tatian’s gospel. If the Syriac
                    culture of Nisibis and Edessa had absorbed Hellenistic philosophy
                    by at least the mid-fourth century, it is unlikely that the version of
                    Christianity that existed in those places remained untouched by
                    Greek Christian sources.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    To be clear, there is good reason to think that churches in
                    Syriac-speaking areas were peculiar in their usage of Tatian’s
                    gospel. While there is slim evidence that Tatian’s work circulated
                    widely in the Greek world, it was quite possibly the earliest version
                    in which the written gospel reached the Syriac world, and it enjoyed
                    a primacy in some areas until the first half of the fifth century
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p xml:lang="en">
                        7 For an up-to-date introduction to early Syriac versions, see Peter J.
                        Williams, “The Syriac Versions of the New Testament,” in <hi rend="italic">The Text of the
                            New Testament in Contemporary Research: Essays on the Status Quaestionis</hi>, 2nd
                        ed., ed. Bart D. Ehrman and Michael W. Holmes (Leiden: Brill, 2013),
                        143-166.
                    </p></note>
                    However, given the interaction between Greek and Syriac sources
                    apparent in Ephrem’s writings, we should expect that his
                    knowledge of gospel texts presents a similarly mixed picture.
                    Hence, in what follows, I intend to investigate Ephrem’s corpus in
                    search of evidence that he knew and availed himself of not only the
                    Syriac version of Tatian’s gospel, but also the fourfold, or separated
                    gospel.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    I wish to argue that, although Tatian’s work remained the
                    standard gospel version for Ephrem and his community, he
                    nevertheless was aware of the existence of the fourfold gospel, and,
                    moreover, he knew the Matthean and Lukan genealogies and the
                    Johannine prologue as distinct texts linked with their respect
                    evangelists. A handful of other passages in his corpus which display
                    <pb n="12"/>
                    a greater knowledge of evangelist traditions are likely later
                    interpolations and so do not reflect Ephrem’s own knowledge.
                    Furthermore, I suggest that Ephrem’s allusions to “the Greek”
                    gospel, although almost universally taken by previous scholarship
                    as references to a separated, Syriac gospel, are best understood as
                    allusions to an actual Greek version, and possibly to a Greek
                    edition of Tatian’s work. This picture of Ephrem making use of a
                    range of gospel literature is in keeping with Possekel’s argument
                    that he had a foot in both the Syriac and Greek worlds. Moreover,
                    it suggests that he occupied a transitional moment in the cross-
                    fertilization of Greek and Syriac Christianity. His willingness to
                    continue using Tatian’s gospel despite his awareness of the fourfold
                    gospel contrasts sharply with the attitude displayed two generations
                    later by Theodoret and Rabbula who insisted that only the fourfold
                    gospel in Syriac translation be used in the churches under their
                    care. To this degree Brock’s interpretation of Ephrem is correct,
                    since the Syriac milieu in which he wrote apparently tolerated a
                    greater diversity than would be the case in the following century.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    One way to approach this topic would be to compare the
                    gospel texts cited by Ephrem with the Vetus Syra or with the
                    Peshitta to see if they correspond to either of the earliest known
                    Syriac versions of the separated gospel. This was the method
                    followed by F. C. Burkitt one hundred years ago, who concluded
                    that Ephrem certainly did not use the Peshitta, and more often
                    than not used Tatian’s version rather than the Vetus Syra
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p xml:lang="en">
                        8 F.C. Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Quotations From the Gospel</hi>, Texts and
                        Studies 7.2 (Cambridge: University Press, 1901), 56. The articles of T.
                        Baarda over the past several decades have mounted much additional
                        evidence for Ephrem’s usage of the so-called “Diatessaron.” See, e.g.,
                        “‘The Flying Jesus’: Luke 4:29-30 in the Syriac Diatessaron,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae
                            Christianae</hi> 40 (1986): 313-341.
                    </p></note>
                    However, positive evidence that the Syrian usually used Tatian’s
                    gospel does not exclude the possibility that he also knew and
                    availed himself of other gospel versions. Therefore, I intend to take
                    a different approach, considering three different lines of inquiry:
                    first, the imagery for the fourfold gospel that occurs in Ephrem’s
                    corpus; second, Ephrem’s awareness of individual evangelists; and
                    third, what to make of the references in his corpus to “the Greek”
                    version. As will become clear in what follows, many of the passages
                    I will consider have been examined previously by Burkitt and
                    <pb n="13"/>
                    several others. However, several important passages have been
                    overlooked in these prior discussions, and even those passages
                    which have previously received some attention merit further
                    scrutiny. Hence, I intend to provide the most thorough
                    consideration thus far of the evidence for Ephrem’s knowledge of
                    the fourfold gospel.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv18n1.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1. IMAGERY FOR THE FOURFOLD GOSPEL IN EPHREM’S
                    CORPUS</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Metaphorical imagery occupied a central place in Irenaeus’ famous
                    defense of the fourfold gospel, and such imagery became a
                    widespread and consistent feature of the Christian tradition,
                    whether in its Greek, Latin, or Syriac forms. Ephrem, who was
                    chiefly remembered for his poetic insight, also used such imagery,
                    though only in a very small number of passages. Three are
                    particularly relevant.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The first passage occurs in his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> 48.10. Here, at
                    the end of this hymn, Ephrem writes,
                    <lg>
                        <l>The Gospel pours forth (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܚܬ</foreign>) in the type of the
                            Gihon (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܝܚܘܢ</foreign>) to give water.
                        </l>
                        <l>By the Euphrates (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܦܪܬ</foreign>) its fruit (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܝܗ</foreign>) is
                            represented because it multiplied its teaching.
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            He depicts its type by the Pishon (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܦܝܫܘܢ</foreign>) and
                            the cessation (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܦܘܫܗ</foreign>) (of its investigation. 
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            It cleans us (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܩܠܬܢ</foreign>) like the Tigris (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܩܠܬ</foreign>) (by its
                            speech. 
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            We will bathe and we will ascend through it to the
                            encounter in Paradise . . 
                            <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en">
                                9 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. de fide</hi> 48.10 (Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des
                                    Syrers Hymnen de Fide</hi>, CSCO 154, Scriptores Syri 73 (Louvain: L. Durbecq,
                                1955), 154). I am grateful to Paul S. Russell for allowing me to consult his
                                pre-publication version of the English translation of these hymns, which I
                                reproduce above.
                            </p></note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    Other early Christian authors, such as Hippolytus, Cyprian,
                    Victorinus of Petovium and Jerome used the four rivers of paradise
                    as a metaphor for the fourfold gospel
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p xml:lang="en">
                        10 Hippolytus, <hi rend="italic">comm. Dan.</hi> 1.18; Cyprian, <hi rend="italic">ep.</hi> 73.10.3; Victorinus, <hi rend="italic">In
                            Apoc.</hi> 4.4; Jerome, <hi rend="italic">comm. Mt.</hi>, prol.
                    </p></note>
                    so it is not without warrant
                    <pb n="14"/>
                    that Louis Leloir and Christian Lange have taken this passage as a
                    reference to the four gospels
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p xml:lang="en">
                        11 Cf. Louis Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le témoignage d’Éphrem sur le Diatessaron</hi>, CSCO 227,
                        Subsidia 19 (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1962), 72-73; Christian
                        Lange, “Ephrem, His School, and the Yawnaya: Some Remarks on the
                        Early Syriac Versions of the New Testament,” in <hi rend="italic">The Peshitta: Its Use in
                            Literature and Liturgy: Papers Read At the Third Peshitta Symposium</hi>, ed. Robert
                        Bas ter Haar Romeny, Monographs of the Peshitta Institute Leiden 15
                        (Leiden: Brill, 2006), 166-67.
                    </p></note>
                    However, a closer examination
                    suggests that, while this interpretation of the passage is possible, it
                    is not required. First of all, we should note that the word translated
                    here as “Gospel” is not <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign> but rather <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܒܪܬܐ</foreign> .%$#Though the
                    two terms have obviously overlapping semantic domains, the
                    former is clearly transliterated from Greek whereas the latter is a
                    native Syriac term. In the Peshitta New Testament these terms are
                    used interchangeably, with no discernible distinction between them,
                    and Tj. Baarda has argued that for Aphrahat they are also
                    synonymous
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en">
                        12 Tjitze Baarda, <hi rend="italic">The Gospel Quotations of Aphrahat, the Persian Sage:
                            Aphrahat’s Text of the Fourth Gospel</hi> (Amsterdam: Vrije Universiteit 
                        Amsterdam, 1975), 323-324, disagreeing with F.C. Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-
                            Mepharreshe</hi>, 2 vols. (Cambridge: The University Press, 1904), II.180, 
                        regards the two words as synonymous for Aphrahat, since in his usage
                        “both words may mean both the Gospel-Book and the Good Message.”
                        Baarda does not discuss Ephrem’s usage of the terms. 13 Cf. Matthew R. Crawford, “Diatessaron, A
                    </p></note>
                    It is difficult to know for certain how Ephrem
                    distinguished them, if indeed he did so at all, but it is clear that he
                    called his gospel commentary an exposition of the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign> and
                    not the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܒܪܬܐ</foreign>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p xml:lang="en">
                        13 Cf. Matthew R. Crawford, “Diatessaron, A Misnomer? The
                        Evidence of Ephrem’s Commentary,” <hi rend="italic">Early Christianity</hi> 4 (2013): 362-85.
                    </p></note>
                    Hence, it is possible that <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign> in his usage
                    refers to his written text while <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܒܪܬܐ</foreign> is associated more generally
                    with the proclamation of the good news, in which case we need not
                    read the above passage as a reference to the fourfold gospel.
                    Furthermore, there is certainly a poetic play on words going on in
                    this passage, since each of the names of the four rivers sounds
                    similar to the four qualities of the gospel mentioned in each line.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p xml:lang="en">
                        14 So also Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide</hi>,
                        CSCO 155, Scriptores Syri 74 (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1967),
                        131.
                    </p></note>
                    Thus, the imagery of the four rivers may simply serve the purpose
                    of this poetic device, being used to illustrate the manifold effect of
                    <pb n="15"/>
                    gospel proclamation, rather than standing as an allusion to its
                    fourfold written form.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The next two passages much more clearly demonstrate an
                    awareness of the gospel in its fourfold form. Lange has drawn
                    attention to Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Faith</hi> 2.39-40, in which the Syrian
                    says, “Four fountains (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܪ̈ܒܥܐ ܡܒ̈ܘܥܝܢ</foreign>) (flow down with truth for
                    the four regions of the world.” Just prior to this sentence he speaks
                    of the “former fountains” which are “sufficient,” and in what
                    follows he refers to the revelation given to Simon Peter. He then
                    tells his hearers that the “mighty stream” which came to Simon
                    flowed also to them, a torrent that is even greater than the “fount
                    of Eden.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p xml:lang="en">
                        15 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Ser. de fide</hi> 2.39-48 (Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des
                            Syrers Sermones de Fide</hi>, CSCO 212, Scriptores Syri 88 (Louvain: Secrétariat
                        du CorpusSCO, 1961), 8-9). Cf. Lange, “Ephrem, His School, and the
                        Yawnaya,” 167.
                    </p></note>
                    Ephrem’s intent in this paragraph seems to be to
                    exhort his hearers to be content with what Scripture says as they
                    contemplate the divine, rather than attempting to pry into matters
                    that remain hidden to human knowledge. In light of the reference
                    to Peter, the “former fountains” presumably refers to the divine
                    revelation given to the apostles, which Ephrem’s opponents
                    transgress by attempting to provide an explanation for the Son’s
                    generation. The “four fountains” then, is likely a reference to the
                    four gospels which preserve the apostolic witness to the revelation
                    of Christ. Furthermore, Ephrem’s cosmological notion that the
                    four gospels correspond to the four regions of the world was a
                    point first made by Irenaeus and then picked up by a number of
                    later Greek and Latin authors
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p xml:lang="en">
                        16 See <hi rend="italic">haer.</hi> 3.11.8.
                    </p></note>
                    so in this respect his understanding
                    of the fourfold gospel was in keeping with the wider Christian
                    tradition.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The final passage is even more telling than the previous three.
                    In his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Virginity</hi> 51.2, Ephrem once again poetically
                    interweaves imagery from creation with the themes of Scripture
                    and revelation. This time he notes that, just as the sun shone forth
                    in every place on the fourth day of creation, so also “our sun shone
                    forth in four books” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܐܪܒܥܐ ܣܦܪ̈ܝܢ ܐܙܠܓ ܠܗ ܗܘ ܫܡܫܢ</foreign>).<hi rend="superscrip">17</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en">
                        17 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. de virg.</hi> 51.2 (Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des
                            Syrers Hymnen de Virginitate</hi>, CSCO 223, Scriptores Syri 94 (Louvain:
                        Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1962), 162).
                    </p></note>
                    <pb n="16"/>
                    There can be little doubt that the “four books” mentioned here are
                    the four canonical gospels, from which the light of the gospel has
                    gone forth into the earth. Moreover, the geographic spread of the
                    gospel to the four regions mentioned above in the <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Faith</hi>
                    is also evident here in the metaphor of the sun that shines upon all
                    creation.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    These references to the fourfold gospel are few in Ephrem’s
                    corpus, but they do demonstrate that he was at least aware of the
                    tetraevangelium, though they leave open the question of to what
                    extent he actually used it. It is notable that in the unambiguous
                    reference to the fourfold gospel in the <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Faith</hi> he is
                    particularly concerned with emphasizing the authoritative tradition
                    handed down from the apostles, which they had received from
                    Christ. The same intent is possibly also implicit in the latter passage
                    from the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Virginity</hi>. In other words, he does not speak of
                    the fourfold gospel as though it were the text regularly used by him
                    and his community, but rather as the original deposit of revelation
                    given by Christ to his followers. It is also striking that in these
                    passages he demonstrates no attempt to state the relationship
                    between the fourfold gospel and Tatian’s gospel upon which he
                    authored a commentary, nor does he betray any sense that these
                    gospel versions should be opposed one to another.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Moreover, we should also observe that Ephrem does not say
                    there are “four gospels,” but rather “four books.” In fact, he
                    displays a consistent pattern of speaking of the “Gospel” only in
                    the singular. This tendency is well illustrated in his <hi rend="italic">Hymns against
                        Heresies</hi> 22.1. He begins this acrostic poem by comparing Scripture
                    to the alphabet. As the alphabet is complete and lacks no letter, so
                    too also is “the truth written / In the holy Gospel / With the
                    letters of the alphabet, / A perfect measure that admits / Neither
                    lack nor surplus.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p xml:lang="en">
                        18 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. contra haer.</hi> 22.1 (Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem
                            des Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses</hi>, CSCO 169, Scriptores Syri 76 (Louvain: L.
                        Durbecq, 1957), 78). I have here used the unpublished translation of
                        Adam C. McCollum which can be accessed at <ref target="http://archive.org/details/
                            EphremSyrusHymnsAgainstHeresies22">http://archive.org/details/
                            EphremSyrusHymnsAgainstHeresies22</ref> 
                    </p></note>
                    The mention of truth being written indicates
                    that here Ephrem has in mind not just generic gospel
                    proclamation, but specifically the gospel in written form. It is
                    therefore notable to see him refer to the gospel in the singular (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign>). Thus, even though he on occasion acknowledged
                    <pb n="17"/>
                    the existence of the gospel in its fourfold form, Ephrem’s idea of
                    “gospel” retains a notion of unity that corresponds with the
                    singular form in which he knew the gospel in Syriac.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In fact, Ephrem’s mention of “four books” corresponds to at
                    least one other roughly contemporaneous Syriac source that is of
                    great significance. The earliest copy of the separated gospels in
                    Syriac, the Codex Sinaiticus Palimpsest written in the late fourth or
                    early fifth century, calls itself the “Gospel of the Four Separated
                    Books” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ ܕܡܦܪ̈ܫܐ ܐܪ̈ܒܥܐ ܣܦܪ̈ܝܢ</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en">
                        19 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>, II.31. My translation differs
                        slightly from that of Burkitt.
                    </p></note>
                    This parallel does
                    not necessarily imply a direct link between Ephrem and Sinaiticus,
                    but does suggest that the unknown Syriac scribe responsible for the
                    manuscript inhabited a Syriac milieu similar to that of Ephrem. The
                    scribe, who was likely accustomed to the gospel in its singular
                    form, sought to retain the notion of singularity for the word
                    “gospel” and preferred to speak of the plurality in terms of
                    multiple “books.”
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv18n1.2.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2. EPHREM’S KNOWLEDGE OF EVANGELIST TRADITIONS</head>
                <head>2.1 Evangelist Traditions in the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi></head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    We have now seen that Ephrem knew that the gospel existed in a
                    fourfold form, but we should press further and look for clues that
                    he knew more about these “four books” beyond their mere
                    existence. It is, of course, possible that some of the gospel citations
                    in his corpus actually come from the separated gospel, but since
                    much of Tatian’s gospel presumably overlapped with the
                    tetraevangelium, it is often difficult to determine the source of any
                    given citation. However, information about the individual
                    evangelists is a more sure sign that Ephrem knew something of
                    what made each of the gospels distinct from one another.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In searching for evangelist traditions in Ephrem’s corpus, it is
                    best to begin with his gospel commentary before extending the net
                    more widely
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p xml:lang="en">
                        slightly from that of Burkitt. 20 The authenticity of the commentary has been questioned by some
                        on the grounds that it is inconsistent with the authentic works of Ephrem
                        and on the basis of the fact that it exists in two separate versions, an
                        Armenian and a Syriac one, which diverge from one another in a number
                        <pb n="18"/>
                        of instances. Nevertheless, Carmel McCarthy, Ephrem’s English
                        translator, asserts that it would be “unduly sceptical to remove Ephrem’s
                        name totally from [the] commentary” (<hi rend="italic">Saint Ephrem’s Commentary on
                            Tatian’s Diatessaron: An English Translation of Chester Beatty Syriac MS 709</hi>, Journal of Semitic Studies Supplement 2 (Oxford: Published by Oxford
                        University Press on behalf of the University of Manchester, 1993), 34).
                        For a recent survey of such matters, see Christian Lange, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of
                            Christ in the Syriac Commentary on the Diatessaron</hi>, CSCO 616, Subsidia 118
                        (Louvain: Peeters, 2005), 36-68; id., <hi rend="italic">Ephraem der Syrer. Kommentar zum
                            Diatessaron I</hi>, Fontes Christiani 54/1 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2008), 56-81.
                        Perhaps, as suggested in Sebastian P. Brock, “Notulae Syriacae: Some
                        Miscellaneous Identifications,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 108 (1995): 77, n.15, the
                        commentary derives from notes taken down by Ephrem’s disciples.
                        Similarly, Lange, <hi rend="italic">Kommentar zum Diatessaron</hi>, 81, considers it likely that a
                        student compiled the work. In other words, while the commentary must
                        be handled with an awareness of potential interpolations, we should not
                        conclude that it tells us nothing about Ephrem’s gospel versions.
                    </p></note>
                    As I have noted in a previous publication, nowhere
                    <pb n="18"/>
                    in Ephrem’s gospel commentary is the title “Diatessaron” or the
                    name “Tatian” mentioned. Instead, Ephrem gave his exposition
                    the rather austere title <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> (hereafter <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi>), as
                    can be seen from the sole surviving Syriac manuscript, Chester
                    Beatty 709, as well as from later Syriac references to his work. This
                    title suggests that he knew Tatian’s work as simply the “Gospel,”
                    despite Eusebius’ report that Tatian called it the “Gospel through
                    Four,” or “Diatessaron.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p xml:lang="en">
                        21 Crawford, “Diatessaron, A Misnomer?” See Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 4.29.6.
                    </p></note>
                    In keeping with this generic title, the
                    gospel cross-references cited in the commentary are introduced on
                    six occasions as coming from an unspecified <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܣܛܐ</foreign> (“evangelist”)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en">
                        22 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.7; II.1; III.9; VII.15; IX.14a. At <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26 the word also
                        occurs, though in a section that I shall argue below is an interpolation into
                        Ephrem’s text.
                    </p></note>
                    On two occasions the word is used to introduce a
                    citation from the Gospel of John (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.7; IX.14a), three times for
                    the Gospel of Matthew (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> II.1; III.9), and once for the Gospel
                    of Luke (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> VII.15).
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    As can be seen from a passage early in commentary, these
                    citations attributed to an <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܣܛܐ</foreign> are best taken as references
                    to the gospel text upon which Ephrem is commenting, with the
                    result that the unspecified “evangelist” is probably the individual
                    responsible for this united gospel text, rather than one of the four
                    canonical authors. The Syriac gospel commented upon by Ephrem
                    <pb n="19"/>
                    began with John 1:1-5 before transitioning to Luke 1:5 and the
                    subsequent Lukan narrative about the birth of John the Baptist.
                    Hence John 1:5 and Luke 1:5 stand on either side of a “seam” at
                    which Tatian stitched together his source materials. As Ephrem
                    concludes the section of his commentary on John 1:1-5 he writes,
                </p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block" xml:lang="en">
                    [The evangelist] next proclaims the inauguration
                    of the economy with the body, and begins by
                    saying that he whom the darkness did not
                    comprehend (Jn 1:5), nonetheless came into being
                    in the days of Herod, king of Judea (Lk 1:5)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en">
                        23 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.7 (Louis Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem, Commentaire de l’Évangile
                            concordant, texte syriaque (Manuscrit Chester Beatty 709)</hi>, Chester Beatty
                        Monographs 8 (Dublin: Hodges Figgis &amp; Co., 1963), 6).
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block" xml:lang="syr">
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">
                        ܐܩܦ ܕܢܪܙܝܘܗܝ ܠܫܪܝܐ ܕܡܕܒܪܢܘܬܗ ܕܒܝܕ
                        ܦܓܪܐ. ܘܫܪܝ ܕܢܐܡܪ ܕܡܢ ܕܚܫܘܟܐ ܠܐ ܐܕܪܟܗ.
                        ܗܘܐ ܕܝܢ ܒܝܘ̈ܡܝ ܗܪܘܕܣ ܡܠܟܐ ܕܝܗܘܕܐ
                    </foreign>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Although Ephrem is surely aware that the subject matter of John
                    1:1-5 differs markedly from that which is taken up in Luke 1:5 and
                    following, he seems here to attribute the authorship of both
                    passages to the same individual, likely the “evangelist” to whom he
                    refers earlier in his exposition of John 1:5. The author who
                    previously said the darkness did not comprehend the light “next”
                    said that this one came to pass in the days of Herod. Therefore,
                    this passage suggests that Ephrem’s “evangelist” mentioned several
                    times in the commentary was the individual responsible for the text
                    before him, rather than Matthew, Mark, Luke, or John individually.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    There are, however, two passages in the commentary that seem
                    to present a different picture. One of these is almost certainly a
                    later interpolation though the second is possibly original. Ephrem’s
                    commentary as it is available to us today exists in two recensions,
                    one in Syriac and one in Armenian, and although the Armenian
                    usually represents a close rendering of the Syriac original, there are
                    passages which appear only in the Armenian and also some which
                    show up only in the Syriac. As a result of this divergence in the two
                    traditions, Christian Lange has argued that interpolations occurred
                    <pb n="20"/>
                    in both recensions
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p xml:lang="en">
                        24 See Lange, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ</hi>, 36-68. See also the useful table
                        comparing the two recensions at Lange, <hi rend="italic">Kommentar zum Diatessaron</hi>, 56-59.
                    </p></note>
                    One such passage that occurs only in the
                    Syriac version is the second half of <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26, a paragraph that
                    evinces a greater knowledge of the individual evangelists than is
                    evident from the other unspecified references to the “evangelist.”
                    This paragraph occurs in the midst of Ephrem’s exegesis of the
                    annunciation to Mary, and Mary’s subsequent visit with Elizabeth.
                    Here Ephrem is primarily concerned with emphasizing Mary’s
                    descent from the tribe of Judah, rather than from the tribe of Levi,
                    despite the fact that Elizabeth, who was presumably a Levite, was
                    called her kinswoman (Luke 1:36). For Ephrem it is essential that
                    Mary be descended from David, and therefore from the tribe of
                    Judah, in order for Christ to be the heir of the promises given to
                    David. He makes this point by arguing on the basis of Luke 2:4,
                    which in his version states that both Mary and Joseph were from
                    the house of David (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.25)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en">
                        25 On the peculiar version of Luke 2:4 cited by Ephrem, see Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le témoignage</hi>, 84-88. Leloir posits that Ephrem’s version represents a later
                        revision of Tatian’s work, since Theodoret reported that Christ’s descent
                        from David was omitted by the supposed heretic. However, it is more
                        likely that this was Theodoret’s own contrived explanation for Tatian’s
                        omission of the genealogies, which he mentioned immediately prior to
                        discussing the issue of Davidic descent. In other words, we need not posit
                        a later revision of Tatian’s work to account for Ephrem’s text of Luke 2:4. 
                    </p></note>
                    He next cites a string of cross-
                    references all of which mention Jesus’ Davidic lineage (Luke 1:32;
                    Isa 11:1; Luke 1:69; 3 Cor 5; 2 Tim 2:8), and then suggests that the
                    tribes of Levi and Judah had mixed through the marriage of Aaron
                    and the sister of Nahshon (cf. Exod 6:23) (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="en">
                        26 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> revision of Tatian’s work to account for Ephrem’s text of Luke 2:4. 26 CGos I.26 (Leloir 1963, 24-26). In the midst of this paragraph, the
                        Syriac recension contains three additional cross-references that do not
                        appear in the Armenian version, and which are likely interpolations (Rom
                        1:2-3; Heb 7:14; Acts 2:30). Cf. Lange, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ</hi>, 37-42.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Thus, Jesus’ Davidic lineage is established and Mary’s kinship
                    to Elizabeth is explained. Having sufficiently made his point,
                    Ephrem’s exposition seems to be complete. However, the Syriac
                    text subsequently launches into a new discussion regarding the
                    genealogies of Matthew and Luke, in which both authors are
                    named, with Luke even being called “Luke the evangelist”
                    (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܩܐ ܐܘܢܓܠܣܛܐ</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p xml:lang="en">
                        27 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26 (Leloir 1963, 26).
                    </p></note>
                    The apparent intention of this paragraph is
                    <pb n="21"/>
                    to reconcile the two discordant genealogies in the canonical gospels
                    (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26), a concern that did not feature at all in the previous
                    section. The solution proffered is that Matthew wrote regarding
                    Mary’s descent and Luke about that of Joseph
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p xml:lang="en">
                        28 Although this solution to the problem appears to be unique to the
                        commentary, the discordant genealogies vexed other early Christian
                        authors as well. See Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 1.7.1-17, which records the explanation
                        offered by Julius Africanus who highlighted the possibility of Levirate
                        marriage. Eusebius reports the same material in his <hi rend="italic">qu. Steph.</hi> 4.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    If authentic, this passage would serve as indisputable evidence
                    that Ephrem knew at least some traditions from the separated
                    gospels, both because Ephrem explicitly names Matthew and Luke,
                    and because it is known from Theodoret’s report that Tatian’s
                    gospel omitted the genealogies
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en">
                        29 Theodoret, <hi rend="italic">haer.</hi> I.20 (PG 83.372). The text and translation are also
                        given at Petersen, <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 41-42. The Arabic Diatessaron, a
                        medieval translation from a Syriac exemplar, also provides supporting
                        evidence here. There are two recensions of the Arabic. In one the
                        genealogies are included as an appendix, and in the other the genealogies
                        are situated within the infancy narrative. This divergence among the
                        Arabic witnesses testifies to an earlier common ancestor from which the
                        genealogies were absent, and to which later scribes have made additions in
                        order to bring the text more into line with the accepted, fourfold form.
                        See A.S. Marmardji, M <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron de Tatien</hi> (Beirut: Imprimerie catholique,
                        1935), 36; Petersen, <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 136-137. Recently David Pastorelli
                        has used this passage in <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26 to argue that the genealogies actually
                        were originally in Tatian’s work (“The Genealogies of Jesus in Tatian’s 
                        <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron</hi>: The Question of their Absence or Presence,” in <hi rend="italic">Infancy Gospels:
                            Stories and Identities,</hi> 216-30). However, Pastorelli fails to recognize that this
                        passage is an interpolation. Moreover, he places too much weight on the
                        so-called “Western witnesses,” not taking into account the recent work of
                        Ulrich Schmid, “In Search of Tatian’s Diatessaron in the West,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae
                            Christianae</hi> 57 (2003): 176-99. 30 The addition material
                    </p></note>
                    However, there is reason to think
                    otherwise. As noted above, this passage does not occur in the
                    Armenian recension
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p xml:lang="en">
                        30 The addition material begins with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܛܘܒ</foreign> (<hi rend="italic">Et iterum</hi> in Leloir’s
                        Latin translation). 
                    </p></note>
                    which immediately casts a shadow of
                    suspicion upon its authenticity, a suspicion that is strengthened by
                    the fact that the additional material is internally incoherent with the
                    surrounding context. In the midst of the prior discussion in <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi>
                    I.25, Ephrem states that Scripture reckons genealogies <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܪ̈ܒܬܐ</foreign>
                    <pb n="22"/>
                    through male descent, and “is silent” <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܬܩ</foreign> about the genealogies
                    of women
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en">
                        31 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.25 (Leloir 1963, 24). Lange, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ</hi>, 42, also
                        notes the internal contradiction in <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.25-26 and concludes that the
                        extra material is an interpolation.
                    </p></note>
                    This same point, that Scripture accounts genealogies
                    through men rather than women, is also made by Ephrem in his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi> 2.13, where he again notes that both Mary and
                    Joseph were of Davidic descent
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en">
                        32 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. de Nativitate</hi> 2.13.
                    </p></note>
                    It is difficult to see how to
                    reconcile this clearly Ephremic idea with the additional material at
                    <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.26, which states explicitly that “Matthew wrote concerning 
                    the geneaology of Mary (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܬܝ ܕܝܢ ܫܪܒܬܗ̇ ܗܘ ܕܡܪܝܡ ܐܟܬܒ</foreign>), This
                    discrepancy suggests that the additional material is best regarded as
                    a later interpolation made sometime following the division of the
                    manuscript tradition into the two recensions available today. As
                    such, it tells us nothing about Ephrem’s own knowledge of gospel
                    traditions. Given the age of the Syriac manuscript of Ephrem’s
                    commentary (late fifth or early sixth century), this addition
                    provides further evidence alongside Theodoret’s report that some
                    in the fifth-century Syriac-speaking communitiy were troubled by
                    the genealogies of Jesus, whether how to reconcile them or their
                    omission from Tatian’s gospel.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    There is one further passage in the commentary which appears
                    to indicate knowledge of individual gospel traditions. The very end
                    of the Syriac manuscript contains a brief paragraph as a conclusion
                    or appendix, which bears the title “The Evangelists” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝ̈ܣܛܐ</foreign>),
                    and which offers an explanation as to why there are four gospels.
                    The author of this short section acknowledges that “the words of the
                    apostles are not in agreement” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܠܐ ܕܝܢ ܫܠܡܢ ܡ̈ܠܝܗܘܢ ܕܫܠܝ̈ܚܐ</foreign>),
                    but explains this discrepancy by noting that they did not write “the
                    Gospel” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign>) at the same time, since, unlike the giving of
                    the tablets to Moses, they each wrote by the Spirit under various
                    circumstances (cf. Jer. 31:31-33). In what follows the author of this
                    paragraph gives a brief recounting of the origins of the gospels:
                    Matthew is said to have written in Hebrew which others later
                    translated into Greek; Mark followed Peter and wrote from Rome
                    after the faithful persuaded him to take up the task; Luke began his
                    account with the “baptism of John;” and finally John, finding that
                    Matthew and Luke had spoken of the “genealogies [showing] that
                    <pb n="23"/>
                    he was the Son of Man” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܪ̈ܒܬܗ ܕܡܪ ܐܢܫܐ ܗܘ</foreign>), ,(,+)*decided to
                    highlight his divinity by beginning with “In the beginning was the
                    Word.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p xml:lang="en">
                        33 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi>, Evangelistae (Leloir 1963, 250). Leloir did not number this
                        as a section of the commentary, but set it apart as a separate paragraph
                        titled “Evangelistae”, the same title it bears in the Syriac manuscript.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    If authentic, then this passage provides undeniable evidence
                    that evangelist traditions from the Greek church had reached into
                    Ephrem’s Syriac world. The comment about Matthew goes back to
                    a report of Papias preserved by Eusebius
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p xml:lang="en">
                        34 Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 3.39.16. 
                    </p></note>
                    The description of
                    Mark’s writing activities also draws on statements from Papias and
                    Clement of Alexandria, though, once again, these were mediated
                    via Eusebius
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en">
                        35 Papias’ account of Mark’s origins is recorded in Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi>
                        3.39.15. Compare the two versions of Clement’s report in <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 2.15.1-2 and
                        6.14.6-7. On the distinction between the two passages, see Francis
                        Watson, <hi rend="italic">Gospel Writing: A Canonical Perspective</hi> (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans,
                        2013), 442-444.
                    </p></note>
                    Furthermore, the fact that the author of this
                    paragraph alludes to the Matthean and Lukan genealogies in order
                    to introduce the fourth gospel likewise draws on earlier tradition.
                    In terms of its structure, this passage is similar once again to
                    Eusebius’ summary of Clement’s argument that the gospels with
                    the human genealogies were written first, and that John, seeing the
                    “bodily facts” recorded in them, decided to compose a “spiritual
                    gospel.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p xml:lang="en">
                        36 Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 6.14.5-7. In between his description of the gospels
                        with genealogies (i.e., Matthew and Luke) and his description of John,
                        Eusebius has inserted Clement’s report about Mark, thereby obscuring the
                        original contrast between Matthew and Luke on the one hand and John
                        on the other. On the interpolation and the interpretation of this passage,
                        see Watson, <hi rend="italic">Gospel Writing</hi>, 432-433.
                    </p></note>
                    However, despite this clear structural similarity, the way
                    this paragraph describes the two genealogies is idiosyncratic,
                    asserting that “one” of these evangelists spoke about Christ’s
                    “incarnation and about his kingdom from David” while another
                    evangelist highlighted his descent “from Abraham.” Matthew’s
                    genealogy does indeed begin with Abraham, so this is
                    straightforward. However, there is no obvious reason why
                    someone would refer to the Lukan account as being “about his
                    kingdom from David,” a description that is, as far as I am aware,
                    without parallel. Both the Matthean and the Lukan genealogies 
                    <pb n="24"/>
                    include David, so the description offered is unsuccessful if it is an
                    attempt to identify what is distinctive about Luke’s genealogy.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    This final paragraph occurs in both the Syriac and in the
                    Armenian recensions of the commentary, so we might initially be
                    inclined to regard it as authentic. However, Lange has highlighted
                    the fact that some interpolations occurred prior to the division of
                    the Syriac and Armenian versions, so this observation alone is
                    insufficient to settle the matter. The paragraph has no connection
                    with what precedes it, nor with any other portion of the
                    commentary, leading Leloir and McCarthy to question its
                    authenticity
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p xml:lang="en">
                        37 Leloir 1963, 251, n.1; Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe: Commentaire de
                            l’Évangile concordant ou Diatessaron</hi>, Sources Chrétiennes 121 (Paris: Éditions
                        du Cerf, 1966), 409, n.1; McCarthy, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 344,
                        n.1.
                    </p></note>
                    Furthermore, the awareness of specified
                    “evangelists” in the plural contrasts with the singular and undefined
                    usage elsewhere in the commentary. Moreover, the Armenian adds
                    a further paragraph describing the journeys and missions of the
                    apostles, which demonstrates that the end of a commentary was a
                    prime location for later scribes to supplement the preceding
                    discussion with traditional material
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p xml:lang="en">
                        38 Louis Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem. Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant, version
                            arménienne</hi>, CSCO 145, Scriptores Armeniaci 2 (Louvain: L. Durbecq,
                        1954), 247-248. In the Armenian, this section is titled “Evangelists and
                        Apostles,” in contrast to the Syriac which has simply “Evangelists.”
                    </p></note>
                    For these reasons it seems
                    most likely that this paragraph is not authentic, in which case it
                    should not be used as evidence of Ephrem’s knowledge of
                    evangelist traditions.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Even if not authentically Ephremic, this passage does shed
                    valuable light on Syriac Christianity. Whenever this interpolation
                    occurred, it must have been prior to the copying of Chester Beatty
                    709, a fifth- or sixth-century manuscript. It was during this same
                    period that Eusebius’ <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi> was making itself known
                    in the Syriac world, which agrees with the fact that the paragraph
                    reveals the influence of Eusebius’ reports about gospel origins.
                    Eusebius’ works were translated into Syriac at an early stage,
                    possibly even within his own lifetime. The oldest Syriac
                    manuscript, written in Edessa in 411 (BM Add. 12,150), contains
                    several of his works, and the oldest extant witness to his
                    <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi> in any language is a Syriac manuscript dated to
                    <pb n="25"/>
                    462
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p xml:lang="en">
                        39 William Wright and Norman McLean, <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical History of
                            Eusebius in Syriac</hi> (Cambridge: University Press, 1898), ix. Wright and
                        McLean suggest that the text had already gone through several copies by
                        this point.
                    </p></note>
                    Eusebius is known to have had some connection with
                    Edessene sources, given his knowledge of the Agbar legend
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p xml:lang="en">
                        40 Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 1.3, on which see Sebastian Brock, “Eusebius and
                        Syriac Christianity,” in <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Christianity, and Judaism,</hi> ed. Harold W.
                        Attridge and Gohei Hata, Studia Post-Biblica 42 (Leiden: Brill, 1992).
                    </p></note>
                    and
                    certainly by the early fifth century at the latest this cultural
                    transmission was going in the reverse direction as well. Whoever
                    authored this paragraph was apparently drawing on the <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                        History</hi> to supplement Ephrem’s commentary, which probably
                    came to appear out-of-date rather quickly once the fourfold gospel
                    was established as the norm.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv18n1.2.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2.2 Evangelist Traditions in Ephrem’s Broader Corpus</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    At this point we should consider whether this pattern we have
                    observed in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> is consistent with
                    what we find throughout his corpus. To begin with, it is important
                    to observe that the transliterated term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܣܛܐ</foreign>”) evangelist”),
                    noted above as occurring on a handful of occasions in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>, is exceedingly rare in Ephrem’s writings.
                    Edmund Beck, who during the mid-twentieth-century provided
                    new editions for a number of Ephrem’s works, noted that the only
                    other occurrence of the word in Ephrem’s genuine corpus comes
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Genesis</hi>, in which the Syrian introduces a
                    citation of John 1:3 with the formula, “the evangelist has said.”<hi rend="superscript"></hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p xml:lang="en">
                        41 Edmund Beck, “Der syrische Diatessaronkommentar zu Jo. 1, 1-
                        5,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 67 (1983): 20, n.28. For the reference to, “the
                        evangelist,” see <hi rend="italic">Comm. Gen.</hi> I.28 (R.-M. Tonneau, <hi rend="italic">Sancti Ephraem Syri in
                            Genesim et in Exodum Commentarii</hi>, CSCO 152, Scriptores Syri 71 (Louvain:
                        L. Durbecq, 1955), 23).
                    </p></note>
                    The fact that the word shows up at least once elsewhere in
                    Ephrem’s corpus demonstrates that its occurrence in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> cannot be used as an argument against
                    Ephremic authorship of the gospel exposition, though certainly it
                    presents an unusually high concentration of the term, perhaps due
                    to the fact that it is, after all, a commentary on a gospel text. Still,
                    <pb n="26"/>
                    the paucity of the term in Ephrem’s corpus is striking and speaks
                    against it having been a common word in his Syriac milieu.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Furthermore, Ephrem’s gospel citations typically lack any
                    attribution to a specified evangelist. In his study of Ephrem’s gospel
                    citations Burkitt pointed out that he knew of only two passages from
                    his corpus in which the Syrian refers to an individual evangelist
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p xml:lang="en">
                        42 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Quotations</hi>, 59-61. Burkitt cites and translates
                        both Syriac passages. 
                    </p></note>
                    The first passage comes from Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi>. Here he
                    states that “John is like Moses” and “the one ‘In the beginning’ is
                    like the other ‘In the beginning.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p xml:lang="en">
                        43 <hi rend="italic">Hy. de fide</hi> 35.2 (Beck, <hi rend="italic">Hymnen de Fide</hi>, 114).
                    </p></note>
                    The second passage noted by
                    Burkitt is similar, and occurs in a memra on the Johannine
                    prologue preserved in fragmentary form by Philoxenus of Mabbug.
                    Here Ephrem states that “John” “began with the generation of the
                    Son (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܫܪܒܗ ܕܒܪܐ</foreign>) from the point where [it says] ‘Through him all
                    things were created’.” The following fragment from this homily
                    likewise notes that when “John” said the Word was “in the
                    beginning” he was calling in Moses as a witness
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p xml:lang="en">
                        44 Burkitt cites the fragments of this homily from the older edition of
                        Ephrem’s works by Lamy, but see the new edition of Philoxenus’ treatise,
                        along with the Ephrem fragments, in F. Graffin, <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> 41
                        (Turnhout: Brepols, 1982), 62-63.
                    </p></note>   
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In addition to the naming of the evangelist John, we should
                    also note that the version of John 1:3 cited here differs from that
                    given elsewhere in Ephrem’s corpus. In the fragmentary memra he
                    cites the passage in the form <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܐܝܕܗ ܐܬܒܪܝ ܟܠ ܡܕܡ</foreign>, whereas in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>, the passage is cited as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܘܐ ܟܠ ܡܕܡ ܒܗ</foreign>.<hi rend="superscript">45></hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p xml:lang="en">
                        45 See <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.6 (Leloir 1963, 4).
                    </p></note>
                    Since these fragments are preserved in a work by
                    Philoxenus, we might conjecture that Philoxenus has emended
                    Ephrem’s original citation to correspond to his own gospel version.
                    However, it is fairly certain that Philoxenus’ version read <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܐܝܕܗ ܗܘܐ ܟܠܡܕܡ</foreign>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p xml:lang="en">
                        46 J. Edward Walters, “The Philoxenian Gospels as Reconstructed
                        from the Writings of Philoxenus of Mabbug,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac
                            Studies</hi> 13 (2010): 217.
                    </p></note>
                    so Philoxenus was probably not responsible for the
                    alteration. In fact, none of the Syriac versions available to us today
                    <pb n="27"/>
                    have <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܒܪܝ</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐγένετο</foreign> of John 1:3
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p xml:lang="en">
                        47 See George Anton Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Edition of the Syriac Gospels,
                            Volume 4: John</hi> (Brill: Leiden, 1996), 3.
                    </p></note>
                    leading Burkitt to
                    remark, “the texts used by Ephraim in the beginning of the Fourth
                    Gospel are thus diverse and their source is not at all clear.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p xml:lang="en">
                        48 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>, II.139-140. For further
                        discussion of this issue, see Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">S Ephraim’s Quotations</hi>, 59-62. For a
                        more recent listing of all of Ephrem’s citations of John 1:3, see Louis
                        Leloir, <hi rend="italic">L’Évangile d’Éphrem d’après les oeuvres éditées: Recueil des textes</hi>, CSCO
                        180, Subsidia 12 (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1958), 98-99.
                    </p></note>
                    We
                    should also consider the possibility that the version of John 1:3
                    cited by Ephrem here is something less than an exact quotation. He
                    introduces the passage by saying that John began “from where 
                    (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢ ܟܪ</foreign>) all things were created through him,” and notably does not
                    use the citation marker <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܡ</foreign>. Therefore, the verb <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܒܪ</foreign> may be
                    Ephrem’s own gloss on the more ambiguous <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܘܐ</foreign> of John 1:3, in
                    which case we need not posit a distinct, now lost, Syriac version
                    lying behind the apparent citation
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p xml:lang="en">
                        49 Sebastian Brock, “The Use of the Syriac Fathers for New
                        Testament Textual Criticism,” in <hi rend="italic">The Text of the New Testament in
                            Contemporary Research</hi>, 420, notes “the difficulty (especially in earlier
                        writers) of identifying what is a quotation and what is a gloss or
                        paraphrase. Even in cases where the author may seem to introduce a
                        quotation as direct, by using <hi rend="italic">lam</hi>, ‘it says,’ he may nevertheless insert his
                        own gloss on a particular word within the quotation.”
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In addition to these two references to John the evangelist,
                    there are at least two other relevant passages that Burkitt failed to
                    mention. The first is a brief allusion in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Virginity</hi>,
                    in which the poet does not explicitly name John the evangelist, but
                    does identify the author of the Johannine prologue with the
                    beloved disciple who reclined upon Jesus in the upper room (cf.
                    John 13:23-25), implying an awareness of the fourth gospel as a
                    distinct source
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p xml:lang="en">
                        50 <hi rend="italic">Hy. de virg.</hi> 15.4-5 (Beck, <hi rend="italic">Hymnen de Virginitate</hi>, 52-53). <hi rend="italic">Hy. de virg.</hi> 25
                        is also devoted to a meditation on the beloved disciple, though again
                        Ephrem does not name him. However, at <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XX.27 Ephrem makes
                        much the same point as in <hi rend="italic">Hy. de virg.</hi> 25, comparing Mary and John, and
                        in this instance he does name the disciple. 
                    </p></note>
                    The second passage also refers to individual
                    evangelists, though this time it is the synoptic gospels that are in
                    view. At the end of the second of his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi>, Ephrem
                    notes that “Luke and Matthew traced his [i.e., Christ’s] lineage: Son
                    <pb n="28"/>
                    of Abraham they reckoned him—and of David and of Joseph, so
                    that by the learned mouths of two witnesses ...
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p xml:lang="en">
                        51 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. de Nativitate</hi> 2.22 (Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem
                            des Syrers Hymnen de Nativitate (Epiphania)</hi>, CSCO 186, Scriptores Syri 82
                        (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1959), 19). English translation taken
                        from <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns</hi>, trans. Kathleen E. McVey (Mahwah, NJ:
                        Paulist Press, 1989), 81. 
                    </p></note> 
                    This passage not
                    only mentions the evangelists and their genealogies, but also
                    provides a theological rationale for the existence of genealogies in
                    two sources. In addition, in hymn nine of this series, Ephrem
                    singles out Tamar, Rahab, and Ruth for special attention,
                    undoubtedly because they are the only three women to appear in
                    the Matthean genealogy
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p xml:lang="en">
                        52 Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Hy. de Nativitate</hi> 9.7-16. Tamar and Ruth are also
                        mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Hy. de Nativitate</hi> 1.12-13. 
                    </p></note>
                    In the light of these passages, it is
                    difficult to avoid the conclusion that Ephrem knew not only of the
                    existence of the genealogies, but some specific details about their
                    content. We should observe, however, that the genealogies are not
                    viewed here as a potential problem needing to be resolved, as was
                    the case in the already mentioned interpolation in the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on
                        the Gospel.</hi> Rather they harmoniously function together to attest to
                    Christ’s origins.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    There is yet another passage in Ephrem’s corpus also
                    overlooked by Burkitt, also pertaining to the fourth gospel, but it is
                    of questionable authenticity. In 1917 J. Schäfers, in his 
                    <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate in Ephraems des Syrers Kommentar zu den paulinischen
                        Schriften</hi>, first drew attention to a passage from an Ephesians
                    Commentary attributed to Ephrem that survives only in
                    Armenian
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p xml:lang="en">
                        53 J. Schäfers, <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate in Ephraems des Syrers Kommentar zu den
                            paulinischen Schriften</hi> (Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder, 1917), 27-31.
                    </p></note>
                    In the preface to the commentary, the author notes
                    that “the Ephesians were taught by John the evangelist,” who,
                    when he “saw that his three companions had composed their
                    gospels (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">evangeliorum</hi></foreign>) from the body (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">a corpore</hi></foreign>)," began his own
                    gospel with Christ’s descent not “from Mary, or from David, and
                    from Abraham, and from Adam,” but rather “from the beginning
                    was the Word and the Word was with God and the Word was
                    God.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p xml:lang="en">
                        54 Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le témoignage</hi>, 71-72. I am translating here from Leloir’s Latin
                        translation of the Armenian text. A Latin translation of the Armenian text
                        <pb n="29"/>
                        can also be found at <hi rend="italic">S. Ephræm Syri commentarii in epistolas D. Pauli</hi> (Venice:
                        Typographia Sancti Lazari, 1893), 140. There is no translation into any
                        modern language, as far as I am aware. The full extract reads: <foreign xml:lang="la">“Ephesii
                            edocti erant a Iohanne evangelista. Hic, quia viderat tres socios suos
                            initium evangeliorum suorum a corpore fecisse, ne perpendentes
                            existimarent homines, hominem (tantum) fuisse illum qui apparuit ipsi, et
                            non Filium Dei, declinavit a sociis suis, ut faveret iter novum, quod non
                            fecerant socii. Initium itaque fecit ille dicendo in capite evangelii sui, non
                            quod natus esset ille e Maria, aut e Davide, et ex Abrahamo, et ex Adamo,
                            sed: A principio erat Verbum, et ipsum Verbum erat apud Deum, et Deus
                            erat ipsum Verbum. Apostolos igitur, quoniam sciebat Ephesios in
                            divinitate Domini nostri perfectos esse iuxta evangelium Iohannis
                            praedicatoris eorum, reliquit istud, quia perfecti erant in eo, et incepit ille
                            scribere eis de dispensatione corporis eius.”</foreign>
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    This passage is largely in keeping with what we saw above in
                    the final paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>. It has exactly the
                    same structure, introducing the fourth gospel by way of a contrast
                    with the beginning of the synoptics, and, moreover, summarizing
                    the message of the fourth gospel by way of quoting its opening
                    lines. Furthermore, as in the previous passage, so also here the
                    description of the synoptics is somewhat unclear. Although Mark is
                    presumably in view as well, since the passage speaks of “three”
                    gospels prior to John’s writing, the phrase “from Mary, or from
                    David, and from Abraham, and from Adam” hardly serves as a
                    description for the Markan gospel, since it includes no infancy
                    narrative. Furthermore, it is not even clear what in this passage
                    serves to refer to Matthew and Luke. Neither include Mary in their
                    genealogies of Jesus, though both include David and Abraham, and
                    only Luke includes Adam (Matt 1:1-18; Luke 3:23-38). Thus,
                    although we can say with certainty that this passage draws upon the
                    same Clementine-Eusebian tradition that contrasted the
                    genealogies of Matthew and Luke with the opening of John, it
                    appears that again the information has somehow become confused
                    in transmission, just as in the final paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p xml:lang="en">
                        55 On the basis of this passage, Leloir, following the earlier work of
                        Schäfers, noted <foreign xml:lang="fr">“l’imprécision des renseignements que donne Éphr sur
                            l’évangile tétramorphe”</foreign> (<hi rend="italic">Le Témoignage</hi>, 71-72).
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    If the final paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> is an
                    interpolation, as I have argued, then this implies we should be
                    skeptical of this section as well in light of the parallels between the
                    <pb n="30"/>
                    two. The Pauline commentaries attributed to Ephrem survive only
                    in Armenian and have been very little studied, while it is known
                    that much spurious material survived under Ephrem’s name,
                    especially in Armenian
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p xml:lang="en">
                        56 For example, the Armenian <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Genesis</hi> attributed to
                        Ephrem apparently bears little relation to the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Genesis</hi>
                        that also names him as its author, and for this reason the Armenian is
                        generally regarded as spurious. See Edward G. Matthews, <hi rend="italic">The Armenian
                            Commentary on Genesis Attributed to Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, CSCO 573, Scriptores
                        Armeniaci 24 (Louvain: Peeters, 1998); Edward G. Mathews, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Armenian Commentaries on Exodus-Deuteronomy Attributed to Ephrem the Syrian</hi>,
                        CSCO 587, Scriptores Armeniaci 25 (Louvain: Peeters, 2001).
                    </p></note>
                    Finally, Lange has argued that in at least
                    one instance the commentary provides an interpretation that differs
                    from the “authentic Ephrem,” and he therefore advocates keeping
                    open the question of its authenticity pending further study
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p xml:lang="en">
                       57 See Christian Lange, “Zum Taufverständnis im syrischen
                        Diatessaronkommentar,” in <hi rend="italic">Syriaca. Zur Geschichte, Theologie, Liturgie und
                            Gegenwartslage der syrischen Kirchen. 2. Deutsches Syrologen-Symposium (Juli 2000,
                            Wittenberg)</hi>, ed. M. Tamcke, Studien zur orientalischen Kirchengeschichte
                        17 (Münster: Lit, 2002), who also briefly summarizes his argument in
                        Lange, “Ephrem, His School, and the Yawnaya,” 165.
                    </p></note>
                    I
                    suggest, then, that we not view this passage as evidence of
                    Ephrem’s knowledge of evangelist traditions.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Excluding the final paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>
                    and the short passage from the Pauline commentaries, there is no
                    clear evidence that Ephrem knew the otherwise common evangelist
                    traditions explaining the origins of the four gospels. Moreover, the
                    only specific passages we can be sure that he knew from the
                    separated gospels are the Matthean and Lukan genealogies and the
                    Johannine prologue. In one sense this is not too surprising since
                    these texts had long been the twin pillars for understanding the
                    nature of Christ, going back to Irenaeus who first stated that
                    Matthew told of Jesus’ “generation as a man” and John his
                    “generation from the Father.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p xml:lang="en">
                        58 Irenaeus, <hi rend="italic">a.h.</hi> 3.11.8.
                    </p></note>
                    As noted above, Clement passed
                    on a version of this tradition as well, contrasting the Synoptic
                    genealogies with the opening of the fourth gospel. The fact that
                    Tatian’s edition excluded the genealogies would make have made
                    these passages from the fourfold gospel stand out prominently to
                    Ephrem. The genealogies might, then, have been viewed as a sort
                    of supplement to his usual gospel text. Moreover, the Johannine
                    <pb n="31"/>
                    prologue is perhaps the most unique passage in all four canonical
                    gospels, and was notably important in the ‘Arian’ controversy of
                    the fourth century, in which Ephrem took part
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p xml:lang="en">
                        59 See Peter Bruns, “Arius Hellenizans? Ephraem der Syrer und die
                        neoarianischen Kontroversen seiner Zeit. Ein Beitrag zur Rezeption des
                        Nizänums im syrischen Sprachraum,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Kirchengeschichte</hi> 101
                        (1990): 21-57; Sidney H. Griffith, “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint
                        Ephraem’s Hymns Against Heresies,” in <hi rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient Christianity:
                            Essays on Late Antique Thought and Culture in Honor of R. A. Markus</hi>, ed.
                        William E. Klingshirn and Mark Vessey, (Ann Arbor: The University of
                        Michigan Press, 1999); Lewis Ayres, <hi rend="italic">Nicaea and Its Legacy: An Approach to
                            Fourth-Century Trinitarian Theology</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004),
                        229-235. Ephrem mentions “the Arian” at <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XII.9.
                    </p></note>
                    so it is to be
                    expected that this passage would particularly draw his attention. In
                    other words, even if Ephrem did not necessarily know the
                    Eusebian evangelist traditions, he seemingly shared with his Greek
                    and Latin contemporaries the conviction that the Synoptic
                    genealogies and the Johannine opening were unique and important
                    passages
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p xml:lang="en">
                        60 For an exploration of how Ephrem interpreted the opening of
                        Tatian’s gospel, see my “Reading the Diatessaron with Ephrem: The
                        Word and the Light, the Voice and the Star,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi>,
                        forthcoming.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv18n1crawford.3">
                <head>3. EPHREM AND “THE GREEK”</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In light of the material considered thus far, it is clear that Ephrem
                    knew of the existence of the four gospels, knew that the opening of
                    the fourth gospel was written by the evangelist John, and knew the
                    Matthean and Lukan genealogies in some detail. These
                    observations leave little doubt that he worked with some version of
                    the separated gospels alongside his unified gospel text. We should
                    now consider whether there are any explicit references in his
                    corpus to distinct gospel versions aside from the sort of
                    unspecified references to the “gospel” that remain difficult to
                    identify. The only such passages are a half-dozen instances in
                    which he provides variant readings that he says derive from “the
                    Greek Gospel” or simply “the Greek.” One of these references
                    occurs in his <hi rend="italic">Refutationes ad Hypatium</hi> and a further five show up in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>, both texts that are usually dated during
                    the final decade of Ephrem’s life that he spent in Edessa.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="32"/>
                    Since it has been traditionally assumed that Ephrem did not
                    know Greek, Burkitt and Arthur Vööbus suggested that Ephrem
                    refers in these passages to a Syriac translation of the fourfold
                    gospel which he calls “the Greek” to distinguish it from Tatian’s
                    version, which was more well known among Syriac speakers
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p xml:lang="en">
                        61 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>, II.190; Arthur Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                            the History of the Gospel Text in Syriac</hi>, CSCO 128, Subsidia 3 (Louvain: L.
                        Durbecq, 1951), 38-39.
                    </p></note>
                    In
                    other words, Burkitt and Vööbus argued that by calling this version
                    the “Greek” Ephrem was referring not to its language of
                    composition, but to the form in which this gospel existed. Leloir
                    was more cautious, preferring instead to suppose that Ephrem had
                    access to a number of individual variant readings from the Greek
                    separated gospels
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p xml:lang="en">
                        62 Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le Témoignage</hi>, 72-73. Later Leloir hypothesized that some
                        Greek-speaking Christians in Edessa could have passed along to Ephrem
                        these readings from their version of the fourfold gospel (<hi rend="italic">Commentaire de
                            l’Évangile concordant ou Diatessaron</hi>, 29-30).
                    </p></note>
                    Lange, also assuming that these represent a
                    separated, Syriac translation, has most recently surveyed these
                    passages in an attempt to determine what version of gospel text lies
                    behind the citations, but he was unable to clearly identify the
                    passages with either the Vetus Syra or the Peshitta
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p xml:lang="en">
                        63 Lange, “Ephrem, His School, and the Yawnaya,” 167-174.
                        Theodor Zahn, <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, Forschungen zur Geschichte des
                        neutestamentlichen Kanons und der altkirchlichen Literatur, Tl. 1
                        (Erlangen: Deichert, 1881), 62, ascribed the idiosyncrasies of these
                        passages to the lack of skill of the translator, concluding that they
                        represent <foreign xml:lang="de">“ein ziemlich ungeschickter Versuch, das grieschische Original
                            zu übersetzen”.</foreign>
                    </p></note>
                    In what
                    follows I intend to consider each of these passages closely to
                    determine if they indicate usage of the fourfold, separated gospel,
                    as has often been supposed.
                </p>     
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In the passage from the <hi rend="italic">Refutationes ad Hypatium</hi>, the Syrian
                    opposes an interpretation of John 1:4 offered by the Manicheans.
                    He begins by saying that the passage “in the Gospel” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܐܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign>)
                    reads “the life is the light of a man” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܐܢܫܐ ܕܗܢܘܢ ܚܝ̈ܐ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܢܘܗܪܐ</foreign>).
                    .(Apparently the Manicheans draw from the singular “man”
                    the conclusion that the passage speaks of the “primal man” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܡܝܐ ܐܢܫܐ</foreign>)
                    who plays a role in Manichean cosmology. Against this
                    exegesis Ephrem brings the reading from “the Greek Gospel”
                    <pb n="33"/>
                    (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ ܝܘܢܝܐ</foreign>), which says “the life is the light of men”
                    (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܝ̈ܐ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܒ̈ܢܝ ܐܢܫܐ ܕܗܢܘܢ</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p xml:lang="en">
                        64 C.W. Mitchell, <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Prose Refutations of Mani, Marcion, and
                            Bardaisan. Volume I: The Discourses Addressed to Hypatius, Text and Translation
                            Society</hi> (London: Williams and Norgate, 1912), 121-122 (text), xc
                        (translation).
                    </p></note>
                    As David Bundy and
                    Christian Lange have observed, the singular form <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܫܐ</foreign> is
                    ambiguous in that it could be a collective singular (“humanity”) or
                    a true singular (“a man”). This is the ambiguous reading that
                    apparently occurred in Ephrem’s “Gospel” and that lent itself to
                    Manichean exegesis. However, the plural rendering <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ̈ܢܝ ܐܢܫܐ</foreign> 
                    derived from “the Greek gospel,” removes the ambiguity by
                    explaining the singular as a collective singular, ruling out any
                    reference to the primal man
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p xml:lang="en">
                        65 D. Bundy, “Revising the Diatessaron Against the Manicheans:
                        Ephrem of Syria on John 1:4,” <hi rend="italic">Aram</hi> 5 (1993): 65-74; Lange, “Ephrem,
                        His School, and the Yawnaya,” 167-169.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    It is curious then that, in the only citation of John 1:4 in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi>, the reading given is <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ̈ܢܝ ܐܢܫܐ</foreign>, which
                    corresponds to the reading from “the Greek Gospel” rather than
                    to that which occurs in Ephrem’s standard gospel text according to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Refutationes ad Hypatium</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p xml:lang="en">
                        66 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> I.6 (Leloir 1963, 6). Leloir, <hi rend="italic">L’Évangile d’Éphrem</hi>, 99, does not
                        list any further citations of John 1:4 in Ephrem’s corpus, so we do not
                        have any other citations with which to compare it.
                    </p></note>
                    If Ephrem composed his <hi rend="italic">Commentary
                        on the Gospel</hi> after engaging in this bit of anti-Manichean polemic,
                    then he might have revised the reading himself when commenting
                    upon the passage in his gospel commentary in order to rule out the
                    heretical implication. At any rate, the reading in the Greek gospel
                    tradition is indeed <foreign xml:lang="grc">τῶν ἀνθρώπων</foreign>, and the Curetonian manuscript
                    of the Old Syriac agrees with Ephrem’s “Greek” version in the
                    ̈reading <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ̈ܢܝ ܐܢܫܐ</foreign>, so his alternate version finds support in the
                    wider tradition of the separated gospels
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p xml:lang="en">
                        67 See Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Edition of the Syriac Gospels, Volume 4: John</hi>, 4. 
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    We should also observe that Ephrem refers to this additional
                    gospel text in a way that is parallel to the manner in which he refers
                    to his standard gospel text. He titled his gospel exposition the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܘܫܩܐ ܕܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign>) and called the text
                    upon which he commented simply the “Gospel” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ</foreign>). 
                    However, when he refers to the alternate version in the <hi rend="italic">Refutationes
                        <pb n="34"/>
                        ad Hypatium</hi>, he offers no further description of this text beyond
                    simply calling it the “Greek Gospel” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ ܝܘܢܝܐ</foreign>). In other
                    words, pace Burkitt and Vööbus, he does not distinguish these two
                    gospel versions on the basis of their form, but simply on the basis
                    of their language. If Ephrem had been referring to a fourfold
                    gospel, it seems likely that he would have needed to provide some
                    further description to signal to his readers that this was a reference
                    to a four-part gospel, in contrast to his singular, united gospel.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The remaining five references to “the Greek” all occur in
                    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> and present a pattern in keeping
                    with the passage from the <hi rend="italic">Refutationes ad Hypatium</hi>. In <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> V.2
                    Ephrem, while commenting upon the wedding feast at Cana, notes
                    in passing “in Greek he wrote, ‘he was reclining and the wine ran
                    short’” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܘܢܝܐ ܟܬܒ ܕܣܡܝܟ ܗܘܐ ܘܚܣܪ ܚܡܪܐ</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p xml:lang="en">
                        68 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> V.2 (Louis Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem, Commentaire de l’Évangile
                            concordant, texte syriaque (Manuscrit Chester Beatty 709), Folios Additionnels</hi>
                        (Leuven: Peeters, 1990), 38). Schäfers, <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate</hi>, 38-40, regarded this
                        passage as a marginal note by a scribe that was later incorporated into the
                        text, but this is unduly skeptical.
                    </p></note>
                    When
                    commenting on this passage Theodor Zahn pointed out that
                    Ephrem’s version of “the Greek” represents a confusion of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐκλίθη</foreign>
                    (“he reclined”) with <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐκλήθη</foreign> (“he was invited”), a textual variant
                    that does not appear in the Greek gospel tradition
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p xml:lang="en">
                        69 <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 62. So also Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>,
                        II.190.
                    </p></note>
                    Whether the
                    written text Ephrem refers to actually had this reading or whether
                    the confusion arose through oral translation from the Greek is
                    impossible to determine. What this citation seems to add to
                    Ephrem’s surrounding discussion is precisely the fact that Jesus
                    “was reclining,” though it is unclear how this point serves the
                    purpose of the paragraph which is to explain the Savior’s rebuke of
                    his mother’s request. Since this citation does not in any obvious
                    way serve Ephrem’s larger point, it is possible that he has included
                    it simply as a sort of curiosity for his readers. He was obviously
                    aware that his “gospel” text differed from the “Greek” in this
                    instance, and this difference alone could have warranted comment.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    At <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> X.14 Ephrem once more turns to “the Greek.” He
                    cites his Syriac version of Matthew 11:25 as, “I give thanks to you,
                    Father, who is in heaven” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܡܘܕܐ ܐܢܐ ܠܟ ܐܒܐ ܕܒܫܡܝܐ</foreign>), and
                    <pb n="35"/>
                    then follows by noting, “the Greek says, ‘I give thanks to you, God,
                    Father, Lord of heaven and earth’ and ‘that you have hidden [it]
                    from the wise and revealed [it] to children’ (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܛ̈ܠܝܐ ܐܒܐ ܡܪܐ ܕܫܡܝܐ ܘܕܐܪܥܐ. ܘܕܟܣܝܬ ܡܢ ܚܟܝ̈ܡܐ ܘܓܠܝܬ ܡܘܕܐ ܐܢܐ ܠܟ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign>).
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p xml:lang="en">
                        70 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> X.14 (Leloir 1963, 48). Schäfers, <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate</hi>, 40,
                        conjectured that this reference to “the Greek” is an interpolation that
                        arose through a marginal note added by a reader, which was accidentally
                        incorporated into the text by a later scribe. Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le Témoignage</hi>, 145,
                        disagreed, noting that the citation occurs in both the Armenian and Syriac
                        recensions. Schäfers is unduly skeptical in this instance. 71 According to Leloir, L’Évangile d’Éphrem, 11,
                    </p></note>
                    The most obvious difference between the two passages
                    is that the Syriac reads “Father who is in heaven,” while “the
                    Greek” reads “God, Father, Lord of heaven and earth.” The initial
                    citation given, which derives from Ephrem’s standard gospel text,
                    reads like an amalgamation of Matthew 11:25 (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐξομολογοῦμαί σοι,
                        πάτερ, κύριε τοῦ οὐρανοῦ καὶ τῆς γῆς</foreign>) and the <hi rend="italic">Pater Noster</hi> of
                    Matthew 6:9 (<foreign xml:lang="grc">Πάτερ ἡμῶν ὁ ἐν τοῖς οὐρανοῖς</foreign>). Given that Ephrem’s
                    “Gospel” involved Tatian’s editing of preexisting material, it is
                    entirely possible that the prayer of Jesus recorded here was Tatian’s
                    own combination of these two passages
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p xml:lang="en">
                        71 According to Leloir, <hi rend="italic">L’Évangile d’Éphrem</hi>, 11, 24, 83, no other
                        citations of Matthew 6:9 or Luke 10:21 survive in Ephrem’s corpus, and
                        the only other citation of Matthew 11:25 occurs in a passage of
                        questionable authenticity.
                    </p></note>
                    On the other hand, the
                    reading Ephrem here gives as coming from “the Greek” largely
                    corresponds with the Greek version of the passage as given in
                    Matthew 11:25 and Luke 10:21 (<foreign xml:lang="grc">κύριε τοῦ οὐρανοὐ καὶ τῆς γῆς</foreign>),
                    although it has the unusual addition of “God.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p xml:lang="en">
                        72 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>, II.190, might be right in seeing
                        the mention of “God” as a simple “piece of carelessness” due to Ephrem
                        citing from memory.
                    </p></note>
                    The next reference to “the Greek” is a citation of Matthew
                    28:18 and it occurs in a short section consisting of three sentences
                    that are absent from the Armenian recension. The fact that this
                    passage shows up only in the Syriac version calls into question its
                    authenticity, though we have at least to reckon with the possibility
                    that the Armenian translator omitted this passage rather than that it
                    was a later interpolation to the Syriac. After citing an expanded
                    version of John 16:15 (“All that my Father has is mine and what is
                    mine is my Father’s”), the Syriac continues beyond the Armenian
                    <pb n="36"/>
                    and cites as further proof an expanded version of Matthew 28:18
                    (“All authority that is in heaven and on earth has been given to me
                    by my Father”), before then quoting the same passage as it occurs
                    in “the Greek.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p xml:lang="en">
                        73 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XV.19 (Leloir 1963, 158).
                    </p></note>
                    In this instance the only difference between the
                    Syriac and “the Greek” is that, whereas the Syriac reads “in heaven
                    and on earth” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܒܫܡܝܐ ܘܒܐܪܥܐ</foreign>), ܕ” ,(the Greek” has “as in heaven,
                    so also on earth” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܟ ܕܒܫܡܝܐ ܐܦ ܒܐܪܥܐ</foreign>). .(It is unclear in this
                    instance what extra exegetical pay-off is gained from the “Greek”
                    text that cannot be had from the Syriac. Equally puzzling is the fact
                    that Ephrem’s original text, which stood in his Syriac harmony, is
                    closer to the proper Greek version of Matthew 28:18 than the text
                    which he says comes from “the Greek.” Ephrem’s “Greek” version
                    contains the phrase “as in heaven, so also on earth” which seems
                    more like a fairly close translation of Matthew 6:10c (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὡς ἐν οὐρανῷ
                        καὶ ἐπὶ γῆς</foreign>) rather than 28:18 (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐν οὐρανῷ καὶ ἐπὶ τῆς γῆς</foreign>), Similar
                    to the two previous passages from “the Greek,” Ephrem’s citation
                    here is an unusual rendering of the Greek text as it is available to us
                    today.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Furthermore, both of the versions of Matthew 28:18 cited
                    here, the Syriac and the Greek, have the unusual phrase “by my
                    Father” that does not occur in the Greek gospel tradition. It is
                    possible that the additional phrase “by my Father” is Ephrem’s
                    own loose citation, since immediately preceding his quotation of
                    Matthew 28:18 is a quotation of John 16:15 which speaks of the
                    Son receiving “all that the Father has.” Alternatively, it is also
                    possible that Tatian added this phrase to Matthew 28:18 when
                    compiling his harmony. The Peshitta inserts a phrase from John
                    20:21 (“As my Father sent me, so also I send you”) immediately
                    following Matthew 28:18, a reading that, as Burkitt pointed out,
                    was probably taken over from the Old Syriac version, which
                    happens to be lost in this section
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p xml:lang="en">
                        74 Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe</hi>, I.172-173. 
                    </p></note>
                    As with so many of the peculiar
                    Old Syriac readings, it is likely that this insertion derives ultimately
                    from the influence of Tatian’s gospel
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p xml:lang="en">
                        75 On the influence of Tatian’s gospel upon the Vetus Syra, see
                        Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History</hi>, 34-35; Petersen, <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 130-133.
                    </p></note>
                    Further evidence to this
                    point is that the Arabic Diatessaron likewise places John 20:21
                    <pb n="37"/>
                    immediately following Matthew 28:18
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p xml:lang="en">
                        76 Tat<hi rend="superscript">AR</hi> <hi rend="italic">LV</hi>. 4-5 (Marmardji, <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron de Tatien</hi>, 528-529).
                    </p></note>
                    Viewed in this light, it is
                    plausible that the Johannine-sounding phrase “by my Father”
                    which Ephrem reads in Matthew 28:18 was also due to Tatian’s
                    mixing of his Matthean and Johannine sources. Notably, the Syriac
                    translation of Eusebius’ <hi rend="italic">Theophania</hi>, which provides the only other
                    early citation of this verse in Syriac, likewise includes the phrase
                    “by my Father,” supporting the reading in Ephrem’s text
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p xml:lang="en">
                        77 Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">Theophania</hi> 4.8. The passage is cited in Ignatius Ortix de
                        Urbina, <hi rend="italic">Vetus Evangelium Syrorum et Exinde Excerptum Diatessaron Tatiani</hi>,
                        Biblia Polyglotta Matritensia, Series VI (Madrid: Consejo Superior de
                        Investigaciones Cientificas, 1967), 201. Urbina, who collated gospel
                        citations from early Syriac texts, provides one other citation of Matthew
                        28:18, and it too includes the phrase “by my Father,” though it occurs in a
                        work of questionable authenticity. Leloir, <hi rend="italic">L’Évangile d’Éphrem</hi>, 59, noted
                        the same ps-Ephremic passage.
                    </p></note>
                    If it is
                    plausible to regard this phrase as Tatian’s own addition, then it is
                    striking that it shows up both in Ephrem’s Syriac gospel text as
                    well as in his alternate “Greek” gospel.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The final two reference to “the Greek” occur in sections of the
                    commentary for which the folios of Chester Beatty 709 are missing,
                    and for which therefore only the Armenian recension is available.
                    At <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> II.17 Ephrem is explaining the meaning of Simeon’s
                    prediction to Mary that “You will remove the sword” (<hi rend="italic">Amovebis
                        gladium</hi>), a reading of Luke 2:35a that makes Mary the subject of the
                    action, rather than the object as is read in the Greek gospel
                    tradition (<foreign xml:lang="grc">σοῦ αὐτῆς τὴν ψυχὴν διελεύσεται ῥομφαία</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p xml:lang="en">
                        78 On the unusual reading of Luke 2:35 given by Ephrem, see Leloir,
                        <hi rend="italic">Le Témoignage</hi>, 92-93; Robert Murray, “The Lance Which Re-Opened
                        Paradise, a Mysterious Reading in the Early Syriac Fathers,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                            Christiana Periodica</hi> 39 (1973): 224-234, 491. The passage is cited again in
                        the same peculiar form at CGos XXI.27 where Ephrem is commenting
                        upon the appearance to “Mary” at the empty tomb. I translate here and in
                        the passage that follows from Leloir’s Latin translation of the Armenian.
                    </p></note>
                    Ephrem
                    provides two alternate interpretations of the verse. He first
                    connects Mary’s removal of the sword with the sword that guarded
                    paradise after Eve’s failure, relying on the common typological link
                    between Eve and Mary. His second interpretation is that the verse
                    refers to Mary’s “denial” (<hi rend="italic">negationem</hi>). Assuming that Mary, the
                    mother of Jesus, is the same Mary present at the empty tomb in
                    John 20:15, Ephrem regards this “denial” as her doubting when she
                    <pb n="38"/>
                    encountered the risen Christ, when she thought that he was the
                    gardener
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p xml:lang="en">
                        79 The exegetical move of linking Simeon’s prediction to Mary, the
                        mother of Jesus, with the Mary who doubted at the tomb (cf. John 20:15)
                        demonstrates a conflation of the different “Mary’s” in the Jesus tradition,
                        an idea that Ephrem shares with some other early Syriac sources. Cf.
                        Robert Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac
                            Tradition</hi>, Rev. ed. (London: T&amp;T Clark, 2006), 329-335; Sebastian Brock,
                        “Mary and the Gardiner: An East Syrian Dialogue Soghitha for the
                        Resurrection,” <hi>Parole de l’Orient</hi> 11 (1983): 225-26. For similar passages in
                        the commentary, see CGos V.5; XXI.27.
                    </p></note>
                    It is in the midst of this second interpretation that the
                    commentary introduces Luke 2:35b with the words, “the Greek
                    says quite clearly, ‘the thoughts from many hearts will be revealed,’
                    that is, the thoughts of those who doubted” (<foreign xml:lang="a"><hi rend="italic">Graecum clare quidem
                        dicit: Revelabuntur ex multis cordibus cogitationes (nimirum) eorum qui
                        dubitaverunt</hi></foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p xml:lang="en">
                        80 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> II.17 (Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant, version
                            arménienne</hi>, 24). 
                    </p></note>
                    In this instance, Ephrem does not contrast the
                    reading of “the Greek” with that which is given in his primary
                    gospel text, so it is unclear what exegetical value he thought he
                    could derive from the Greek version that could not be had simply
                    from the Syriac. Nevertheless, “the Greek” version of this passage
                    as reported by Ephrem does correspond well with the Greek text
                    as it is known to us today (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀποκαλυφθῶσιν ἐκ πολλῶν καρδιῶν
                        διαλογισμοί</foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p xml:lang="en">
                        81 Leloir, <hi rend="italic">L’évangile d’Éphrem</hi>, 74, does not provide any further
                        citations of Luke 2:35b in Ephrem’s corpus.
                    </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    However, there have been doubts as to the authenticity of this
                    passage. Harris, Schäfers, Leloir, and Lange have noted that
                    Isho‘dad of Merv later cites this very passage from Ephrem’s
                    commentary, but notably omits the line that introduces the reading
                    from “the Greek.
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p xml:lang="en">
                        82 J. Rendel Harris, <hi rend="italic">Fragments of the Commentary of Ephrem Syrus Upon the
                            Diatessaron</hi> (London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1895), 34; Schäfers,
                        <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate</hi>, 32-38; Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Le Témoignage</hi>, 94; Lange, “Ephrem, His
                        School, and the Yawnaya,” 172-173. Harris gives the passage with a
                        translation. See also the passage in the context of Isho’dad’s commentary
                        in Margaret Dunlop Gibson, <hi rend="italic">The Commentaries of Isho’dad of Merv, Bishop of
                            Hadatha</hi> (c. 850 A.D.) (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2011),
                        vol. 1, p.159 (translation); vol. 3, p. 21 (text).
                    </p></note>
                    On this basis they concluded that the citation
                    of “the Greek” must be a later interpolation. While this
                    <pb n="39"/>
                    interpretation of the evidence cannot be ruled out, it seems to me
                    that the passage in Isho‘dad reads more like a paraphrase of
                    Ephrem’s commentary rather than an exact citation. Isho‘dad has
                    clearly shortened the passage in the latter half of his quotation,
                    since the version as it stands in the commentary is longer and more
                    detailed. Isho‘dad includes no reference to the “gardener” of John
                    20:15, as does Ephrem’s original passage, and whereas Isho‘dad
                    merely mentions the “miracles” of the Savior, the commentary
                    explicitly names these marvels: the conception and birth. Given
                    that Isho‘dad apparently compressed the passage when he cited it,
                    it is possible that he simply chose to leave out Ephrem’s reference
                    to “the Greek” which he probably found puzzling and ill-suited to
                    his purpose. For this reason, I suggest we regard the reference “the
                    Greek” here as Ephremic.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    The final citation of “the Greek” in <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> also comes from a
                    passage extant only in the Armenian. At <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XIX.17 Ephrem is
                    concerned to explain the meaning of Jesus’ prayer in John 17:5,
                    which he initially cites as “Give me glory in your presence from
                    that which you gave me before the world had been made” (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Da mihi
                        gloriam apud te ex illa, quam dedisti mihi, antequam mundus factus esset</hi></foreign>). In
                    the following exegesis, the Syrian wants to make clear that the
                    “glory” spoken of is understood as the glory which the Son
                    previously possessed with the Father when the two were creating.
                    Now that the Son is engaged in bringing to pass a new creation,
                    Ephrem argues, he prays to receive this same glory from the
                    Father. After pressing this point for a paragraph or so, he then
                    recapitulates his argument, asserting that the “Give me” (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Da mihi</hi></foreign>)
                    refers to that glory which “he had before creatures, with the Father,
                    and in the Father’s presence.” As proof for this interpretation he
                    next asserts, “for the reading of the Greek also quite clearly says,
                    ‘Glorify me with that glory which I myself possessed in your
                    presence, before the world was’” (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">quoniam et lectio (Graeci) habet et
                        aperte quidem dicit: Glorifica me, ait, gloria illa quam possidebam ego coram
                        te, antequam esset mundus</hi></foreign>)
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p xml:lang="en">
                        83 <hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XIX.17 (Leloir, <hi rend="italic">Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant, version
                            arménienne</hi>, 199-200). Leloir notes that manuscript B reads in <foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Graeco lectio</hi></foreign>,
                        while manuscript A has <foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">lectio habet et</hi></foreign>. He has inserted <foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Graeci</hi></foreign> in brackets
                        into his version of the text, presumably because he assumed <foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">Greacus</hi></foreign> has
                        dropped out from the text in A. 
                    </p></note>
                    Ephrem’s citation of “the Greek” in this
                    instance is a fairly close rendering of the Greek text as it is known
                    <pb n="40"/>
                    to us today (<foreign xml:lang="grc">δόξασόν με σύ, πάτερ, παρὰ σεαυτῷ τῇ δόξῃ ᾗ εἶχον
                        πρὸ τοῦ τὸν κόσμον εἶναι παρὰ σοί</foreign>). Unlike in the previous passage,
                    he here cites both his gospel text as well as that of “the Greek,” so
                    we are in a position to compare them. The primary difference
                    seems to be that the first citation speaks of the glory <hi rend="italic">given</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">quam
                        dedisti mihi</hi></foreign>) to the Son by the Father before the world, whereas “the
                    Greek” describes the Son as actually <hi rend="italic">possessing</hi> this glory before the
                    world (<foreign xml:lang="la"><hi rend="italic">quam possidebam ego</hi></foreign>). Perhaps the latter rendering seemed to
                    Ephrem to make the point “more clearly” that the Son actually had
                    this glory previously and was therefore not simply receiving it for
                    the first time. 
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    What then are we to make of these passages? To begin with, as
                    I have already suggested, it is unduly skeptical to reject them all as
                    later scribal interpolations, as Schäfers has done
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p xml:lang="en">
                        84 Though, to be fair, Schäfers was working only with the Armenian
                        version since the Syriac had not yet been discovered.
                    </p></note>
                    The fact that
                    Ephrem engages in this sort of reading in the <hi rend="italic">Refutationes ad
                        Hypatium</hi>, in a passage whose authenticity no one disputes, implies
                    that the references in the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Gospel</hi> should be given
                    the benefit of the doubt unless further arguments can be adduced
                    against their authenticity. Furthermore, I suggest it is most likely
                    that in these passages Ephrem really does refer to a Greek version,
                    rather than simply a Syriac tetraevangelium, as Burkitt, Vööbus,
                    and Lange assumed, since the study of Possekel has laid to rest the
                    idea that Ephrem had no access to Greek sources. Ephrem’s
                    labeling of this source as “the Greek” makes much more sense as a
                    straightforward reference to a text written in Greek, rather than
                    awkwardly supposing that by “Greek” he actually means “Syriac in
                    a separated form.” If then it is an actual Greek version to which
                    Ephrem refers, we should not be greatly surprised that the citations
                    from “the Greek” correspond with neither the Vetus Syra nor the
                    Peshitta.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    However, we still have to contend with the fact that several of
                    the “Greek” passages cited by Ephrem include readings that are
                    nowhere to be found in the Greek gospel tradition, and at least one
                    of these readings, the “by my Father” in Matthew 28:18, occurs
                    both in his Syriac text as well as in the “Greek” version to which he
                    refers. Moreover, it is striking that he provides no mention
                    whatsoever of a difference in form between the “Gospel” and “the
                    <pb n="41"/>
                    Greek Gospel.” Rather, his language denotes a difference of
                    language, while conversely implying a similarity in the form in
                    which these two gospels existed. In light of these observations I
                    suggest we consider the possibility that in these passages Ephrem
                    refers to a Greek version of Tatian’s gospel to which he had access
                    in Edessa. The original language of Tatian’s gospel has been a
                    subject of much debate, and I do not intend to enter into it here.
                    However, there is good reason to think that Tatian’s work did exist
                    in Greek, as well as in Syriac. The only Greek witness to have
                    survived is the bit of parchment from Dura Europos dated to
                    sometime before the destruction of the city by the Persians in 256-
                    257. Although David Parker, D.G.K. Taylor, and Mark Goodacre
                    have attempted to show that this fragment does not derive from
                    Tatian’s gospel, Jan Joosten has recently provided a convincing
                    counter-argument
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p xml:lang="en">
                        85 D.C. Parker, D.G.K Taylor, and M.S. Goodacre, “The Dura-
                        Europos Gospel Harmony,” in <hi rend="italic">Studies in the Early Text of the Gospels and
                            Acts</hi>, ed. D.G.K. Taylor (Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature, 1999), 192-
                        228; Jan Joosten, “The Dura Parchment and the Diatessaron,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae
                            Christianae</hi> 57 (2003): 159-175. The fragment was originally published in
                        Carl H. Kraeling, <hi rend="italic">A Greek Fragment of Tatian’s Diatessaron From Dura</hi>,
                        Studies and Documents 3 (London: Christophers, 1935). Petersen
                        provides an overview of the evidence in <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron</hi>, 196-203. Most
                        recently the issue has been considered in Ulrich Mell, <hi rend="italic">Christliche Hauskirche
                            und Neues Testament. Die Ikonologie des Baptisteriums von Dura Europos und das
                            Diatessaron Tatians</hi>, Novum Testamentum et Orbis Antiquus 77
                        (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2010), 189-204. Mell writes, “Um
                        die These, dass es sich bei dem Dura-Fragment um den Text einer
                        Evangelienharmonie handelt, und zwar ausgerechnet derjenigen von
                        Tatian, entscheidend zu verifizieren, ist das Dura-Fragment in seinem
                        Umfang zu klein” (p.204). Mell seems unaware of Joosten’s work, which,
                        through a comparison of the text with other Tatianic witnesses, succeeds
                        in showing that the Dura fragment is related to Tatian’s gospel. On the
                        Dura fragment, see also Matthew R. Crawford, “The Diatessaron,
                        Canonical or Non-canonical? Rereading the Dura Fragment,” <hi rend="italic">New
                            Testament Studies</hi> 61 (2015): forthcoming. 
                    </p></note>
                    If Tatian’s work survived in a Greek version in
                    Dura-Europos as late as the mid-third century, then the possibility
                    must at least be considered that a copy was also housed in the
                    library at Edessa a century or so later during Ephrem’s residence
                    <pb n="42"/>
                    there
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p xml:lang="en">
                        86 Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History</hi>, 40, noted that a letter originally
                        written in Syriac but now preserved only in Armenian, was sent by
                        Aithallah, presumably bishop of Edessa, to Persian Christians. Twice in
                        this letter the bishop says he is quoting from the Gospel of John (once
                        “John the evangelist” and once just “John”), leading Vööbus to conclude
                        that he had quoted from the separated gospels. See the two passages at
                        Joannes Thorossian, <hi rend="italic">Aithallae Episcopi Edesseni Epistola Ad Christianos in
                            Persarum Regione De Fide</hi> (Venice: Lazari, 1942), 46, 53. Since Aithallah’s
                        tenure as bishop began in 324/5 and ended with his death in 345, Vööbus
                        used the letter as proof that the separated gospels were in use prior to
                        Ephrem’s decade in Edessa. However, it has recently been shown that this
                        letter dates to the early fifth century, rather than to the mid-fourth
                        century. As a result, it does not tell us anything about what form of gospel
                        text was in use in Edessa prior to Ephrem. On the date of the letter, see
                        David D. Bundy, “The Letter of Aithallah (CPG 3340): Theology,
                        Purpose, Date,” in <hi rend="italic">III Symposium Syriacum 1980</hi>, ed. René Lavenant,
                        (Rome: Pont. Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1983), who points out
                        that the letter cites the third article of the Niceno-Constantinopolitan
                        Creed of 381. See also David Bundy, “The Creed of Aithallah: A Study in
                        the History of the Early Syriac Symbol,” <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Theologicae Lovanienses</hi>
                        63 (1987): 157-163.
                    </p></note>
                    The fact that these readings from “the Greek” occur only
                    during the final ten years of Ephrem’s life imply that this text was
                    not available to him in Nisibis but was only found by him once he
                    had relocated to Edessa. If Ephrem found in Edessa a Greek copy
                    of the gospel text familiar to him in Syriac, he or perhaps some
                    other bilingual Christian could easily have provided variant
                    readings from the Greek to supplement his exposition of the Syriac
                    text.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Of course, the evidence is too slim to allow us to conclude
                    with certainty that Ephrem’s “Greek” version is a Greek
                    Diatessaron, but nothing rules out the possibility and there is at
                    least some slim evidence in its favor. This explanation of these
                    references is, therefore, at least as plausible as the notion that
                    Ephrem is referring to Greek, separated gospels, even if final
                    certitude is beyond our reach. If the idea of him using a Greek
                    Diatessaron initially strikes us as odd, this reaction might simply
                    reflect the fact that history is written by the victors—in this case
                    the fourfold, separated gospel—, and what seems strange to us
                    now might have been commonplace in fourth-century Edessa. We
                    know that a Greek version of Tatian’s work once existed. That
                    <pb n="43"/>
                    Ephrem’s allusive references to the “Greek” might be to such a
                    text is at least as plausible an explanation as any other.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Finally, we should observe the way in which Ephrem uses
                    these cross-references. Vööbus argued that since Ephrem on one
                    occasion (<hi rend="italic">CGos</hi> XIX.17) calls this variant reading a <hi rend="italic">lectio</hi> (the Syriac
                    in this section is lost), implying authoritative scriptural status, the
                    Syrian regarded this alternate text as the normative one, rather than
                    the “Diatessaron” upon which he commented
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p xml:lang="en">
                        87 Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History</hi>, 38-39.
                    </p></note>
                    In the previous
                    century Harnack made a similar argument, though he held that
                    Ephrem knew Greek and was making his own translation from the
                    Greek separated gospels, while Vööbus regarded the text as a pre-
                    Peshitta Syriac translation of the separated gospels
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p xml:lang="en">
                        88 “Tatian’s Diatessaron und Marcion’s Commentar zum Evangelium
                        bei Ephraem Syrus,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Kirchengeschichte</hi> 4 (1881): 495.
                    </p></note>
                    The
                    conclusion that <hi rend="italic">lectio</hi> here implies a more authoritative text is
                    probably assuming too much on the basis of a single word. In my
                    reading of these five passages, it seems that Ephrem introduces the
                    variant readings simply as further evidence for the particular
                    interpretation he wishes to pursue, rather than as the definitive and
                    ultimately authoritative textual form. His practice is in keeping with
                    the way many contemporary Greek authors were content to rely
                    simultaneously on readings of the Septuagint alongside the Hebrew
                    Old Testament, without choosing one text over another. It is
                    notable that in the final two passages I considered above, Ephrem
                    says “the Greek” “speaks clearly,” suggesting that he thought the
                    Greek version was a more lucid rendering that better served his
                    purpose. There is no hint in his exposition of any opposition
                    between the Syriac “Gospel” and “the Greek Gospel,” and he
                    seems happy to use either to illuminate the meaning of a given
                    passage. 
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv18n1crawford.4">
                <head>4. GOSPEL VERSIONS IN EPHREM’S CORPUS</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    In light of the above three lines of inquiry, there is no doubt that
                    Ephrem had access to gospel versions beyond the Syriac gospel
                    upon which he authored a commentary. Most significant is the
                    conclusion that he knew some form of the fourfold gospel, which,
                    in terms of its form, would have contrasted sharply with Tatian’s
                    <pb n="44"/>
                    gospel. Although, as I have argued elsewhere
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p xml:lang="en">
                        89 Crawford, “Diatessaron, A Misnomer?”
                    </p></note>
                    Tatian’s version
                    was quite likely anonymous and intended as a way of erasing the
                    memory of the evangelist traditions, it is clear that Ephrem knew
                    the names of the four canonical evangelists, and had worked with
                    these texts at least with respect to the Johannine prologue and the
                    Matthean and Lukan genealogies. It is likely that this knowledge is
                    due to his acquaintance with an early Syriac translation of the
                    tetraevangelium. The sole surviving witnesses of the Vetus Syra
                    date from the period after Ephrem’s death, but these may represent
                    a much older translation attempt. In addition, Ephrem also made
                    use of a Greek version of the gospel, which may have been a Greek
                    edition of Tatian’s work.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    This picture of Ephrem is broadly in keeping with what we can
                    reconstruct of his context. Aphrahat, who wrote a few decades
                    earlier than Ephrem and who lived further East under Persian rule,
                    never mentions evangelist traditions nor does he name Tatian or
                    the Diatessaron. Ephrem, living in Nisibis and eventually in
                    Edessa, appears to be more in touch with the Greek-speaking
                    world further west. I have already noted Possekel’s demonstration
                    of his usage of Greek philosophical contexts, and we should also
                    note his engagement with the Arian controversy of the fourth
                    century. Given this greater contact with the Greek world, it would
                    be surprising if Ephrem did not know of the gospel in its fourfold
                    form. In fact, he clearly did, in keeping with his knowledge of other
                    Greek sources.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Nevertheless, we should not overlook the significance of the
                    rather obvious fact that when he came to author a commentary, he
                    did so not upon Matthew, Mark, Luke, or John, but upon Tatian’s
                    gospel in its Syriac form. His authoring of the commentary
                    suggests that for both he and his community this text held some
                    kind of authoritative status. Defining the nature of this authority
                    more precisely is, however, more difficult. The most likely
                    explanation is that this Syriac gospel was the widely accepted
                    liturgical gospel for Ephrem and many other Syriac-speaking
                    Christians, as reported also by Theodoret a century later, who
                    noted its usage in 200 of the 800 churches in his diocese. As the
                    gospel regularly used liturgically, it would have seemed natural for
                    Ephrem to have written an exposition of it, in a manner parallel to
                    <pb n="45"/>
                    the way that Greek and Latin authors explained the meaning of the
                    fourfold gospel used liturgically in their churches.
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    Yet, even if Tatian’s gospel served as his primary gospel
                    version, Ephrem apparently felt free to supplement it with
                    additional material from elsewhere, such as the alternate readings
                    of the “Greek gospel,” and the genealogies of Jesus which were
                    absent from his liturgical text. He also treats as authentic certain
                    traditions about Mary, Zechariah, Elizabeth, and John the Baptist
                    which were likely drawn from some text like the <hi rend="italic">Protoevangelium of
                        James</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p xml:lang="en">
                        90 On apocryphal gospel traditions in the Syriac tradition, see Agnes
                        Smith Lewis, <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha Syriaca: The Protevangelium Jacobi and Transitus
                            Mariae, With Texts From the Septuagint, the Corân, the Peshitta, and From a
                            Syriac Hymn in a Syro-Arabic Palimpsest of the Fifth and Other Centuries</hi>, Studia
                        Sinaitica 11 (London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1902); Cornelia B. Horn, “Syriac
                        and Arabic Perspectives on Structural and Motif Parallels Regarding Jesus’
                        Childhood in Christian Apocrypha and Early Islamic Literature: The
                        ‘Book of Mary,’ the Arabic Apocryphal Gospel of John and the Qu’rān,” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha</hi> 19 (2008): 267-291; Charles Naffah, “Les ‘histoires’ syriaques de
                        la Vierge: traditions apocryphes anciennes et récentes,” <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha</hi> 20
                        (2009): 137-188. 
                    </p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Ayres, Lewis. <hi rend="italic">Nicaea and Its Legacy: An Approach to Fourth-Century
                        Trinitarian Theology</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baarda, Tjitze. <hi rend="italic">The Gospel Quotations of Aphrahat, the Persian Sage:
                        Aphrahat’s Text of the Fourth Gospel</hi>. Amsterdam: Vrije
                        Universiteit Amsterdam, 1975.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “‘The Flying Jesus’: Luke 4:29-30 in the Syriac
                        Diatessaron,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 40 (1986): 313-341.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beck, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide.</hi> CSCO
                        154, Scriptores Syri 73. Louvain: L. Durbecq, 1955.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________.<hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses.</hi> 
                        CSCO 169, Scriptores Syri 76. Louvain: L. Durbecq, 1957.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Nativitate
                        (Epiphania).</hi>CSCO 186, Scriptores Syri 82. Louvain: Secrétariat
                        du CorpusSCO, 1959.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Sermones de Fide.</hi> CSCO
                        212, Scriptores Syri 88. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO,
                        1961.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Virginitate.</hi> 
                        CSCO 223, Scriptores Syri 94. Louvain: Secrétariat du
                        CorpusSCO, 1962.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide.</hi> CSCO 155,
                        Scriptores Syri 74. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “Der syrische Diatessaronkommentar zu Jo. 1, 1-5,” 
                        <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 67 (1983): 1-31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, Sebastian. “Mary and the Gardiner: An East Syrian
                        Dialogue Soghitha for the Resurrection,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 11
                        (1983): 225-26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________.<hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision of Saint
                        Ephrem the Syrian.</hi> Cistercian Studies 124. Kalamazoo, MI:
                        Cistercian Publications, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “Eusebius and Syriac Christianity.” In <hi rend="italic">Eusebius,
                        Christianity, and Judaism,</hi> ed. Harold W. Attridge and Gohei
                        <pb n="47"/>
                        Hata, Studia Post-Biblica 42. Leiden: Brill, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “The Use of the Syriac Fathers for New Testament
                        Textual Criticism.” <hi rend="italic">In The Text of the New Testament in
                            Contemporary Research: Essays on the Status Quaestionis,</hi> ed. Bart D.
                        Ehrman, and Michael W. Holmes, 2nd ed. Leiden: Brill, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bruns, Peter. “Arius Hellenizans? Ephraem der Syrer und die
                        neoarianischen Kontroversen seiner Zeit. Ein Beitrag zur
                        Rezeption des Nizänums im syrischen Sprachraum,”<hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift
                            für Kirchengeschichte</hi> 101 (1990): 21-57.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bundy, David. “The Letter of Aithallah (CPG 3340): Theology,
                        Purpose, Date.” In <hi rend="italic">III Symposium Syriacum 1980,</hi> ed. René
                        Lavenant. Rome: Pont. Institutum Studiorum Orientalium,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “Revising the Diatessaron Against the Manicheans:
                        Ephrem of Syria on John 1:4,” <hi rend="italic">Aram</hi> 5 (1993): 65-74.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “The Creed of Aithallah: A Study in the History of the
                        Early Syriac Symbol,” <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Theologicae Lovanienses</hi> 63
                        (1987): 157-163.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Burkitt, F.C. <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Quotations From the Gospel.</hi> Texts and
                        Studies 7.2. Cambridge: The University Press, 1901.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Evangelion Da-Mepharreshe.</hi> 2 vols. Cambridge: The
                        University Press, 1904.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Crawford, Matthew R. “Diatessaron, A Misnomer? The Evidence
                        of Ephrem’s Commentary,” <hi rend="italic">Early Christianity</hi>4 (2013): 362-85.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “Reading the Diatessaron with Ephrem: The Word and
                        the Light, the Voice and the Star,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae,</hi> forthcoming.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">S. Ephræm Syri commentarii in epistolas D. Pauli</hi>(Venice: Typographia
                        Sancti Lazari, 1893).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gibson, Margaret Dunlop. <hi rend="italic">The Commentaries of Isho’dad of Merv,
                        Bishop of Hadatha (c. 850 A.D.).</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge
                        University Press, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Graffin, F. <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> 41. Turnhout: Brepols, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Griffith, Sidney H. “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint
                        <pb n="48"/> Ephraem’s Hymns Against Heresies.” In <hi rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient
                            Christianity: Essays on Late Antique Thought and Culture in Honor of
                            R. A. Markus,</hi> ed. William E. Klingshirn and Mark Vessey. Ann
                        Arbor: The University of Michigan Press, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harnack, Adolf. “Tatian’s Diatessaron und Marcion’s Commentar
                        zum Evangelium bei Ephraem Syrus,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                            Kirchengeschichte</hi> 4 (1881): 471-505.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harris, J. Rendel. <hi rend="italic">Fragments of the Commentary of Ephrem Syrus Upon the
                        Diatessaron. </hi>London: C.J. Clay and Sons, 1895.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horn, Cornelia B. “Syriac and Arabic Perspectives on Structural
                        and Motif Parallels Regarding Jesus’ Childhood in Christian
                        Apocrypha and Early Islamic Literature: The ‘Book of Mary,’
                        the Arabic Apocryphal Gospel of John and the Qu’rān,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha </hi>19 (2008): 267-291.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Joosten, Jan. “The Dura Parchment and the Diatessaron,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae
                        Christianae </hi>57 (2003): 159-175.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kiraz, George Anton. <hi rend="italic">Comparative Edition of the Syriac Gospels. </hi>4 vols.
                        Brill: Leiden, 1996.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kraeling, Carl H. <hi rend="italic">A Greek Fragment of Tatian’s Diatessaron From Dura. </hi>
                        Studies and Documents 3. London: Christophers, 1935.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lange, Christian. “Zum Taufverständnis im syrischen
                        Diatessaronkommentar.” In <hi rend="italic">Syriaca. Zur Geschichte, Theologie,
                            Liturgie und Gegenwartslage der syrischen Kirchen. 2. Deutsches
                            Syrologen-Symposium (Juli 2000, Wittenberg), </hi>ed. M. Tamcke.
                        Studien zur orientalischen Kirchengeschichte 17. Münster: Lit,
                        2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ in the Syriac Commentary on the
                        Diatessaron, </hi>CSCO 616, Subsidia 118. Louvain: Peeters, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. “Ephrem, His School, and the Yawnaya: Some
                        Remarks on the Early Syriac Versions of the New Testament.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">The Peshitta: Its Use in Literature and Liturgy: Papers Read At the
                            Third Peshitta Symposium, </hi>ed. Robert Bas ter Haar Romeny,
                        Monographs of the Peshitta Institute Leiden 15. Leiden: Brill,
                        2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Ephraem der Syrer. Kommentar zum Diatessaron. </hi> 2 vols.
                        <pb n="49"/>
                        Fontes Christiani 54/1-2. Turnhout: Brepols, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl>Leloir, Louis. <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem. Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant, version
                        arménienne. </hi>CSCO 145, Scriptores Armeniaci 2. Louvain: L.
                        Durbecq, 1954.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">L’Évangile d’Éphrem d’après les oeuvres éditées: Recueil des
                        textes. </hi>CSCO 180, Subsidia 12. Louvain: Secrétariat du
                        CorpusSCO, 1958.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Le témoignage d’Éphrem sur le Diatessaron. </hi>CSCO 227,
                        Subsidia 19. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1962.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem, Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant, texte
                        syriaque (Manuscrit Chester Beatty 709). </hi>Chester Beatty
                        Monographs 8. Dublin: Hodges Figgis &amp; Co., 1963.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe: Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant ou
                        Diatessaron. </hi>Sources Chrétiennes 121. Paris: Éditions du Cerf,
                        1966.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lewis, Agnes Smith. <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha Syriaca: The Protevangelium Jacobi and
                        Transitus Mariae, with Texts from the Septuagint, the Corân, the
                        Peshitta, and from a Syriac Hymn in a Syro-Arabic Palimpsest of the
                        Fifth and Other Centuries. </hi>Studia Sinaitica 11. London: C.J. Clay
                        and Sons, 1902.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marmardji, A. S. <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron de Tatien. </hi>Beirut: Imprimerie catholique,
                        1935.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matthews, Edward G. <hi rend="italic">The Armenian Commentary on Genesis Attributed
                        to Ephrem the Syrian. </hi>CSCO 573, Scriptores Armeniaci 24.
                        Louvain: Peeters, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">The Armenian Commentaries on Exodus-Deuteronomy
                        Attributed to Ephrem the Syrian. </hi>CSCO 587, Scriptores Armeniaci
                        25. Louvain: Peeters Publishers, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McCarthy, Carmel. <hi rend="italic">Saint Ephrem’s Commentary on Tatian’s Diatessaron:
                        An English Translation of Chester Beatty Syriac MS 709. </hi>Journal of
                        Semitic Studies Supplement 2. Oxford: Published by Oxford
                        University Press on behalf of the University of Manchester,
                        1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mell, Ulrich. <hi rend="italic">Christliche Hauskirche und Neues Testament. Die Ikonologie
                        des Baptisteriums von Dura Europos und das Diatessaron Tatians. </hi>
                        <pb n="50"/>Novum Testamentum et Orbis Antiquus 77. Göttingen:
                        Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mitchell, C.W. <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Prose Refutations of Mani, Marcion, and
                        Bardaisan. Volume I: The Discourses Addressed to Hypatius. </hi>Text and
                        Translation Society. London: Williams and Norgate, 1912.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Murray, Robert. “The Lance Which Re-Opened Paradise, a
                        Mysterious Reading in the Early Syriac Fathers,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                            Christiana Periodica </hi>39 (1973): 224-234, 491.</bibl>
                    <bibl>________. <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac
                        Tradition. </hi>Rev. ed. London: T&amp;T Clark, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McVey, Kathleen E. <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns. </hi>Mahwah, NJ: Paulist
                        Press, 1989.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Naffah, Charles. “'Les ‘histoires’ syriaques de la Vierge: traditions
                        apocryphes anciennes et récentes,” <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha </hi>20 (2009): 137-
                        188.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Parker, D.C., D.G.K Taylor, and M.S. Goodacre. “The Dura-
                        Europos Gospel Harmony.” In <hi rend="italic">Studies in the Early Text of the
                            Gospels and Acts, </hi>ed. D.G.K. Taylor. Atlanta: Society of Biblical
                        Literature, 1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pastorelli, David. “The Genealogies of Jesus in Tatian’s
                        Diatessaron: The Question of their Absence or Presence.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">Infancy Gospels: Stories and Identities, </hi>ed. Claire Clivaz, Andreas
                        Dettwiler, Luc Devillers, and Enrico Norelli. WUNT 281.
                        Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petersen, William L. <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron: Its Creation, Dissemination,
                        Significance, and History in Scholarship. </hi>Supplements to Vigiliae
                        Christianae 25. Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Possekel, Ute. <hi rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts in the Writings of
                        Ephrem the Syrian. </hi>CSCO 580, Subsidia 102. Louvain: Peeters,
                        1999.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reinink, Gerrit J. “Neue Fragmente zum Diatessaronkommentar
                        des Ephraemschülers Aba,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica </hi>11
                        (1980): 117-133.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schäfers, J. <hi rend="italic">Evangelienzitate in Ephraems des Syrers Kommentar zu den
                        paulinischen Schriften. </hi>Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder, 1917.</bibl>
                    <pb n="51"/>
                    <bibl>Thorossian, Joannes. <hi rend="italic">Aithallae Episcopi Edesseni Epistola Ad
                        Christianos in Persarum Regione De Fide. </hi>Venice: Lazari, 1942.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tonneau, R.-M. <hi rend="italic">Sancti Ephraem Syri in Genesim et in Exodum
                        Commentarii. </hi>CSCO 152, Scriptores Syri 71. Louvain: L.
                        Durbecq, 1955.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Urbina, Ignatius Ortix de. <hi rend="italic">Vetus Evangelium Syrorum et Exinde
                        Excerptum Diatessaron Tatiani. </hi>Biblia Polyglotta Matritensia,
                        Series VI. Madrid: Consejo Superior de Investigaciones
                        Cientificas, 1967.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vööbus, Arthur. <hi rend="italic">Studies in the History of the Gospel Text in Syriac. </hi>
                        CSCO 128, Subsidia 3. Louvain: L. Durbecq, 1951.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Walters, J. Edward. “The Philoxenian Gospels as Reconstructed
                        from the Writings of Philoxenus of Mabbug,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of
                            Syriac Studies </hi>13 (2010): 177-249.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Watson, Francis. <hi rend="italic">Gospel Writing: A Canonical Perspective. </hi>Grand
                        Rapids: Eerdmans, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Williams, Peter J. “The Syriac Versions of the New Testament.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">The Text of the New Testament in Contemporary Research: Essays on
                            the Status Quaestionis, </hi>ed. Bart D. Ehrman, and Michael W.
                        Holmes. Leiden: Brill, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wright, William and Norman McLean. <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical History of
                        Eusebius in Syriac. </hi>Cambridge: University Press, 1898.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zahn, Theodor. <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Diatessaron, </hi>Forschungen zur Geschichte
                        des neutestamentlichen Kanons und der altkirchlichen
                        Literatur, Tl. 1 Erlangen: Deichert, 1881.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>