<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2017</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                        <surname>Brock</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Grigory</forename>
                        <surname>Kessel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences and University of Manchester</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sergey</forename>
                        <surname>Minov</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n1bib-recent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Sebastian P. Brock</author>
                        <author>Grigory Kessel</author>
                        <author>Sergey Minov</author>
                        <title level="a">Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2017</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1Bib-Recent.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="143" to="195">143–195</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="6"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>

            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="bibliography">
        <body>

            <div type="title">
                <head>Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2017</head>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="*">
                    <p rend="footnote text"> The list of publications is based on the
                            online Comprehensive Bibliography on Syriac Christianity, supported by
                            the Center for the Study of Christianity at the Hebrew Univesity of
                            Jerusalem (<ref target="HYPERLINK"/>). Suggested additions and
                            corrections can be sent to: csc@mail.huji.ac.il</p>
                </note>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <head>Books</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Akhrass, R.-Y., and Syryany, I. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">160 Unpublished
                            Homilies of Jacob of Serugh</hi>. 2 vols (Damascus: Syriac Orthodox
                        Patriarchate, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Akopian, A., <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Aramean and Syriac Studies:
                            A Manual</hi> (Gorgias Handbooks; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Andrews, T.L., <hi rend="italic">Matt‘ēos Uṙhayec‘i and His Chronicle:
                            History as Apocalypse in a Crossroads of Cultures</hi> (The Medieval
                        Mediterranean 108; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Blidstein, M.B., <hi rend="italic">Purity, Community, and Ritual in Early
                            Christian Literature</hi> (Oxford Studies in the Abrahamic Religions;
                        Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bouffard, E., and Ziadé, R. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Chrétiens d’Orient:
                            2000 ans d’histoire</hi> (Paris: Gallimard, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bremmer, J.N., <hi rend="italic">Maidens, Magic and Martyrs in Early
                            Christianity: Collected Essays I</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen
                        zum Neuen Testament 379; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F., and Debié, M., <hi rend="italic">Le Monde syriaque.
                            Sur les routes d’un christianisme ignoré</hi> (Paris: Les Belles
                        Lettres, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S.P., <hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Syriac Studies</hi>
                        (Gorgias Handbooks; 3rd ed.; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S.P., and Kiraz, G.A., <hi rend="italic">Pocket Gorgias
                            Syriac-English Dictionary</hi> (Gorgias Handbooks; Piscataway, New
                        Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Burke, T., <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Tradition of the Infancy Gospel of
                            Thomas: A Critical Edition and English Translation</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 48; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Burns, R., <hi rend="italic">Aleppo: A History</hi> (Cities of the Ancient
                        World; London / New York: Routledge, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Origins of the Colonnaded Streets in the Cities of
                            the Roman East</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Büttner, W., <hi rend="italic">“Gottheit in uns”: Die monastische und
                            psychologische Grundlegung der Mystik nach einer überlieferten
                            Textkollektion aus dem Werk des Šem‘on d-Ṭaibuṯeh</hi> (Eichstätter
                        Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 5; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Calder, M., <hi rend="italic">Bethlehem’s Syriac Christians: Self, Nation
                            and Church in Dialogue and Practice</hi> (The Modern Muslim World 4;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cambraia, C.N., <hi rend="italic">Livro de Isaac: edição crítica da
                            tradução medieval portuguesa da obra de Isaac de Nínive</hi>
                        (Palimpsesto; Belo Horizonte: Editora UFMG, 2017). </bibl>
                    <bibl>Cerbelaud, D. (tr.), <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe. Hymnes contres
                            les hérésies, Hymnes contre Julien</hi>. 2 vols (Sources chrétiennes
                        587, 590; Paris: Cerf, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coakley, J.F. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Holy Mar Pappos
                            and Twenty-Four Thousand Who Were Martyred with Him</hi> (Ely,
                        Cambridgeshire: Jericho Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cochrane, S., <hi rend="italic">Many Monks across the Sea: Church of the
                            East Monastic Mission in Ninth-Century Asia</hi> (Regnum Studies in
                        Mission; Eugene, Oregon: Wipf and Stock Publishers, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coloru, O., <hi rend="italic">L’imperatore prigioniero: Valeriano, la
                            Persia e la disfatta di Edessa</hi> (Storia e Società; Roma: Laterza,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>den Biesen, K., <hi rend="italic">Hemels Brood en Geestelijke Drank: Orde
                            van de viering van de goddelijke Qurobo volgens de traditie van de
                            Syrisch Orthodoxe Kerk van Antiochië</hi> (Losser, The Netherlands: Bar
                        Ebroyo Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Duncan, P.A., <hi rend="italic">Novel Hermeneutics in the Greek
                            Pseudo-Clementine Romance</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum
                        Neuen Testament 395; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Filoni, F., <hi rend="italic">The Church in Iraq</hi>. trans. by E. Condon
                        (Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gallagher, E.L., and Meade, J.D., <hi rend="italic">The Biblical Canon
                            Lists from Early Christianity: Texts and Analysis</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                        University Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gaunt, D., Atto, N., and Barthoma, S.O. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them
                            Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and
                            Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New
                        York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Géhin, P., <hi rend="italic">Les manuscrits syriaques de parchemin du
                            Sinaï et leurs membra disjecta</hi> (CSCO 665, Subs. 136; Louvain:
                        Peeters, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gianazza, G. (trans.), <hi rend="italic">Ṣalībā ibn Yūḥannā al-Mawṣilī. I
                            libri dei misteri (Kitāb asfār al-asrār)</hi> (Patrimonio culturale
                        arabo cristiano 12; Roma: Aracne, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Brani scelti della Chiesa dell’Oriente (XI-XIV
                            secolo)</hi> (Udine: Edizioni Segno, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gramaglia, E.J. (trans.), <hi rend="italic">Astrological Works of
                            Theophilus of Edessa</hi> (Minneapolis, Minnesota: The Cazimi Press,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gzella, H., <hi rend="italic">De eerste wereldtaal: De geschiedenis van
                            het Aramees</hi> (Amsterdam: Athenaeum / Polak &amp; Van Gennep,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Haelewyck, J.-C. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en
                            syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hanna, S.S., <hi rend="italic">Abducted in Iraq: A Priest in Baghdad</hi>
                        (Notre Dame, Indiana: University of Notre Dame Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harrak, A. (ed. and trans.), <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Zuqnīn,
                            Parts I and II: From the Creation to the Year 506/7 AD</hi> (Gorgias
                        Chronicles of Late Antiquity 2; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunter, E.C.D., and Coakley, J.F., <hi rend="italic">A Syriac Service-Book
                            from Turfan: Museum für asiatische Kunst, Berlin MIK III 45</hi>
                        (Berliner Turfantexte 39; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Immerzeel, M., <hi rend="italic">The Narrow Way to Heaven: Identity and
                            Identities in the Art of Middle Eastern Christianity</hi> (Orientalia
                        Lovaniensia Analecta 259; Leuven: Peeters, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Issa, B.T., Issa, T., Issa, T.B., Issa, T., and Issa, T., <hi rend="italic">Readings in the 20th Century Genocide of the Syriac
                            Orthodox Church of Antioch (Sayfo)</hi> (Hauppauge, New York; Nova
                        Science Publishers, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Issa, M. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le latin des maronites</hi> (Paris:
                        Geuthner, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kavvadas, N., <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem zwischen Aachen und Bagdad: Zur
                            Existenzkrise des byzantinischen Christentums im Abbasidenreich</hi>
                        (Jenaer mediävistische Vorträge 6; Stuttgart: Franz Steiner, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lahdo, A., <hi rend="italic">A Traitor among Us: The Story of Father Yusuf
                            Akbulut. A Text in the Ṭuroyo Dialect of ‘Iwardo</hi> (Semitica viva 56;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lee, R., <hi rend="italic">Symbolic Interpretations in Ethiopic and Early
                            Syriac Literature</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 24; Leuven: Peeters,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mack, J., <hi rend="italic">The Construction of Equality: Syriac
                            Immigration and the Swedish City</hi> (Minneapolis, Minnesota:
                        University of Minnesota Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marciak, M., <hi rend="italic">Sophene, Gordyene, and Adiabene: Three
                            Regna Minora of Northern Mesopotamia between East and West</hi> (Impact
                        of Empire 26; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Messo, J., <hi rend="italic">Arameans and the Making of ‘Assyrians’: The
                            Last Aramaic-speaking Christians of the Middle East</hi> (The
                        Netherlands: Aramaic Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Meyer, M.R., Kiraz, G.A., and Bali, J. (eds. and trans.), <hi rend="italic">Exodus according to the Syriac Peshitta Version, with
                            English Translation</hi> (Surath Ktobh; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                        Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nin, M., and Vergani, E., <hi rend="italic">“La preghiera è il nostro
                            ornamento”: Una scelta di testi siriaci (IV-VII secolo)</hi> (Milano:
                        Centro Ambrosiano, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Papoutsakis, M., <hi rend="italic">Vicarious Kingship: A Theme in Syriac
                            Political Theology in Late Antiquity</hi> (Studien und Texte zu Antike
                        und Christentum 100; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pedersen, N.A., Falkenberg, R., Larsen, J.M., and Leurini, C., <hi rend="italic">The Old Testament in Manichaean Tradition: The Sources in
                            Syriac, Greek, Coptic, Middle Persian, Parthian, Sogdian, New Persian,
                            and Arabic</hi> (Corpus Fontium Manichaeorum: Biblia Manichaica 1;
                        Turnhout: Brepols, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Phenix, R.R., Jr., and Horn, C.B., <hi rend="italic">The Rabbula Corpus:
                            Comprising the Life of Rabbula, His Correspondence, a Homily Delivered
                            in Constantinople, Canons, and Hymns</hi> (SBL Writings from the
                        Greco-Roman World 17; Atlanta: SBL Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ramos, M.V., <hi rend="italic">O Apocalipse siríaco de Daniel</hi>
                        (Apocrypha; São Paulo: Paulus, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Řoutil, M., Košťálová, P., and Novák, P., <hi rend="italic">Katastrofa
                            křesťanů: Likvidace Arménů, Asyřanů a Řeků v Osmanské říši v letech
                            1914–1923</hi> (Pro Oriente; Červený Kostelec / Praha: Pavel Mervart,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rajan, M., <hi rend="italic">Martyrs, Saints and Prelates of the Syriac
                            Orthodox Church. Volume 5</hi> (Kottayam, India: Travancore Syriac
                        Orthodox Publishers, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Martyrs, Saints and Prelates of the Syriac Orthodox
                            Church</hi> (Puthencruz, India: Travancore Syriac Orthodox Publishers,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ruggieri, V. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin
                            in the Fondo Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Saadi, A.-M., <hi rend="italic">Moshe Bar Kepha’s Cause of the Celebration
                            of the Nativity: A Genre for Exegesis, Ecumenism, and Apology</hi>
                        (Texts from Christian Late Antiquity 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                        Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scully, J., <hi rend="italic">Isaac of Nineveh’s Ascetical
                            Eschatology</hi> (Oxford Early Christian Studies; Oxford: Oxford
                        University Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <hi rend="italic">Service Book of the Holy Qurbono, according to the Rite
                            of the Syriac Orthodox Church</hi> (The Divine Mysteries 1; Whippany,
                        New Jersey: Malankara Archdiocese of the Syriac Orthodox Church in North
                        America, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sims-Williams, N., <hi rend="italic">An Ascetic Miscellany: The Christian
                            Sogdian Manuscript E28</hi> (Berliner Turfantexte 42; Turnhout: Brepols,
                        2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Taylor, R.A., Kiraz, G.A., and Bali, J. (eds. and trans.), <hi rend="italic">The Psalms according to the Syriac Peshitta Version, with
                            English Translation</hi> (Surath Ktobh; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                        Press, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Teule, H.G.B., Keser-Kayaalp, E., Akalin, K., Doru, N., and Toprak, M.S.
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                            International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University,
                            Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern
                        Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tieszen, C., <hi rend="italic">Cross Veneration in the Medieval Islamic
                            World: Christian Identity and Practice under Muslim Rule</hi> (The Early
                        and Medieval Islamic World; London: I.B. Tauris, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Trigona-Harany, B., <hi rend="italic">Adıyaman Süryanilerinin tarihi.
                            Maqdasi Barsom ve evlatlarının yedi gubağa [kuşağa] olan tarihi ve soğan
                            kabukları</hi> (Bibliotheca nisibinensis 3; Cağaloğlu, İstanbul: Su
                        Yayınları, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>van Bladel, K.T., <hi rend="italic">From Sasanian Mandaeans to Ṣābians of
                            the Marshes</hi> (Leiden Studies in Islam and Society 6; Leiden /
                        Boston: Brill, 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Varghese, B. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">West Syrian Anaphoras</hi> (Awsār
                        Slāwōt’ō 4; Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute,
                        2017).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <head>Theses</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Abi-Hassoun, F., <hi rend="italic">On God’s Holy Mountain: The Maronite People
                        on Pilgrimage</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Fordham University, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Asade, D.,<hi rend="italic"> La literatura farmacéutica siríaca y árabe.
                        Comparación de las recetas de El Libro de las Medicinas (siríaco) con
                        recetas en la literatura farmacéutica árabe</hi> (Tesis de doctorado en
                    Farmacia; Universidad de Buenos Aires, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Fiano, E., <hi rend="italic">Three Powers in Heaven: The Trinitarian
                        Controversies in Fourth-Century Roman Syria and the Christian-Jewish
                        Continuum</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Duke University, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Hartung, B.A., <hi rend="italic">“Stories of the Cross”: Ephrem and His
                        Exegesis in Fourth-Century Mesopotamia</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Saint Louis
                    University, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Jett, M.J., <hi rend="italic">The Trinity Is Not Just a List of Three Words:
                        Theology, Scripture and Politics in the Patristic Twelve Prophet
                        Commentaries</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Union Theological Seminary, New York,
                    2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Karickakunnel, P., <hi rend="italic">The Eastern Triple Anaphorae: A
                        Theological Comparative Study of the East Syrian Anaphoral Prayers of Addai
                        and Mari, Theodore of Mopsuestia and Nestorius and Their Relevance on the
                        Syro-Malabar Church</hi> (Thesis ad Doctoratum; Pontificium Institutum
                    Orientale, Facultas Scientiarum Ecclesiasticarum Orientalium, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Korsvoll, N.H., <hi rend="italic">Reconsidering ‘Christian’: Context and
                        Categorisation in the Study of Syriac Amulets and Incantation Bowls</hi>
                    (Ph.D. dissertation; Norwegian School of Theology, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Mylammoottil Antony, J., <hi rend="italic">Episcopal Ordination and Ministry:
                        A Theological Study Based on the Tradition and the Pontifical Rite of the
                        Syro Malabar Church</hi> (Thesis ad Doctoratum; Pontificium Institutum
                    Orientale, Facultas Scientiarum Ecclesiasticarum Orientalium, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pirtea, A.C., <hi rend="italic">Die geistigen Sinne in der ostsyrischen
                        christlichen Mystik: Untersuchungen zum Wahrnehmungsbegriff und zur
                        Gotteserkenntnis in der griechischen und syro-orientalischen asketischen
                        Literatur der Spätantike</hi> (Inauguraldissertation zur Erlangung des
                    Grades eines Doktors der Philosophie; Freie Universität Berlin, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Platt, A., <hi rend="italic">The Church of the East at Three Critical Points
                        in its History</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; The Catholic University of America,
                    2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pullankunnel, A.S., <hi rend="italic">“Dolus” as a Ground of Marriage Nullity
                        (can. 1098/CIC/1983 and can. 821/CCEO) with Special Focus on the
                        Jurisprudence of the Major Archiepiscopal Tribunal of the Syro-Malabar
                        Church</hi> (Thesis ad Doctoratum; Pontificium Institutum Orientale,
                    Facultas Iuris Canonici Orientalis, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Rassi, S., <hi rend="italic">Justifying Christianity in the Islamic Middle
                        Ages: The Apologetic Theology of ‘Abdīshō‘ bar Brīkhā (d. 1318)</hi> (Ph.D.
                    dissertation; University of Oxford, 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl>Sebastian, J., <hi rend="italic">Ṣlīvā in the East Syriac Liturgy: A
                        Theological Analysis Based on the Holy Qurbānā of the Syro Malabar
                        Church</hi> (Thesis ad Doctoratum; Pontificium Institutum Orientale,
                    Facultas Scientiarum Ecclesiasticarum Orientalium, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Sebastian, Sh., <hi rend="italic">The Mystery of the Triple Gradated Church: A
                        Theological Analysis of the Ktābā d-Massqātā (Book of Steps) with Particular
                        Reference to the Writings of Aphrahat and John the Solitary</hi> (Thesis ad
                    Doctoratum; Pontificium Institutum Orientale, Facultas Scientiarum
                    Ecclesiasticarum Orientalium, 2017).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <head>Articles</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Ab Rahman, Z., and Omar, M.N., “Yahya Ibn ‘Adi Perspective on Islamic
                    Psychotherapy,” in: <hi rend="italic">Regionalism and Community Building in
                        ASEAN: Perspectives from Social Sciences and Humanities. Proceedings of
                        ICOSH-UKM 2017: The 6th International Conference on Social Sciences and
                        Humanities</hi> (Bangi, Selangor: Universiti Kebangsaan Malaysia, 2017),
                    973-980.</bibl>
                <bibl>Abou Seke, F., “Die Eremiten der Höhlenklöster. Das Beispiel der Felsenklöster
                    in Phoenice Libanensis, Syrien,” <hi rend="italic">Hortus artium
                        medievalium</hi> 23 (2017), 96-106.</bibl>
                <bibl>Abousamra, G., “Syriac Inscriptions on Tablitos,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                        l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 33-84.</bibl>
                <bibl>Adamson, P., and Wisnovsky, R., “Yaḥyā Ibn ‘Adī on a <hi rend="italic">Kalām
                    </hi>Argument for Creation,” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Studies in Medieval
                        Philosophy</hi> 5 (2017), 213-239.</bibl>
                <bibl>Adler, W., “The Creation of Christian Elite Culture in Roman Syria and the
                    Near East,” in: D.S. Richter and W.A. Johnson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Oxford Handbook of the Second Sophistic</hi>(New York: Oxford University
                    Press, 2017), 655-668.</bibl>
                <bibl>Aïm, E., “Les racines avec <hi rend="italic">waw</hi> fort en syriaque,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 130:3-4 (2017), 301-325.</bibl>
                <bibl>Akhrass, R.-Y., “La tradition syriaque sous-jacente au <hi rend="italic">Psautier spirituel </hi>attribué à Éphrem le Syrien,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal Journal</hi> 55 (2017), 63-77.</bibl>
                <bibl>Akyüz, G., “The Status of Süryanis in and around Mardin,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E.
                    Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies
                        Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22
                        April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters,
                    2017), 371-393.</bibl>
                <bibl>Al-Kajela, A., “The Effect of Culture Learning on Neo-Aramaic: Empirical
                    Evidence from Politeness Theory,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of
                        Linguistics, Literature and Culture</hi> 4:2 (2017), 47-78.</bibl>
                <bibl>Al-Khoury, Y.Y., “Les aspects du sacerdoce selon saint Éphrem le Syrien,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal Journal</hi> 55 (2017), 77-100 [in
                    Arabic].</bibl>
                <bibl>Allen, P., “Severus of Antioch: Homilies and Hymns on Martyrs,” in: F.P.
                    Barone, C. Macé and P. Ubierna (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philologie,
                        herméneutique et histoire des textes entre Orient et Occident. Mélanges en
                        hommage à Sever J. Voicu</hi> (Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 73;
                    Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 323-341.</bibl>
                <bibl>Arzhanov, Y.N., “<hi rend="italic">Amrus Philosophus Graecus</hi>: A New
                    Witness to the Syriac Sentences of Menander,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi>
                    130:1-2 (2017), 71-121.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Menander in Syriac: From Euthalian Apparatus to Scholia on Gregory of
                    Nazianzus,” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017), 57-74.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Syriac Parallels to <hi rend="italic">Muḫtār Al-ḥikam wa-Maḥāsin
                        Al-Kalim</hi> of Mubaššir b. Fātik as Evidence for Translations from Syriac
                    into Arabic,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 119-130.</bibl>
                <bibl>Atto, N., “What Could Not Be Written: A Study of the Oral Transmission of
                    Sayfo Genocide Memory among Assyrians,” <hi rend="italic">Genocide Studies
                        International</hi> 10 (2017), 183-209.</bibl>
                <bibl>Atto, N., and Barthoma, S.O., “Syriac Orthodox Leadership in the Post-Genocide
                    Period (1918–26) and the Removal of the Patriarchate from Turkey,” in: D. Gaunt,
                    N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo –
                        The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the
                        Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn,
                    2017), 113-131.</bibl>
                <bibl>Aydin, P.A., “Qlido d-Leshono – Key of Language: A Comprehensive Syriac
                    Lexicon by Abbot Yuyakim of Tur Islo,” in: T. Li and K. Dyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient Manuscripts to Modern Dictionaries: Select
                        Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and Greek</hi> (Perspectives on Linguistics and
                    Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017),
                    173-178.</bibl>
                <bibl>Baasten, M.F.J., “A Syriac Reading of the Qur’ān? The Case of <hi rend="italic">Sūrat al-Kawṯar</hi>,” in: A. Al-Jallad (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Arabic in Context: Celebrating 400 Years of Arabic at Leiden
                        University</hi> (Studies in Semitic Languages and Linguistics 89; Leiden /
                    Boston: Brill, 2017), 372-392.</bibl>
                <bibl>Badwi, A., “Boutros al-Qobrsi (Pierre le Chypriote), un grand pionnier de la
                    peinture Maronite et libanaise,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43
                    (2017), 85-91.</bibl>
                <bibl>BarAbraham, A., “Turkey’s Key Arguments in Denying the Assyrian Genocide,” in:
                    D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not
                        Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean
                        Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New York /
                    Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 219-232.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bardakci, M., Freyberg-Inan, A., Giesel, C., and Leisse, O., “Like a Drop in
                    the Ocean: The Last Syriacs in Turkey in a Maelstrom of Nationalism, Islamism,
                    Assimilation, and Diverging Socio-Political Interests,” in: M. Bardakci, A.
                    Freyberg-Inan, C. Giesel and O. Leisse (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Religious
                        Minorities in Turkey: Alevi, Armenians, and Syriacs and the Struggle to
                        Desecuritize Religious Freedom</hi> (London: Palgrave Macmillan, 2017),
                    165-192.</bibl>
                <bibl>Benevich, F., “Fire and Heat: Yaḥyā b. ‘Adī and Avicenna on the Essentiality
                    of Being Substance or Accident,” <hi rend="italic">Arabic Sciences and
                        Philosophy</hi> 27:2 (2017), 237-267.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bernabò, M., “Miniatures and Ornament in the Fondo Grünwald,” in: V. Ruggieri
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin in the Fondo
                        Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2017), 249-286.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bernabò, M., Fani, S., Farina, M., and Rao, I.G., “Le miniature del Vangelo
                    arabo della Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana di Firenze, codice Orientali 387
                    (Mardin, 1299 d.C.),” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi>
                    83:2 (2017), 293-447.</bibl>
                <bibl>Berti, V., “Il sinodo itinerante di Mar Aba del 540,” <hi rend="italic">Cristianesimo nella storia</hi> 38:3 (2017), 673-728.</bibl>
                <bibl>Braida, E., “The 9th Century Syriac Culture between Greeks and Arabs,” in: V.
                    Ruggieri (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin in the
                        Fondo Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2017),
                    159-202.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Manuscripts in the Fondo Grünwald: An Overview,” in: V. Ruggieri
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin in the Fondo
                        Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2017), 13-36.</bibl>
                <bibl>Braida, E., and Pavan, M., “Manuscripts Folder,” in: V. Ruggieri (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin in the Fondo
                        Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2017), 203-248.</bibl>
                <bibl>Berti, V., “L’intreccio tra fisiologia e vita spirituale in Simone di
                    Taibuteh, medico e mistico cristiano siriaco del secolo VII,” in: I. Adinolfi,
                    G. Gaeta and A. Lavagetto (eds.), <hi rend="italic">L’anti-Babele: Sulla mistica
                        degli antichi e dei moderni</hi> (Genova: Il Melangolo, 2017),
                    231-249.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Les évêques de l’Église de Perse face au pouvoir séculier (V<hi rend="sup">e</hi>–VIII<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle),” in: S. Destephen
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">L’évêque de Cour. Figure politique, figure
                        polémique</hi> (Paris: Hermann, 2017), 123-145.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Mar Aba the Great on Exodus: Fragments from the <hi rend="italic">Commentary </hi>of Isho‘dad of Merv and the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                        Topography</hi> of Cosmas Indicopleustes,” <hi rend="italic">Cristianesimo
                        nella storia</hi> 38 (2017), 27-50.</bibl>
                <bibl>Berti, V., and Cantone, V., “New Light on the Sources of the Illuminations of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Christian Topography</hi> of Kosmas Indikopleustes,” <hi rend="italic">Вестник Санкт-Петербургского Универси-тета, Серия 2:
                        История</hi> 62:2 (2017), 244-254.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bhayro, S., “Galen in Syriac: Rethinking Old Assumptions,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017), 132-154.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Judaeo-Syriac Medical Fragment from the Cairo Genizah: A New Edition
                    and Analysis,” in: L. Lehmhaus and M. Martelli (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Collecting Recipes: Byzantine and Jewish Pharmacology in Dialogue</hi>
                    (Science, Technology, and Medicine in Ancient Cultures 4; Berlin / New York:
                    Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 273-300.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “On the Problem of Syriac “Influence” in the Transmission of Greek
                    Science to the Arabs: The Cases of Astronomy, Philosophy, and Medicine,” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of the Islamicate World</hi> 5:3 (2017),
                    211-227.</bibl>
                <bibl>Birol, S., “Interpretation of the ‘Sayfo’ in Gallo Shabo’s Poem,” in: D.
                    Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return:
                        Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians
                        in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford:
                    Berghahn, 2017), 157-177.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bitton-Ashkelony, B., “Monastic Hybridity and Anti-Exegetical Discourse: From
                    Philoxenus of Mabbug to Dadišo Qatraya,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Patristica</hi> 91 (2017), 417-433.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Theories of Prayer in Late Antiquity: Doubts and Practices from Maximos
                    of Tyre to Isaac of Nineveh,” in: B. Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in Eastern Christianities, 5th to 11th
                        Centuries</hi> (London / New York: Routledge, 2017), 10-33.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bohas, G., “Les méfaits de l’optique hébraisante sur le tratement des <hi rend="italic">bgdkpt </hi>en syriaque,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                        l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 93-112.</bibl>
                <bibl>Böhmisch, F., “Die Vorlage der syrischen Sirachübersetzung und die gereimte
                    hebräische Paraphrase zu Ben Sira aus der Ben-Ezra-Geniza,” in: G. Karner, F.
                    Ueberschaer and B.M. Zapff (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Texts and Contexts of the
                        Book of Sirach / Texte und Kontexte des Sirachbuches</hi> (Septuagint and
                    Cognate Studies 66; Atlanta, Georgia: SBL Press, 2017), 199-237.</bibl>
                <bibl>Borbone, P.G., “From Tur ‘Abdin to Rome: The Syro-Orthodox Presence in
                    Sixteenth-Century Rome,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru
                    and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context:
                        First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University,
                        Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern
                    Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 277-287.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. ““Monsignore Vescovo di Soria”, also Known as Moses of Mardin, Scribe and
                    Book Collector,” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017),
                    79-114.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bourgel, J., “The Holders of the “Word of Truth”: The Pharisees in
                    Pseudo-Clementine <hi rend="italic">Recognitions </hi>1.27–71,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 25:2 (2017),
                    171-200.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brändle, R., “Eucharistie und christliches Leben bei Johannes Chrysostomos und
                    Theodor von Mopsuestia,” in: D. Hellholm and D. Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist – Its Origins and Contexts: Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table
                        Fellowship in Late Antiquity, Early Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume
                        2: Patristic Traditions, Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen
                    zum Neuen Testament 376; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1185-1209.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brelaud, S., and Briquel-Chatonnet, F., “Quelques réflexions sur la
                    désignation des chrétiens dans l’inscription du mage Kirdīr et dans l’empire
                    sassanide,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 113-136.</bibl>
                <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F., “Naissance et développement des églises en monde
                    syriaque,” in: E. Bouffard and R. Ziadé (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Chrétiens
                        d’Orient: 2000 ans d’histoire</hi> (Paris: Gallimard, 2017), 32-39.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, S.P., “The Armenian Translation of the Syriac Life of St Ephrem and Its
                    Syriac Source,” in: C. Esche-Ramshorn (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Reflections on
                        Armenia and the Christian Orient: Studies in Honour of Vrej Nersessian</hi>
                    (Yerevan: Ankyunacar, 2017), 119-130.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “God as the Educator of Humanity: Some Voices from the Syriac Tradition,”
                    in: G.J. Brooke and R. Smithuis (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Jewish Education from
                        Antiquity to the Middle Ages: Studies in Honour of Philip S. Alexander</hi>
                    (Ancient Judaism and early Christianity 100; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017),
                    236-251.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “A Historical Note of October 1915 Written in Dayro D-Zafaran
                    (Deyrulzafaran),” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 148-156.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Martyrdom of Crescus (Crescens) of Myra,” <hi rend="italic">Analecta
                        Bollandiana</hi> 135:1 (2017), 5-22.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Patriarch Severos’ Letter on His Flight from Antioch in 518,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017),
                    25-50.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, S.P., and Kessel, G., “The “Departure of Mary” in Two Palimpsests at
                    the Monastery of St. Сatherine (Sinai Syr. 30 &amp; Sinai Arabic 514),” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017), 115-152.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, S.P., Kessel, G., and Minov, S., “Recent Publications on Syriac Topics:
                    2016,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017),
                    257-315.</bibl>
                <bibl>Butts, A.M., “Assyrian Christians,” in: E. Frahm (ed.), <hi rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Assyria</hi> (Blackwell Companions to the Ancient World;
                    Hoboken, New Jersey: Wiley Blackwell, 2017), 599-612.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Between Aramaic *<hi rend="italic">᾿Iðayn</hi> and Greek <hi rend="italic">Δέ</hi>: The Linguistic History of Syriac <hi rend="italic">Den</hi>,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 13-30.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Manuscript Transmission as Reception History: The Case of Ephrem the
                    Syrian (d. 373),” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 25:2
                    (2017), 281-306.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “A Syriac Dialogue Poem between the Vine and Cedar by Dawid bar Pawlos,”
                    in: E. Jiménez (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Babylonian Disputation Poems: With
                        Editions of the Series of the Poplar, Palm and Vine, the Series of the
                        Spider, and the Story of the Poor, Forlorn Wren</hi> (Culture and History of
                    the Ancient Near East 87; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 462-473.</bibl>
                <bibl>Çağlayan, E., “The Süryanis in the Archival Documents of the Turkish Republic
                    (1923-1960),” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 343-357.</bibl>
                <bibl>Calà, I., and Hawley, R., “Transliteration versus Translation of Greek Plant
                    Names in the Syriac Medical Writings of Sergius of Reš ‘Aynā: On the Tables of
                    Contents in BL Add. 14,661,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017),
                    155-182.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cambraia, C.N., and de Avellar, J.B.C., “Um ensaio de estemática: tradição
                    ibero-românica da obra de Isaac de Nínive,” <hi rend="italic">Revista da
                        ABRALIN</hi> 16:1 (2017), 15-36.</bibl>
                <bibl>Camplani, A., “Bardaisan and the Bible,” in: A. van den Kerchove and L.G.
                    Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose et manichéisme: Entre les
                        oasis d’Égypte et la Route de la Soie. Hommage à Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi>
                    (Bibliothèque de l’École des hautes études, Sciences religieuses 176; Turnhout:
                    Brepols, 2017), 699-716.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Mosè, Elia e Abramo nel Vangelo di Marcione,” <hi rend="italic">Quaderni
                        di Vicino Oriente</hi> 11 (2017), 55-75.</bibl>
                <bibl>Carbajosa, I., “<hi rend="italic">Samuel–Kings</hi>, Secondary Translations:
                    Late Syriac Translations,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Hebrew Bible, Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi>
                    (Textual History of the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 415-419.</bibl>
                <bibl>Carlson, S.C., “Eschatological Viticulture in <hi rend="italic">1 Enoch</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">2 Baruch</hi>, and the Presbyters of Papias,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 71:1 (2017), 37-58.</bibl>
                <bibl>Carlson, T.A., “Syriac Christology and Christian Community in the
                    Fifteenth-Century Church of the East,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K.
                    Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    265-276.</bibl>
                <bibl>Carpentieri, N., “On the Meaning of <hi rend="italic">Birsām</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Sirsām</hi>: A Survey of the Arabic Commentaries on the
                    Hippocratic <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Mélanges de
                        l’Institut Dominicaine des Études Orientales du Caire</hi> 32 (2017),
                    81-92.</bibl>
                <bibl>Carpentieri, N., and Mimura, T., “Arabic Commentaries on the Hippocratic <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms</hi>, vi.11: A Medieval Medical Debate on
                        Phrenitis,”<hi rend="italic">Oriens</hi> 45:1-2 (2017), 176-202.</bibl>
                <bibl>Caseau, B., and Fayant, M.-C., “Le renouveau du culte des Stylites syriens aux
                        X<hi rend="sup">e</hi> et XI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècles? La Vie abrégée de
                    Syméon Stylite le Jeune (BHG 1691C),” in: B. Flusin and J.-C. Cheynet (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Autour du Premier humanisme byzantin &amp; des Cinq études
                        sur le XI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle, quarante ans après Paul Lemerle</hi>
                    (Travaux et Mémoires 21.2; Paris: Association des amis du Centre d’histoire et
                    civilisation de Byzance, 2017), 701-732.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cerbelaud, D., “Les Pères syriens et les juifs,” in: J.-M. Auwers, R. Burnet
                    and D. Luciani (eds.), <hi rend="italic">L’antijudaïsme des Pères. Mythe et/ou
                        réalité?</hi> (Théologie historique 125; Paris: Beauchesne, 2017),
                    183-196.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cetrez, Ö.A., “The Psychological Legacy of the Sayfo: An Inter-Generational
                    Transmission of Fear and Distrust,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 178-204.</bibl>
                <bibl>Chialà, S., “Prayer and the Body according to Isaac of Nineveh,” in: B.
                    Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in
                        Eastern Christianities, 5th to 11th Centuries</hi> (London / New York:
                    Routledge, 2017), 34-43.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “St Ephrem the Syrian as a Reader of Holy Scrip-ture: A Witness of
                    Plurality in Biblical Hermeneutics,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox
                        Patriarchal Journal</hi> 55 (2017), 39-49.</bibl>
                <bibl>Childers, J.W., “Constructing the Syriac Chrysostom: The Transformation of a
                    Greek Orator into a Native Syriac Speaker,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp,
                    K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    47-57.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. ““You Have Found What You Seek”: The Form and Function of a Sixth-Century
                    Divinatory Bible in Syriac,” in: L.I. Lied and H. Lundhaug (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Snapshots of Evolving Traditions: Jewish and Christian
                        Manuscript Culture, Textual Fluidity, and New Philology</hi> (Texte und
                    Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 175; Berlin /
                    Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 242-271.</bibl>
                <bibl>Comfort, A., “Fortresses of the Tur Abdin and the Confrontation between Rome
                    and Persia,” <hi rend="italic">Anatolian Studies</hi> 67 (2017), 181-229.</bibl>
                <bibl>Conway-Jones, A., “An Ambiguous Type: The Figure of Aaron Interpreted by
                    Gregory of Nyssa and Ephrem the Syrian,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Patristica</hi> 95 (2017), 389-398.</bibl>
                <bibl>Corke-Webster, J., “A Man for the Times: Jesus and the Abgar Correspondence in
                    Eusebius of Caesarea’s <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Harvard Theological Review</hi> 110:4 (2017), 563-587.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cowe, S.P., “Doctrinal Union or Agreement to Disagree? Armenians and Syrians
                    at the Synod of Manazkert (726 CE),” in: P.S. Avetisyan and Y.H. Grekyan (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Bridging Times and Spaces: Papers in Ancient Near Eastern,
                        Mediterranean and Armenian Studies Honouring Gregory E. Areshian on the
                        Occasion of His Sixty-Fifth Birthday</hi> (Oxford: Archaeopress, 2017),
                    61-84.</bibl>
                <bibl>Crosignani, C., “The Influence of Demons on the Human Mind according to
                    Athenagoras and Tatian,” in: S. Bhayro and C. Rider (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Demons and Illness from Antiquity to the Early-Modern Period</hi> (Magical
                    and Religious Literature of Late Antiquity 5; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017),
                    175-191.</bibl>
                <bibl>Daiber, H., “The Syriac Tradition in the Early Islamic Era,” in: U. Rudolph,
                    R. Hansberger and P. Adamson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophy in the Islamic
                        World. Volume 1: 8th–10th Centuries</hi> (Handbook of Oriental Studies.
                    Section 1: The Near and Middle East 115.1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017),
                    74-94.</bibl>
                <bibl>Danacıoğlu Tamur, E., “Asahel Grant and the Nestorian Mission,” in: H.G.B.
                    Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First International
                        Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living
                        Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23;
                    Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 313-326.</bibl>
                <bibl>Davis, S.J., “Cataloguing the Coptic and Arabic Manuscripts in the Monastery
                    of the Syrians: A Preliminary Report,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi>
                    92 (2017), 179-186.</bibl>
                <bibl>de Bruyn, T.S., “Jesus’ Correspondence with Abgar,” in: Idem, <hi rend="italic">Making Amulets Christian: Artefacts, Scribes, and
                        Contexts</hi> (Oxford Early Christian Studies; Oxford: Oxford University
                    Press, 2017), 153-157.</bibl>
                <bibl>de Dieuleveult, M., “L’exégèse de la faute de David (<hi rend="italic">2Règnes</hi> 11-12): Jean Chrysostome et Théodoret de Cyr,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017), 95-102.</bibl>
                <bibl>de Ghantuz Cubbe, M., “Unité et trinité de Dieu dans la tradition antiochienne
                    et syriaque jusqu’à l’avènement de le l’Islam: quelques linéaments,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 137-161.</bibl>
                <bibl>de Navascués, P., “Paul de Samosate,” in: B. Pouderon (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la littérature grecque chrétienne des origines à 451, T. III:
                        De Clément d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi> (L’Âne d’or 65; Paris: Les
                    Belles Lettres, 2017), 593-602.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Slavery and Asceticism in John of Ephesus’ <hi rend="italic">Lives of
                        the Eastern Saints</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Scrinium</hi> 13 (2017),
                    84-113.</bibl>
                <bibl>Debié, M., ““La science est commune”: sources syriaques et culture grecque en
                    Syrie-Mésopotamie par-delà les siècles obscurs byzantins,” <hi rend="italic">Travaux et Mémoires</hi> 21:2 (2017), 87-127.</bibl>
                <bibl>Demir, M., and Keçiş, M., “Nisibis at the Border of Romans and Sasanians
                    between the Third and Fifth Centuries AD,” <hi rend="italic">Tarih Araştırmaları
                        Dergisi</hi> 36 [62] (2017), 1-29.</bibl>
                <bibl>den Biesen, K., “‘A Drop of Salvation’: Ephrem the Syrian on the Eucharist,”
                    in: D. Hellholm and D. Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist – Its
                        Origins and Contexts: Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table Fellowship in Late
                        Antiquity, Early Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume 2: Patristic
                        Traditions, Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen
                    Testament 376; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1121-1142.</bibl>
                <bibl>Desreumaux, A., “De quelques pièces du dossier syriaque sur Pilate: de la
                    correspondance byzantine à la correspon-dance médiévale,” in: A. van den
                    Kerchove and L.G. Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose et
                        manichéisme: Entre les oasis d’Égypte et la Route de la Soie. Hommage à
                        Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’École des hautes études, Sciences
                    religieuses 176; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 619-634.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Mgr. Petros Yousif (4 July 1936 – 17 December 2015), From Karemlesh to
                    Paris,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017),
                    3-23.</bibl>
                <bibl>Di Rienzo, A., “Risemantizzare la memoria. Il conflitto tra Papa bar Aggai e
                    Miles di Susa nell’ottica del catholicos di Seleucia,” <hi rend="italic">Cristianesimo nella storia</hi> 38:3 (2017), 637-654.</bibl>
                <bibl>Diamadis, P., “Controversies around Governmental and Parliamentary Recognition
                    of the Armenian, Hellenic and Assyrian Genocides,” in: S. Totten, H. Theriault
                    and E. von Joeden-Forgey (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Controversies in the Field of
                        Genocide Studies</hi> (Genocide: A Critical Bibliographic Review 11; New
                    Brunswick: Transaction Publishers, 2017), 91-152.</bibl>
                <bibl>Diez, M., “The Profession of Monotheism by Elias of Nisibis: An Edition and
                    Translation of the Fifth Session of the <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                    al-majālis</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations</hi>
                    28:4 (2017), 493-514.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dinno, K., “The Synods and Canons in the Syrian (Syriac) Orthodox Church in
                    the Second Millennium – An Overview,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian
                        Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 17 (2017), 21-36.</bibl>
                <bibl>Donabed, S.G., “Neither “Syriac-Speaking” nor “Syrian Orthodox Christians”:
                    Harput Assyrians in the United States as a Model for Ethnic Self-Categorization
                    and Expression,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 359-369.</bibl>
                <bibl>Donef, R., “Sayfo and Denialism: A New Field of Activity for Agents of the
                    Turkish Republic,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 205-218.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dorandi, T., and Marjani, I., “La tradizione siriaca e araba delle cosiddette
                        <hi rend="italic">Divisiones Aristoteleae</hi>: Analisi e commento della
                    versione siriaca (ed. Brock) e delle due traduzioni arabe (ed.
                    Kellermann-Rost),” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017),
                    1-55.</bibl>
                <bibl>Duca, V., “Pride in the Thought of Isaac of Nineveh,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Patristica</hi> 92 (2017), 137-148.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dudzik, P., “Tatian the Assyrian and Greek Rhetoric: Homer’s Heroes Agamemnon,
                    Nestor and Thersites in Tatian’s <hi rend="italic">Oratio ad Graecos</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 93 (2017), 179-190.</bibl>
                <bibl>Duncan, P.A., “The Case for Tolerance in the Early Christian
                    (Pseudo-Clementine) Novel,” in: M. Bar-Asher Siegal, W. Grünstäudl and M.
                    Thiessen (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Perceiving the Other in Ancient Judaism and
                        Early Christianity</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen
                    Testament 394; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 83-94.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ebeid, B., “Christology and Deification in the Church of the East: Mar
                    Gewargis I, His Synod and His Letter to Mina as a Polemic against
                    Martyrius-Sahdona,” Cristianesimo nella storia 38:3 (2017), 729-784.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ebied, R.Y., “A Short Version in Syriac and Arabic of the <hi rend="italic">Gloria in Excelsis Deo</hi>, with Additions by St. Athanasius the Great,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Collectanea Christiana Orientalia</hi> 14 (2017),
                    65-71.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ekenberg, A., “The Eucharist in Early Church Orders,” in: D. Hellholm and D.
                    Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist – Its Origins and Contexts:
                        Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table Fellowship in Late Antiquity, Early
                        Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume 2: Patristic Traditions,
                        Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testament 376;
                    Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1011-1060.</bibl>
                <bibl>Endress, G., “Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s Arabic Version and Commen-tary of Aristotle’s
                        <hi rend="italic">De Caelo</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017), 213-275.</bibl>
                <bibl>Endress, G., and Ferrari, C., “The Baghdad Aristotelians,” in: U. Rudolph, R.
                    Hansberger and P. Adamson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophy in the Islamic
                        World. Volume 1: 8th–10th Centuries</hi> (Handbook of Oriental Studies.
                    Section 1: The Near and Middle East 115.1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017),
                    421-525.</bibl>
                <bibl>Erdman, M., “From Language to Patois and Back Again: Syriac Influences on
                    Arabic in Mont Liban during the 16th to 19th Centuries,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal Journal</hi> (2017), 1-19.</bibl>
                <bibl>Faivre, A., “La <hi rend="italic">Constitution ecclésiastique des
                    apôtres</hi>,” in: B. Pouderon (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la
                        littérature grecque chrétienne des origines à 451, T. III: De Clément
                        d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi> (L’Âne d’or 65; Paris: Les Belles
                    Lettres, 2017), 511-519.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “La <hi rend="italic">Didascalie des apôtres</hi>,” in: B. Pouderon
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la littérature grecque chrétienne des
                        origines à 451, T. III: De Clément d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi>
                    (L’Âne d’or 65; Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2017), 495-510.</bibl>
                <bibl>Falla, T.C., “What to Do About Citing Ambiguity in a Corpus-Specific Lexicon,”
                    in: T. Li and K. Dyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient Manuscripts to
                        Modern Dictionaries: Select Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and Greek</hi>
                    (Perspectives on Linguistics and Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                    Gorgias Press, 2017), 9-60.</bibl>
                <bibl>Farina, M., “The Syro-Arabic Glosses to Barhebraeus’ <hi rend="italic">Metrical Grammar</hi>,” in: P. Molinelli (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Language
                        and Identity in Multilingual Mediterranean Settings: Challenges for
                        Historical Sociolinguistics</hi> (Trends in Linguistics. Studies and
                    Monographs 310; Berlin / New York: Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 157-170.</bibl>
                <bibl>Fathi, J., “Ibn al-Ghurayr,” in: D.R. Thomas and J. Chesworth (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christian-Muslim Relations: A Bibliographical History. Volume
                        10: Ottoman and Safavid Empires (1600–1700)</hi> (History of
                    Christian-Muslim Relations 32; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 299-307.</bibl>
                <bibl>Féghali, P., “Le livre des Chroniques dans la Peshitta, traduction ou targum,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 163-174.</bibl>
                <bibl>Fiori, E., “A Hitherto Unknown Medical Fragment in Syriac: Evidence of Recipes
                    and Prescriptions from the Qubbet el-Ḫazne of the Umayyad Mosque in Damascus,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017), 200-229.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Il nous e l’altare: la teologia mistica di Dionigi Areopagita al di là
                    di Evagrio,” in: I. Adinolfi, G. Gaeta and A. Lavagetto (eds.), <hi rend="italic">L’anti-Babele: Sulla mistica degli antichi e dei moderni</hi>
                    (Genova: Il Melangolo, 2017), 193-224.</bibl>
                <bibl>Forness, P.M., “New Textual Evidence for Jacob of Serugh’s Letters: An
                    Analysis and Collation of Five Monastic Miscellanies,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye:
                        Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017), 51-128.</bibl>
                <bibl>French, T.E., “Just Deserts: Origen’s Lingering Influence on Divine Justice in
                    the Hagiographies of John of Ephesus,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi>
                    92 (2017), 105-112.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gaunt, D., “Sayfo Genocide: The Culmination of an Anatolian Culture of
                    Violence,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let
                        Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and
                        Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New
                    York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 54-69.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gaunt, D., Atto, N., and Barthoma, S.O., “Introduction: Contextualizing the
                    Sayfo in the First World War,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 1-32.</bibl>
                <bibl>Géhin, P., “Saint Jean Chrysostome dans les manuscrits syriaques du Sinaï,”
                    in: F.P. Barone, C. Macé and P. Ubierna (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philologie,
                        herméneutique et histoire des textes entre Orient et Occident. Mélanges en
                        hommage à Sever J. Voicu</hi> (Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 73;
                    Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 867-893.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Un cas insolite d’allographie: la litanie diaconale grecque en écriture
                    syriaque sogdienne du ms. <hi rend="italic">Leiden Oriental</hi> 14236,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 130:3-4 (2017), 279-299.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gelston, A., “The Post-Sanctus in the East Syrian Anaphoras,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92 (2017), 77-82.</bibl>
                <bibl>Georgis, M., “Nation and Identity Construction in Modern Iraq: (Re)Inserting
                    the Assyrians,” in: S. Saffari, R. Akhbari, K. Abdolmaleki and E. Hamdon (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Unsettling Colonial Modernity in Islamicate Contexts</hi>
                    (Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2017), 67-87.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ghobrial, J.-P., “Migration from Within and Without: In the Footsteps of
                    Eastern Christians in the Early Modern World,” <hi rend="italic">Transactions of
                        the Royal Historical Society</hi> 27 (2017), 153-173.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gibson, N.P., Michelson, D.A., and Schwartz, D.L., “From Manuscript Catalogues
                    to a Handbook of Syriac Literature: Modeling an Infrastructure for Syriaca.org,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal of Data Mining and Digital Humanities</hi> May 30
                    (2017), 1-15.</bibl>
                <bibl>Given, J.G., ““Finding” the <hi rend="italic">Gospel of Thomas</hi> in
                    Edessa,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 25:4 (2017),
                    501-530.</bibl>
                <bibl>Goldberg, M., “New Syriac Edition and Translation of Theodore of Mopsuestia’s
                    Reconstructed <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Paul’s Minor Epistles</hi>:
                    Fragments Collected from MS (<hi rend="italic">olim</hi>) <hi rend="italic">Diyarbakir 22</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017),
                    293-300.</bibl>
                <bibl>Goldstein, B.Y., “The Jewish Recension of a Syriac Version of Aesop’s Fables,”
                    in: T. Li and K. Dyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient Manuscripts to
                        Modern Dictionaries: Select Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and Greek</hi>
                    (Perspectives on Linguistics and Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                    Gorgias Press, 2017), 61-76.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gonnet, D., “Les citations patristiques syriaques du Nouveau Testament,” in:
                    J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi>
                    (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 219-230.</bibl>
                <bibl>———.““Car la sagesse est Dieu lui-même”: la sagesse de Dieu chez Isaac le
                    Syrien,” in: T. Hainthaler, F. Mali, G. Emmenegger and M.L. Ostermann (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Sophia: The Wisdom of God – die Weisheit Gottes. Forscher
                        aus dem Osten und Westen Europas an den Quellen des gemeinsamen Glaubens:
                        Studientagung Varna, 27. September – 3. Oktober 2015 “Sophia, the Wisdom of
                        God”</hi> (Pro Oriente 40, Wiener patristische Tagungen 7; Innsbruck-Wien:
                    Tyrolia, 2017), 335-346.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Les Pères syriaques et le <hi rend="italic">Sensus fidelium</hi>,” in:
                    M.-L. Chaieb (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les Pères de l’Eglise à l’écoute du Peuple
                        de Dieu. Sensus fidelium et discours autorisés durant l’Antiquité tardive,
                        Colloque de Patristique de La Rochelle (9-11 octobre 2015)</hi> (La
                    Rochelle: CaritasPatrum, 2017), 281-290.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gray, A.M., “The People, Not the Peoples: The Talmud Bavli’s “Charitable”
                    Contribution to the Jewish-Christian Conversation in Mesopotamia,” <hi rend="italic">Review of Rabbinic Judaism</hi> 20:2 (2017), 137-167.</bibl>
                <bibl>Griffin, C.W., “Vessel of Wrath: Judas Iscariot in Cyrillona and Early Syriac
                    Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017), 33-50.</bibl>
                <bibl>Griffith, S.H., “The Poetics of Scriptural Reasoning: Syriac <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê </hi>at Work,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017),
                    5-24.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “St. Ephraem the Syrian, the Quran, and the Grapevines of Paradise: An
                    Essay in Comparative Eschatology” in: S. Günther and T. Lawson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Roads to Paradise: Eschatology and Concepts of the Hereafter
                        in Islam</hi>. 2 vols. (Islamic History and Civilization 136.1-2; Leiden /
                    Boston: Brill, 2017), vol. 2, 781-805.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gross, S., “When the Jews Greeted Ali: Sherira Gaon’s Epistle in Light of
                    Arabic and Syriac Historiography,” <hi rend="italic">Jewish Studies
                        Quarterly</hi> 24:2 (2017), 122-144.</bibl>
                <bibl>Guevin, B.M., “Dialogue between Death and the Devil in Saint Ephrem the Syrian
                    and Saint Romanos the Melodist,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92
                    (2017), 113-118.</bibl>
                <bibl>Haelewyck, J.-C., “<hi rend="italic">Histoire de Zosime sur la vie des
                        Bienheureux Réchabites</hi>: les trois recensions syriaques. Édition de la
                    version résumé,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017),
                    175-194.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Les versions syriaques des <hi rend="italic">Discours </hi>de Grégoire
                    de Nazianze: un processus continu de revision,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de
                        l’Académie Belge pour l’Etude des Langues Anciennes et Orientales</hi> 6
                    (2017), 75-124.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Les Vieilles versions syriaques des Évangiles,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques
                    14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 67-113.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hainthaler, T., “<hi rend="italic">Colossians</hi> 1:15 in the Christological
                    Reflection of East Syrian Authors,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92
                    (2017), 165-174.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hansbury, M.T., “Patterns of Divine Mercy in Jacob of Serugh and Isaac the
                    Syrian,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 195-211.</bibl>
                <bibl>Harrak, A., “The Code of Law of Simeon, Bishop of Rev-Ardashir: Presentation
                    and Translation,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac
                        Studies</hi> 17 (2017), 49-68.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “A Vernacular Aramaic Statement from the 10th Century <hi rend="italic">History of Mosul</hi> by al-Azdī,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of
                        Syriac Studies</hi> 20:2 (2017), 365-373.</bibl>
                <bibl>Harvey, S.A., “The Poet’s Prayer: Invocational Prayers in the <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> of Jacob of Sarug,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Patristica</hi> 78 (2017), 51-60.</bibl>
                <bibl>Havrylyk, I., “L’insegnamento “ereticale” sulla visione di Dio nelle opere di
                    Giuseppe Hazzāyā, mistico siro-orientale del secolo VIII,” <hi rend="italic">Vox
                        Patrum</hi> 38 [68] (2017), 535-549.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hayakawa, H., Mitsuma, Y., Fujiwara, Y., Kawamura, A.D., Kataoka, R., Ebihara,
                    Y., Kosaka, S., Iwahashi, K., Tamazawa, H., and Isobe, H., “The Earliest
                    Drawings of Datable Auroras and a Two-Tail Comet from the Syriac Chronicle of
                    Zūqnīn,” <hi rend="italic">Publications of the Astronomical Society of
                        Japan</hi> 69:2 (2017), 1-15.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hayes, A.J., “The Manuscripts and Themes of Jacob of Serugh’s <hi rend="italic">Mêmrâ</hi> ‘On the Adultery of the Congregation’,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017), 61-72.</bibl>
                <bibl>Heal, K.S., “Catalogues and the Poetics of Syriac Manuscript Cultures,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:2 (2017),
                    375-417.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Construal and Construction of Genesis in Early Syriac Sermons,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017), 25-32.</bibl>
                <bibl>Healey, J.F., “Syriac before Christianity: Epigraphic Research in South-East
                    Turkey,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 1-12.</bibl>
                <bibl>Heide, M., “Die syrische Apokalypse oder Offenbarung an Johannes: Kritische
                    Edition der harklensischen Textzeugen,” in: M. Sigismund and D. Müller (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Studien zum Text der Apokalypse II</hi> (Arbeiten zur
                    neutestamentlichen Textforschung 50; Berlin / Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017),
                    81-187.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hellot-Bellier, F., “The Resistance of Urmia Assyrians to Violence at the
                    Beginning of the Twentieth Century,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 70-99.</bibl>
                <bibl>Herren, M.W., “The <hi rend="italic">Revelationes </hi>of Pseudo-Methodius in
                    the Eighth Century,” in: G. Guldentops, C. Laes and G. Partoens (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Felici curiositate. Studies in Latin Literature and Textual
                        Criticism from Antiquity to the Twentieth Century in Honour of Rita
                        Beyers</hi> (Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 72; Turnhout: Brepols,
                    2017), 409-418.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hjälm, M.L., “The Major Prophets in Arabic: The Authorship of Pethiōn
                    Revisited in Light of New Findings,” in: M.L. Hjälm (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Senses of Scriptures, Treasures of Tradition: The Bible in Arabic among
                        Jews, Christians and Muslims</hi> (Biblia Arabica 5; Leiden / Boston: Brill,
                    2017), 448-483.</bibl>
                <bibl>Horn, C.B., “Apocrypha on Jesus’ Life in the Early Islamic Milieu: From Syriac
                    into Arabic,” in: M.L. Hjälm (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Senses of Scriptures,
                        Treasures of Tradition: The Bible in Arabic among Jews, Christians and
                        Muslims</hi> (Biblia Arabica 5; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 58-78.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hughes, E.E., “When the Nation is Under Threat: The Assyrian and
                    Chaldean-American Diaspora and the Complicated Politics of Refugee
                    Resettlement,” <hi rend="italic">St Antony’s International Review</hi> 12:2
                    (2017), 44-65.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H., “Un cours sur la syllogistique d’Aristote à l’époque
                    tardo-antique: le commentaire syriaque de Proba (VI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle)
                    sur les <hi rend="italic">Premiers Analytiques</hi>. Édition et traduction du
                    texte, avec introduction et commentaire,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017), 105-170.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hunter, E.C.D., “Syriac Manuscripts from Turfan: Public Worship and Private
                    Devotion,” in: T. Li and K. Dyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient
                        Manuscripts to Modern Dictionaries: Select Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and
                        Greek</hi> (Perspectives on Linguistics and Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway,
                    New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017), 77-96.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ioan, O., “Das Kirchenverständnis der Kirche des Ostens im 7. Jahrhundert,”
                    in: P. Gemeinhardt (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Was ist Kirche in der Spätantike?
                        Publikation der Tagung der Patristischen Arbeitsgemeinschaft in Duderstadt
                        und Göttingen (02.-05.01.2015)</hi> (Patristic Studies 14; Leuven: Peeters,
                    2017), 193-206.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Die Weisheit in der ostsyrischen Mystik,” in: T. Hainthaler, F. Mali, G.
                    Emmenegger and M.L. Ostermann (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sophia: The Wisdom of
                        God – die Weisheit Gottes. Forscher aus dem Osten und Westen Europas an den
                        Quellen des gemeinsamen Glaubens: Studientagung Varna, 27. September – 3.
                        Oktober 2015 “Sophia, the Wisdom of God”</hi> (Pro Oriente 40, Wiener
                    patristische Tagungen 7; Innsbruck-Wien: Tyrolia, 2017), 323-334.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jamali, N., “The Book VI of Īšō‘-bokht’s Corpus Juris and the Emergence of
                    Procedural Laws in the Church of the East,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the
                        Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 17 (2017), 37-48.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jarjour, T., “Local Sources and the Limits of Music Scholarship: The Case of
                    Syriac Chant,” <hi rend="italic">Música em Contexto</hi> 1 (2017),
                    111-141.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Safeguarding Tradition and the Authority of Representation,” in: S.
                    Ziegler, I. Åkesson, G. Lechleitner and S. Sardo (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Historical Sources of Ethnomusicology in Contemporary
                    Debate</hi>(Newcastle: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2017), 249-267.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Syriac Chant as Music in Culture: A New Approach,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 17 (2017),
                    77-88.</bibl>
                <bibl>Johnson, N., “Anger Issues: Mark 1.41 in Ephrem the Syrian, the Old Latin
                    Gospels and Codex Bezae,” <hi rend="italic">New Testament Studies</hi> 63:2
                    (2017), 183-202.</bibl>
                <bibl>Johnson, S.F., “Biblical Historiography in Verse Exegesis: Jacob of Sarug on
                    Elijah and Elisha,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017),
                    99-106.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Silk Road Christians and the Translation of Culture in Tang China,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Church History</hi> 53 (2017), 15-38.</bibl>
                <bibl>Joosten, J., “Language and Textual History of Syriac Ben Sira,” in: G. Karner,
                    F. Ueberschaer and B.M. Zapff (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Texts and Contexts of
                        the Book of Sirach / Texte und Kontexte des Sirachbuches</hi> (Septuagint
                    and Cognate Studies 66; Atlanta, Georgia: SBL Press, 2017), 189-198.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Le <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron </hi>syriaque,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck
                    (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques
                    14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 55-66.</bibl>
                <bibl>Josephson, J., “The Pahlavi Psalter as a Translation,” in: E. Morano, E.
                    Provasi and A.V. Rossi (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Philologica Iranica:
                        Gherardo Gnoli Memorial Volume</hi> (Serie Orientale Roma, Nuova Serie 5;
                    Roma: Scienze e Lettere, 2017), 187-198.</bibl>
                <bibl>Juckel, A.K., “La Peshitta du Nouveau Testament (<hi rend="italic">Corpus
                        Paulinum</hi>): histoire du texte et histoire de la transmission,” in: J.-C.
                    Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études
                    syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 115-147.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “La version harqléenne du Nouveau Testament: forme, intention,
                    tradition,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en
                        syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017),
                    149-180.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jurasz, I., “Éphrem le Syrien, lecteur du Prologue de Jean,” in: M. Stavrou
                    and J. van Rossum (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Écriture et tradition chez les Pères
                        de l’Église</hi> (Cahiers de Biblia Patristica 17; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    73-91.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Éphrem, Bardesane et Albinus sur les incorporels. Une confrontation
                    entre le platonisme et le stoïcisme en milieu syriaque,” <hi rend="italic">Philosophie antique</hi> 17 (2017), 169-204.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “L’image de Dieu dans la tradition syriaque: monophysisme et
                    iconoclasme,” in: K. Mitalaitė and A. Vasiliu (eds.), <hi rend="italic">L’icône
                        dans la pensée et dans l’art: Constitutions, contestations, réinventions de
                        la notion d’image divine en contexte chrétien</hi> (Byzantioς 10; Turnhout:
                    Brepols, 2017), 111-152.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kalantzis, G., “Passibility, Tentability, and the Divine <hi rend="italic">Οὐσία</hi> in the Debate between Cyril and Nestorius,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017), 249-256.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kaplan, A., “Calligraphy in the Dioscoros Theodoros Lectionary,” in: H.G.B.
                    Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First International
                        Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living
                        Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23;
                    Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 231-242.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kaufhold, H., “Die syrischen Fragmente,” in: W. Kinzig and T. Brggemann
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Kyrill von Alexandrien, Werke. Erster Band: “Gegen
                        Julian”, Teil 2: Buch 6–10 und Fragmente</hi> (Die Griechischen Christlichen
                    Schriftsteller der ersten Jahrhunderte, Neue Folge 21; Berlin / Boston: Walter
                    de Gruyter, 2017), 821-895.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kermeli, E., “Christian Communities under the Ottomans in the 17th Century,”
                    in: D.R. Thomas and J. Chesworth (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christian-Muslim
                        Relations: A Bibliographical History. Volume 10: Ottoman and Safavid Empires
                        (1600–1700)</hi> (History of Christian-Muslim Relations 32; Leiden / Boston:
                    Brill, 2017), 35-42.</bibl>
                <bibl>Keryo, B., “Enjeux et défis de la traduction des textes anciens. La traduction
                    en français du texte de saint Éphrem sur la visite de Jonas à Ninive,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 213-224.</bibl>
                <bibl>Keser-Kayaalp, E., “The Monastery of Mor Barṣawmo in the Ṭur ‘Abdin: Artistic
                    Continuities and Encounters,” in: T. Papacostas and M. Parani (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Discipuli dona ferentes: Glimpses of Byzantium in Honour of
                        Marlia Mundell Mango</hi> (Byzantioς 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    261-290.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kessel, G., “Field Notes on Syriac Manuscripts I: Two Medical Manuscripts
                    Digitized by the Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript Library,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:2 (2017), 419-434.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Syriac Ascetic and Mystical Literature: An Update (2011-2017),” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 20:2 (2017),
                    435-488.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “A Syriac Medical <hi rend="italic">Kunnāšā </hi>of Īšō‘ bar ‘Alī (9th
                    c.): First Soundings,” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of the Islamicate
                        World</hi> 5:3 (2017), 228-251.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kessel, G., and Seleznyov, N.N., “Bibliography of Syriac and Christian Arabic
                    Studies in Russian, 2016,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac
                        Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017), 317-331.</bibl>
                <bibl>Khalifé-Hachem, É., ““Ktobō d’Theologia” de Mar Basilius Šem‘ūn Man‘amoyō,
                    Maphrian de Ṭūr ‘Abdīn (m. 1740) (Conférence inaugurale),” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 25-32.</bibl>
                <bibl>Khayyat, N., “L’Irak spirituel. Première partie,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                        l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 225-235.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kitchen, R.A., “Three Young Men Redux: The Fiery Furnace in Jacob of Sarug and
                    Narsai,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017), 73-84.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Trying to Fix What is Broken in a Broken Age: Syrian Orthodox Synodical
                    Canons (628–896),” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac
                        Studies</hi> 17 (2017), 3-20.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kleinkopf, K., “A Landscape of Bodies: Exploring the Role of Ascetics in
                    Theodoret’s <hi rend="italic">Historia Religiosa</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Patristica</hi> 96 (2017), 283-292.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kosiński, R., “The Date of the Martyrdom of Simeon bar Sabba’e and the
                    Persecution of Christians in Persia under Shapur II,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Antikes Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity</hi>
                    21:3 (2017), 496-519.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Once again on the Date of the Martyrdom of Simeon bar Sabba’e and the
                    Persecution of Christians in Persia under Shapur II,” <hi rend="italic">Zeszyty
                        Naukowe Uniwersytetu Jagiellońskiego, Prace Historyczne</hi> 144:1 (2017),
                    1-24 [in Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>Kozah, M., “The Syriac Writers of Beth Qaṭraye in the Seventh Century: An
                    Overview of the Current State of Studies,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp,
                    K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    59-79.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kurek, J., “Saint Ephrem the Syrian: Sacred Time and Historical Time Seen from
                    a Crossroads of Cultures,” <hi rend="italic">Śląskie Studia
                        Historyczno-Teologiczne</hi> 50:1 (2017), 19-28.</bibl>
                <bibl>Landau, B.C., “Under the Influence (of the Magi): Did Hallucinogens Play a
                    Role in the Inspired Composition of the Pseudepigraphic <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>?,” in: T. Burke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Fakes,
                        Forgeries, and Fictions: Writing Ancient and Modern Christian Apocrypha.
                        Proceedings from the 2015 York University Christian Apocrypha Symposium</hi>
                    (Eugene, Oregon: Cascade Books, 2017), 79-94.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lattke, M., “Einsetzung und Vollzug der christlichen Paschafeier bei
                    Aphrahat,” in: D. Hellholm and D. Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist
                        – Its Origins and Contexts: Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table Fellowship in
                        Late Antiquity, Early Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume 2: Patristic
                        Traditions, Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen
                    Testament 376; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1091-1119.</bibl>
                <bibl>Le Boulluec, A., “Mani déguisé en monophysite,” in: A. van den Kerchove and
                    L.G. Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose et manichéisme: Entre les
                        oasis d’Égypte et la Route de la Soie. Hommage à Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi>
                    (Bibliothèque de l’École des hautes études, Sciences religieuses 176; Turnhout:
                    Brepols, 2017), 333-348.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lied, L.I., “Between “Text Witness” and “Text on the Page”: Trajectories in
                    the History of Editing the Epistle of Baruch,” in: L.I. Lied and H. Lundhaug
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Snapshots of Evolving Traditions: Jewish and Christian
                        Manuscript Culture, Textual Fluidity, and New Philology</hi> (Texte und
                    Unter-suchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 175; Berlin /
                    Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 272-296.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lieu, S.N.C., ““In the Name of Jesus”. Observations on the Term “Jesus the
                    Messiah” in Christian and Manichaean Texts from Central Asia,” in: A. van den
                    Kerchove and L.G. Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose et
                        manichéisme: Entre les oasis d’Égypte et la Route de la Soie. Hommage à
                        Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’École des hautes études, Sciences
                    religieuses 176; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 399-412.</bibl>
                <bibl>Loopstra, J.A., “Le Nouveau Testament dans les manuscrits syriaques
                    massorétiques: où en sommes-nous?,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul
                    Geuthner, 2017), 181-201.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Reading the Bible with the Taḥtāyā ḏa-Ṯlāṯā,” in: T. Li and K. Dyer
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient Manuscripts to Modern Dictionaries:
                        Select Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and Greek</hi> (Perspectives on
                    Linguistics and Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press,
                    2017), 109-138.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lorrain, A., “Exégèse et argumentation scripturaire chez Théodoret de Cyr:
                        l’<hi rend="italic">In Romanos</hi>, écho des controverses trinitaires et
                    christologiques des IV<hi rend="sup">e</hi> et V<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècles,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017), 273-282.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lourié, B., “Slavonic Pseudepigrapha, Nubia, and the Syrians,” in: T. Nicklas,
                    C.R. Moss, C. Tuckett and J. Verheyden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Other Side:
                        Apocryphal Perspectives on Ancient Christian “Orthodoxies”</hi> (Novum
                    Testamentum et Orbis Antiquus / Studien zur Umwelt des Neuen Testaments 117;
                    Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 2017), 225-250.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lund, J.A., “<hi rend="italic">Pentateuch</hi>, Primary Translations:
                    Peshitta,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Hebrew Bible,
                        Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi> (Textual History of
                    the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 173-179.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lunn-Rockliffe, S., “The Invention and Demonisation of an Ascetic Heresiarch:
                    Philoxenus of Mabbug on the ‘Messalian’ Adelphius,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        Ecclesiastical History</hi> 68:3 (2017), 455-473.</bibl>
                <bibl>Macabasag, N.Q., “Jacob of Serugh’s <hi rend="italic">memra</hi> on the Star
                    which Appeared to the Magi and on the Slaughter of Infants (Vat. Syr. 118),” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 237-301.</bibl>
                <bibl>Maksymiuk, K., “Las deportaciones masivas de los habitantes de Siria y de
                    Mesopotamia septentrional por Cosroes I (540–542),” in: F. Puell de la Villa and
                    D. García Hernán (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Los efectos de la guerra:
                        desplazamientos de población a lo largo de la historia</hi>(Madrid:
                    Instituto Universitario General Gutiérrez Mellado, 2017), 121-131.</bibl>
                <bibl>Maróth, M., “Die syrische Epistolographie,” in: Team “Turfanforschung” (ed.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Zur lichten Heimat: Studien zu Manichäismus, Iranistik und
                        Zentralasienkunde im Gedenken an Werner Sundermann</hi> (Iranica 25;
                    Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2017), 381-394.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martelli, M., “Alchemy, Medicine and Religion: Zosimus of Panopolis and the
                    Egyptian Priests,” <hi rend="italic">Religion in the Roman Empire</hi> 3:2
                    (2017), 202-220.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Hippocrates in Two Syriac Alchemical Collections,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017), 230-251.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Recipes Ascribed to the Scribe and Prophet Ezra in the Byzantine and
                    Syriac Tradition,” in: L. Lehmhaus and M. Martelli (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Collecting Recipes: Byzantine and Jewish Pharmacology in Dialogue</hi>
                    (Science, Technology, and Medicine in Ancient Cultures 4; Berlin / New York:
                    Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 195-219.</bibl>
                <bibl>Martens, J.W., “The Disability Within: Sexual Desire as Disability in Syriac
                    Christianity,” in: C. Laes (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Disability in Antiquity</hi>
                    (Rewriting Antiquity; London / New York: Routledge, 2017), 376-387.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mathew, S., “The Jewish Ritual in the Liturgy of the Holy Matrimony in the
                    West Syriac Tradition among St. Thomas Christians,” in: V. Ruggieri (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Liturgy from Below: Popular Liturgical Rites in the Eastern
                        Churches</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana &amp; Valore Italiano,
                    2017), 279-303.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mazzucotelli, F., “The Shift of the Syriac Catholic Patriarchate to Mardin:
                    Sources and Voices from Rome,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N.
                    Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural
                        Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu
                        University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi>
                    (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 289-311.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mengozzi, A., “Fighting Beasts: The Pseudo-Callisthenes Account of Alexander
                    the Great in India – From Rhetoric to Narrative and Return,” in: E. Adami, F.
                    Bellino and A. Mengozzi (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Other Worlds and the Narrative
                        Construction of Otherness</hi> (Milano: Mimesis International, 2017),
                    155-181.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mengozzi, A., and Pastore, D., “The Late East-Syriac Genre of the Turgāmā:
                    Forms, Function, Vitality in the Liturgy,” <hi rend="italic">Христианский
                        Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017), 171-186.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menn, S., and Wisnovsky, R., “Yaḥyā ibn ‘Adī and Ibrāhīm ibn ‘Adī: On Whether
                    Body Is a Substance or a Quantity. Introduction, <hi rend="italic">Editio
                        Princeps</hi> and Translation,” <hi rend="italic">Arabic Sciences and
                        Philosophy</hi> 27:1 (2017), 1-74.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menze, V.-L., “The Power of the Eucharist in Early Medieval Syria: Grant for
                    Salvation or Magical Medication?” in: B. Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in Eastern Christianities, 5th to 11th
                        Centuries</hi> (London / New York: Routledge, 2017), 116-131.</bibl>
                <bibl>Metzger, B.M., “Le genre littéraire de la <hi rend="italic">Constitution des
                        apôtres</hi>, de la <hi rend="italic">Didascalie</hi> et de la <hi rend="italic">Tradition apostolique</hi>,” in: B. Pouderon (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la littérature grecque chrétienne des origines à
                        451, T. III: De Clément d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi> (L’Âne d’or
                    65; Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2017), 486-494.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mimura, T., “Comparing Interpretative Notes in the Syriac and Arabic
                    Translations of the Hippocratic <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017), 183-199.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “A Reconsideration of the Authorship of the Syriac Hippocratic <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms</hi>: The Creation of the Syro-Arabic Bilingual
                    Manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms </hi>in the Tradition of Ḥunayn
                    ibn Isḥāq’s Arabic Translation,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens</hi> 45:1-2 (2017),
                    80-104.</bibl>
                <bibl>Minov, S., “Date and Provenance of the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Cave of
                        Treasures</hi>: A Reappraisal,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac
                        Studies</hi> 20:1 (2017), 129-229.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Therapy for Grief and the Practice of Incubation in Early Medieval
                    Palestine: The Evidence of the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Story of a Woman from
                        Jerusalem</hi>,” in: B. Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in Eastern Christianities, 5th to 11th
                        Centuries</hi> (London / New York: Routledge, 2017), 210-238.</bibl>
                <bibl>Moolan, J., “Structure and Theology of East Syriac Initiation Rite,” <hi rend="italic">Malabar Theological Review</hi> 12:1 (2017), 14-45.</bibl>
                <bibl>Moretsi, L.H., “The Translation Technique and the Translation of Verbal Forms
                    in Psalm 84 of the Masoretic Text as Employed by the Peshitta,” <hi rend="italic">In die Skriflig / In Luce Verbi</hi> 51:1 (2017), 1-7.</bibl>
                <bibl>Morris, J.H., “The Figures of Kōho and Li-mi-i, and the Origins of the Case
                    for a Christian Missionary Presence in Tenpyō Era Japan,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society</hi> 27:2 (2017), 313-323.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Rereading the Evidence of the Earliest Christian Communities in East
                    Asia during and prior to the <hi rend="italic">Táng</hi> Period,” <hi rend="italic">Missiology: An International Review</hi> 45:3 (2017),
                    252-264.</bibl>
                <bibl>Morrison, C.E., “<hi rend="italic">Samuel–Kings</hi>, Primary Translations:
                    Peshitta,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Hebrew Bible,
                        Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi> (Textual History of
                    the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 375-382.</bibl>
                <bibl>Moss, Y., “‘A Religion Assembled from Many Religions:’ A Syncretizing
                    Characterization of Islam Attributed to Cyril of Alexandria,” <hi rend="italic">Henoch</hi> 39 (2017), 287-305.</bibl>
                <bibl>Moukarzel, J., “Le portrait des maronites et du Mont-Liban au début du XVII<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle,” in: M. Issa (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le latin des
                        maronites</hi> (Paris: Geuthner, 2017), 157-188.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mroczek, E., “The End of the Psalms in the Dead Sea Scrolls, Greek Codices,
                    and Syriac Manuscripts,” in: L.I. Lied and H. Lundhaug (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Snapshots of Evolving Traditions: Jewish and Christian Manuscript Culture,
                        Textual Fluidity, and New Philology</hi> (Texte und Untersuchungen zur
                    Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 175; Berlin / Boston: Walter de
                    Gruyter, 2017), 297-322.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mugler, J., “Recent Constructions: How the Churches of Classical Baghdad Were
                    Built,” <hi rend="italic">The Muslim World</hi> 107:3 (2017), 496-510.</bibl>
                <bibl>Müller-Kessler, C., “A Trilingual Pharmaceutical Lexical List: Greek – Aramaic
                    – Middle Persian,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 130:1-2 (2017),
                    31-69.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mushayabasa, G., “The Text-Critical Utility of the Peshitta to Ezekiel in View
                    of Recent Research,” <hi rend="italic">Vetus Testamentum</hi> 67:1 (2017),
                    42-58.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nayernouri, T., “Gondeshapur Revisited: What Historical Evidence?” <hi rend="italic">Archives of Iranian Medicine</hi> 20:4 (2017), 254-260.</bibl>
                <bibl>Neary, D., “The Image of Justinianic Orthopraxy in Eastern Monastic
                    Literature,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 25:1
                    (2017), 119-147.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nechaeva, E., “Seven Hellenes and One Christian in the Endless Peace Treaty of
                    532,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Late Antiquity</hi> 4:1 (2017),
                    359-380.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nicák, M., “The Theological Perspective on Adam and the Inclination toward Sin
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rose</hi>,” in: A. Laato and L. Valve
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Adam and Eve Story in Jewish, Christian and Islamic
                        Perspectives</hi> (Studies in the Reception History of the Bible 8; Åbo: Åbo
                    Akademi University, 2017), 185-198.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nicolini-Zani, M., “Il cristianesimo nella Cina dei Tang di fronte alla
                    diversità religiosa,” in: S. Botta, M. Ferrara and A. Saggioro (eds.), <hi rend="italic">La Storia delle religioni e la sfida dei pluralismi. Atti del
                        Convegno della Società Italiana di Storia delle Religioni – Roma, Sapienza,
                        8-9 aprile 2016</hi> (Quaderni di SMSR 18; Brescia: Morcelliana, 2017),
                    239-248.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Da Seleucia a Chang’an: monaci cristiani sulla Via della seta nel primo
                    millennio,” in: E. Giunipero (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Uomini e religioni sulla
                        Via della seta</hi> (Milano: Guerini e Associati, 2017), 61-75.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Xu Guangqi, Disciple of the Luminous Teaching: A Study of the “Stone
                    Inscription for the Church of the Luminous Teaching” (<hi rend="italic">Jingjiaotang beiji</hi>) at Jangzhou, around 1632,” in: B. Hoster, D.
                    Kuhlmann and Z. Wesolowski (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Rooted in Hope:
                        China–Religion–Christianity. Festschrift in Honor of Roman Malek S.V.D. on
                        the Occasion of His 65th Birthday. Volume 1</hi> (Monumenta Serica Monograph
                    Series 68.1; Sankt Augustin: Institut Monumenta Serica, 2017), 155-172.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oegema, A., “The Reception of Isa 40:15 in <hi rend="italic">Liber
                        antiquitatum biblicarum</hi>, <hi rend="italic">2 Baruch</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">4 Ezra</hi>,” in: D. Batovici and K. De Troyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Authoritative Texts and Reception History: Aspects and
                        Approaches</hi> (Biblical Interpretation Series 151; Leiden / Boston: Brill,
                    2017), 94-111.</bibl>
                <bibl>Osawa, T., “The Acceptance of Syrian Christianity by the Ancient Turks in
                    Central Asia in the Sixth and Seventh Centuries, and the Stone Sculptures
                    Reflecting Their Beliefs,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N.
                    Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural
                        Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu
                        University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi>
                    (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 81-106.</bibl>
                <bibl>Özcoşar, I., “Community, Power, Identity: Identity Crisis of the Ottoman
                    Süryanis,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 327-335.</bibl>
                <bibl>Öztemiz den Butter, M., “Cultural Boundaries and Homeland among the Aramaeans
                    (Syriacs),” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 303-314.</bibl>
                <bibl>Paar, C., “The Walking on Water in the Exegesis of Ephrem, Dionysius and the
                    Hagiography of Mar Awgīn,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal
                        Journal</hi> 55 (2017), 21-37.</bibl>
                <bibl>Palmer, A., “The Tombstone, Dated 1246, of Īšō‘yab, Metropolitan of Nisibis: A
                    Celebration of Bilingualism,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N.
                    Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural
                        Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu
                        University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi>
                    (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 131-167.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pang, G.M.Y., “The Reverse Translation of “Daqin Jingjiao Sanwei Mengdu Zan”:
                    A Masterpiece of Chinese Hymn,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43
                    (2017), 315-336.</bibl>
                <bibl>Papoutsakis, M., “<hi rend="italic">United in the Strife That Divided
                        Them</hi>: Narsai and Jacob of Serugh on the Ascension of Christ,” <hi rend="italic">Δελτίο Βιβλικών Μελετών</hi> 32:A-B (2017), 45-77.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pasquesi, P.M., “<hi rend="italic">Qnoma</hi> in Narsai: Anticipating <hi rend="italic">Energeia</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92
                    (2017), 119-128.</bibl>
                <bibl>Patterson, L.E., “Minority Religions in the Sasanian Empire: Suppression,
                    Integration, and Relations with Rome,” in: E.W. Sauer (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Sasanian Persia: Between Rome and the Steppes of Eurasia</hi> (Edinburgh
                    Studies in Ancient Persia; Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2017),
                    181-198.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pavan, M., “Gospel Books and NT Codices in the Fondo Grünwald,” in: V.
                    Ruggieri (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin in the
                        Fondo Grünwald</hi> (Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2017),
                    39-158.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pedersen, N.A., “Observations on the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Giants</hi>
                    from Coptic and Syriac Sources,” in: S.N.C. Lieu, E.C.D. Hunter, E. Morano and
                    N.A. Pedersen (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Manichaeism East and West</hi> (Corpus
                    Fontium Manichaeorum, Analecta Manichaica 1; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    185-202.</bibl>
                <bibl>Penn, M.P., “Know Thy Enemy: The Materialization of Orthodoxy in Syriac
                    Manuscripts,” in: L.I. Lied and H. Lundhaug (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Snapshots
                        of Evolving Traditions: Jewish and Christian Manuscript Culture, Textual
                        Fluidity, and New Philology</hi> (Texte und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte
                    der altchristlichen Literatur 175; Berlin / Boston: Walter de Gruyter, 2017),
                    221-241.</bibl>
                <bibl>Penn, M.P., Howe, N.R., and Crawford, K., “Automated Syriac Script Charts,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92 (2017), 175-178.</bibl>
                <bibl>Peppard, M., “Valentinians on the Euphrates?” in: D. Brakke, S.J. Davis and S.
                    Emmel (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Gnostics to Monastics: Studies in Coptic
                        and Early Christianity in Honor of Bentley Layton</hi> (Orientalia
                    Lovaniensia Analecta 263; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 117-142.</bibl>
                <bibl>Perczel, I., “Theodoret of Cyrrhus: The Main Source of Pseudo-Dionysius’
                    Christology?,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017),
                    351-376.</bibl>
                <bibl>Petrosyan, E., “Manuscript Cairo Syriac 11 as a Gateway to Understanding the
                    17th-Century Socio-Cultural Environment in Diarbakir,” <hi rend="italic">Banber
                        Matenadarani</hi> 24 (2017), 70-76.</bibl>
                <bibl>Phillips, D., “Les canons des Nouveaux Testaments en syriaque,” in: J.-C.
                    Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études
                    syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 7-26.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pirtea, A.C., “Is There an Eclipse Dragon in Manichaeism? Some Problems
                    Concerning the Origin and Function of <hi rend="italic">āṯālyā</hi> in
                    Manichaean Sources,” in: Team “Turfanfor-schung” (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Zur
                        lichten Heimat: Studien zu Manichäismus, Iranistik und Zentralasienkunde im
                        Gedenken an Werner Sundermann</hi> (Iranica 25; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz
                    Verlag, 2017), 535-554.</bibl>
                <bibl>Poirier, P.-H., “Exégèse manichéenne et anti-manichéenne de 2 Corinthiens 4,4
                    chez Titus de Bostra (<hi rend="italic">Contre les manichéens</hi> IV 108),” in:
                    A. van den Kerchove and L.G. Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose
                        et manichéisme: Entre les oasis d’Égypte et la Route de la Soie. Hommage à
                        Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’École des hautes études, Sciences
                    religieuses 176; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 273-286.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Les <hi rend="italic">Actes de Thomas</hi>,” in: B. Pouderon (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la littérature grecque chrétienne des origines à
                        451, T. III: De Clément d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi> (L’Âne d’or
                    65; Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2017), 585-592.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “L’obstruction de l’abîme d’après Titus de Bostra (<hi rend="italic">Contre les manichéens</hi> I, 42). Un aspect de l’eschatologie
                    manichéenne,” in: Team “Turfanforschung” (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Zur lichten
                        Heimat: Studien zu Manichäismus, Iranistik und Zentralasienkunde im Gedenken
                        an Werner Sundermann</hi> (Iranica 25; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag,
                    2017), 555-565.</bibl>
                <bibl>Poorthuis, M.J.H.M., “About Naked Women and Adam’s Body: The Syriac-Christian
                        <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi> as a Source of Islamic
                    Storytelling,” in: P. Geest, M.J.H.M. Poorthuis and E. Rose (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sanctifying Texts, Transforming Rituals: Encounters in
                        Liturgical Studies. Essays in Honour of Gerard A.M. Rouwhorst</hi> (Brill’s
                    Studies in Catholic Theology 5; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 81-102.</bibl>
                <bibl>Popa, C.-S., “Adam’s Instruction on Full Knowledge: An East Syrian Theological
                    Issue According to Narsai and Gīwargīs I,” in: A. Laato and L. Valve (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Adam and Eve Story in Jewish, Christian and Islamic
                        Perspectives</hi> (Studies in the Reception History of the Bible 8; Åbo: Åbo
                    Akademi University, 2017), 171-183.</bibl>
                <bibl>Popkonstantinov, K., “The Letter of King Abgar to Jesus Christ and the
                    Byzantino-Slavic World: According to Sources from Philippi, Genoa, and
                    Bulgaria,” in: E. Bakalova, M. Dimitorva and M.A. Johnson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Medieval Bulgarian Art and Letters in a Byzantine Context</hi>
                    (Sofia: American Research Center in Sofia, 2017), 466-478.</bibl>
                <bibl>Potoczny, M., “Saint or Sinner? The Figure of the Priest-Celebrant in the
                    Pre-Anaphoric Prayers of the Liturgy of the East Syriac Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 337-352.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Word which Becomes an Image in the Tradition of Syriac Christians,” <hi rend="italic">Teologia i Człowiek</hi> 37:1 (2017), 169-188 [in
                    Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>Pouderon, B., “Le Roman Pseudo-clémentin,” in: B. Pouderon (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la littérature grecque chrétienne des origines à
                        451, T. III: De Clément d’Alexandrie à Eusèbe de Césarée</hi> (L’Âne d’or
                    65; Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2017), 561-578.</bibl>
                <bibl>Premat, C., “Who Killed Whom? A Comparison of Political Discussions in France
                    and Sweden about the Genocide of 1915,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the
                        Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War
                    and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 233-254.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pritula, A., “One More Unknown Khāmīs’ Ode in Honor of Bar ‘Ebrōyō,” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017), 187-194.</bibl>
                <bibl>Proverbio, D.V., “On the Phonetic Unpredictability Denoted by Some Old Turkic
                    Texts Written in Syriac Script: Or the Encoding Ambiguity Intrinsic to the
                    Aramaic Writing,” <hi rend="italic">Turkic Languages</hi> 21:1 (2017),
                    115-149.</bibl>
                <bibl>Raby, J., and Brock, S.P., “New Light on Syriac Painting in the Eleventh
                    Century: Re-Dating British Library Or. 3372,” <hi rend="italic">Eastern
                        Christian Art</hi> 10 (2014-2016 [2017]), 33-80.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rambow, G.F., “Theodore vs. the “Arians” and the Parable of Humanity’s
                    Creation: A Syriac Fragment of Theodore of Mopsuestia’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Genesis</hi> 1.26,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early
                        Christian Studies</hi> 25:2 (2017), 231-254.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rassi, S., “Between<hi rend="italic"> ‘Aṣabiyya</hi> and Ecumenism: ‘Abdīshō‘
                    Bar Brīkhā’s Attitudes to Other Christians,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp,
                    K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    169-186.</bibl>
                <bibl>Reller, J., “Patriarch Michael the Syrian’s Views on Islam in the Context of
                    Syriac Historiography and Philosophy,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K.
                    Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    187-207.</bibl>
                <bibl>Renoux, C., “Glanes apocryphales chrétiennes dans des textes arméniens et
                    géorgiens,” in: F.P. Barone, C. Macé and P. Ubierna (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philologie, herméneutique et histoire des textes entre Orient et Occident.
                        Mélanges en hommage à Sever J. Voicu</hi> (Instrumenta Patristica et
                    Mediaevalia 73; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 671-684.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ribolov, S., “The Relationship between Sin and Mortality in the History of
                    Mankind: Insights from Theodore of Mopsuestia’s Theology,” in: E. Bakalova, M.
                    Dimitorva and M.A. Johnson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Medieval Bulgarian Art and
                        Letters in a Byzantine Context</hi> (Sofia: American Research Center in
                    Sofia, 2017), 267-293.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “‘Wisdom of God’ in Theodore of Mopsuestia’s Theology,” in: T.
                    Hainthaler, F. Mali, G. Emmenegger and M.L. Ostermann (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sophia: The Wisdom of God – die Weisheit Gottes. Forscher aus dem Osten und
                        Westen Europas an den Quellen des gemeinsamen Glaubens: Studientagung Varna,
                        27. September – 3. Oktober 2015 “Sophia, the Wisdom of God”</hi> (Pro
                    Oriente 40, Wiener patristische Tagungen 7; Innsbruck-Wien: Tyrolia, 2017),
                    181-202.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rigolio, A., “<hi rend="italic">Erostrophus</hi>, a Syriac Dialogue with
                    Socrates on the Soul,” in: A. Cameron and N. Gaul (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Dialogues and Debates from Late Antiquity to Late Byzantium</hi> (London /
                    New York: Routledge, 2017), 20-31.</bibl>
                <bibl>Robertson, P., “Greco-Roman Ethical-Philosophical Influences in Bardaisan’s
                    “Book of the Laws of Coun-tries”,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi>
                    71:5 (2017), 511-540.</bibl>
                <bibl>Robinson Burke, S.L., “Critical Editions of the Commen-taries of Dionysius bar
                    Ṣalībī on Obadiah, Jonah, and Nahum with Introduction and English Translation,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Collectanea Christiana Orientalia</hi> 14 (2017),
                    1-63.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rouwhorst, G.A.M., “La lecture liturgique du Nouveau Testament dans les
                    Églises syriaques,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau
                        Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner,
                    2017), 203-218.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rouxpetel, C., “A circulação de narrativas hagiográficas entre Oriente e
                    Ocidente,” in: I.S. Teixeira (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Tempo, espaço e texto: a
                        Hagiografia Medieval em perspectiva</hi> (São Leopoldo: Oikos, 2017),
                    139-157.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ruani, F., “John of Dara on Mani: Manichaean Interpre-tations of Genesis 2:17
                    in Syriac,” in: S.N.C. Lieu, E.C.D. Hunter, E. Morano and N.A. Pedersen (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Manichaeism East and West</hi> (Corpus Fontium
                    Manichaeorum, Analecta Manichaica 1; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 203-222.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Preliminary Notes on Edifying Stories in Syriac Hagiographical
                    Collections,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 91 (2017),
                    257-266.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Sur les traces syriaques des manichéens: les réfutations de Moïse bar
                    Kepha (IX<hi rend="sup">e</hi> s.) et de Jacques bar Šakko (XIII<hi rend="sup">e</hi> s.),” in: A. van den Kerchove and L.G. Soares Santoprete (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Gnose et manichéisme: Entre les oasis d’Égypte et la Route de
                        la Soie. Hommage à Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’École des
                    hautes études, Sciences religieuses 176; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    299-332.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ryan, S.D., “<hi rend="italic">Minor Prophets</hi>, Secondary Translations:
                    Late Syriac Translations,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Hebrew Bible, Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi>
                    (Textual History of the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 689-694.</bibl>
                <bibl>Saadi, A.-M., “Ninth Century Syriac Exegete and Apologist: Moshe Bar Kepha’s
                    Commentary on Luke,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi>
                    20:1 (2017), 231-256.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sadowski, M., “The Arab Christian Teaching on Astrology in the Light on Elias’
                    of Nisibis Treatise <hi rend="italic">On Christian Faith in the Sentences of the
                        Stars</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Polonia Sacra</hi> 21:1 [46] (2017), 183-204
                    [in Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>Salvesen, A., “<hi rend="italic">Pentateuch</hi>, Secondary Translations: Late
                    Syriac Translations,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Hebrew Bible, Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi>
                    (Textual History of the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 219-224.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sanzo, J.E., and Korsvoll, N.H., “A New Testament Text on a Syriac Incantation
                    Bowl: Eph. 6:10-17 on IBC 3,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 71:4
                    (2017), 417-432.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schmidt, A.B., “Die syrischen Handschriften des Kekelidze
                    Handschrifteninstituts in Georgien. Ein Überblick,” <hi rend="italic">Mravaltavi</hi> 25:1 (2017), 287-303.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schor, A.M., “The Letter Collection of Theodoret of Cyrrhus,” in: C. Sogno,
                    B.K. Storin and E.J. Watts (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Late Antique Letter
                        Collections: A Critical Introduction and Reference Guide</hi> (Oakland,
                    California: University of California Press, 2017), 269-285.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sembiante, A.S., “Appunti sulla tradizione siriaca delle opere di Gregorio
                    Nazianzeno,” <hi rend="italic">KOINΩNIA: Rivista dell’ Associazione
                        Internazionale di Studi Tardoantichi</hi> 41 (2017), 607-635.</bibl>
                <bibl>Shahîd, I., “Arab-Ethiopian Relations in the Aksumite Period: The Role of
                    Simeon, Bishop of Bēth-Arshām,” in: A.C. McCollum (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Studies in Ethiopian Languages, Literature, and History: Festschrift for
                        Getatchew Haile, Presented by his Friends and Colleagues</hi>
                    (Aethiopistische Forschungen 83; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2017),
                    95-120.</bibl>
                <bibl>Simonet, J.-L., “Les citations des Actes des Apôtres dans la littérature
                    syriaque: la <hi rend="italic">Vetus Syra</hi> et la première version
                    arménienne,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament
                        en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017),
                    231-267.</bibl>
                <bibl>Simonsohn, U.I., “Muslim Involvement in Non-Muslim Political Affairs in the
                    Early Islamic Period,” in: J.V. Tolan, C. Nemo-Pekelman, N. Berend and Y.
                    Hameau-Masset (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Religious Minorities in Christian,
                        Jewish and Muslim Law (5th–15th Centuries)</hi> (Religion and Law in
                    Medieval Christian and Muslim Societies 8; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    341-352.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sims-Williams, N., “Two Iranian Loanwords in Syriac,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies</hi> 80:3 (2017),
                    485-490.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Two Words in the Sogdian Version of the <hi rend="italic">Antirrheticus
                    </hi>of Evagrius Ponticus,” <hi rend="italic">DABIR: The Digital Archive of
                        Brief Notes &amp; Iran Review</hi> 1 [4] (2017), 36-39.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Werner Sundermann and the Christian Texts of the Berlin Turfan
                    Collection,” in: Team “Turfanfor-schung” (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Zur lichten
                        Heimat: Studien zu Manichäismus, Iranistik und Zentralasienkunde im Gedenken
                        an Werner Sundermann</hi> (Iranica 25; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag,
                    2017), 11-18.</bibl>
                <bibl>Smine, R.E., “The Ornaments in Syriac Lectionaries between East and West:
                    Preliminary Notes on British Library Add. 7170 and Oriental 3372,” in: H.G.B.
                    Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First International
                        Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living
                        Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23;
                    Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 209-229.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stambolov, A., “Chrysostomic or Ephremian? Tracing the Origins of a Saying
                    Attributed to Chrysostom in the <hi rend="italic">Apophthegmata Patrum</hi>,”
                    in: D. Costache and M. Baghos (eds.), <hi rend="italic">John Chrysostom: Past,
                        Present, Future</hi> (Sydney: AIOCS Press, 2017), 87-103.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stang, C.M., “The “Nestorian” (<hi rend="italic">Jingjiao</hi>) Monument and
                    Its Theology of the Cross,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N.
                    Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural
                        Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu
                        University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi>
                    (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 107-118.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stewart, C., “Psalms and Prayer in Syriac Monasticism: Clues from Psalter
                    Prefaces and their Greek Sources,” in: B. Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in Eastern Christianities, 5th to
                        11th Centuries</hi> (London / New York: Routledge, 2017), 44-62.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “An Update on the Digitization and Cataloging Work of the Hill Museum and
                    Manuscript Library (HMML),” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14]
                    (2017), 153-170.</bibl>
                <bibl>Stoneman, R., “Alexander the Great and the End of Time: The Syriac
                    Contribution to the Development of the <hi rend="italic">Alexander
                    Romance</hi>,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S.
                    Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 39-46.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tabet, J., “Le don des larmes dans deux Beth-Gazzé maronites: l’Add. 14.703
                        (XII<hi rend="sup                    ">e</hi>-XIII<hi rend="sup">e</hi> s.)
                    et le Vat. Syr. 324 (XIII<hi rend="sup">e</hi> s.),” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                        l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 353-388.</bibl>
                <bibl>Takahashi, H., “Armenian Garshuni (Armenian in Syriac Characters) and Its
                    Users,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First
                        International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute
                        of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian
                    Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017), 243-264.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Syriac Fragments in the Ōtani Collection at Ryukoku University,
                    Kyoto,” in: T. Irisawa and K. Kitsudo (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Essays on the
                        Manuscripts written in Central Asian Languages in the Otani Collection:
                        Buddhism, Manichaeism, and Christianity</hi> (Ryukoku University Silk Road
                    Studies 6; Kyoto: Research Institute for Buddhist Culture, Ryukoku University,
                    2017), 181-211 [in Japanese].</bibl>
                <bibl>Takahashi, H., and Yaguchi, N., “On the Medical Works of Barhebraeus: With a
                    Description of the Abridgement of Ḥunain’s <hi rend="italic">Medical
                        Questions</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 15:2 (2017),
                    252-276.</bibl>
                <bibl>Talay, S., “<hi rend="italic">Sayfo</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Firman</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Qafle</hi>: The First World War from the Perspective of Syriac
                    Christians,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and
                        Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New
                    York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 132-147.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tamcke, M., “The Adam of the Syrian <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>:
                    Some Comments on the Report of the Creation of Adam According to the Syrian <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>,” in: A. Laato and L. Valve (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Adam and Eve Story in Jewish, Christian and Islamic
                        Perspectives</hi> (Studies in the Reception History of the Bible 8; Åbo: Åbo
                    Akademi University, 2017), 161-169.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Ephrem and the Lutherans,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal
                        Journal</hi> 55 (2017), 51-62.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Lutheran Contacts with the Syrian Orthodox Church of the St. Thomas
                    Christians and with the Syrian Apostolic Church of the East in India
                    (Nestorians),” <hi rend="italic">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</hi> 1 (2017),
                    13-49.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Mardin and the Tur ‘Abdin in Interaction with the “Deutsche
                    Orientmission” (German Oriental Mission),” in: H.G.B. Teule, E. Keser-Kayaalp,
                    K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its
                        Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin
                        Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                    337-342.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Paradise? America! The Metaphor of Paradise in the Context of the
                    Iraqi-Christian Migration,” in: S. Günther and T. Lawson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Roads to Paradise: Eschatology and Concepts of the Hereafter
                        in Islam.</hi> 2 vols. (Islamic History and Civilization 136.1-2; Leiden /
                    Boston: Brill, 2017), vol. 2, 806-813.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The Relationship between Theological Teaching and Religious Practice by
                    the East-Syrian Christians in Qatar (Sixth–Seventh Centuries),” in: K. Dmitriev
                    and I. Toral-Niehoff (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Religious Culture in Late Antique
                        Arabia: Selected Studies on the Late Antique Religious Mind</hi> (Islamic
                    History and Thought 6; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2017),
                    89-102.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Syrian Eyewitnesses Report to their German Partners about the Genocide:
                    A Little Inventory to the Reports of Syrian Survivors from the Archives of
                    German Missions,” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017),
                    205-214.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Using Philosophical Competence: The Heads of the Church of the East in
                    the 8th Century,” <hi rend="italic">Христианский Восток</hi> 8 [14] (2017),
                    195-204.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “The “World” in Its Eschatological Dimension in East-Syrian Synodical
                    Records,” in: S. Günther and T. Lawson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Roads to
                        Paradise: Eschatology and Concepts of the Hereafter in Islam</hi>. 2 vols.
                    (Islamic History and Civilization 136.1-2; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), vol.
                    2, 773-780.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tannous, J., “Greek Kanons and the Syrian Orthodox Liturgy,” in: B.
                    Bitton-Ashkelony and D. Krueger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Prayer and Worship in
                        Eastern Christianities, 5th to 11th Centuries</hi> (London / New York:
                    Routledge, 2017), 151-180.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tannous, Y.A., “Le chant syriaque, spiritualité et art,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 389-412.</bibl>
                <bibl>Taylor, D.G.K., “L’Apocalypse de Jean en syriaque: des origines à Diamper,”
                    in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en
                        syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017),
                    27-53.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Répertoire des manuscrits syriaques du Nouveau Testament,” in: J.-C.
                    Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament en syriaque</hi> (Études
                    syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017), 291-313.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Rufinus the Silver Merchant’s Miaphysite Refutation of Leontius of
                    Byzantium’s <hi rend="italic">Epaporemata</hi> (CPG 6814): A Rediscovered Syriac
                    Text,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92 (2017), 127-136.</bibl>
                <bibl>Taylor, R.A., “Psalm 2 in Syriac: Issues of Text and Language,” in: T. Li and
                    K. Dyer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Ancient Manuscripts to Modern
                        Dictionaries: Select Studies in Aramaic, Hebrew, and Greek</hi>
                    (Perspectives on Linguistics and Ancient Languages 9; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                    Gorgias Press, 2017), 179-198.</bibl>
                <bibl>Thomas, D.R., “Conversion out of Personal Principle: ‘Ali b. Rabban al-Tabari
                    (d. c. 860) and ‘Abdallah al-Tarjuman (d. c. 1430), Two Converts from
                    Christianity to Islam,” in: A.C.S. Peacock (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Islamisation: Comparative Perspectives from History</hi> (Edinburgh:
                    Edinburgh University Press, 2017), 56-68.</bibl>
                <bibl>Treiger, A., “Reconstructing Isḥāq ibn Ḥunayn’s Arabic Translation of
                    Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">De Anima</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017), 193-211.</bibl>
                <bibl>Тумара, Н., “Афраат, персијски мудрац. Приказ 18: Против Јевреја, о
                    девствености и светости,” <hi rend="italic">Теолошки погледи</hi> 50:1 (2017),
                    9-24.</bibl>
                <bibl>Uciecha, A., “Aphrahat, <hi rend="italic">On the Passover</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Demonstratio XII</hi>. <hi rend="italic">De paschate</hi>.
                    Patrologia Syriaca I, 505-540),” <hi rend="italic">Śląskie Studia
                        Historyczno-Teologiczne</hi> 50:1 (2017), 5-18 [in Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Aphrahat – Expositio XVIII: Against the Jews about Virginity and
                    Holiness: Introduction, Translation and Notes,” <hi rend="italic">Vox
                        Patrum</hi> 38 [68] (2017), 593-604 [in Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Biblical Exegesis in the Syriac Commentaries of Aphrahat, Ephraim the
                    Syrian, Ishodad of Merv and Theodore Bar Koni: The Outline of Issues,” <hi rend="italic">Vox Patrum</hi> 37 [67] (2017), 673-688 [in Polish].</bibl>
                <bibl>Üngör, U.Ü., “How Armenian Was the 1915 Genocide?,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and
                    S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let Them Not Return: Sayfo – The
                        Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and Chaldean Christians in the
                        Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New York / Oxford: Berghahn,
                    2017), 33-53.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Dalen, E., “Subjectivity in Translation: Ḥunayn Ibn Isḥāq’s Ninth-Century
                    Interpretation of Galen’s “Ego” in His <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the
                        Hippocratic Aphorisms</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens</hi> 45:1-2 (2017),
                    53-79.</bibl>
                <bibl>van der Kooij, A., “<hi rend="italic">Minor Prophets</hi>, Primary
                    Translations: Peshitta,” in: A. Lange and E. Tov (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Hebrew Bible, Volume 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter Prophets</hi>
                    (Textual History of the Bible 1; Leiden / Boston: Brill, 2017), 630-636.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Ginkel, J.J., “Mor Dionysios ‘Abd an-Nur Aslan: Church Leader during a
                    Genocide,” in: D. Gaunt, N. Atto and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Let
                        Them Not Return: Sayfo – The Genocide against the Assyrian, Syriac, and
                        Chaldean Christians in the Ottoman Empire</hi> (War and Genocide 26; New
                    York / Oxford: Berghahn, 2017), 100-112.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Pelt, J., “The <hi rend="italic">Life of Thaïs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Life of Abraham and his Niece Mary</hi>: An Intertextual Connection,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 71:4 (2017), 402-416.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Reeth, J.M.F., “Le <hi rend="italic">Vaticinans Puer</hi> III: La <hi rend="italic">Mémoire de la Mère de Dieu</hi> et son <hi rend="italic">Kathisma </hi>selon la tradition occidentale,” in: G. Guldentops, C. Laes
                    and G. Partoens (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Felici curiositate: Studies in Latin
                        Literature and Textual Criticism from Antiquity to the Twentieth Century in
                        Honour of Rita Beyers</hi> (Instrumenta Patristica et Mediaevalia 72;
                    Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 85-111.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Vossel, V., “A Christian Icon Rescued from War,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                        of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 17 (2017), 69-76.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vergani, E., “Il canone siriaco,” in: E.G. Farrugia and E. Vergani (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Il canone biblico nelle Chiese orientali: Atti del simposio
                        Pontificio Istituto Orientale, Roma 23 marzo 2010</hi> (Orientalia
                    Christiana Analecta 302; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2017),
                    27-53.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Il sinodo di Mar Isaac (410). Appunti e alcune linee di indagine,”
                    Cristianesimo nella storia 38:3 (2017), 655-672.</bibl>
                <bibl>Varghese, B., “Psalms in the East Syrian Liturgy of the Hours,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017), 423-438.</bibl>
                <bibl>Verheyden, J., “Eating with Apostles: Eucharist and Table Fellowship in the
                    Apocryphal Acts of the Apostles – The Evidence from the <hi rend="italic">Acts
                        of John</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Acts of Thomas</hi>,” in: D. Hellholm
                    and D. Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist – Its Origins and
                        Contexts: Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table Fellowship in Late Antiquity,
                        Early Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume 2: Patristic Traditions,
                        Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testa-ment 376;
                    Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1011-1060.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vesa, V., “The Divine Vision in Isaac of Niniveh and the East Syriac
                    Christology,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 92 (2017),
                    149-164.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Joseph Hazzaya and the Spiritual Itinerary,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                        Universitatis Babeş-Bolyai, Theologia Orthodoxa</hi> 62:2 (2017),
                    105-118.</bibl>
                <bibl>Villey, É., “Syriac Astronomical Texts (500-700 CE): Christian Voices
                    Defending Ptolemaic Astronomy,” in: H. Amirav and F. Celia (eds.), <hi rend="italic">New Themes, New Styles in the Eastern Mediterranean:
                        Christian, Jewish, and Islamic Encounters, 5th-8th Centuries</hi> (Late
                    Antique History and Religion 16; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 205-232.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wakelnig, E., “What Does Aristotle Have to Do with the Christian Arabic
                    Trinity? The Triad ‘Generosity-Wisdom-Power’ in the Alexandrian Prolegomena and
                    Yaḥyā ibn ‘Adī,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 130:3-4 (2017),
                    445-477.</bibl>
                <bibl>Walsh, E.G., “Holy Boldness: Narsai and Jacob of Serugh Preaching the
                    Canaanite Woman,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 78 (2017),
                    85-98.</bibl>
                <bibl>Watt, J.W., “The Curriculum of Aristotelian Philosophy among the Syrians,” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017), 171-192.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wehnert, J., “Mahl und Mahlgemeinschaft in den Pseudo-klementinen,” in: D.
                    Hellholm and D. Sänger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Eucharist – Its Origins and
                        Contexts: Sacred Meal, Communal Meal, Table Fellowship in Late Antiquity,
                        Early Judaism, and Early Christianity. Volume 2: Patristic Traditions,
                        Iconography</hi> (Wissenschaftliche Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testa-ment 376;
                    Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2017), 1061-1089.</bibl>
                <bibl>Weitz, L.E., “Slavery and the Historiography of Non-Muslims in the Medieval
                    Middle East,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Middle East
                        Studies</hi> 49:1 (2017), 139-142.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wellington, J.F., “Let God Arise: The Divine Warrior <hi rend="italic">Motif
                    </hi>in Theodoret of Cyrrhus’ Commentary on <hi rend="italic">Psalm </hi>67,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 96 (2017), 265-272.</bibl>
                <bibl>Whiting, M., “A River Runs Through It: The Role of the Tigris and Euphrates in
                    Transport and Communication in Late Antiquity,” in: T. Papacostas and M. Parani
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Discipuli dona ferentes: Glimpses of Byzantium in
                        Honour of Marlia Mundell Mango</hi> (Byzantioς 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2017),
                    37-67.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wilkinson, R.J., “Les éditions imprimées de la Peshitta syriaque du Nouveau
                    Testament.,” in: J.-C. Haelewyck (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Le Nouveau Testament
                        en syriaque</hi> (Études syriaques 14; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2017),
                    269-289.</bibl>
                <bibl>Winkler, G., “The Significance of the Two Syriac Versions of the Liturgy of
                    James in the Context of the Other Redactions,” in: H.G.B. Teule, E.
                    Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru and M.S. Toprak (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies
                        Symposium, Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22
                        April 2012, Mardin</hi> (Eastern Christian Studies 23; Leuven: Peeters,
                    2017), 31-37.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wolf, K.B., “Back to the Future: Constantine and the Last Roman Emperor,” in:
                    M.S. Bjornlie (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Life and Legacy of Constantine:
                        Traditions through the Ages</hi> (New York: Routledge, 2017),
                    115-132.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wood, P., “Constantine in the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of Seert</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Late Antiquity</hi> 1:2 (2017), 150-172.</bibl>
                <bibl>Yoshida, Y., “Christian Sogdians in China, Turfan, and Sogdiana: Problems
                    raised by a Christian Sogdian text Ōtani 2497,” in: T. Irisawa and K. Kitsudo
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Essays on the Manuscripts written in Central Asian
                        Languages in the Otani Collection: Buddhism, Manichaeism, and
                        Christianity</hi> (Ryukoku University Silk Road Studies 6; Kyoto: Research
                    Institute for Buddhist Culture, Ryukoku University, 2017), 155-180 [in
                    Japanese].</bibl>
                <bibl>Younes, M., “Blessing, Clinging, Familiarity, Custom – or Ship? A New Reading
                    of the Word <hi rend="italic">Īlāf</hi> in Q 106,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        Semitic Studies</hi> 62:1 (2017), 181-189.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zapff, B.M., “Einige hermeneutische Beobachtungen zur syrischen Version des
                    Sirach-Buches,” in: G. Karner, F. Ueberschaer and B.M. Zapff (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Texts and Contexts of the Book of Sirach / Texte und Kontexte
                        des Sirachbuches</hi> (Septuagint and Cognate Studies 66; Atlanta, Georgia:
                    SBL Press, 2017), 239-262.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zampaki, T., “Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s <hi rend="italic">Istithmār </hi>on Proclus’
                    Commentary on the Pythagorean <hi rend="italic">Golden Verses</hi>,” in: D.D.
                    Butorac and D.A. Layne (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Proclus and his Legacy</hi>
                    (Millennium-Studien 65; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2017), 311-321.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zawadzki, K.F., “Hat Cyrill von Alexandrien sich selbst ‘plagiiert’? Ein
                    neues, rätselhaftes syrisches Fragment aus dem <hi rend="italic">Codex British
                        Library Add</hi>. 14529,” <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Theologicae
                        Lovanienses</hi> 93:2 (2017), 343-360.</bibl>
                <bibl>———. “Syrische Fragmente des Kommentars Cyrills von Alexandrien zum <hi rend="italic">1. Korintherbrief</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                        Antikes Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity</hi> 21:2 (2017),
                    304-360.</bibl>
                <bibl>Zellentin, H.M., “Trialogical Anthropology: The Qur’ān on Adam and Iblīs in
                    View of Rabbinic and Christian Discourse,” in: R. Braun and H.I. Çiçek (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">New Approaches to Human Dignity in the Context of the
                        Qur’ānic Anthropology: The Quest for Humanity</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge
                    Scholars Publishing, 2017), 61-131.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>