<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of: The Gospel of Mark in the Syriac Harklean Version. An
                    Edition Based upon the Earliest Witnesses</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Andreas</forename>
                        <surname>Juckel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Münster</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/review/hv21n1prjuckel</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Andreas Juckel</author>
                        <title level="a">The Gospel of Mark in the Syriac Harklean Version. An
                            Edition Based upon the Earliest Witnesses</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1PRJuckel.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="204" to="217">204–217</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="8"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-03">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Samer S. Yohanna, <hi rend="italic">The Gospel of Mark in
                        the Syriac Harklean Version. An Edition Based upon the Earliest
                        Witnesses</hi>, Biblica et Orientalia 52 (Rome: Pontifical Biblical
                    Institute, Gregorian &amp; Biblical Press, 2015). Pp. xi + 196; € 60.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">The book under review is the doctoral dissertation of Samer
                    Soreshow Yohanna, Chaldean priest and member of the Chaldean Antonian Order of
                    St. Hormizd (Iraq). It was supervised by Craig Morrison, O. Carm. and St.
                    Pisano, S. J. and defended in 2014 at the Pontifical Biblical Institute in Rome.
                    The idea behind this book is clear and simple: to provide scholars with the
                    (still missing) critical edition of the Ḥarklean Gospel of Mark, based on the
                    earliest Ḥarklean manuscripts and presented ‘in a user-friendly style, that will
                    allow scholars to read this version, study its character and appreciate its
                    place in the New Testament criticism’ (p. 8). The introduction clearly states
                    that this book does not intend to offer such a text-critical study, but rather a
                    convenient display of the Syriac evidence as a preparatory stage for textual
                    criticism and for establishing the ‘original’. There is no explicit theory
                    concerning the history of the text or the ‘critical’ approach to the ‘original’.
                    A critical impact Yohanna expects from the restriction to the earliest Ḥarklean
                    Gospel manuscripts and especially from the inclusion of his ms. C, a Gospel
                    codex in the possession of the Chaldeans in Iraq, which here for the first time
                    is fully described and used in a scholarly publication.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> In his unpublished Licentiate Thesis, submitted
                            2011 to the Pontifical Biblical Institute, Yohanna presented this ms.
                            witness: <hi rend="italic">Towards the ‛Original’ Text of the Harklean
                                Version of the Tetraeuangelion. A Descriptive Study of a Harklean
                                Manuscript from the Depository of the ‛Chaldean Antonian Order of
                                St. Hormizd.’ The Syriac Text of Mark 1–5 Including a Critical
                                Apparatus</hi>. During the 11th Symposium Syriacum at Malta (2012),
                            Yohanna presented this to a large audience: “Between Two Millennia:
                            Assessing the Syriac Harklean Tetra-Euangelion Manuscript C 25 from the
                            Depository of the ‛Chaldean Antonian Order of St. Hormizd-Iraq’.”
                            Unfortunately, this paper was not published in the Symposium
                            proceedings.</p>
                    </note> This 10th/11th cent. witness is the (occasionally modified) base line of
                    the edition to which the Syriac evidence of thirteen early witnesses is
                    attached.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Before turning to the details of the edition, the reader must
                    understand the major difficulties that so far have prevented scholars from
                    producing a critical edition of the Ḥarklean Gospels, namely the revisional
                    development of the version and the corresponding editorial challenges. This
                    development is traceable in the Gospels only<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts and Epistles are transmitted in four witnesses
                            only.</p>
                    </note> and mainly reflected in modifications to the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’, which
                    is the most characteristic feature of the version. By this ‘apparatus’, Thomas
                    of Ḥarqel attached to his translation Greek variants (translated into Syriac),
                    drawn from a collation of Greek manuscripts and of the Philoxenian version.
                    These variants Thomas introduced by putting words between critical signs
                    (asteriskos, obelos), or by placing them in the margin and linking them to the
                    main text by a graphic sign.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Photographic samples in Yohanna’s book on p. 113 and
                            115.</p>
                    </note> This complex layout was not only prone to alterations by inattentive
                    scribes but also to intentional alterations by revisers. By and large, the
                    Ḥarklean Gospel text was continually adapted to the Greek-Byzantine text, and
                    this adaptation primarily affected the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’: non-Byzantine
                    readings were removed from the text to the margin or marked with asteriskos; and
                    non-Byzantine marginalia that could not be identified at all by revisers were
                        omitted.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In some manuscripts, mainly of the second
                            millennium, the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’ is dropped completely. However,
                            even the oldest dated Ḥarklean Gospel Codex F (of 757, see below) omits
                            the critical signs and the Syriac marginalia.</p>
                    </note> On the one hand, this shift within the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’ allows one
                    to relate the history of the Ḥarklean version to the history of the Greek text;
                    on the other hand, the revisional impact of the Greek on each individual
                    Ḥarklean witness diminishes the chance of establishing a genealogical-stemmatic
                    relation between them. The necessity of research on this revisional impact, the
                    complexity of editorial decisions and layout of the evidence in a printed
                    edition are the major reasons that have delayed the production of a critical
                    edition. In the meantime, it has become clear that an edition of the Ḥarklean
                    Gospels should be based on that witness which is byzantinized to the least
                        extent,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">According to my own knowledge, Vat. Syr. 268
                            (8th/9th cent.) shows the smallest extent of byzantinization. The text
                            of this witness is printed in the <hi rend="italic">Comparative edition
                                of the Syriac Gospels</hi> by G. Kiraz.</p>
                    </note> should primarily include witnesses to the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’, and
                    should keep the variants of the Ḥarklean main text separated from those of the
                    ‘apparatus’. To visualize the authentic layout of the version and the revisional
                    shifts of text and marginalia constitutes the main task of the editor.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although Yohanna is aware of the revisional development<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Yohanna describes the revisional development in too
                            general a way and remains overly centered on the outward graecisation:
                            ‛The revisional developments of the Harklean version mark the Harklean
                            witnesses with a distinct stamp and indicate the development of the text
                            towards a kind of perfectionism’ (p. 18). − ‛The manuscripts of the
                            second millennium…are most likely of little help towards uncovering the
                            ‘original Ḥarklean’, because the Greek imprint on Thomas’ original work
                            is thought to be more moderate than what is found in the later Graecized
                            Harklean manuscripts which show significant revisional developments’ (p.
                            22).</p>
                    </note> of the version, his editorial policy does not sufficiently account for
                    it; rather, he claims to put to the test Ḥarklean scholarship by offering a new
                    textual foundation, based on the evidence of the first millennium.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‛But because no modern critical edition of his
                            [i.e., Thomas’] version exists (especially for the four Gospels), there
                            is no clear and convincing interpretation of the function and exact
                            meaning of his marginalia and critical signs’ (p. 7–8). This statement
                            is not up-to-date; a convincing interpretation of the marginalia and
                            critical signs (<hi rend="italic">asteriskos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">obelos</hi>) is given by B. Aland in her edition of the (major)
                            catholic epistles (1986) and of the Corpus Paulinum (1991–2002).
                            Unfortunately, Yohanna did not put to the test her interpretation in his
                            introduction to the Gospel of Mark.</p>
                    </note> The introduction (3–8) sketches the life of Thomas of Ḥarqel. Chapter 1
                    (pp. 9–19) informs the reader about previous studies and editions and about the
                    ‘characteristics of the Ḥarklean version’. These characteristics are, 1. the
                    extreme graecizing translation technique (11–15), especially of the proper
                    names; 2. the revisional link to the Philoxenian version (p. 15), which Thomas
                    compared with Greek manuscripts; 3. the participation of the Ḥarklean Gospels in
                    the Greek-Byzantine text-type (6–17); 4. ‘philological glosses, in both Greek
                    and Syriac,’ in the margins (17–18), and the revisional development of the
                    version (18–19). The obvious purpose of Yohanna’s brief overview of the Ḥarklean
                    version is to introduce the typical Ḥarklean features in a general way before
                    their presentation in this edition of Mark. The author thus only touches upon
                    the complex features of the Ḥarklean Gospels; no detailed discussion of the
                    ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’ in Mark is given.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‛Thomas’ intention was to bring the Philoxenian in
                            line with the generally accepted Greek text by producing a critical
                            study that would present the variant readings in the margin’ (p. 11). −
                            ‛Nevertheless, the nature of his [i.e., Thomas’] work can be described
                            in two ways: (1) Thomas took a copy of Polycarp’s text [i.e., of the
                            Philoxenian], compared it with Greek manuscripts and added to the margin
                            the Greek readings which were different, or (2) he pushed to the margin
                            the readings of Polycarp, replacing them with new readings from Greek
                            manuscripts known to him’ (p. 15). </p>
                    </note> This is a matter of regret, because Yohanna’s fine understanding of the
                    version’s complexity would have enriched the scholarly discussion. Yet as the
                    main concern of his editorial policy is the practical mastering of the complex
                    features, the neglect of discussing them in greater detail is no severe
                    disadvantage to the edition proper.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Chapter 2 (p. 20–49) presents the manuscripts used in this
                        edition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text"/>
                    </note> Following the catalogues, Yohanna identifies nineteen witnesses as from
                    the first millennium, fourteen of which are witnesses to the Gospel of Mark;
                    these are described in detail. In the following list, the witnesses in <hi rend="italic">italics</hi> are those furnished with <hi rend="italic">asteriskos/obelos</hi> and Syriac marginalia.</p>
                <table>
                    <row n="1">
                        <cell>Abbrev.</cell>
                        <cell>Manuscript</cell>
                        <cell>Yohanna's Date</cell>
                        <cell>Jucekel's Estimated Date</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="2">
                        <cell>C</cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. 25, Chald. Order of St. Hormizd, Alqosh</cell>
                        <cell>9th/10th</cell>
                        <cell>10th/11th c</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="3">
                        <cell>M<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. olim syr. 1, Imp. Moscow Archaeol. Society,
                            Moscow</cell>
                        <cell>7th</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="4">
                        <cell>B</cell>
                        <cell>Ms. 220.43/B58s/c.1, American University of Beirut</cell>
                        <cell>7th/8th</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="5">
                        <cell>H<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. syr. 16, Houghton Library, Harvard, Cambridge,
                            MA</cell>
                        <cell>7th/8th</cell>
                        <cell>10th/11th</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="6">
                        <cell>S<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. Mingana syr. 124, Birmingham</cell>
                        <cell>'ca. 730'</cell>
                        <cell>9th/10th</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="7">
                        <cell>F</cell>
                        <cell>Ms. Plut. 1,40, Biblioteca Laurenziana, Florence</cell>
                        <cell>757 AD</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row n="8">
                        <cell>V<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. Vat. Syr. 267, Bibl. Apost. Vaticana, Vatican</cell>
                        <cell>8th</cell>
                        <cell>8th/9th</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="9">
                        <cell>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. Vat. Syr. 268, Bibl. Apost. Vaticana, Vatican</cell>
                        <cell>8th/9th</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row n="10">
                        <cell>S<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Ms. Mingana syr. 42, Birmingham</cell>
                        <cell>835 AD</cell>
                        <cell>12th/13th c</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="11">
                        <cell>K</cell>
                        <cell>Ms. Ori. 1, University Library Kiel/Germany</cell>
                        <cell>9th/10th</cell>
                        <cell>?</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="12">
                        <cell>L<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="italic">Ms. BL Add. 7163, London</cell>
                        <cell>9th/10th</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row n="13">
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>Ms. or. 74, Biblioteca Angelica, Rome</cell>
                        <cell>9th/10th</cell>
                        <cell>11th/12th c</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row n="14">
                        <cell>L<hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Ms. BL Add. 14,469, London</cell>
                        <cell>936 AD</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row n="15">
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>Ms. syr. 3, Chester Beatty Library, Dublin</cell>
                        <cell>1177 AD</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p xml:lang="en">Six witnesses only (S<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, F, V<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, L<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, L<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) belong to the first millennium with certainty, while three (C, H<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, S<hi rend="sup">1</hi>) are likely to derive from the
                    turn to the second millennium; the remaining five witnesses are either late
                        (S<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, D) or charged with chronological problems.
                    Regarding the questionable date of most of these witnesses, the restriction to
                    the first millennium itself becomes disputable. In addition, the critical impact
                    of the chosen witnesses is mainly reduced to the two Vatican manuscripts (V<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), because F and L<hi rend="sup">2</hi> omit the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’, and S<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, L<hi rend="sup">1</hi> (and M<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, H<hi rend="sup">1</hi>)
                    cannot contribute much to the ‘original’ due to their defective conditions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See the useful Diagram 2 on p. 101, outlining the
                            contents of the manuscripts.</p>
                    </note> This calls for the inclusion of later witnesses, which by their features
                    and variations are not too different from those chosen by Yohanna. If the
                    twelfth century were to constitute the upper limit, at least five additional
                    dated witnesses (besides D) could be included:</p>
                <list rend="indent">
                    <item>Ms. 12/8 of the Syriac Orth. Patriarchate Damascus, dated 1055
                        (aster./obel., Syr. &amp; Greek margin);</item>
                    <item>Ms. or. 227 Cambridge Univ. Library, dated 1061/62 AD (aster./obel., Greek
                            margin);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                            <p rend="footnote text">M. H. Gottstein, “A list of some uncatalogued
                                Syriac Biblical manuscripts,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the John
                                    Rylands Library</hi> 37, 429–445, esp. 441.</p>
                        </note>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ms. Add. 1700 Cambridge Univ. Library, dated 1169/70 AD (no aster./obel.,
                        no margin);</item>
                    <item>Ms. BN syr. 52 (Paris), dated 1164/65 (no aster./obel., no margin);</item>
                    <item>Ms. BN syr. 54 (Paris), dated 1192 (no aster./obel., no margin).</item>
                </list>
                <p xml:lang="en">By their age, the first two manuscripts can duly be regarded as
                    witnesses to the text of the first millennium. The three later ones offer a
                    dated text for comparison with the earlier text; their inclusion would also
                    enlarge the textual base and sharpen the profile of this earlier text by their
                    agreement, disagreement, or modification. There is no doubt that putting the
                    focus on the Ḥarklean witnesses of the first millennium is a sound starting
                    point for tracing the ‘original’; as a mechanical and exclusive rule, however,
                    this focus will miss the dynamic of the textual development away from the
                    ‘original’ and thus prevent the editor from finding the way back to it. In this
                    regard, Yohanna’s complete neglect of ms. New College 333 (on which the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of the Ḥarklean Gospels is based) is much
                    to be regretted. This admittedly late, 13th/14th-cent. manuscript is a witness
                    to all revisional stages of the Ḥarklean and to some extent also to Yohanna’s
                    ms. C, which is related to the Dionysius-stage of the 12th century (on which see
                    below). </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The description of each manuscript concludes with indicating the
                    genealogical relation (based on agreements of readings)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="#12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">“The text and apparatus presented in this edition
                            will allow scholars to trace the genealogy of the earliest Ḥarklean
                            witnesses. For example, some manuscripts report the haplography in Mk
                            2,21. The text between the two <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܠܝܐ</foreign> is
                            missing in manuscript V<hi rend="sup">1</hi> and this error has been
                            transmitted to S<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and K, revealing the direct
                            dependence of S<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and K on V<hi rend="sup">1</hi>”
                            (p. 51).</p>
                    </note> to the co-witnesses.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The ‛genealogical families’ are summarized by <hi rend="italic">Diagram 3</hi> on p. 102. </p>
                    </note> Yohanna himself points (p. 30) to the provisional character of the three
                    ‘genealogical families’ C-S<hi rend="sup">1</hi>-H<hi rend="sup">1</hi> | V<hi rend="sup">1</hi>-V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-L<hi rend="sup">1</hi>-D | K-S<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-L<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-A (while M<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, F,
                    B are outside of these ‘families’ but contribute to them) and announces a
                    detailed study for the future. One may conclude that consistent genealogical
                    research will arrive at the ‘original’ by reconstructing the common ancestry
                    (archetype) of these ‘families’. However, the present writer is in doubt whether
                    the genealogical-stemmatic study of the witnesses is the appropriate methodology
                    for reconstructing the ‘original’ of the Ḥarklean Gospels; the revisional
                    development of the version towards the Greek-Byzantine text is likely to have
                    blurred their genealogical relations. More feasible is the grouping of witnesses
                    according to their respective participation in the same revisional stage.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Chapter 3 (‘Methodology’, pp. 62–67) presents the editorial policy
                    of the edition. Basically, the edition imitates the Ḥarklean layout and gives
                    the text (occasionally modified) and margin of ms. C. There are two apparatuses,
                    which keep the variants of the Ḥarklean text and those of the margin separated.
                    Variant use of the asteriskos/obelos in the witnesses is quoted in the first
                    apparatus. This layout with distinct areas of data gives easy access to the
                    textual information: the text, which includes the critical signs; the margin,
                    which gives the variant readings and Greek words quoted by Thomas; and the
                    apparatuses for the variations of the witnesses. Regarding the complexity of the
                    Ḥarklean features, this is the best way of presenting and visualizing the data,
                    especially for understanding their shifting from the text to the margin (or vice
                    versa) during transmission. This layout is extremely clear, the data are correct
                    and skilfully presented, the printing is brilliant.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although his edition reproduces ms. C, Yohanna replaced 27 singular
                    readings (within his choice of witnesses) by the majority reading and marked
                    them with a pair of daggers, considering them scribal errors in ms. C (p. 64). A
                    second textual feature of ms. C is explicitly marked in the text line: words
                    marked with a pair of <hi rend="italic">double</hi> daggers are ones that other
                    witnesses omit or put in the marginalia (some of these words even have a special
                    sign in ms. C). A total of 12 words is marked this way in the edition; in fact,
                    there are 34 readings<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">They can be looked up in Y.’s edition. There are 34
                            integrations of marginalia into the main text: <hi rend="bold">1</hi>:13, <hi rend="bold">2</hi>:4. 7. 8. 16. 18 (twice). 21, <hi rend="bold">3</hi>:27, <hi rend="bold">4</hi>:13. 37, <hi rend="bold">5</hi>:34. 37, <hi rend="bold">6</hi>:25. 52 (twice),
                                <hi rend="bold">7</hi>:13. 14. 18. 24. 25, <hi rend="bold">8</hi>:34, <hi rend="bold">10</hi>:17, 32. 40. 50, <hi rend="bold">11</hi>:28, <hi rend="bold">12</hi>:7. 11. 20. 32, <hi rend="bold">13</hi>:35, <hi rend="bold">14</hi>:19, 15:12 – Five marginalia are
                            completely omitted in ms C: 3:14. 18, 12:31. 34, <hi rend="bold">13</hi>:13.</p>
                    </note> in ms. C, which are in the margin of all or some of the other witnesses.
                    In addition, ms. C exchanges the text reading with the marginal reading in 19
                        cases.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="bold">3</hi>:5. 27. 31, <hi rend="bold">4</hi>:36, <hi rend="bold">5</hi>:1. 18, <hi rend="bold">6</hi>:1.
                            11. 41, <hi rend="bold">9</hi>:19, <hi rend="bold">10</hi>:49, <hi rend="bold">11</hi>:19. 32, <hi rend="bold">12</hi>:28. 36. 41, <hi rend="bold">14</hi>:72, <hi rend="bold">15</hi>:4.25.</p>
                    </note> I am not sure whether the author recognized the significance of these
                    phenomena for the evaluation of ms. C.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">“The instances where manuscript C stands almost
                            alone against all the other Harklean witnesses are not mentioned here
                            because they exhibit a dependence on some Greek witnesses; in other
                            words, they are variant readings. A careful study of theses readings may
                            identify the original Harklean reading” (p. 64, note 12). Does Yohanna
                            here mean the text readings of C, which are in the margin of the other
                            witnesses?</p>
                    </note> These unique features make ms. C a ‘stranger’ among the witnesses used
                    by Yohanna and may point to the secondary formation of ms. C within the
                    revisional development of the Ḥarklean Gospels (on this see below). This dispute
                    on the ‘originality’ of ms. C gives proof of Yohanna’s sound editorial policy,
                    which enables scholars to put ms. C in a critical perspective. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Chapter 4 (‘The Ḥarklean Tradition’, pp. 68–115) is the longest
                    chapter and offers a wealth of information by printing (in Syriac and in English
                    translation) numerous additional texts associated with the Ḥarklean Gospels: 1.
                    the Eusebian materials (<hi rend="italic">Ep. ad Carpianum</hi>; the ten Canon
                    Tables; the sections and their references in the Gospel of Mark); 2. the <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Titloi</hi> in Mark; 3.
                    the famous subscription to the Ḥarklean Gospels including the variants from
                    single manuscripts; 4. a full list of patristic, theological, and linguistic
                    notes and comments from the margins of ms. C, including the liturgical rubrics
                    and Old Testament quotations; 5. lists and diagrams concerning the Syriac
                    manuscripts, their contents and relation to each other; 6. a list that shows the
                    orthographical development in the proper names; 7. the history of the depository
                    of manuscripts in the Chaldean Antonian Order of St. Hormizd (Yohanna himself
                    was involved in the transfer of the manuscripts from Baghdad to Al-Qosh in
                    2006); some color images of ms. C for the illustration of the Ḥarklean textual
                    features. ‘Final considerations’ give a summary of the book. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Yohanna’s concern is to pave the way for establishing the
                    ‘original’ of the Ḥarklean Gospel of Mark. In this respect, ms. C plays a key
                    role and is chosen as the textual base of the edition. By age, intactness, and
                    by the exhaustive ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’, this witness is believed to be ‘one of
                    the better representatives of the Ḥarklean Gospels’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">“This manuscript, wrongly attributed to the 13th
                            century, is one of the better representatives of the Harklean Gospels
                            because it contains a high percentage of the text (99,97% of the four
                            Gospels), and it has more accurate marginalia, including a full
                            representation of the Harklean critical signs (surpassing manuscript V2
                            in this respect).”</p>
                    </note> This general statement is correct but in need of a better specification.
                    According to my own research,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I was kindly allowed to photograph ms C during my
                            visit to the Chaldean Monastery in Dora/Baghdad in April 1989. There is
                            a project of editing the Harklean Gospels under my direction, located at
                            Beth Mardutho/The Syriac Institute, NJ (headed by Dr. G. A. Kiraz).</p>
                    </note> the significance of ms. C for the history of the Ḥarklean Gospel text is
                    given by its place within the revisional development of the version. Ms. C
                    reflects a pre-history of the revisional stage, which is related to Dionysius
                    bar Ṣalibi (d. 1171) and extant in two manuscripts (New College 334 of the
                    12th/13th cent., and BL Add. 17,124, dated 1233/34 AD).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See G. A. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Comparative
                                Edition of the Syriac Gospels. Aligning the Sinaiticus,
                                Curetonianus, Peshîṭtâ and Ḥarklean Versions</hi> [New Testament
                            Texts and Studies 21/I–IV]. Leiden 1996/Piscataway 2004, vol. 1 p.
                            xxxvii-xxxix. The subscription to ms BL Add. 17,124 is given in W.
                            Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the British
                                Museum Acquired since the Year 1838</hi>, Part I (London 1870,
                            reprint Piscataway 2002), 42.</p>
                    </note> Still substantially rooted in the still undistorted Ḥarklean textual
                    tradition of the first millennium, ms. C already exhibits the typical features
                    of the Dionysius-stage,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This stage exhibits a strongly reduced ‘Harklean
                            apparatus’ and seems to be an individual attempt to ‛fix and seal’ the
                            Harklean Gospels. Besides this revisional stage, the still undistorted
                            Harklean textual tradition continues, as can be seen from the mss.
                            Chester Beatty syr. 3 (Dublin), dated 1177 AD, Cambridge Univ. Library
                            Add. 1903 (the <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> dated 1210 AD), and ms.
                            New College 333 (Oxford, 13th/14th cent.). The manuscript from Oxford is
                            significantly related to the Dionysius stage but to the undistorted
                            Harklean textual tradition as well, see G. A. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Edition of the Syriac Gospels</hi>, vol. 1, xli –
                            xliv.</p>
                    </note> i.e., 1. the integration of a sizable number of marginalia into the main
                    text, and 2. several exchanges of text readings with readings from the
                        margin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See above notes 20 and 21.</p>
                    </note> Almost half of the 120 Syriac marginalia in Mark extant in V2 (Vat. syr.
                    168) are affected by this revisional shift. A revisional background of this
                    shift seems very likely, because in some cases other witnesses offer the same
                    integrations of marginalia into the main text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See <hi rend="bold">4</hi>:13, <hi rend="bold">5</hi>:37, <hi rend="bold">6</hi>:25.52 <hi rend="bold">10</hi>:32,
                                <hi rend="bold">12</hi>:11, <hi rend="bold">15</hi>:12.</p>
                    </note> The exchange of text and margin we do not meet outside the
                    Dionysius-stage and its pre-history; it may reflect the latest results of
                    revisional activities. As witness to the developing Dionysius-stage, the
                    terminus ante quem to produce ms. C is the 12th century. The still obvious
                    integrity of the ‘Ḥarklean apparatus’ in this witness suggests a 10th/11th-cent.
                    date. Yohanna cannot be blamed for having missed the relation of ms. C to the
                    Dionysius-stage, because in the two manuscripts representing this stage, the
                    Gospel of Mark is almost entirely missing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mk 15:34 – only the end is preserved in ms. BL Add.
                            17,124 (on fol. 5).</p>
                    </note> In the Gospel of John, which is fully transmitted in both witnesses,
                    this relation is obvious. Nevertheless, Yohanna should have treated with more
                    suspicion the unique features of ms. C.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Yohanna’s edition of the Ḥarklean Mark is a pioneering work and a
                    model for future editions of the Ḥarklean New Testament. For the first time, we
                    have a published<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Unfortunately, the Ph.D. dissertation of Peter A. L.
                            Hill, <hi rend="italic">The Harklean Version of St. Luke 1–11: A
                                Critical Introduction and Edition</hi> (Univ. of Melbourne, 2002),
                            remains unpublished.</p>
                    </note> Ḥarklean Gospel text at hand, which is not a one-manuscript-edition, but
                    a critical edition based on fourteen manuscripts. In addition, the author made
                    available to scholarship a remarkable (and difficult to access) manuscript of
                    immense importance for the revisional development of the Ḥarklean Gospels. It is
                    hoped that he will edit the remaining Gospels in the future. In Ḥarklean
                    research ‘diversity’ is a sign of good health, and three remarkably different
                    printed editions (of J. White, G. A. Kiraz, and S. S. Yohanna) are now standing
                    side by side.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Finally, some corrections: Yohanna does not always properly
                    distinguish between (actual) ‘text’ and (intended) ‘reading’ of the marginalia,
                    i.e., the interpretation of the marginalia (replacement or addition?) is wrong
                    in several cases. The following list gives the correct interpretation (all items
                    are from the second apparatus of Yohanna’s edition):</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="bold">Verse</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="bold">MSS</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="bold">Margin</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="bold">Interpretation (Intended Reading)</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2:18</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi> D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܬܠܡܝܕ̈ܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>(<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܬܠܡܝܕ̈ܐ (ܕܦܪ̈ܝܫܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>H<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> V<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>mg ܘܬܠܡܝܕ̈ܐ</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">by err.</hi> refers to ܬܠܡܝܕ̈ܝܟ</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4:30</cell>
                        <cell>C</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܣܝܡܝܗܿ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="text">
                            <hi rend="italic">by err.</hi> refers to <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܕܡܝܗܿ</foreign> (besides the
                            correct <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܦܠܐܬܝܗܿ</foreign>)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6:7</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܢܦܩܘܢ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rend="text">
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܢܦܩܘܢ (ܛܡ̈ܐܐ ܪ̈ܘܚܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6:8</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="gr">πήραν</foreign> (bag)</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">by err.</hi> affixed to <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܘܛܪܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6:14</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܝܫܘܥ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܫܘܥ ܥܠ (ܗܪܘܕܝܣ ܡܠܟܐ ܘܫܡܼܥ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6:38</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܚܡ̈ܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܚܡ̈ܐ (ܟܡܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܪܟܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܪܟܐ (ܠܟܘܢ ܐܝܬ ܠܚܡ̈ܐ ܟܡܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܚܡ̈ܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܚܡ̈ܐ (ܚܡܫܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7:18</cell>
                        <cell>M<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                            S<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">1 </hi>L<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܕܟܝܠ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܠܐ) ܥܕܟܝܠ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>7:25</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">1 </hi>L<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܐ ܡܚܕܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܐ ܡܚܕܐ (ܫܡܥܬ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8:12</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܥܙܙ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>for <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܬܢܚ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>8:29</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗ̇ܘ ܒܪܗ ܕܐܠܗܐ ܚܝܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܝܐ ܕܐܠܗܐ ܒܪܗ ܗܘܿ (ܡܫܝܚܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10:14</cell>
                        <cell>M<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> L<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                            V<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">1 </hi>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܿܐܐ ܘܟܕ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܼܪ (ܟܿܐܐ ܘܟܕ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10:17</cell>
                        <cell>H<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                            V<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">1 </hi>V<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                            L<hi rend="superscript" xml:space="preserve">1 </hi>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܫ ܥܬܝܪܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p>
                                <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܬܝܪܐ ܐܢܫ (ܪܗܛܼ)</foreign>, no <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܕ</foreign> after <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܗܛ</foreign>
                            </p>
                            <p>C mechanically inserts <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܫ
                            ܥܬܝܪܐ</foreign> into the text and wrongly reads <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܬܝܪܐ ܐܢܫ ܚܕ ܪܗܛܼ</foreign>
                            </p>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>10:32</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܝܢ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܗܘܘ) ܕܝܢ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>11:8</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܪ̈ܣܡܬܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">by err.</hi> affixed to <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܣܩܝܢ</foreign> (correct to <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘ̈ܟܐ</foreign>)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>14:12</cell>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܝܘܕ̈ܝܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܝܘܕ̈ܝܐ (ܕܦܨܚܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>14:49</cell>
                        <cell>C</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܢܒܝ̈ܐ ܟܬܒ̈ܐ܌ ܍</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">error</hi> for <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܢܒܝ̈ܐ܌ ܍ ܟܬܒ̈ܐ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>D</cell>
                        <cell>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܕܐ ܗܘܬ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܕܐ ܗܘܬ (ܕܢܒܝ̈ܐ܌ ܍ ܟܬܒ̈ܐ)</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>15:13</cell>
                        <cell>V<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> D</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <p>mg <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܐܬܬܢܝܦ</foreign> <hi rend="italic">until</hi> <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܐܡܪܝܢ</foreign>
                            </p>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">by err.</hi> affixed to <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܝܦ</foreign> vs 11; correct in vs 13
                            after <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܝܢ ܗܼܢܘܢ</foreign>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>