<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Bardaisan's Influence on Late Antique Christianity</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Ute</forename>
                        <surname>Possekel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Harvard Divinity School</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n1possekel</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Ute Possekel</author>
                        <title level="a">Bardaisan's Influence on Late Antique Christianity</title>
                        <idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/####</idno>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1Possekel.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="81" to="125">81-125</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="4"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Bardaisan</term>
                    <term>Book of the Laws of Countries</term>
                    <term>Philosophy</term>
                    <term>Late Antiquity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-03">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
       <front>
           <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
           <head>Abstract</head>
           <p xml:lang="en">This article seeks to evaluate how the thought of Bardaisan of
               Edessa was received by later generations of Christians. The article shows that
               the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws of Countries</hi>, a Syriac dialogue in
               which Bardaisan is the main interlocutor, exercised considerable influence in
               both the Greek- and Syriac-speaking worlds. Although later authors tended to
               denigrate Bardaisan’s views on fate and free will as an undue compromise, they
               nevertheless did not hesitate to borrow freely from his cogent anti-
               deterministic arguments and integrate them into their own discourses. But
               Bardaisan’s influence, especially in the Syriac-speaking regions, extended into
               other areas as well: his innovations in the realm of poetry and music, his
               astronomical calculations, his ethnographic discourse, and his anti-Marcionite
               polemics were all appreciated and adapted by subsequent authors. While it is
               well known that later Christians tended to malign Bardaisan’s thought, and
               especially his cosmology, as tainted with heresy, this article favors a more
               nuanced view: alongside the late antique rejection of Bardaisan runs a notable
               current of positive reception of his innovative contributions in the realms of
               science, music, and apologetics.</p>
           </div>
       </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.1" xml:lang="en">  
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan (154–222) composed numerous works on a wide array of theological and
                    philosophical topics, ranging from cosmology to eschatology, from ethnographic
                    surveys to astronomy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi> mentions dialogues composed by
                            Bardaisan against the Marcionites and other heretics, as well as a
                            dialogue <hi rend="italic">On Fate</hi> (<hi rend="italic">h.e</hi>.
                            4.30.1, ed. E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >chwartz</hi> / Th<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >ommsen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Werke II.1. Die
                                Kirchengeschichte</hi>, second edition, GCS N.F. 6,1 (Berlin 1999),
                            392,15–17.21–22). <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi> explicitly refers to
                            a <hi rend="italic">Book of Domnos</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܕܡܢܘܣ</foreign>) and a <hi
                                rend="italic">Book of Mysteries</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܦܪ ܪ̈ܐܙܐ</foreign>). <hi rend="italic"
                                >Book of Domnos</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Prose Refutations</hi> (hereafter cited as <hi
                                rend="italic">PR</hi>), ed. with Engl. transl. C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">itchell</hi> / A<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">evan</hi> / F<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">urkitt</hi>, <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Prose
                                Refutations of Mani, Marcion, and Bardaisan</hi>, 2 vols. (London
                            1912–1921), vol. 2, p. 1 and p. 6,42–43; <hi rend="italic">Book of
                                Mysteries</hi>: <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hymns against Heresies</hi> 56,9, ed. with German transl. E<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">eck</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra haereses</hi>, CSCO
                            169–170 /Syr. 76–77 (Louvain 1957) (hereafter cited as <hi rend="italic"
                                >CH</hi>), text in CSCO 169, 211,22; cf. <hi rend="italic">CH</hi>
                            1,14 (ed. Beck, 4,11). He also notes that Bardaisan composed hymns (<hi
                                rend="italic">CH</hi> 53,5–6, ed. Beck, 203,5–14), and a treatise on
                            the resurrection (<hi rend="italic">Hymns on Nisibis</hi> 51,2–3, ed.
                            with German transl. E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >eck</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Carmina
                                Nisibena</hi>, CSCO 218–219 / Syr. 92–93 [Louvain 1961–1963]).
                            Bardaisan also wrote on astronomical subjects and composed a treatise on
                            India (on these, see below).</p></note> Yet of his large literary output
                    nothing has been preserved in its entirety save the Syriac dialogue known as the
                        <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws of the Countries</hi>, written down by
                    Bardaisan’s disciple Philip, in which Bardaisan is the main interlocutor.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> The <hi
                                rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> is preserved in only one
                            manuscript, BL Syr. add. 14658, fol. 129a–141a, dated by Wright to the
                            seventh century (W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >right</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts
                                in the British Museum</hi>, vol. 3 [London 1872], 1154). This
                            manuscript contains various treatises of philosophical and scientific
                            content (see ibid., 1154–1160).</p></note> The fact that only this was
                    preserved by later generations of Christians is already indicative of its impact
                    upon the late antique church. Yet while Bardaisan’s reflections on free will and
                    fate, as set down in this dialogue, evidently had a long trajectory of influence
                    upon both Syriac and Greek-speaking readers, upon closer inspection it emerges
                    that other aspects of his teachings did so as well. This essay will highlight
                    some areas in which Bardaisan’s oeuvre shaped and challenged subsequent
                    generations of Christians.</p>
            </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1. The Memory of Bardaisan</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Before addressing particular aspects of Bardaisan’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Wirkungs-geschichte</hi>, it will be convenient to trace how the memory of
                    Bardaisan as a person was preserved in Greek, Latin, Syriac, and Arabic
                        literature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            For reasons of space, the Armenian tradition cannot be considered
                            here.</p></note> Although his writings were lost, his remembrance was
                    kept alive by friend and foe alike.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> The (in his view irreconcilable) discrepancies in
                            the reception history of Bardaisan in late antiquity were emphasized by
                            the Dutch scholar T<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >ansma</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Natuur, lot en vrijheid. Bardesanes,
                                de filosoof der Arameeërs en zijn images</hi>, Cahiers bij het
                            Nederlands theologisch tijdschrift 6 (Wageningen 1969).</p></note>
                    Considering the fierce polemics of later Syriac authors, it comes as a surprise
                    to note that many of those late antique writers who mention him express rather
                    an amicable attitude towards the Edessene theologian. Amongst those who
                    expressly value Bardaisan are Julius Africanus (who left the only historical
                    account of a personal encounter with Bardaisan), Eusebius of Caesarea, Didymus
                    the Blind, the anonymous fourth-century author of the <hi rend="italic">Life of
                        Aberkios</hi>, and Jerome.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius Africanus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kestoi</hi> 7.20, ed. and transl. M. Wallraff / C. Scardino / L.
                            Mecella / Ch. Guignard / W. Adler, <hi rend="italic">Cesti: The Extant
                                Fragments</hi>, GCS N.F. 18 (Berlin 2012), 98–103; <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h.e</hi>. 4.30.1,
                            ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Schwartz / Mommsen</hi>, 392,15–17.21–22
                            (praises Bardaisan’s ingenuity); <hi rend="smallcaps">didymus the
                                Blind</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Psalms</hi> 181,8–9 (on
                            Ps. 32), ed. with German transl. A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">esché</hi> / M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ronewald</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Didymus der
                                Blinde, Psalmen-kommentar (Tura-Papyrus)</hi>, vol. 3,
                            Papyrologische Texte und Abhandlungen 8 (Bonn 1969), 182–184 (discusses
                            Bardaisan without a negative comment); <hi rend="italic">Life of
                                Aberkios</hi>, ed. Th<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">issen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">S. Abercii Vita</hi>
                            (Leipzig 1912); <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerome</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vir.
                                ill</hi>. 33, ed. E<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ichardson</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hieronymus, Liber
                                de viris inlustribus. Gennadius, Liber de viris inlustribus</hi>, TU
                            14.1 (Leipzig 1896), 24–25.</p></note> Even Epiphanius, in spite of his
                    objections, cannot but concede that Bardaisan was ἄριστός τις ἀνήρ.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephiphanius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pan</hi>.
                            56.1.2, ed. K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">oll</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Epiphanius, Werke II</hi>, GCS (Leipzig 1922),
                            338,5. English transl. F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">illiams</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Panarion of
                                Epiphanius. Books II and III (Sects 47–80, De Fide)</hi>, Nag
                            Hammadi and Manichaean Studies 36 (Leiden 1994). </p></note> Although
                    several of these authors express some doubt regarding Bardaisan’s orthodoxy –
                    based, of course, on their own later theological perspectives – they all
                    articulate their admiration for the man: his learning, his eloquence, his
                    refutation of heresy, his skill as an archer, his scientific mindset. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Over against this group of predominantly Greek-speaking authors favorably
                    disposed towards the Edessene stand those with a hostile attitude, most of whom
                    flourished in the same Syriac milieu as did Bardaisan. His most outspoken critic
                    was the poet Ephrem (d. 373), yet even he does not hesitate occasionally to
                    borrow from Bardaisan’s ideas – without acknowledgement, to be sure. Eusebius of
                    Emesa (d. ca. 359), who grew up bilingually in Edessa and wrote in Greek,
                    engages with Bardaisan’s views in his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on
                        Genesis</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="Footnote Text1"
                            > The commentary is preserved only in an Armenian version and in Greek
                            and Syriac fragments, ed. F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>P<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">etit</hi> /
                                L<hi rend="smallcaps">. van </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi> /
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">eitenberg</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eusèbe d’Émèse,
                                Commentaire de la Genèse. Texte arménien de l’édition de Venise
                                (1980). Fragments grecs et syriaques. Avec traductions</hi>,
                            Traditio Exegetica Graeca 15 (Louvain 2011); section on Bardaisan on pp.
                            92–95, 212–215, 292–295. See also
                                R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">. ter </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">aar </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">omeny</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A Syrian in Greek
                                Dress. The Use of Greek, Hebrew, and Syriac Biblical Texts in
                                Eusebius of Emesa’s Commentary on Genesis</hi>, Traditio Exegetica
                            Graeca 6 (Louvain 1997), 265–271. Space does not suffice here to discuss
                            to what extent the opinions attributed to Bardaisan by Eusebius of Emesa
                            reflects Bardaisan’s own thought, and to what extent they may represent
                            either later developments among his disciples or heresiological attempts
                            to discredit Bardaisan.</p></note> Significantly, the only two
                    non-biblical authors mentioned by name in this commentary are Bardaisan and
                        Homer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> P<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">etit</hi> /
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">van </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi> / W<hi rend="smallcaps">eitenberg</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Eusèbe d’Émèse</hi>, xxxviii, note 69.</p></note>
                    In the course of the christological controversies of the fifth and sixth
                    centuries, associating one’s opponent with Bardaisan and his theology became a
                    convenient rhetorical tool, but here, too, authors sometimes unintentionally
                    cited passages from Bardaisan’s works that seem to have become part of the
                    common lore.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Cf. L<hi rend="smallcaps">. van </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi>, “Bardaisan and Mani in Philoxenus of
                            Mabbog’s <hi rend="italic">Mēmrē Against Habbib</hi>,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Syriac Polemics. Studies in Honour of Gerrit Jan
                                Reinink</hi>, ed. W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. v. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ekkum</hi> / J<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">rijvers</hi> / A<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">lugkist, OLA 170</hi> (Louvain 2007),
                        77–90.</p></note> A negative memory of Bardaisan is preserved in the
                    heresiological summaries of a much later age, including those by Barḥadbeshabba
                    ʿArbaia (6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent.), Theodore bar Koni (late 8<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> cent.), Moses bar Kepha (d. 903), and Michael the
                    Syrian (12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                        n="11"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Barḥadbeshabba ʿArbaia</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >History</hi> 2.5, ed. F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">au</hi>, <hi rend="italic">La première partie de l’
                                Histoire de Barḥadbešabba ‘Arbaïa. Texte syriaque édité et
                                traduit</hi>, PO 23.2 (1932), 191–192; <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodore
                                bar Koni</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Scholion</hi> 11.49, ed. A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps">cher</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Theodorus bar Kōnī, Liber scholiorum</hi> II, CSCO 69
                            / Syr. 26 (Louvain 1954), 307,20–308,20; French transl. R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">espel</hi> / R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps">raguet</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Théodore bar Koni, Livre des scolies (recension de
                                Séert)</hi>, CSCO 432 / Syr. 188 (Louvain 1982),
                            229f.;<hi rend="smallcaps"> Moses bar Kepha</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Hexaemeron Commentary</hi> 1.14, relevant section
                            ed. F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Patrologia
                                Syriaca</hi> 1.2 (1907), 513–514; section also ed. H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">rijvers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardaiṣan of
                                Edessa</hi>, Studia Semitica Neerlandica 6 (Assen 1966), 98–104;
                            German transl. of the entire treatise
                                L<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">chlimme</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Der
                                Hexaemeronkommentar des Moses bar Kepha. Einleitung, Übersetzung und
                                Untersuchungen</hi>, 2 vols., Göttinger Orientforschungen, 1. Reihe:
                            Syriaca, vol. 14.1–2 (Wiesbaden 1977), passage on Bardaisan in vol. 1,
                            137–140; <hi rend="smallcaps">Michael the Syrian</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Chronicle</hi>, ed. with French transl. J<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >.-</hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">habot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chronique de Michel
                                le Syrien</hi>, 4 vols. (Paris 1899–1910, reprint Brussels 1963),
                            vol. 1, 183–185 (transl.), vol. 4, 109–111 (text).</p></note> On the
                    other hand, some later Syriac authors do express a favorable attitude towards
                    Bardaisan, namely with regard to his scientific understanding of astronomy.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">One reason for this surprising disparate reception within the Greek and Syriac
                    traditions is that fact that in the Syriac-speaking communities of northern
                    Mesopotamia Bardaisanite teachings long continued to be a force to be reckoned
                    with, challenging the established church with doctrines at times much more
                    radical than had been those of Bardaisan himself. Another, and not entirely
                    unconnected reason for this disjunct memory of Bardaisan is that in the Syriac
                    tradition Bardaisan’s name primarily remained associated with his cosmology
                    (later judged to be heretical), whereas Christians in territories to the West of
                    Edessa remembered Bardaisan principally for his capable refutation of astral
                    determinism.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A third and distinct memory of Bardaisan is preserved by later Arabic-speaking
                    authors, many of whom regard him as a dualist (which he was not) and attribute
                    to him otherwise unknown (and most likely inauthentic) works. Ibn al-Nadim, for
                    instance, lists three book titles for Bardaisan that are unknown in the Syriac
                        tradition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ibn al-Nadim</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi>
                            9.1, ed. G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>F<hi rend="smallcaps">lügel</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Kitab al-Fihrist</hi>, 2 vols. (Leipzig
                            1871–1872); transl. B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >odge</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Fihrist of al-Nadīm. A
                                Tenth-Century Survey of Muslim Culture</hi>, 2 vols. (New York
                            1970), vol. 2, 805f. Al-Nadim mentions a <hi rend="italic">Book of Light
                                and Darknes</hi>s, a <hi rend="italic">Book of the Spirituality of
                                the Truth</hi>, and a <hi rend="italic">Book of the Moving and the
                                Static</hi>.</p></note> By and large, the Arabic testimonies to
                    Bardaisan reflect much later concerns with dualist sects and fall outside the
                    scope of this essay.<anchor xml:id="Ref305783540"/><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Important references to the
                            Bardaisanites by Arabic authors can be found in the writings of
                            al-Nadim, al-Warraq, al-Maturidi, and al-Biruni. Some of these are
                            translated and discussed in the following publications: G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>V<hi rend="smallcaps">ajda</hi>, “Le
                            témoigne de al-Māturidī sur la doctrine des Manichéens, des Dayṣānites
                            et des Marcionites,” <hi rend="italic">Arabica</hi> 13 (1966), 1–38;
                                W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps">adelung</hi>,
                            “Abū ʿĪsā al-Warrāq über die Bardesaniten, Marcioniten und Kantäer,” in:
                                <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Geschichte und Kultur des Vorderen
                                Orients. Festschrift für Bertold Spuler zum siebzigsten
                                Geburtstag</hi>, ed. H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">oemer</hi> / A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">oth</hi> (Leiden 1981), 210–224; G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps">onnot</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Islam et religions</hi>, Islam d’hier et d’aujourd’hui
                            27 (Paris 1986), 34–37, 167–168;
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. van </hi>E<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ss</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Theologie und
                                Gesellschaft im 2. und 3. Jahrhundert Hidschra. Eine Geschichte des
                                religiösen Denkens im frühen Islam</hi>, 6 vols. (Berlin 1991–1995),
                            vol. 1 (1991), 426–430 (with further bibliography).</p></note>
                </p>
                </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2. Fate and Free Will</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s refutation of astral determinism, as expressed in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, has had the most obvious impact upon
                    late antique Christianity. This is the only work preserved in its entirety, and
                    it is also the one cited most widely – with or without attribution to Bardaisan
                    – in the patristic literature. The Syriac dialogue has come down to us in a
                    seventh-century manuscript, thus it was still read and copied at that time.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Detailed
                            discussion of the manuscript’s content and its possible Sitz in Leben as
                            a school curriculum may be found in <hi rend="smallcaps">D. King</hi>,
                            “Origenism in Sixth Century Syria: The Case of a Syriac Manuscript on
                            Pagan Philosophy,” in <hi rend="italic">Origenes und sein Erbe in Orient
                                und Okzident</hi>, edited by <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Fürst</hi>
                            (Münster 2011), 179–212. King’s assertion, however, that this collection
                            represents Origenist teachings (see esp. 208–211; elsewhere in the
                            article the subject of Origenism is hardly mentioned) is not wholly
                            convincing.</p></note> Both Greek and Syriac-speaking Christians would
                    have been familiar with Bardaisan’s thought also through reading Eusebius’ <hi
                        rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>, the Syriac version of which
                    likely dates from the fourth century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> The Syriac version of Eusebius’ <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ecclesiastical History</hi> is ed. W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">right</hi> / N<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps">c</hi>L<hi rend="smallcaps">ean</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical History of Eusebius in Syriac,
                                edited from the manuscripts. With a collation of the ancient
                                Armenian version by Adalbert Merx</hi> (Cambridge 1898), the section
                            on Bardaisan is on p. 243f. The Syriac version of the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ecclesiastical History</hi> is extant in several manuscripts; on
                            these, see A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >aumstark</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der syrischen Literatur
                                mit Ausschluß der christlich-palästinensischen Texte</hi> (Bonn
                            1922), 58–59. </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Several early Syriac treatises, such as the <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi> of
                    Ps.- Melito or the <hi rend="italic">Acts of Thomas</hi>, <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ps.-Melito</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>,
                            ed. W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">ureton</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Spicilegium Syriacum: containing remains of Bardesan,
                                Meliton, Ambrose and Mara bar Serapion</hi> (London 1855), 21–31
                            (text), 41–51 (transl.). Space does not permit here a discussion of the
                            relation between the <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> and Ps.-Melito’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Apology</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Acts of
                                Thomas</hi>, respectively.</p></note> contain passages that show
                    close affinities with the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>. This might
                    suggest, as some scholars have posited,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                                I<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">amelli</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardaisan of Edessa.
                                A Reassessment of the Evidence and a New Interpretation</hi>
                            (Piscataway, NJ 2009), 111–114, maintains the <hi rend="italic">Acts of
                                Thomas</hi> “include an unequivocal quotation” from the <hi
                                rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> (p. 111).</p></note> that the
                    respective authors of these treatises were familiar with the Syriac dialogue,
                    but only a close textual analysis can ascertain whether such similarities are
                    not better explained by the authors’ common cultural and intellectual
                    milieu.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem the Syrian in the fourth century was confronted, much like Bardaisan was
                    in the early third, with deep-seated astrological beliefs among members of his
                    community. In his <hi rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies</hi>, the poet
                    specifically targets his congregants’ misguided trust in horoscopes and fate,
                    and at times Ephrem’s arguments are reminiscent of those set forth in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> so that a familiarity with Bardaisan’s
                    most important work appears likely. Bardaisan in the dialogue asserts that fate
                    does not control human free will in ethical matters, nor does it determine
                    natural processes such as bodily growth or the need for nourishment. Prominent
                    among Bardaisan’s examples in support of his claim that fate does not have power
                    over nature, is that not before puberty or in old age are people able to
                    conceive children, regardless of fate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 20, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            572,1–575,3. On Bardaisan’s defense of free will against astral
                            determinism, see for example
                                T<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">egedus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Early Christianity
                                and Ancient Astrology</hi> (New York 2007), 261–278.</p></note> In
                    his hymns, Ephrem employs a very similar rationale to oppose the view that fate
                    is responsible for sexual transgressions, for that would imply that only during
                    a certain age does fate have this power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 4,15, ed.
                            Beck, 17,9–14. In <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 6,12–13, ed. Beck,
                            25,25–26,10, he mentions the example of old age.</p></note> Moreover,
                    Ephrem brings forth several extensive objections to the claim, articulated in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, that fate is the cause of sickness,
                    health, or a person’s social status.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 4,8–11.14;
                            5,4.9–10; 6,2.6 and passim, ed. Beck, 15,22–16,18; 17,3–8; 19,11–16;
                            20,13–24; 23,15–20; 24,16–21.</p></note> Taken alone, any of these
                    arguments would not suffice to establish Ephrem’s familiarity with the Syriac
                    dialogue, but in their entirety they would seem to allow no conclusion other
                    than that Ephrem was well aware of the book’s content.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s rebuttal of astral determinism was still well remembered and
                    appreciated among learned Syriac authors in the early eighth century, for Jacob
                    of Edessa (d. 708) favorably comments on the Bardaisanite refutation of fate in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Hexaemeron</hi>. In this remarkable
                    passage, Jacob recalls how a man from Edessa, who belonged to the school of
                    Bardaisan, capably refuted the astral determinism advocated by an astrologer
                    from Harran.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacob of Edessa</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hexaemeron</hi>, ed. I.-B. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chabot</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, CSCO 92 / Syr. 44
                            (Louvain 1953), 61a,35–62a,24. Jacob even knows the name of the
                            Bardaisanite: Vologeses.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Turning to the reception history of Bardaisan’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi> in Greek patristic literature, it becomes apparent that here,
                    unlike among Syriac authors, Bardaisan’s authorship is generally much more
                    readily acknowledged. Eusebius records in his <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                        History</hi> that Bardaisan’s disciples translated his dialogues from Syriac
                    into Greek,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e</hi>. 4.30.1, ed. Schwartz / Mommsen,
                            392,19–21.</p></note> and we may assume that the <hi rend="italic">Book
                        of the Laws</hi> was among these treatises so that the dialogue would have
                    been available to Greek readers from a very early time.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A long excerpt from the
                    <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws </hi>is contained in the
                    Ps.-Clementine <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi>, a fascinating novel produced
                    in fourth-century Syria that extensively reworks earlier materials. In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> Clement of Rome recounts in the first person
                    his conversion to Christianity, his adventurous journeys with Peter the apostle,
                    and his eventual reunification with his (now likewise converted) family.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Ps.-Clementine
                                <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi>, ed.
                                B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ehm</hi> /
                                G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">trecker</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Pseudoklementinen II: Rekognitionen in Rufins Übersetzung</hi>,
                            second edition, GCS (Berlin 1994); English transl.
                                T<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">mith</hi>, ANF 8 (reprint 1989), 73–211.</p></note>
                    The book includes also lively conversations between the chief protagonists and
                    prolonged theological discourses. In book nine, Clement debates with a defender
                    of astrological fate, and Clement’s counter-arguments here include of a long
                    section lifted from the second part of the <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi> (25–46), without, however, naming either Bardaisan or Philip.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Ps.-Clementine
                                <hi rend="italic">Rec</hi>. 9.19–29, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Rehm</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Strecker</hi>, 270–314. <hi
                                rend="italic">BLC</hi> 25–46, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            582,5–608,13.</p></note> Although parts of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Recognitions</hi> survive in a Syriac translation of the Greek
                        original,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            A Syriac translation of portions from the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ps.-Clementines</hi> is contained in the famous manuscript BL Syr.
                            add. 12150, dated to AD 411 and thereby the oldest dated Syriac
                            manuscript. Ed. of the Syriac in W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>F<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">rankenberg</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Die syrischen
                                Clementinen mit griechischem Paralleltext</hi>, TU 48/3 (Leipzig
                            1937). English transl. F.
                            S.<hi rend="smallcaps"> Jones</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Syriac Pseudo-Clementines. An Early Version of the
                                First Christian Novel</hi> (Turnhout 2014).</p></note> the relevant
                    passage is extant only in the Latin version of Rufinus and shows a number of
                    deviations from the Syriac text of the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>.
                    The encounter between Clement and the defender of astrology (who in the end
                    turns out to be Clement’s father) is narrated in the Ps.-Clementine <hi
                        rend="italic">Homilies</hi> as well, although here the section from the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> is wanting.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Ps.-Clementine <hi
                                rend="italic">Hom</hi>. 14, ed.
                                B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ehm</hi> /
                                G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">trecker</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Pseudo-klementinen I. Homilien</hi>, third edition, GCS (Berlin
                            1992), 204–211.</p></note> The great number of parallels between the <hi
                        rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> has led
                    scholars to postulate the existence of a Ps.-Clementine <hi rend="italic"
                        >Grundschrift</hi> (dated to between 220 and 260), and this <hi
                        rend="italic">Grundschrift</hi> already would have included the sections
                    from Bardaisan’s dialogue.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                                B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ehm</hi>, “Bardesanes in den Pseudoclementinen,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Philologus</hi> 93 (1938), 218–247; F<hi
                                rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ones</hi>, “The Pseudo-Clementines: A History of
                            Research,” <hi rend="italic">Second Century</hi> 2 (1982), 1–33, 63–96;
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps">. Bremmer</hi>,
                            ed., <hi rend="italic">The Pseudo-Clementines</hi>, Studies on Early
                            Christian Apocrypha 10 (Louvain 2010).</p></note> The Ps.-Clementines
                    thus contain the oldest known quotation from the <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi>.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The earliest Greek author explicitly to attribute quotations from the
                    dialogue on fate to Bardaisan is Eusebius, who in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Praeparatio evangelica</hi> excerpts lengthy passages.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Praep. ev</hi>.
                            6.10.1–48, ed. K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >ras</hi> /
                                É<hi rend="smallcaps">. des </hi>P<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">laces</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Werke
                                VIII.1</hi>, second edition, GCS (Berlin 1982), 335,1–343,15.
                        </p></note> The church historian remarks that he quotes from Bardaisan’s
                    dialogues with his companions, but he does not specify a title. The sections
                    cited by Eusebius are almost the same as those quoted in the Ps.-Clementine <hi
                        rend="italic">Recognitions</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> Synoptic printing of all three texts in <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Rehm / Strecker</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Pseudo-klementinen II</hi>, 270–317.</p></note> a fact that has
                    given rise to an extensive scholarly debate concerning the original language of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> and the various intertextual
                    dependencies between the Syriac dialogue, Eusebius, and the Ps.-Clementine <hi
                        rend="italic">Recognitions</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> This question need not be taken up here. See the
                            extensive discussion by R<hi rend="smallcaps">ehm</hi>, “Bardesanes in
                            den Pseudoclementinen.” That the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>
                            originally was composed in Syriac (and not in Greek) has been argued
                            convincingly by Th<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">öldeke</hi>, “Zum ‘Buch der Gesetze der Länder’,”
                                <hi rend="italic">ZDMG</hi> 64 (1910), 555–560. See also F<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps">au</hi>, “Notes
                            d’astronomie syrienne,” <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi>, 10th
                            series, vol. 16 (1910), 209–228, esp. 216–219;
                                G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>L<hi rend="smallcaps">evi della </hi>V<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ida</hi>, “Appunti Bardesanici,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Rivista degli studi orientali</hi> 8 (1919–1920), 709–722.
                        </p></note> Whereas in his <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>
                    Eusebius acknowledges Bardaisan’s contribution to Christian theological
                        discourse,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">h.e</hi>. 4.30, ed. Schwartz / Mommsen,
                            392,14–28.</p></note> in the <hi rend="italic">Praeparatio
                        evangelica</hi> he treats the excerpts from Bardaisan among the
                    non-Christian refutations of astrology<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Praep. ev</hi>.
                            6.9.32 (ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mras / des Places</hi> 334,20–24),
                            introduces the quotation from Bardaisan by stating that now he will
                            produce the arguments of the astrologers against the Chaldeans. In <hi
                                rend="italic">Praep. ev</hi>. 6.10.49 (ed. ibid., 343,17–20), he
                            indicates that the discussion of non-Christian authors is now concluded
                            and that he will move on to Christian authors. In fact, Origen comes
                            next.</p></note> – perhaps because in his Greek <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vorlage</hi>, unlike in the extant Syriac version, Bardaisan does not
                    explicitly identify himself as a Christian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33"
                        n="33"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> In the Syriac dialogue, Bardaisan says,
                            “what shall we say, then, about the new race of us Christians?” (ܡܐܢܐ
                            ܕܝܢ ܢܐܡܪ ܥܠ ܫܪܒܬܐ ܚܕܬܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܕܟܪ̈ܣܛܝܢܐ) (<hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 46,
                            ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>, 607,16–17), whereas Eusebius’ text
                            reads τί δὲ ἐροῦμεν περὶ τῆς τῶν Χριστιανῶν αἱρέσεως (<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Praep. ev</hi>.
                            6.10.45, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mras / des Places,</hi>
                            342,23–24).</p></note> The church historian first quotes a segment in
                    which Bardaisan outlines the respective powers of nature and free will (<hi
                        rend="italic">BLC</hi> 15–16) and then produces a long passage of νόμιμα
                    βαρβαρικά from the dialogue’s latter part (<hi rend="italic"
                        >BLC</hi> 25–47).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 15–16 and 25–47, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Nau</hi>, 558,10–562,3; 582,5–610,7.</p></note> For understanding
                    the dissemination of Bardaisan’s dialogue it is vitally important to note that
                    Eusebius – unlike the Ps.-Clementine <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> – cites
                    from two separate sections of the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>.
                    Eusebius thus had access to the entire dialogue, whereas the author of the
                    Ps.-Clementine <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> reveals familiarity only with
                    the second, ethnographic part of this work.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The famous Antiochene exegete Diodore of Tarsus (d. ca. 390) takes up the subject
                    of fate and free will in his κατὰ εἱμαρμένης. This book is now lost, but we are
                    well informed of its arguments through the summary provided by the ninth-
                    century Constantinopolitan patriarch Photios in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Library</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Photios</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bibl</hi>. 223
                            (208b–222a), ed. R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">enry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Photius,
                                Bibliothèque</hi>, vol. 4 (Paris 1991), 8–48.</p></note> Right at
                    the beginning of his synopsis, Photios favorably comments that Diodore (whose
                    theology he apparently generally does not much appreciate) set forth a clear and
                    zealous refutation of Bardaisan’s doctrines in the fifty-first chapter of his
                    treatise. According to the patriarch, Diodore began this section by summarily
                    criticizing Bardaisan’s position as a half-hearted compromise, because his
                    discourse freed the soul from fate but kept the body and all which concerns it
                    subject to fate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Photios</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bibl</hi>. 223
                            (208b), ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi>, 8,18–9,32.</p></note> It is
                    likely that Diodore regarded Bardaisan’s coherent and well- argued position as a
                    particular threat to his own anthropology and therefore wished to raise
                    objections to it already at the beginning of his treatise <hi rend="italic">On
                        Fate</hi>. Bardaisan’s theology apparently was still a force to be reckoned
                    with at the end of the fourth century. After surveying Diodore’s refutation,
                    Photios in due course rehearses several specific points brought forth by the
                    Antiochene exegete against Bardaisan. Diodore challenged Bardaisan’s theory on
                    biblical, theological, and philosophical grounds.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Photios</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bibl</hi>. 223
                            (221b–222a), ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi>,
                        45,12–47,16.</p></note> Much of Diodore’s reasoning against fate elsewhere
                    in this treatise rests on anti-deterministic arguments in the tradition of
                    Carneades, which, of course, were also employed by Bardaisan.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Cf.
                                E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">mand de Mendieta</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fatalisme
                                et liberté dans l’antiquité grecque. Recherches sur la survivance de
                                l’argumentation morale antifataliste de Carnéade chez les
                                philosophes grecs et les théologiens chrétiens des quatre premiers
                                siècles</hi> (Louvain 1945). On Bardaisan’s notion of fate and its
                            relation to Alexander of Aphrodisias, see A. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Dihle</hi>, “Zur Schicksalslehre des Bardesanes,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Kerygma und Logos. Beiträge zu den
                                geistesgeschichtlichen Beziehungen zwischen Antike und Christentum.
                                Festschrift für Carl Andresen zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, edited by A.
                            M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ritter</hi> (Göttingen 1979),
                        123–135.</p></note> Interestingly, certain parallels between Diodore and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> are apparent,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> For instance, in 215b
                            Diodore stresses that unlike the behavior of various animals, human
                            action exhibits much variety, so that it consequently cannot possibly be
                            determined by fate (ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi>, 28,6–29,28). In
                            218a Diodore refers to the customs of Jews and Christians as counter
                            examples (ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi>, 35,13–36,33).</p></note>
                    so that the question presents itself to what degree Diodore might have mined his
                    opponent’s dialogue for those kinds of arguments that well suited his
                    agenda.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The reception history of Bardaisan’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>
                    continues well into Byzantine times. In the sixth century, an anonymous author
                    attributed certain theological dialogues to Caesarius, the brother of Gregory of
                    Nazianzus, and these treatises show familiarity with the <hi rend="italic">Book
                        of the Laws</hi>. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ps.-Caesarius</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Erotapokriseis</hi>, ed.
                                R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iedinger</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Kaisarios,
                                Die Erotapokriseis</hi>, GCS (Berlin 1989), 83–87. Older ed. in PG
                            38 (1862), 977–987 (= <hi rend="italic">dial</hi>. 2, 109–110). On this
                            author, see R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >iedinger</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Kaisarios.
                                Überlieferungsgeschichte und Verfasserfrage</hi>, Byzantinisches
                            Archiv 12 (München 1969). Brief overview in
                                D<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">amos-</hi>L<hi rend="smallcaps">issón</hi>,
                            “Pseudo-Caesarius,” <hi rend="italic">LThK</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                                >3</hi> 8 (1999), 708.</p></note> In the ninth century, the
                    historian George Harmatolos quotes from the <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">George Hamartolos</hi>, ed.
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ramer,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Anecdota Graeca Bibliothecarum Oxoniensium</hi>,
                            vol. 4 (Oxford 1837, reprint Amsterdam 1963), 236–237. Brief overview of
                            George in A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi rend="smallcaps">azhdan</hi>
                            / A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">utler</hi>, “George
                            Hamartolos,” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium</hi> 2
                            (1991), 836.</p></note> But inasmuch as George mentions Caesarius
                    directly prior to his discussion of Bardaisan, and since the two passages
                    contain many parallels, it appears likely that George may have derived his
                    knowledge from Ps.-Caesarius, as already A. Hilgenfeld surmised.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                                A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ilgenfeld</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes, der
                                letzte Gnostiker</hi> (Leipzig 1864), 93.</p></note> Finally, a
                    reference to Bardaisan occurs in the <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                        History</hi> composed by Nikephoros Kallistos in the early part of the
                    fourteenth century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nikephoros Kallistos</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >h.e.</hi> 4.11, PG 145 (1904), 1001.</p></note> Much of what
                    Nikephoros writes about the Edessene is taken directly – at times even verbatim
                    – from Eusebius’ <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>, but his account
                    also includes an interesting detail that remains without parallel in the Greek
                    patristic literature,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> Noteworthy is Nikephoros’ statement in the
                            dialogue that Bardaisan characterized the “Father of the Logos” (PG 145,
                            1001). However, the section in Nikephoros is only brief and no definite
                            conclusions can be drawn from it.</p></note> so that one is led to
                    wonder if, perhaps, he was acquainted with some of Bardaisan’s treatises. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Of all of Bardaisan’s works, the <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi> clearly is the one with the most significant impact upon late
                    antique Christianity. Although Bardaisan was often criticized for entering a
                    compromise on the subject of fate and thereby ceding too much to the power of
                    the stars, the arguments set forth in his dialogue favorably impressed later
                    generations of theologians and provided useful resources for the ongoing
                    refutation of astral determinism. Yet Bardaisan’s influence upon Christian
                    thought, especially in his native Syriac tradition, far exceeds his reflections
                    on fate and free will and pertains to many other areas as well. Some of these
                    will be outlined in the remainder of this essay.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>3. Poetry and Madrashe</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The Syriac Christian tradition is rightly famous for its abundance of
                    imaginative religious poetry, a feature that has characterized it from its
                    inception. What constitutes perhaps the oldest extant literary text in Syriac,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Odes of Solomon</hi>, is a collection of hymns.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Odes of Solomon</hi>, ed.
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">harlesworth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Odes of
                                Solomon. The Syriac texts, edited with translation and notes</hi>,
                            SBL Texts and Translations 13, Pseudepigrapha 7 (Chico, CA 1977); also
                            ed. with German transl.
                                M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>L<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">attke</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Oden Salomos. Text,
                                Übersetzung, Kommentar</hi>, 3 vols., Novum Testamentum et Orbis
                            Antiquus 41 (Göttingen 1999–2005). Scholarly opinion varies as to the
                            date and original language of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Odes</hi>.</p></note> The <hi rend="italic">Acts of Thomas</hi>, dating to
                    the early third century, incorporate poetic material. And Bardaisan, too, wrote
                    hymns and psalms – one hundred and fifty of them in imitation of the psalms of
                    David, Ephrem claims. Ephrem speaks of Bardaisan as a composer of both hymns
                    (ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ) and psalms (ܙܡܝܪ̈ܬܐ),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 53,5–6;
                            54,1, ed. Beck, 203,5–14; 204,25–205,3. </p></note> and his remarks
                    suggest that in the Syriac world it was Bardaisan who first set the previously
                    existing literary genre of <hi rend="italic">madrasha</hi> to music.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 53,5, ed.
                            Beck, 203,5–9. See
                                K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">c</hi>V<hi rend="smallcaps">ey</hi>, “Were the
                            Earliest <hi rend="italic">Madrašē</hi> Songs or Recitations?” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">After Bardaisan. Studies on Continuity and Change in
                                Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professor Han J. W. Drijvers</hi>,
                            ed. G<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">einink</hi> / A<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">lugkist</hi>, OLA 89 (Louvain 1999), 185–199, esp.
                            187–190.</p></note> Bardaisan’s son is said to have continued in the
                    footsteps of his father and to have composed chants.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">PR</hi> II, 221. See
                            also the passages in Sozomen and Theodoret, cited below in n. 49.
                        </p></note> These Bardaisanite <hi rend="italic">madrashe</hi> significantly
                    influenced the Syriac tradition, for Ephrem in the later fourth century laments
                    that Bardaisan’s followers still chant these hymns with their altogether
                    objectionable content.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 1,17, ed. Beck, 5,1–3.</p></note> According to
                    the fifth-century Greek church historians Sozomen and Theodoret, Ephrem
                    consequently set out himself to compose <hi rend="italic">madrashe</hi> with
                    orthodox content, so that the tunes championed by Bardaisan and his son could
                    now be sung without causing doctrinal offense.<anchor xml:id="Ref305947697"
                        /><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sozomen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">h.e.</hi> 3.16.5–7;
                            ed. J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">idez</hi> /
                                G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ansen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Sozomenus,
                                Kirchengeschichte</hi>, second edition, GCS N.F. 4 (Berlin 1995),
                            128,15–129,8; <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodoret</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >h.e</hi>. 4.29.2–3, ed. L<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>P<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">armentier</hi> / G<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ansen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Theodoret,
                                Kirchengeschichte</hi>, third edition, GCS N.F. 5 (Berlin 1998),
                            269,13–18.</p></note> Bardaisan, even if he cannot be credited with
                    having invented the genre of <hi rend="italic">madrasha</hi>, appears to have
                    been the earliest among the Syriac Christians to enhance this poetic form with
                    music. He was a pioneer in setting poetry to music, and he did so with great and
                    long-lasting success. From Ephrem’s comments and the few extant fragments of
                    Bardaisan’s poetry, we can gather that certain of his hymns had educational
                    theological content, discussing, for example, the doctrine of creation.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> H. H. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Schaeder</hi> argued that the heresiological
                            summary by Theodore bar Koni contains excerpts from Bardaisan’s
                            writings, cf. H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">chaeder</hi>, “Bardesanes von Edessa in der
                            Überlieferung der griechischen und der syrischen Kirche,” <hi
                                rend="italic">ZKG</hi> 51 (1932), 21–73, esp. 47–49. In <hi
                                rend="italic">CH</hi> 55, Ephrem quotes fragments of hymns
                            attributed to Bardaisan’s followers. These fragments seem to relate a
                            cosmogonic myth. </p></note> Thereby Bardaisan’s hymns constitute the
                    oldest Syriac <hi rend="italic">madrashe</hi> (a term derived from <hi
                        rend="italic">drš</hi>, ‘to instruct’) that have come down to us,
                    ‘teaching-songs’ in the true meaning of the word.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Some of Bardaisan’s theological poems were apparently not only
                    popular but also sufficiently orthodox to become disconnected from their
                    author’s name and to enter the mainstream of the Syriac tradition. In the late
                    fifth century, Philoxenus of Mabbug and the deacon Habbib engaged in a literary
                    controversy on christology, in the course of which Philoxenus articulated his
                    own miaphysite stance as follows:</p>
                <p rend="Quote1">And the Ancient of Ages became a child,</p>
                <p rend="Quote1">and the Most High a baby in the womb,</p>
                <p rend="Quote1">and God became human in the womb,</p>
                <p rend="Quote1">and the spiritual (became) bodily.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                        n="52"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Philoxenus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Letter to the
                                Monasteries</hi>, ed. M<hi rend="smallcaps">. Brière</hi> /
                                F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">raffin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes decem
                                de uno et sancto Trinitate incorporate et passo</hi>, PO 41.1
                            (1982), 44,10–12.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The well-read Habbib<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> See Habbib’s own statement, quoted by Philoxenus
                            in <hi rend="italic">Diss</hi>. 3,12, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Brière</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Graffin</hi>, PO 38.3, 486,4–6;
                            cf. <hi rend="smallcaps">van </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi>, “Bardaisan and Mani,” 81. On
                            Philoxenus’ objections to Habbib’s reading list, see <hi rend="italic"
                                >Diss</hi>. 10, 189–190, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Brière</hi> / <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Graffin</hi>, PO 40.2 (1980), 344–346.</p></note>
                    claimed at once to have recognized the phrase “the Ancient of Ages became a
                    child, and God a baby in the womb” as originating from none other than
                    Bardaisan, and he lost no time in accusing Philoxenus of borrowing from a
                        heretic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Philoxenus, <hi rend="italic">Diss</hi>., ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Brière</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Graffin</hi>, PO 41.1, Paris
                            1982, 14,27–16,2 (no. 17); cf. PO 41.1, 16,23–24 (no. 22); <hi
                                rend="italic">Diss</hi>. 1, 35, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Brière,</hi> PO 15.4 (1920), 464,11–12.</p></note> Philoxenus’ own
                    defense against Habbib’s accusation is rather weak and gives the impression that
                    Bardaisan indeed was the author of this metric passage.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> On the details of the debate
                            between Philoxenus and Habbib, see
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">van </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi>, “Bardaisan and Mani.” </p></note> This
                    episode illustrates the power and persuasiveness that Bardaisan’s poetry exerted
                    for centuries to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.5" xml:lang="en">
                <head>4. Astronomy</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan declares in the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>
                    that formerly he himself had belonged to the Chaldeans, that is to the
                    astrologers whose teachings he now so effectively opposes.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 16, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            564,19–23.</p></note> After his conversion to Christianity, he outright
                    rejected the central tenets of astral determinism and upheld human freedom in
                    ethical matters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> Bardaisan upheld that astral phenomena can have
                            some influence over factors that are beyond the control of human beings
                            or the laws of nature, such as sickness or poverty that do occur but are
                            generally undesired. This proposition made him unacceptable to the later
                            normative church.</p></note> As is well known, astrology and astronomy
                    went hand in hand in antiquity and one cannot always clearly distinguish between
                    the two. And while Bardaisan’s counter- arguments in the <hi rend="italic">Book
                        of the Laws</hi> reveal his easy familiarity with astrological doctrines
                    (which he now opposes), other texts demonstrate that he was also well acquainted
                    with astronomy. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It may come as a surprise to realize that, in fact, later Syriac
                    Christians admired him for his specialized astronomical knowledge and upheld his
                    scientific inquiry as exemplary. In the seventh century, Severus Sebokht, the
                    learned bishop and monk at Qenneshre,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> On the intellectual life in the monastery, see
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Tannous</hi>, “You Are What You Read:
                            Qenneshre and the Miaphysite Church in the Seventh Century,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">History and Identity in the Late Antique Near
                                East</hi>, edited
                            by<hi rend="smallcaps"> Ph. Wood</hi> (Oxford
                            2013), 83–102. On Severus at Qenneshre, see É. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Villey</hi>, “Qennešre et l’astronomie aux VIe et VIIe siècles,”
                            in: <hi rend="italic">Les sciences en syriaque</hi>, edited by É. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Villey</hi>, Études syriaques 11 (Paris 2014),
                            149–190.</p></note> proudly points out that Bardaisan’s astronomical
                    insights undeniably demonstrate that not only pagans but also Syriac Christians
                    were well versed in this discipline.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> N<hi rend="smallcaps">au</hi>, “Notes
                            d’astronomie syrienne,” 211,20–212,1. See also
                                E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">eich</hi>, “Ein Brief des Severus Sēḇōḵt,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Sic itur ad astra. Studien zur Geschichte der
                                Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften. Festschrift für den Arabisten
                                Paul Kunitzsch zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, ed. M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>F<hi rend="smallcaps">olkerts</hi> /
                                R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>L<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">orch</hi> (Wiesbaden 2000), 478–489.</p></note> In
                    the eighth century, George, the bishop of the Arab tribes (d. 724), similarly
                    takes recourse to the astronomical calculations of the Bardaisanites in a letter
                    addressed to the stylite John of Litharb who had, among other things, inquired
                    about the rising times of the zodiacal signs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                        n="60"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> George, <hi rend="italic">ep</hi>. 1 (dated
                            714 AD), ed. V<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">yssel</hi>, “Die astronomischen Briefe Georgs des
                            Araberbischofs,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Assyriologie</hi> 8
                            (1893), 1–55, esp. 19,7–20,11. To be precise, George refers not to
                            Bardaisan, but to the “Bardaisanites.” The scientific background and
                            relevance of the particular astronomical topics that are discussed by
                            George and by Severus Sebokht need not be addressed here. For this, see
                            the relevant sections in my forthcoming monograph on
                        Bardaisan.</p></note> Precise knowledge of the rising times was important
                    for astrology, but it also allowed one to calculate the length of day and night
                    for a particular date. Christians most likely were interested in such
                    computations in order to determine the date of moveable feasts such as
                        Easter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Cf. <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ep</hi>. 1, ed.
                                R<hi rend="smallcaps">yssel</hi>, “Die astronomischen Briefe,”
                            8–11.</p></note> Significantly, Bishop George here endorses Bardaisan’s
                    scientific accomplishments as a solid base for calculations of astral phenomena,
                    and he does not at all associate him with astrology. This is not due, as one
                    might surmise, to George not being able adequately to distinguish between
                    astronomy and astrology, for in another letter to the same John of Litharb,
                    George vehemently rejects the claims of the “demonic astrologers.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ep</hi>. 2 (dated
                            716), ed. R<hi rend="smallcaps">yssel</hi>, “Die astronomischen Briefe,”
                            24–25.</p></note> A further illustration of Bardaisan’s astronomical
                    interest comes from a short manuscript notice on the names for the zodiacal
                    signs as they were used by the Bardaisanites.<anchor xml:id="Ref511140630"
                        /><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Ed.
                                E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">achau</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Inedita syriaca. Eine
                                Sammlung syrischer Übersetzungen von Schriften griechischer
                                Profanliteratur. Mit einem Anhang. Aus den Handschriften des
                                Britischen Museums herausgegeben</hi> (Wien 1870, reprint Hildesheim
                            1968), 126. </p></note> This brief segment is preserved in the same
                    manuscript as is the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, but it does not
                    immediately follow upon the dialogue.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> In the manuscript BL Syr. add. 14658, the <hi
                                rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> (the eleventh text in this
                            manuscript) is followed by a treatise by Sergius of Reshʿaina <hi
                                rend="italic">On the Motion of the Moon</hi> and a short appendix
                            thereto (<hi rend="italic">On the Motion of the Sun</hi>), then follows
                            the notice on the names of the signs of the zodiac; cf. W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">right</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol.
                            3, 1158.</p></note> As with the rising times, the signs of the zodiac
                    were certainly relevant to astrology, but they were occasionally also discussed
                    by Christian intellectuals for their scientific relevance, as the letter by
                    George, the bishop of the Arab tribes, illustrates.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> On the terminology for the
                            signs of the zodiac used by George, see his letter to John of Litharb,
                            ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Ryssel</hi>, 19–21. This is the same passage in
                            which George discusses the rising times of the signs of the
                        zodiac.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">These various testimonies show that Bardaisan was known and
                    appreciated by later Syriac Christians for his astronomical insights and helpful
                    calculations. We can thus concur with the view voiced already by François Nau
                    more than a hundred years ago, based on his reading of two of the
                    above-mentioned sources:  “Les deux textes nous montrent encore que les
                    préoccupations de Bardesane étaient d’ordre astronomique et géographique et
                    n’avaient aucun rapport avec les fantaisies théurgiques que les auteurs
                    postérieurs lui ont attribuées en l’adjoignant à Manès.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                                F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">au</hi>, “La cosmographie au VIIe siècle chez les
                            Syriens,” <hi rend="italic">Revue de l’Orient Chrétien</hi> 15 (1910),
                            225–254, quote on p. 227.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.6" xml:lang="en">
                <head>5. Ethnography</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s broad ethnographic interest becomes quickly apparent to
                    the reader of the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, for in the dialogue
                    he reports at length on the various customs and rituals of other peoples. Both
                    the sources employed by him and the later reception history of the diverse
                    ethnographic material compiled in this treatise merit further research. Here,
                    however, I should like to confine myself to some remarks on Bardaisan’s interest
                    in Indian culture and religion. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, Indian customs play
                    an important role and are mentioned in several passages. Bardaisan begins his
                    list of the laws of the countries, presented in the second half of the treatise,
                    with the Seres and then immediately moves on to the Indians. He describes the
                    norms of life common among the ascetic Brahmans as well as the lifestyle of
                    those who are not Brahmans.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 27–28, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            583,27–584,25.</p></note> Later on in the dialogue he again takes up the
                    customs of the Indians, now elaborating on their funerary rites.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 39, ed. Nau, 596,13–20; <hi rend="italic"
                                >BLC</hi> 40, ed. Nau, 599,4–8.</p></note> Moreover, the large
                    territory of India serves him as a suitable example to show that within one
                    climate zone a variety of customs can exist side by side, thus repudiating the
                    Chaldean doctrine that one of the planets rules over each of the seven <hi
                        rend="italic">climata</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> BLC 42, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            600,22–26. On the theory of seven climata, see
                                E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">onigmann</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Die sieben Klimata
                                und die ΠΟΛΕΙΣ ΕΠΙΣΗΜΟΙ. Eine Untersuchung zur Geschichte der
                                Geographie und Astrologie im Altertum und Mittelalter</hi>
                            (Heidelberg 1929).</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s curiosity about India led him to engage with an Indian
                    delegation which he encountered, probably in Edessa, while they passed through
                    the region <hi rend="italic">en route</hi> to Emperor Elagabalus (218–222). In
                    his writings he rehearses some of what he had learned from them, and fragments
                    of his reflections on India have come down to us through the Neo-Platonist
                    philosopher Porphyry (d. 305). In his treatise <hi rend="italic">On the
                        Styx</hi>, Porphyry preserves a passage from Bardaisan in which the Edessene
                    describes an ordeal by water common among the Brahmans. In the same treatise,
                    Porphyry presents another excerpt in which Bardaisan describes an androgynous
                    cosmogonic statue, as it were a prototype of creation, that is said to be
                    located in a grotto in India. In this cave, Brahmans purportedly assemble for
                    prayer, debate the statue’s meaning, and undergo a ritual of
                        self-examination.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Porphyry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">De Styge</hi> (=
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stobaios</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Florilegium</hi>. 1.3.56), ed. F. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacoby</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">FGH</hi> 3C (Leiden 1958), no. 719, Fragm. 1, p.
                            643–645. Ed. with German transl.
                                F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">inter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes von Edessa
                                über Indien. Ein früher syrischer Theologe schreibt über ein fremdes
                                Land</hi>, Frühes Christentum. Forschungen und Perspektiven 5 (Thaur
                            1999), 37–40, 47–55. For the most recent discussion of these fragments,
                            see the excellent study by I. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Tanaseanu-Döbler,</hi> “Bemerkungen zu Porphyrios und Bardaiṣan,”
                                <hi rend="italic">ZAC</hi> 19 (2015), 26–68.</p></note> Porphyry’s
                    interest in Bardaisan’s work on India becomes evident also in his treatise <hi
                        rend="italic">On Abstinence</hi>, where he cites a lengthy passage from
                    Bardaisan that describes the customs of the Indian Brahmans and of the
                        ‘Samaneans’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Porphyry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">De abst</hi>.
                            4.17, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacoby</hi>, <hi rend="italic">FGH</hi>
                            3C, no. 719, Fragm. 2, p. 645–647. Ed. with German transl. W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">inter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes</hi>,
                            41–43, 56–62. Engl. transl.
                                T<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>T<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">aylor</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Porphyry, On
                                Abstinence from Animal Food</hi> (London 1965).</p></note> (the
                    latter of which are to be identified with Buddhist monks).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >inter</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes</hi>, 141–142 and passim;
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tanaseanu-Döbler,</hi> “Bemerkungen,”
                            59–60.</p></note> Via Porphyry’s works Bardaisan’s ethnographic
                    observations became available to a wider audience, including late antique
                    Christian authors. Jerome, for instance, in his <hi rend="italic">Against
                        Jovinian</hi> takes over directly from Porphyry illustrative examples of how
                    various pagan and Jewish groups practice asceticism, and he includes the
                    striking illustration pertaining to India provided by Bardaisan.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerome</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Against
                                Jovinian</hi> 2.14, PL 23, 304. Close textual analysis shows that it
                            is unlikely that Jerome drew on Bardaisan’s works directly.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">We do not know how far-reaching the influence of Bardaisan’s
                    ethnographic discourses was in late antiquity, but the examples shown above make
                    manifest that his reflections on India certainly enjoyed a wider audience.
                    Several passages were favorably cited by the pagan intellectual Porphyry, and
                    Jerome’s <hi rend="italic">Against Jovinian</hi> reveals that Bardaisan’s
                    observations on foreign cultures were well received by patristic authors as
                    well.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.7" xml:lang="en">
                <head>6. Cosmology</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s cosmology, which does not seem to have had much of an
                    afterlife among Greek intellectuals, constitutes the aspect of his oeuvre most
                    controversial among later Syriac authors. Although the <hi rend="italic">Book of
                        the Laws</hi> offers only a sketchy picture of Bardaisan’s cosmology, it
                    nevertheless clearly affirms that Bardaisan believed God to be the creator of
                    the world and humankind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 1, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            536,11–14; <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 19, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Nau</hi>, 567,24–568,1.</p></note> Regarding the heavenly bodies,
                    Bardaisan maintains in the dialogue that these, too, are created entities and
                    subject to the divine commandments.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 19, ed. Nau, 567,26–568,6; <hi rend="italic"
                                >BLC</hi> 8, ed. Nau, 544,14–24.</p></note> He posits that the
                    heavenly bodies were endowed with a certain kind of freedom – a view resonating
                    with the statement in Gen. 1:17 according to which the heavenly bodies were
                    given power to rule over day and night<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Another biblical passage that might have
                            motivated Bardaisan to this statement is Isa. 45:12, where God exclaims,
                            “I have given commandments to all the stars.” This verse is among
                            biblical passages cited by Origen in support of his view that the
                            heavenly bodies are rational beings. <hi rend="smallcaps">Origen</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">De princ.</hi> 1.7.3, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Koetschau</hi>, 88,11–12. On Bardaisan’s use of Scripture more
                            broadly, see my forthcoming article “Bardaisan and the Bible.” See also
                            A. C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>“Bardaisan
                            and the Bible,” in: <hi rend="italic">Gnose et manichéisme: entre les
                                oasis d’Egypte et la route de la soie: hommage à Jean-Daniel
                                Dubois</hi>, edited by <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Van den Kerchove</hi>
                            / <hi rend="smallcaps">G. Soares Santoprete</hi> (Turnhout 2017),
                            699–715.</p></note> – and that based on the use they make of their
                    freedom, they too will be judged on the last day.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 9, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            548,15–19.</p></note> This understanding of the heavenly bodies in some
                    respects resembles the ideas articulated by Origen in <hi rend="italic">On First
                        Principles</hi>, who likewise maintains that the heavenly bodies are
                    rational beings endowed with free will.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Origen</hi>, <hi rend="italic">De princ</hi>.
                            1.7.2–1.7.3, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Koetschau</hi>. On this subject,
                            see my “Bardaisan and Origen on Fate and the Power of the Stars,” <hi
                                rend="italic">JECS</hi> 20 (2012), 515–541. Possible parallels
                            between the thought of Bardaisan and Origen are also addressed by
                                I<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">amelli</hi>, “Origen, Bardaiṣan, and the Origin of
                            Universal Salvation,”<hi rend="italic">HTR</hi> 102 (2009),
                        135–168.</p></note> One cannot be sure whether this constitutes an instance
                    of Bardaisan’s influence upon the great Alexandrian theologian, or if any
                    similarities between the thought of the Edessene and Origen – of which there are
                    more – arise out of them reflecting upon the same questions and on the same
                    biblical passages within a very similar cultural milieu.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> hints at Bardaisan’s
                    belief that the world was created out of pre-existing substances,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 8, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            547,10–12; <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 46, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Nau</hi>, 611,10–15.</p></note> a notion not without parallel among
                    early Christian writers. Justin Martyr, for instance, upheld the view that the
                    world was made from “unformed matter” (ἐξ ἀμόρφου ὕλης).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Justin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">1 Apol</hi>. 10.2,
                            ed. M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">arcovich</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Iustini Martyris
                                Apologiae pro Christianis</hi>, PTS 38 (Berlin 1994),
                        45,7.</p></note> Harmonizing the accounts given by Plato in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> and by Moses in Genesis 1:2, Justin elaborates:
                    “So by God’s word the whole universe was made out of this substratum (ἐκ τῶν
                    ὑποκειμένων), as expounded by Moses, and Plato and those who agree with him, as
                    well as we, have learned it [from him].”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Justin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">1 Apol</hi>. 59, ed.
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Marcovich</hi>, 115,10–11; transl. C. C. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Richardson,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Early Christian Fathers</hi> (New York 1970), <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">280</hi>.</p></note> Hermogenes (fl. 175–205)<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                                M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">urst</hi>, “Hermogenes,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >LThK</hi><hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 5 (1996), 13.</p></note> too
                    interprets the Genesis account of creation, not unlike Bardaisan, in such a way
                    that led him to postulate the existence of several uncreated primal elements
                    (darkness, the abyss, the spirit, and water).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83"
                        n="83"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tertullian</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Adversus
                                Hermogenem</hi> 23.1, 30.1, 41–43, and passim, ed.
                                F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">hapot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Tertullien, Contre
                                Hermogène</hi>, SC 439 (Paris 1999), 140–142, 158–160, 188–194. On
                            Hermogenes and his teachings, see K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">reschat</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Apelles und
                                Hermogenes. Zwei theologische Lehrer des zweiten Jahrhunderts</hi>,
                            Vigiliae Christianae Supplements 48 (Leiden 2000), esp. 148–166, 224f.
                            Brief outline of Bardaisan’s cosmogony in my “Die Schöpfungstheologie
                            des Bardaisan von Edessa,” in: <hi rend="italic">Edessa in
                                hellenistisch-römischer Zeit. Religion, Kultur und Politik zwischen
                                Ost und West. Beiträge des internationalen Edessa-Symposiums in
                                Halle an der Saale, 14.–17. Juli 2005</hi>, ed. L<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi rend="smallcaps">reisiger</hi> / C<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps">ammelt</hi> / J<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>T<hi rend="smallcaps">ubach</hi>, Beiruter
                            Texte und Studien 116 (Beirut 2009), 219–229; see also A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani</hi>, “Note
                            bardesanitiche,” <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea Marciana</hi> 12 (1997),
                            11–43; A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani</hi>,
                            “Rivisitando Bardesane: Note sulle fonti siriache del bardesanismo e
                            sulla sua collocazione storico-religiosa,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Cristianesimo nella storia</hi> 19 (1998), 519–596; A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani</hi>,
                            “Bardesane et bardésanites,” <hi rend="italic">École pratique des hautes
                                études. Section des sciences religieuses Annuaire. Résumé des
                                conférences et travaux</hi> 112 (2003–2004), 29–50 (includes
                            discussion of an unedited fragment on Bardaisan’s cosmogony in the
                            Hexaemeron commentary by Moses bar Kepha).</p></note> In the second
                    century, when Bardaisan formulated his cosmology, a belief in pre-existing
                    substances was thus held by several Christian intellectuals, but in a later age,
                    when the doctrine of a <hi rend="italic">creatio ex nihilo</hi> had emerged as a
                    broad consensus among theologians,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> See the comprehensive study by
                                G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ay</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Schöpfung aus dem
                                Nichts. Die Entstehung der Lehre von der creatio ex nihilo</hi>,
                            Arbeiten zur Kirchengeschichte 48 (Berlin 1978). On Jewish discussions
                            of the subject, see M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iehoff</hi>, “<hi rend="italic">Creatio ex
                                Nihilo</hi> Theology in <hi rend="italic">Genesis Rabbah</hi> in
                            Light of Christian Exegesis,” <hi rend="italic">HTR</hi> 99 (2005),
                            37–64; M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ister</hi>, “Tohu wa-Bohu, Primordial Elements and
                            Creatio ex Nihilo,” <hi rend="italic">Jewish Studies Quarterly</hi> 14
                            (2007), 229–256. On the Syriac Christian interpretation of Gen. 1:2, see
                                A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi rend="smallcaps">uillaumont</hi>,
                            “Genèse 1,1–2 selon les commentateurs syriaques,” in: <hi rend="italic"
                                >In Principio. Interprétations des premiers versets de la
                                Genèse</hi>, Collections des Études Augustiniennes. Série Antiquité
                            38 (Paris 1973), 115–132; S<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">rock</hi>, “The <hi rend="italic">Ruaḥ Elōhīm</hi>
                            of Gen 1,2 and its Reception History in the Syriac Tradition,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">Lectures et relectures de la Bible. Festschrift P.-M.
                                Bogaert</hi>, ed. J<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >.-</hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">uwers</hi> / A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">énin</hi>, Bibliotheca Ephemeridum Theologicarum
                            Lovaniensium 144 (Louvain 1999), 327–349.</p></note> the presupposition
                    of some sort of primordial matter came to be regarded as an outrageous heresy.
                    The fact that Bardaisan’s followers continued to uphold the idea of primordial
                    matter and that, moreover, they appear to have developed his doctrines further
                    into a dualist direction,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">PR</hi> II, 227,2–6.</p></note> relegated them to a
                    place far outside the mainline tradition.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This process can be illustrated by the shifting role attributed to
                    the darkness in the Bardaisanite cosmogony. The <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Laws</hi>, in which the creation of the world receives some attention, never
                    even mentions the darkness. In the Syriac dialogue Bardaisan firmly rejects
                    dualist notions,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 1, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            536,11–12.</p></note> and this makes it highly unlikely that he would
                    have regarded the darkness as some kind of evil entity. On the other hand, since
                    it can be shown that Bardaisan, as a Christian theologian, developed his
                    cosmogony in light of the Genesis account, it would be surprising that the
                    darkness (which features so prominently in Gen 1:2–5) should not have received
                    some attention in his creation theology. It is thus quite plausible, as Ephrem
                    later maintained, that the darkness constituted for Bardaisan one of the
                    primordial elements (alongside water, wind, light, and fire),<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">PR</hi> I, 52–53;
                            II, 222–225.</p></note> although it is highly doubtful that he would
                    have considered the darkness as an evil entity, standing in opposition to God.
                    While Ephrem generally does not characterize Bardaisan’s darkness as evil, he
                    hints at this idea when he calls darkness ‘ugly’ (ܣܢܝܐ) in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hymns against Heresies</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 41,7, ed.
                            Beck, 166,9–13. The passage implies that the attribute “ugly” (or
                            “hateful”) is Ephrem’s and not Bardaisan’s terminology. </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">One may surmise that under Manichaean influence Bardaisan’s disciples
                    radicalized his teachings and increasingly conceptualized darkness as a negative
                    force, so that by the sixth century mainline Syriac Christian authors could
                    describe the darkness in the Bardaisanite cosmology as ‘the enemy’
                        (ܒܥܠܕܒܒܐ).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Barḥadbeshabba ʿArbaia</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >History</hi> 2.5, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                        191,8.</p></note> This process must have continued well into the Islamic
                    era, for Arabic authors generally treat the Bardaisanites among the dualist
                    sects and claim that they proposed a juxtaposition of light and darkness within
                    the cosmogonic system.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> See the literature cited in n. 12
                        above.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Bardaisan’s thought in general, and his cosmology in particular, must
                    have exercised a profound influence upon the formation of the Manichaean
                    doctrinal system. The fact that Mani, just as had Bardaisan before him, composed
                    a book entitled <hi rend="italic">On the Mysteries</hi> already hints at a
                    certain rivalry.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> Bardaisan’s treatise <hi rend="italic">On the
                                Mysteries</hi> is mentioned by <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">CH</hi> 56,9; cf. <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 1,14. On
                            Mani’s book of the same title see the following footnote. </p></note>
                    Ibn al-Nadim in his <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi> reports that in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of Mysteries</hi> Mani dedicated three sections to a
                    refutation of Bardaisan’s teachings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">al-Nadim</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi> 9.1,
                            transl. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dodge</hi>, vol. 2, 797f. It is of course
                            possible that further sections of this book also addressed Bardaisan’s
                            teachings.</p></note> Moreover, the Arabic astronomer and scientist
                    al-Biruni (973–1048) preserves a quotation from Mani’s treatise <hi
                        rend="italic">On the Mysteries</hi>, in which Mani explicitly opposes
                    certain of Bardaisan’s views.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> The passage is ed.
                                E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">achau</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Alberuni’s India. An
                                account of the religion, philosophy, literature, geography,
                                chronology, astronomy, customs, laws and astrology of India about
                                A.D. 1030</hi>, 2 vols. (London 1888), transl. in vol. 1, 54–55. The
                            subject here is the relation between human soul and body. On this
                            source, see A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Camplani</hi>, “Bardaisan’s
                            Psychology: Known and Unknown Testimonies and Current Scholarly
                            Perspectives,” in: <hi rend="italic">Syriac Encounters: Papers from the
                                Sixth North American Syriac Symposium, Duke University, 26–29 June
                                2011</hi>, edited by M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Doerfler</hi> / E. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Fiano</hi> / K. <hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi>
                            (Leuven 2015), 259–276. On the relation between Bardaisan’s thought and
                            the Manichaean system, a subject still deserving further study, see for
                            example H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">rijvers</hi>, “Mani und Bardaiṣan. Ein Beitrag zur
                            Vorgeschichte des Manichäismus,” in: <hi rend="italic">Mélanges
                                d’histoire des religions offerts à Henri-Charles Puech</hi> (Paris
                            1974), 459–469; B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">land</hi>, “Mani und Bardesanes — Zur Entstehung
                            des manichäischen Systems,” in: <hi rend="italic">Synkretismus im
                                syrisch-persischen Kulturgebiet. Bericht über ein Symposium in
                                Reinhausen bei Göttingen in der Zeit vom 4. bis 8. Oktober
                            1971</hi>, ed. A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ietrich</hi>, Abhandlungen der Akademie der
                            Wissenschaften in Göttingen. Philologisch-historische Klasse, dritte
                            Folge, Nr. 96 (Göttingen 1975), 123–143; S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >. </hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>L<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ieu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Manichaeism in the
                                Later Roman Empire and Medieval China. A Historical Survey</hi>
                            (Manchester 1985), 42–45, 103–104; G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">arrison</hi> / J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">e</hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps">uhn</hi>, “The
                            Authenticity and Doctrine of (Ps.?) Mani’s Letter to Menoch,” in: <hi
                                rend="italic">The Light and the Darkness. Studies in Manichaeism and
                                its World</hi>, edited by
                                P<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">irecki</hi> /
                                J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">e</hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps">uhn</hi> (Leiden 2001),
                            128–172, esp. 151–153, 168–171 (on the possible impact of the <hi
                                rend="italic">BLC</hi> on the author of this letter).</p></note>
                    Mani’s letter to the Edessenes, of which the <hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani
                        Codex</hi> preserves an excerpt, confirms that a group of Mani’s followers
                    resided in Edessa.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi> 64,8–65,22, ed. with German
                            transl. L<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">oenen</hi> /
                                C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ömer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Der Kölner Mani-Kodex.
                                Über das Werden seines Leibes</hi> (Opladen 1988), 44f.; ed. with
                            Engl. transl. R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >ameron</hi> /
                                A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ewey</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Cologne Mani Codex
                                (P. Colon. inv. nr. 4780): Concerning the Origin of his Body</hi>
                            (Missoula, Mont. 1979), 50–53.</p></note> In light of such close
                    contacts, it would not come as a surprise to find later followers of Bardaisan
                    in conversation with Manichaeans, adapting their own cosmological views to those
                    of this successful new religious movement, and in turn influenced it as
                    well.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.8" xml:lang="en">
                <head>7. The Refutation of Marcionism</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">A further aspect of Bardaisan’s reception among late antique
                    Christians that ought to be mentioned here is his refutation of Marcionism.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> On Marcion, see
                            now J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lieu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Marcion and the
                                Making of a Heretic: God and Scripture in the Second Century</hi>
                            (Cambridge, UK 2015).</p></note> As W. Bauer has shown long ago, the
                    Marcionites established a community in Edessa at a very early time, perhaps even
                    preceding the arrival of ‘orthodox’ Christianity,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                                W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">auer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Orthodoxy and Heresy
                                in Earliest Christianity</hi> (Mifflintown, PA 1996), first publ. as
                                <hi rend="italic">Rechtgläubigkeit und Ketzerei im ältesten
                                Christentum</hi>, 1934.</p></note> so that Bardaisan most certainly
                    was confronted with the controversial teachings of Marcion and his followers.
                    Bardaisan’s vehement opposition to Marcion’s theology constitutes one of the
                    best documented aspects of his activity,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"
                            ><p rend="Footnote Text1"> The <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> does not
                            explicitly mention Marcion, but Bardaisan’s initial arguments refute the
                            Marcionite postulate of two gods. Eusebius, Ephrem, the <hi
                                rend="italic">Life of Aberkios</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Adamantius Dialogue</hi> (ed. W. H van den Sande Bakhuyzen, <hi
                                rend="italic">Der Dialog des Adamantius</hi>, GCS [Leipzig 1901]),
                            all mention Bardaisan’s anti-Marcionite efforts as well. Hippolytus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ref</hi>. VII 31,1, refers to a treatise by the
                            Marcionite Prepon against Bardaisan, thus confirming the existence of a
                            literary debate between Marcionites and Bardaisan, ed.
                                M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">arcovich</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Hippolytus.
                                Refutatio omnium haeresium</hi>, PTS 25 (Berlin 1986), 312,3–5.
                        </p></note> but unfortunately none of his dialogues against the Marcionites
                    has survived<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            Such dialogues are mentioned by <hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">h.e</hi>. 4.30.1–2, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Schwartz
                                / Mommsen, 392,14–23</hi>.</p></note> and only traces of his
                    anti-Marcionite reasoning remain in the patristic literature. In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>, Bardaisan affirms the doctrine of the
                    oneness and goodness of God, an indication that he here specifically targets,
                    albeit without explicitly mentioning the name, Marcion’s novel distinction
                    between a good god and a foreign god.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">BLC</hi> 1–2, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Nau</hi>,
                            536,9–539,4.</p></note> Further evidence for Bardaisan’s consistent
                    opposition to Marcion is supplied by the
                    <hi rend="italic">Life </hi>of Aberkios, the second-century
                    bishop of Hierapolis in Phrygia whose <hi rend="italic">vita</hi> was composed
                    in the fourth century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> On the date of the <hi rend="italic">Vita
                                Abercii</hi>, see
                                D<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">undy</hi>, “The Life of Abercius: Its Significance
                            for Early Syriac Christianity,” <hi rend="italic">Second Century</hi> 7
                            (1989–90), 163–176; P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thonemann</hi>, “Abercius of
                            Hierapolis: Christianization and Social Memory in Late Antique Asia
                            Minor,” in: <hi rend="italic">Historical and Religious Memory in the
                                Ancient World</hi>, edited by B. Dignas / R. R. R. Smith. (Oxford
                            2012), 257–282.</p></note> Aberkios on his travels purportedly met
                        Bardaisan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Life of Aberkios</hi> 69–70, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Nissen</hi>, 48,17–50,8. French transl. now in P. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Maraval</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Vie d’Abercius. Vie
                                de Polycarpe. Deux biographies légendaires d’évêques du IIe
                                siècle</hi> (Paris 2017).</p></note> The bishop is also said to have
                    encountered a certain Marcionite named Euxenianos and to have engaged him in a
                    lively debate during which Aberkios conveniently drew on Bardaisan’s speeches in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102"
                        n="102"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Life of Aberkios</hi> 31–38,
                            ed.<hi rend="smallcaps"> Nissen</hi>, 23–30.
                            Detailed discussion of the parallels between the <hi rend="italic">Vita
                                Abercii</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi> by
                                Th<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">issen</hi>, “Die Petrusakten und ein
                            bardesanitischer Dialog in der Aberkiosvita,” <hi rend="italic">ZNW</hi>
                            9 (1908), 190–203, 315–328. See also
                                H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">régoire</hi>, “Bardesane et S. Abercius,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Byzantion</hi> 25–27 (1955–1957),
                    363–368.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Even Ephrem the Syrian, Bardaisan’s most vocal antagonist, cannot but
                    acknowledge Bardaisan’s persuasive refutation of Marcionism.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Ephrem repeatedly affirms
                            that Bardaisan criticized Marcion,
                            e.g.,<hi rend="smallcaps"> Ephrem</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">CH</hi> 3,4; <hi rend="italic">PR</hi> I,
                        135.</p></note> Among other arguments, Bardaisan apparently adduced
                    philosophical considerations on the nature of space in order to challenge
                    Marcion’s notion of two gods, though unfortunately the precise ductus of
                    Bardaisan’s reasoning can no longer be accessed on account of the fragmentary
                    nature of our sources. Ephrem on the one hand tries to undermine Bardaisan’s
                    premises on space in order to challenge Bardaisan’s cosmology;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">PR</hi> I, 135f.; cf. <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 3,4.
                        </p></note> but elsewhere Ephrem’s refutation of Marcion reveals such
                    similarity with Bardaisan’s arguments that in the end, the reader of Ephrem’s
                    hymns is left to wonder to what extent his anti-Marcionite polemic is itself
                    indebted to the apologetic discourses of his great Edessene rival.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> See for
                            example <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">CH</hi> 32,14; 35,1–4.</p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.9" xml:lang="en">
                <head>8. The Alphabet of Bardaisan</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">A curiosity in the reception history of Bardaisan is the so-called
                    ‘alphabet of Bardaisan’, a cipher widely used by Syriac scribes to encrypt
                    words, usually their own name, but at times also other short texts. These are
                    normally found in manuscript colophons. This cipher was first noted by Wright
                    and commented upon by some nineteenth-century scholars, but only recently has it
                    garnered more attention.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue … British
                                Museum</hi>, vol. 3, 1207 and passim; B. H. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Cowper</hi>, “The Alphabet of Bardaisan,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                                of Sacred Literature and Biblical Record</hi> 6 (1863), 465–466; A.
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Merx</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes von
                                Edessa, nebst einer Untersuchung über das Verhältnis der
                                clementinischen Recognitionen zu dem Buche der Gesetze der
                                Länder</hi> (Halle 1863), 61–62, n. 1; R. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >Duval</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Traité de grammaire syriaque:
                                écriture, phonétique, orthographie, les parties du discours et les
                                formes des mots, syntaxe, index des mots</hi> (Paris 1881), 12–13;
                            Y. <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>,
                            “From Encoding to Decoding: The AṬBḤ of R. Hiyya in Light of a Syriac,
                            Greek and Coptic Cipher,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern
                                Studies</hi> 74 (2015), 45–65.</p></note> The encryption takes place
                    by permutating the letters of the alphabet according to the following
                        schema.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            BL add. 7202. The scribe here lists assorted other alphabets in
                            conjunction with that of Bardaisan. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Wright</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1207, who
                            however does not here list the alphabet of Bardaisan. For this, see J.
                            P. N. <hi rend="smallcaps">Land</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Anecdota
                                syriaca</hi> (Leiden 1886), 13; <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From Encoding to Decoding,”
                        52.</p></note></p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell>ܬ</cell>
                        <cell>ܫ</cell>
                        <cell>ܪ</cell>
                        <cell>ܩ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܨ</cell>
                        <cell>ܦ</cell>
                        <cell>ܥ</cell>
                        <cell>ܣ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܢ</cell>
                        <cell>ܡ</cell>
                        <cell>ܠ</cell>
                        <cell>ܟ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܝ</cell>
                        <cell>ܛ</cell>
                        <cell>ܚ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܙ</cell>
                        <cell>ܘ</cell>
                        <cell>ܗ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܕ</cell>
                        <cell>ܓ</cell>
                        <cell>ܒ</cell>
                        <cell>ܐ</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>ܩ</cell>
                        <cell>ܪ</cell>
                        <cell>ܫ</cell>
                        <cell>ܬ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܝ</cell>
                        <cell>ܟ</cell>
                        <cell>ܠ</cell>
                        <cell>ܡ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܗ</cell>
                        <cell>ܣ</cell>
                        <cell>ܥ</cell>
                        <cell>ܦ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܨ</cell>
                        <cell>ܐ</cell>
                        <cell>ܒ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܓ</cell>
                        <cell>ܕ</cell>
                        <cell>ܢ</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>ܘ</cell>
                        <cell>ܙ</cell>
                        <cell>ܚ</cell>
                        <cell>ܛ</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p xml:lang="en">Several manuscripts, ranging in date from the 14<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> through the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                    century, spell out this alphabet, occasionally alongside other alphabets or
                    ciphers; this particular code (with some minor variations) is consistently named
                    ‘alphabet of Bardaisan’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> A slight variation is found in the subscription
                            of ms. BL add. 21,211, fol. 146b, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1182. The date of this ms.
                            is AD 1831 (fol. 42b, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1181).</p></note> The cipher
                    is not unique to the Syriac world; similar ciphers occur in rabbinic literature
                    as well as in Greek and Coptic texts. It originated in Greek, where the earliest
                    extant evidence is a graffito from the second century, and was then adapted from
                    the Greek by Coptic and Syriac scribes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109"
                        n="109"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> See the detailed study by <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From
                            Encoding to Decoding.” On the second-century graffito from Egypt, see
                            ibid., 58–59.</p></note> A peculiarity of this code is that when the
                    numerical value of each letter is added to that of its code letter, the sum
                    amounts to 10, 100, 55, or 500.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> For details, and the corresponding Greek
                            numerological analysis, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From Encoding to Decoding.” The first
                            to draw attention to this
                            was<hi rend="smallcaps"> Cowper</hi>,
                            “Alphabet.”</p></note> This numerological aspect, however, is not
                    normally commented upon by Syriac scribes. Although the actual code and its
                    designation as ‘alphabet of Bardaisan’ appears only in later manuscripts,
                    scribes employed it already in some of our oldest extant Syriac manuscripts
                    (dating to the first half of the sixth century).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> BL add. 17,176 (containing
                            Palladius) is dated AD 532, and the encoded name of Stephen appears on
                            fol. 87b, according to Wright written in “[a]nother, but still ancient,
                            hand” (<hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1072–1073). The codex BL add. 14,431
                            contains the books of Samuel in the Peshitta version and was collated in
                            AD 545 by a certain George who wrote his name in this cipher (<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol.
                            1, 14–15).</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The question of whether one can attribute this cipher with some
                    confidence to the historical Bardaisan must be asked, and while it cannot be
                    answered with certainty, I should like here to present some reasons that might
                    suggest a cautiously positive response.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112"
                        n="112"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cowper</hi>, “Alphabet,” left the question open and
                            suggested a “Gnostic origin” (466). <hi rend="smallcaps">Duval</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Traité de grammaire</hi>, 13, posited that the Syriacs
                            received the cipher from the Jews and attributed it to Bardaisan as “le
                            premier et le plus célèbre des gnostiques de la Syrie.” </p></note>
                    While it is true, as Paz and Weiss have observed, that the earliest evidence for
                    the cipher in Syriac “dates to more than three centuries after Bardaisan’s
                    death” and the designation ‘alphabet of Bardaisan’ appears only in later
                        manuscripts,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From
                            Encoding to Decoding,” 58. Because of this, and since no evidence exists
                            that Bardaisan himself or his followers used the cipher, they do not
                            consider it likely that the cipher originated with Bardaisan (51–52).
                            However, in light of the very fragmentary nature of the sources on
                            Bardaisan, an argument <hi rend="italic">ex silentio</hi> does not carry
                            too much weight.</p></note> we must emphasize that the use of the cipher
                    was a <hi rend="italic">scribal</hi> habit documented in some of our oldest
                    Syriac manuscripts; it was not a subject discussed by ancient Syriac authors.
                    The earliest evidence of this alphabet comes from colophons dating from the
                    first half of the sixth century, thus belonging to the oldest layer of Syriac
                    manuscripts since only very few manuscripts produced prior to this date have
                    come down to us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> See S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Brock</hi>, “A
                            Tentative Check List of Dated Syriac Manuscripts up to 1300.“ <hi
                                rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> 15.1 (2012), 21–48. Brock lists only
                            fifteen manuscripts prior to 532.</p></note> Moreover, drawing attention
                    to the fact that this cipher originated with the ill-reputed Bardaisan surely
                    lay not in the interest of any ancient scribe. Nor do these early scribes, in
                    fact, ever spell out the code or its name; only rather later manuscripts contain
                    references to the actual cipher and its name, ‘alphabet of Bardaisan’. Three
                    further points can be adduced in support of the hypothesis that this alphabet
                    may have originated with Bardaisan. First, Julius Africanus – whom Bardaisan met
                    in person – is known to have appreciated codifications and quite possibly
                    employed this particular cipher.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius Africanus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kestoi</hi> 7. 6, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallraff</hi> et al.,
                            58–61. The documentary evidence is somewhat inconclusive, and Paz and
                            Weiss seem to waiver as to whether or no Africanus knew the cipher.
                            However, the persuasive arguments in their Appendix suggest that he may
                            well have been familiar with it. (<hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From Encoding to Decoding,”
                        65).</p></note> It is thus conceivable that Bardaisan learned the code from
                    Africanus. Second, Bardaisan is known to have exhibited interest in
                        numbers,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            This is clear from the astrological calculations with which later
                            writers credit him. He also engaged in experiments intended to ascertain
                            how far an arrow would fly if it were to travel at an equal speed for 24
                            hours. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Julius Africanus</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kestoi</hi> 7.20, ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallraff</hi> et al.
                            98–101.</p></note> and he was fascinated with language and the meaning
                    of words.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> On
                            the names for the signs of the zodiac, see above n. 62. On Bardaisan’s
                            interest in names more generally, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ephrem,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">PR</hi> II, 48 and 221–222.</p></note> Adopting this
                    cipher from the Greek to Syriac would hence fit his intellectual profile
                    precisely. And thirdly, it would be difficult to explain, were he not at all
                    affiliated with the origin of this Syriac code, why it should have been named
                    after him – a contemptible heretic, after all, in the eyes of most Syriac
                    scribes (as they do not fail to point out).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118"
                        n="118"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> The scribe of Vat. sir. 96, fol. 159a,
                            writes out the alphabet and labels it “the alphabet of Bardaisan the
                            wicked, which he and his wicked troop used.” </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The alphabet of Bardaisan enjoyed a surprisingly wide and
                    long-lasting reception. Babylonian Jews adapted the code from the Syriac, and
                    the AṬBḤ cipher had a long afterlife in Jewish literature.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From
                            Encoding to Decoding,” 48–51.</p></note> Interestingly, rabbis would
                    occasionally even employ the cipher to decode a biblical word;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> R. Hiyya employed the
                            cipher to explain the hapax <hi rend="italic">manon</hi> (Prov. 29:21),
                            see <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>,
                            “From Encoding to Decoding,” 45–46.</p></note> a midrash draws on the
                    numerical aspect of the code; and Kabbalistic literature enhances with the
                    cipher its theosophical discourse.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paz</hi> / <hi rend="smallcaps">Weiss</hi>, “From
                            Encoding to Decoding,” 48–51.</p></note> In the Syriac tradition, by
                    contrast, the numerological aspect recedes into the background and the principal
                    application of the alphabet lies in encoding a scribe’s name, a short phrase, or
                    a brief text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="Footnote Text1"
                            > The scribe of BL add. 14,606, an 8<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi>-century codex containing spiritual and monastic literature,
                            wrote a short encoded paragraph in the colophon; see <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol.
                            2, 744–745.</p></note> One scribe even enhanced his encrypted request
                    for prayer by a pictorial representation of the encoded letters.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> Cambridge Or.
                            1142, fol. 324v (Barhebraeus, <hi rend="italic">Ethicon</hi>, ms. dated
                                18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent.; see J. F. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">Coakley</hi>, <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the
                                Syriac Manuscripts in Cambridge University Library and College
                                Libraries Acquired since 1901</hi> (2018), 60–61.</p></note> The
                    practice was seemingly ubiquitous: colophons with encoded words are found in
                    East and West Syriac manuscripts from as early as A.D. 545 to as recent as the
                    nineteenth century, and range in content from New Testament Gospels to saints’
                    lives, from grammar treatises and lexica to philosophical handbooks.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p rend="Footnote Text1"> See for
                            example Cambridge Oo.1.31, fol. 220b (Gospels and Epistles, East Syriac,
                            ca. 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> to 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                            cent.; see<hi rend="smallcaps"> W. Wright</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts Preserved in the
                                Library of the University of Cambridge</hi>, vol. 2 [Cambridge
                            1901], 1109–1110); BL 14,431, fol. 157a (Book of Samuel according to the
                            Peshitta version, dated AD 545; see <hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 1, 14–15); BL add. 21,21,
                            fol. 145a (encoded text), 145b (alphabet of Bardaisan) (the manuscript
                            contains an elementary grammar and the metrical grammar of Bar Hebraeus
                            and is dated AD 1831 (fol. 42b); see <hi rend="smallcaps">Wright</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, vol. 3, 1180–1182); Berlin Syriac
                            ms. 90 (philosophical terms; ms. dating to the 17<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> cent.; see E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sachau</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">Verzeichniss der syrischen Handschriften der
                                Königlichen Bibliothek zu Berlin</hi>, vol. 1 (Berlin 1899),
                            338–339. Further examples can be adduced, and I hope soon to offer a
                            more comprehensive analysis of this scribal habit in Syriac
                            manuscripts.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1possekel.10" xml:lang="en">
                <head>9. Conclusion</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Just as only traces remain from Bardaisan’s numerous works, so we can
                    find only hints in the patristic literature about the impact these have had on
                    the church of late antiquity. Yet the evidence that does survive unequivocally
                    shows the far-reaching and powerful influence this original thinker exercised
                    upon subsequent generations. Although Bardaisan was later considered a dangerous
                    heretic, his most influential work, the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Laws</hi>,
                    was read, used, and criticized by generations of Greek patristic theologians,
                    and it appears to have had an afterlife in the Syriac tradition as well. Its
                    clever anti-deterministic arguments offered convenient tools for those wishing
                    to refute astrology, and its numerous ethnographic illustrations could easily be
                    adapted to other purposes. By setting <hi rend="italic">madrashe</hi> to music,
                    Bardaisan made an innovation of considerable importance. His <hi rend="italic"
                        >madrashe</hi> inspired Ephrem, as Sozomen relates, to write his own
                    teaching hymns that in turn would transform Syriac literature. Bardaisan’s
                    cosmology, perhaps not so exceptional in his own time as later opponents claim,
                    but further radicalized by his later followers, continued to challenge the
                    Syriac church and significantly contributed to the negative image passed down by
                    Syriac authors of Bardaisan the heresiarch. Bardaisan’s objections to Marcion’s
                    thought are well documented, and although but little survives of his reasoning,
                    it appears plausible that his <hi rend="italic">Dialogues against the
                        Marcionites</hi> provided Ephrem with a convenient starting-point for his
                    own anti-Marcionite polemics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p
                            rend="Footnote Text1"> Some of this research was presented several years
                            ago at a workshop entitled “Bardesanes – Liber legum regionum,” held at
                            Göttingen University. I would like to thank the organizers, and
                            especially Dr. Ilaria Ramelli, for the invitation to attend. I am also
                            grateful to the colloquium participants and to Dr. Lucas van Rompay for
                            their comments on an earlier version of this article. </p></note> Later
                    generations of Syriac authors also admired Bardaisan’s scientific
                    accomplishments that ranged from astronomical calculations to experiments on the
                    flight of arrows. His personal acquaintance with Julius Africanus provides a
                    tangible link with Graeco-Roman culture, and it may have been this encounter
                    that inspired Bardaisan to adapt the Greek cipher to the Syriac language. If the
                    attribution of the alphabet to Bardaisan is correct, this may well constitute
                    his longest-lasting legacy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Primary Sources</hi></p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Adamantius Dialogue</hi>. Ed. W.
                        H.<hi rend="smallcaps"> van de Sande Bakhuyzen</hi>.<hi rend="italic"> Der Dialog des Adamantius</hi>.
                        GCS 4 (Leipzig 1901).</bibl>
                    <bibl>B<hi rend="smallcaps">arḥadbešhabba ʿ</hi>A<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >rbaia</hi>. <hi rend="italic">History</hi>. Ed.
                            F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >au.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">La première partie de l’ Histoire de Barḥadbešabba
                            ʿArbaïa. Texte syriaque édité et traduit</hi>. PO 23.2 (Paris 1932).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">al-</hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">iruni</hi>.
                            <hi rend="italic">On India</hi>. Ed. with English transl.
                            E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >achau</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Alberuni’s India. An account of the
                            religion, philosophy, literature, geography, chronology, astronomy,
                            customs, laws and astrology of India about A.D. 1030</hi>. 2 vols.
                        (London 1888).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">s.-</hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >aesarius</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Erotapokriseis</hi>. Ed. R. R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">iedinger</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Kaisarios, Die
                            Erotapokriseis</hi>. GCS (Berlin 1989).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">s.-</hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">lement</hi>.
                            <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>. Ed.
                            B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ehm</hi> / G. S<hi rend="smallcaps">trecker</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Die
                            Pseudoklementinen I. Homilien</hi>. GCS (Berlin 1992).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">s.-</hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">lement</hi>.
                            <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi>. Ed. B. R<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ehm</hi> / G. S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >trecker.</hi><hi rend="italic"> Die Pseudoklementinen II: Rekognitionen in Rufins Übersetzung</hi>.
                        Second edition. GCS (Berlin 1994).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Ps.-Clementines </hi>[Syriac
                        version]. Ed. W. F<hi rend="smallcaps">rankenberg</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Die syrischen Clementinen mit griechischem Paralleltext</hi>. TU 48/3
                        (Leipzig 1937).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Ps.-Clementines</hi>. English transl. F.
                        S.<hi rend="smallcaps"> Jones</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Syriac Pseudo-Clementines. An Early Version of the First Christian
                            Novel</hi> (Turnhout 2014). </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi>. Ed. with German
                        transl. L. K<hi rend="smallcaps">oenen</hi> / C. R<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ömer</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Der Kölner Mani-Kodex. Über das Werden
                            seines Leibes</hi> (Opladen 1988).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi>. Engl. Transl. R. C<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ameron</hi> /
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ewey</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Cologne Mani Codex (P.
                            Colon. inv. nr. 4780). Concerning the Origin of his Body</hi> (Missoula,
                        Mont. 1979).</bibl>
                    <bibl>D<hi rend="smallcaps">idymus the Blind</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Commentary on the Psalms</hi>. Ed.
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >esché</hi> / M. G<hi rend="smallcaps">ronewald</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Didymus der Blinde, Psalmenkommentar (Tura-Papyrus)</hi>. Vol. 3 (Bonn
                        1969).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">phrem</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hymns against
                            Heresies</hi>. Ed. with German transl.
                            E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >eck</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra
                            haereses</hi>. CSCO 169–170 / Syr. 76–77 (Louvain 1957).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">phrem</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
                            Nisibis</hi>. Ed. with German transl.
                            E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >eck</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Carmina
                            Nisibena</hi>. CSCO 218–219 / Syr. 92–93 (Louvain 1961–1963).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">phrem</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Prose
                            Refutations</hi>. Ed. with English transl.
                            C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">itchell</hi> /
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">evan</hi> /
                            F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">urkitt</hi>. <hi rend="italic">S. Ephraim’s Prose
                            Refutations of Mani, Marcion, and Bardaisan</hi>. 2 vols. (London
                        1912–1921).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">piphanius</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Panarion</hi>. Ed.
                            K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >oll</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Epiphanius, Werke II</hi>. GCS (Leipzig
                        1922).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">piphanius</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Panarion</hi>. Transl.
                            F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >illiams.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Panarion of Epiphanius of Salamis. Books II and III
                            (Sects 47–80, De Fide)</hi>. Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies 36
                        (Leiden 1994).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">usebius of Caesarea</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Historia ecclesiastica</hi>. Ed.
                            E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >chwartz</hi> / T<hi rend="smallcaps">h. </hi>M<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ommsen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Werke II.1.
                            Die Kirchengeschichte</hi>. Second edition. GCS N.F. 6.1 (Berlin
                        1999).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">usebius of
                        Caesarea</hi>.<hi rend="italic"> Historia ecclesiastica</hi>
                        [Syriac version]<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Ed. W. W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >right</hi> / N. M<hi rend="smallcaps">c</hi>L<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ean</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical History of Eusebius in
                            Syriac, edited from the manuscripts. With a collation of the Armenian
                            version by Adalbert Merx</hi> (Cambridge 1898).</bibl>
                    <bibl>E<hi rend="smallcaps">usebius of Caesarea</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Praeparatio evangelica</hi>. Ed.
                            K<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ras</hi> / É<hi rend="smallcaps">. des </hi>P<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">laces</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Werke
                            VIII.1</hi>. Second edition. GCS (Berlin 1982).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Eusebius of Emesa</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Commentary on Genesis</hi>. Ed. F.
                        P<hi rend="smallcaps">etit </hi>/
                            L.<hi rend="smallcaps"> van </hi>R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ompay</hi> / J.
                            J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">eitenberg</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Eusèbe d’Émèse,
                            Commentaire de la Genèse. Texte arménien de l’édition de Venise (1980).
                            Fragments grecs et syriaques. Avec traductions</hi>. Traditio Exegetica
                        Graeca 15 (Louvain 2011).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">George, Bishop of the Arabs</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">Letters</hi>. Ed. with German transl. V. R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">yssel.</hi> “Die astronomischen Briefe Georgs des
                        Araberbischofs.” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Assyriologie</hi> 8
                        (1893), 1–55.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi> H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >amartolos</hi>. <hi rend="italic">History</hi>. Ed.
                            J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ramer</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Anecdota Graeca
                            Bibliothecarum Oxoniensium</hi>. Vol. 4 (Oxford 1837, reprint Amsterdam
                        1963).</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">ippolytus</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Refutatio
                            omnium haeresium</hi>. Ed.
                            M<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >arcovich</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hippolytus. Refutatio omnium
                            haeresium</hi>. PTS 25 (Berlin 1986).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">acob of </hi>E<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">dessa</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hexaemeron</hi>.
                        Ed<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>I.-B. <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">Chabot</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                            Hexaemeron</hi>. CSCO 92 / Syr. 44 (Louvain 1953).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">acob of </hi>E<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">dessa</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hexaemeron</hi>. Latin
                        transl. A<hi rend="smallcaps">. Vaschalde</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                            Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>. CSCO 97 / Syr. 48 (Louvain 1953).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Jacoby</hi>, F. <hi rend="italic">Die
                            Fragmente der griechischen Historiker, Dritter Teil, C</hi> (Leiden
                        1958).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Jerome</hi>. <hi rend="italic">De viris
                            illustribus</hi>. Ed.
                            E<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ichardson</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Hieronymus, Liber de
                            viris inlustribus. Gennadius, Liber de viris inlustribus</hi>. TU 14.1
                        (Leipzig 1896).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Jerome</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Against
                            Jovinian</hi>. PL 23 (1845), 211–338.</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">ulius </hi>A<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">fricanus</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Kestoi</hi>. Ed. and
                        transl. M. Wallraff / C. Scardino / L. Mecella / Ch. Guignard / W. Adler.
                            <hi rend="italic">Cesti: The Extant Fragments</hi>. GCS N.F. 18 (Berlin
                        2012).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">ustin</hi>. <hi rend="italic">1
                            Apologia</hi>. Ed. M. M<hi rend="smallcaps">arcovich</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">Iustini Martyris Apologiae pro Christianis</hi>. PTS 38
                        (Berlin 1994).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">ustin</hi>. <hi rend="italic">1
                            Apologia</hi>. Transl. C. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Richardson,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Early Christian Fathers</hi> (New York 1970).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Life of Aberkios</hi>. Ed.
                            T<hi rend="smallcaps">h. </hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >issen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">S. Abercii Vita</hi> (Leipzig 1912).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Life of Aberkios</hi>. French
                        transl. P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Maraval</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vie
                            d’Abercius. Vie de Polycarpe. Deux biographies légendaires d’évêques du
                            IIe siècle</hi> (Paris 2017).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">s.-</hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps">eliton</hi>.
                            <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>. Ed. with English transl.
                            W<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ureton</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Spicilegium Syriacum: containing remains
                            of Bardesan, Meliton, Ambrose and Mara bar Serapion</hi> (London 1855),
                        22–31 (text), 41–51 (transl.).</bibl>
                    <bibl>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ichael the </hi>S<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">yrian</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>. Ed. with
                        French transl. J<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >.-</hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">habot.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chronique de Michel le Syrien</hi>. 4 vols. (Paris
                        1899–1910, reprint Brussels 1963).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Moses bar Kepha</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hexaemeron Commentary</hi>. Transl. L. S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >chlimme</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Der Hexaemeronkommentar des Moses bar
                            Kepha. Einleitung, Übersetzung und Untersuchungen</hi>. 2 vols.
                        Göttinger Orientforschungen, 1. Reihe: Syriaca, vol. 14.1–2 (Wiesbaden
                        1977).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">al-</hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps">adim,
                        Ibn</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi>. Ed.
                            G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>F<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >lügel</hi> (Leipzig 1871–1872).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >al-</hi>N<hi rend="smallcaps">adim, </hi>I<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">bn</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi>. Transl.
                            B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >odge</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Fihrist of al-Nadīm. A Tenth-Century
                            Survey of Muslim Culture</hi>. 2 vols. (New York 1970).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Nikephoros Kallistos</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Historia ecclesiastica</hi>. PG 145 (1904), 549–1332.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Odes of Solomon</hi>. Ed. with German transl.
                        M. L<hi rend="smallcaps">attke. </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >Oden Salomos. Text, Übersetzung, Kommentar</hi>. 3 vols. Novum
                        Tes-tamentum et Orbis Antiquus 41 (Göttingen 1999–2005).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Odes of Solomon</hi>. Ed. with English transl.
                            J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">harlesworth.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Odes of Solomon. The Syriac texts, edited with
                            translation and notes</hi>. SBL Texts and Translations 13,
                        Pseudepigrapha Series 7 (Chico, CA 1977).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Origen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">De
                            principiis</hi>. Ed. <hi rend="smallcaps">P. Koetschau</hi>. <hi
                            rend="italic">Origenes, Werke V. De principiis</hi>. GCS (Leipzig
                        1913).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">hiloxenus of </hi>M<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">abbug</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes decem de
                            uno et sancto</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Trinitate incorporate et passo</hi>. Ed. M.
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Brière </hi>/
                            F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>G<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >raffin</hi>. PO 15.4, 38.3, 39.4, 40.2, 41.1 (Paris 1920–1982).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">hotios</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bibliotheca</hi>. Ed.
                            R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >enry</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Photius, Bibliothèque</hi>. Vol. 4: <hi
                            rend="italic">Codices 223–229</hi> (Paris 1991).</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">orphyry</hi>. <hi rend="italic">De
                            abstinentia</hi>. Transl.
                            T<hi rend="smallcaps">h. </hi>T<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >aylor</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Porphyry, On Abstinence from Animal
                            Food</hi> (London 1965).</bibl>
                    <bibl>S<hi rend="smallcaps">ozomen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Historia
                            ecclesiastica</hi>. Ed.
                            J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >idez</hi> /
                            G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ansen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Sozomenus,
                            Kirchengeschichte</hi>. Second edition. GCS N.F. 4 (Berlin 1995).</bibl>
                    <bibl>T<hi rend="smallcaps">ertullian</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Adversus
                            Hermogenem</hi>. Ed. with French transl.
                            F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >hapot</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Tertullien, Contre Hermogène</hi>. SC 439
                        (Paris, 1999).</bibl>
                    <bibl>T<hi rend="smallcaps">heodore bar </hi>K<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">oni</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Scholion</hi>. Ed.
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >cher</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Theodorus bar Kōnī, Liber scholiorum
                            II</hi>. CSCO 66 / Syr. 26 (Louvain 1912). </bibl>
                    <bibl>T<hi rend="smallcaps">heodore bar </hi>K<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">oni</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Scholion</hi>. Transl.
                            R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >espel</hi> / R. D<hi rend="smallcaps">raguet</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Théodore bar Koni, Livre des scolies (recension de Séert) II. Mimrè
                            VI–XI</hi>. CSCO 432 / Syr. 188 (Louvain 1982).</bibl>
                    <bibl>T<hi rend="smallcaps">heodoret of </hi>K<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">yros</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Historia
                            ecclesiastica</hi>. Ed.
                            L<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>P<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >armentier</hi> /
                            G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ansen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Theodoret,
                            Kirchengeschichte</hi>. Third edition. GCS N.F. 5 (Berlin 1998).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Secondary Sources</hi></p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>A<hi rend="smallcaps">land, </hi>B<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>“Mani
                        und Bardesanes – Zur Entstehung des manichäischen Systems.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Synkretismus im syrisch-persischen Kulturgebiet. Bericht
                            über ein Symposium in Reinhausen bei Göttingen in der Zeit vom 4. bis 8.
                            Oktober 1971</hi>, edited by A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>D<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ietrich</hi> (Göttingen 1975), 123–143.</bibl>
                    <bibl>A<hi rend="smallcaps">mand de Mendieta, </hi>E. <hi
                            rend="italic">Fatalisme et liberté dans l’antiquité grecque. Recherches
                            sur la survivance de l’argumentation morale antifataliste de Carnéade
                            chez les philosophes grecs et les théologiens chrétiens des quatre
                            premiers siècles</hi> (Louvain 1945).</bibl>
                    <bibl>B<hi rend="smallcaps">auer, </hi>W<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Orthodoxy and Heresy in Earliest Christianity</hi>
                        (Mifflin-town, PA 1996). Originally published as <hi rend="italic"
                            >Rechtgläubigkeit und Ketzerei im ältesten Christentum</hi> (Tübingen
                        1934).</bibl>
                    <bibl>B<hi rend="smallcaps">aumstark, </hi>A<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der syrischen Literatur mit Ausschluß der
                            christlich-palästinensischen Texte</hi> (Bonn 1922).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Bremmer, </hi>J. N<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi>, ed. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Pseudo-Clementines</hi>. Studies on Early Christian Apocrypha 10
                        (Louvain 2010).</bibl>
                    <bibl>B<hi rend="smallcaps">rock, </hi>S<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “The <hi rend="italic">Ruaḥ Elōhīm</hi> of Gen
                        1,2 and its Reception History in the Syriac Tradition.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Lectures et relectures de la Bible. Festschrift P.-M.
                            Bogaert</hi>, edited by J<hi rend="smallcaps">.-</hi>M A<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">uwers</hi> /
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >énin</hi> (Louvain 1999), 327–349.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Brock</hi>, S. “A Tentative
                        Check List of Dated Syriac Manuscripts up to 1300.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hugoye</hi> 15.1 (2012), 21–48.</bibl>
                    <bibl>B<hi rend="smallcaps">undy, </hi>D<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “The Life of Abercius: Its Significance for
                        Early Syriac Christianity.” <hi rend="italic">Second Century</hi> 7
                        (1989–90), 163–176.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>A.
                        “Bardesane et bardésanites.” <hi rend="italic">École pratique des hautes
                            études. Section des sciences religieuses. Annuaire. Résumé des
                            conférences et travaux</hi> 112 (2003–2004), 29–50.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>A. “Bardaisan and
                        the Bible.” In: <hi rend="italic">Gnose et mani-chéisme: entre les oasis
                            d’Egypte et la route de la soie: hommage à Jean-Daniel Dubois</hi>,
                        edited by <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Van den Kerchove</hi> / <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">G. Soares Santoprete</hi> (Turnhout 2017), 699–715.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>A. “Bardaisan’s
                        Psychology: Known and Un-known Testimonies and Current Scholarly
                        Perspectives.” <anchor xml:id="ENREF_1"/>In: <hi rend="italic">Syriac
                            Encounters: Papers from the Sixth North American Syriac Symposium, Duke
                            University, 26–29 June 2011</hi>, edited by M. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Doerfler</hi> / E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fiano</hi> / K. <hi
                            rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi> (Leuven 2015), 259–276.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>A. “Note
                        bardesanitiche.” <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea Marciana</hi> 12 (1997),
                        11–43.</bibl>
                    <bibl>C<hi rend="smallcaps">amplani, </hi>A.
                        “Rivisitando Bardesane: Note sulle fonti siri-ache del bardesanismo e sulla
                        sua collocazione storico–religiosa.” <hi rend="italic">Cristianesimo nella
                            storia</hi> 19 (1998), 519–596.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Coakley</hi>, J. F. <hi
                            rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts in Cambridge
                            University Library and College Libraries Acquired since 1901</hi>
                        (2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Cowper</hi>, B. H. “The
                        Alphabet of Bardaisan,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Sacred Literature and
                            Biblical Record</hi> 6 (1863), 465–466.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Dihle</hi>, A. “Zur Schicksalslehre des
                        Bardesanes.” In: <hi rend="italic">Kerygma und Logos. Beiträge zu den
                            geistesgeschichtlichen Beziehungen zwischen Antike und Christentum.
                            Festschrift für Carl Andresen zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, edited by A. M.
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ritter</hi> (Göttingen 1979), 123–135.</bibl>
                    <bibl>D<hi rend="smallcaps">rijvers, </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Bardaiṣan of Edessa</hi>. Studia Semitica Neerlandica 6
                        (Assen 1966).</bibl>
                    <bibl>D<hi rend="smallcaps">rijvers, </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>W.
                        “Mani und Bardaiṣan. Ein Beitrag zur Vorgeschichte des Manichäismus.” In:
                            <hi rend="italic">Mélanges d’histoire des religions offerts à
                            Henri-Charles Puech</hi> (Paris 1974), 459–469.</bibl>
                    <bibl>D<hi rend="smallcaps">urst, </hi>M<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Hermogenes.” <hi rend="italic">LThK</hi><hi
                            rend="superscript">3</hi> 5 (1996), 13.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Duval</hi>, R. <hi rend="italic">Traité de
                            grammaire syriaque: écriture, phonétique, orthographie, les parties du
                            discours et les formes des mots, syntaxe, index des mots</hi> (Paris
                        1881).</bibl>
                    <bibl>G<hi rend="smallcaps">régoire, </hi>H<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Bardesane et S. Abercius.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Byzantion</hi> 25–27 (1955–1957), 363–368.</bibl>
                    <bibl>G<hi rend="smallcaps">reschat, </hi>K. <hi
                            rend="italic">Apelles und Hermogenes. Zwei theologische Lehrer des
                            zweiten Jahrhunderts</hi>. Vigiliae Christianae Supplements 48 (Leiden
                        2000).</bibl>
                    <bibl>G<hi rend="smallcaps">uillaumont, </hi>A<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Genèse 1,1–2 selon les commentateurs
                        syriaques.” In: <hi rend="italic">In Principio. Interprétations des premiers
                            versets de la Genèse</hi> (Paris 1973), 115–132.</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">aar</hi>
                            R<hi rend="smallcaps">omeny, </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>B<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">. ter</hi>. <hi rend="italic">A Syrian in Greek Dress.
                            The Use of Greek, Hebrew, and Syriac Biblical Texts in Eusebius of
                            Emesa’s Commentary on Genesis</hi>. Traditio Exegetica Graeca 6 (Louvain
                        1997).</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">arrison, </hi>G<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> / J. B<hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi>D<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">uhn</hi>. “The Authenticity and Doctrine of (Ps.?)
                        Mani’s Letter to Menoch.” In: <hi rend="italic">The Light and the Darkness.
                            Studies in Manichaeism and its World</hi>, edited by
                            P<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>M<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >irecki</hi> / J. B<hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi>D<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >uhn</hi> (Leiden 2001), 128–172.</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">egedus, </hi>T. <hi
                            rend="italic">Early Christianity and Ancient Astrology</hi> (New York
                        2007).</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">ilgenfeld, </hi>A. <hi
                            rend="italic">Bardesanes, der letzte Gnostiker</hi> (Leipzig 1864).</bibl>
                    <bibl>H<hi rend="smallcaps">onigmann, </hi>E. <hi
                            rend="italic">Die sieben Klimata und die ΠΟΛΕΙΣ ΕΠΙΣΗΜΟΙ. Eine
                            Untersuchung zur Geschichte der Geographie und Astrologie im Altertum
                            und Mittelalter</hi> (Heidelberg 1929).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">ansma, </hi>T. <hi
                            rend="italic">Natuur, lot en vrijheid. Bardesanes, de filosoof der
                            Arameeërs en zijn images</hi>. Cahiers bij het Nederlands theologisch
                        tijdschrift 6 (Wageningen 1969).</bibl>
                    <bibl>J<hi rend="smallcaps">ones, </hi>F<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>S<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “The Pseudo-Clementines: A History of Research.”
                            <hi rend="italic">Second Century</hi> 2 (1982), 1–33, 63–96.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Jurasz, I. “</hi>Éphrem, Bardesane et
                        Albinus sur les Incorporels. Une confrontation entre le platonisme et le
                        stoïcisme en milieu syriaque.” <hi rend="italic">Philosophie antique</hi> 17
                        (2017), 169–204.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Jurasz, I</hi>. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >“</hi>Résurrection de l’âme chez Bardesane.”
                        <hi rend="italic">Chora. Journal of Ancient and Medieval Studies </hi>9–10
                        (2011–2012), 399–427.</bibl>
                    <bibl>K<hi rend="smallcaps">azhdan, </hi>A<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> /
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >utler</hi>. “George Hamartolos.” <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of
                            Byzantium</hi> 2 (1991), 836.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">King</hi>, D. “Origenism in
                        Sixth Century Syria: The Case of a Syriac Manuscript on Pagan Philosophy.”
                        In: <hi rend="italic">Origenes und sein Erbe in Orient und Okzident</hi>,
                        edited by A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Fürst</hi> (Münster 2011), 179–212.</bibl>
                    <bibl>K<hi rend="smallcaps">ister, </hi>M. “Tohu
                        wa-Bohu, Primordial Elements and Creatio ex Nihilo.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Jewish Studies Quarterly</hi> 14 (2007), 229–256.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Land</hi>, J. P. N. <hi
                            rend="italic">Anecdota syriaca</hi> (Leiden 1886).</bibl>
                    <bibl>L<hi rend="smallcaps">evi della</hi>
                            V<hi rend="smallcaps">ida, </hi>G<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Appunti Bardesanici.” <hi rend="italic">Rivista
                            degli studi orientali</hi> 8 (1919–1920), 709–722.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Lieu</hi>, J. <hi
                            rend="italic">Marcion and the Making of a Heretic: God and Scripture in
                            the Second Century</hi> (Cambridge, UK 2015).</bibl>
                    <bibl>L<hi rend="smallcaps">ieu, </hi>S.
                            N<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Manichaeism in the Later Roman Empire and Medieval China.
                            A Historical Survey</hi> (Manchester 1985).</bibl>
                    <bibl>M<hi rend="smallcaps">adelung, </hi>W. “Abū
                        ‘Īsā al-Warrāq über die Bardesaniten, Marcioniten und Kantäer.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Studien zur Geschichte und Kultur des Vorderen Orients.
                            Festschrift für Bertold Spuler zum siebzigsten Geburtstag</hi>, edited
                        by H. R<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">oemer</hi> / A. N<hi rend="smallcaps">oth</hi> (Leiden
                        1981), 210–224.</bibl>
                    <bibl>M<hi rend="smallcaps">ay, </hi>G. <hi
                            rend="italic">Schöpfung aus dem Nichts. Die Entstehung der Lehre von der
                            creatio ex nihilo</hi>. Arbeiten zur Kirchengeschichte 48 (Berlin
                        1978).</bibl>
                    <bibl>McV<hi rend="smallcaps">ey, </hi>K. E<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Were the Earliest <hi rend="italic"
                            >Madrašē</hi> Songs or Recitations?” In: <hi rend="italic">After
                            Bardaisan. Studies on Continuity and Change in Syriac Christianity in
                            Honour of Professor Han J. W. Drijvers</hi>, edited by
                            G<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>J<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">einink</hi> /
                            A<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">lugkist</hi>. OLA 89 (Louvain 1999), 185–198.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Merx</hi>, A. <hi rend="italic">Bardesanes
                            von Edessa, nebst einer Untersuchung über das Verhältnis der
                            clementinischen Recognitionen zu dem Buche der Gesetze der Länder</hi>
                        (Halle 1863).</bibl>
                    <bibl>M<hi rend="smallcaps">onnot, </hi>G. <hi
                            rend="italic">Islam et religions</hi>. Islam d’hier et d’aujourd’hui 27
                        (Paris 1986).</bibl>
                    <bibl>N<hi rend="smallcaps">au, </hi>F<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “La cosmographie au VIIe siècle chez les
                        Syriens.” <hi rend="italic">Revue de l’Orient Chrétien</hi> 15 (1910),
                        225–254.</bibl>
                    <bibl>N<hi rend="smallcaps">au, </hi>F. “Notes
                        d’astronomie syrienne.” <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi>, 10<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> series, vol. 16 (1910), 209–228.</bibl>
                    <bibl>N<hi rend="smallcaps">iehoff, </hi>M. R<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “<hi rend="italic">Creatio ex Nihilo</hi>
                        Theology in <hi rend="italic">Genesis Rabbah</hi> in Light of Christian
                        Exegesis.” <hi rend="italic">HTR</hi> 99 (2005), 37–64.</bibl>
                    <bibl>N<hi rend="smallcaps">issen, </hi>T<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">h</hi>. “Die Petrusakten und ein bardesanitischer
                        Dialog in der Aberkiosvita.” <hi rend="italic">ZNW</hi> 9 (1908), 190–203,
                        315–328.</bibl>
                    <bibl>N<hi rend="smallcaps">öldeke, </hi>T<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">h.</hi> “Zum ‘Buch der Gesetze der Länder’.” <hi
                            rend="italic">ZDMG</hi> 64 (1910), 555–560.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Paz, Y. / T. Weiss.</hi> “From Encoding to
                        Decoding: The AṬBḤ of R. Hiyya in Light of a Syriac, Greek, and Coptic
                        Cipher.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi> 74 (2015),
                        45–65.</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">ossekel, </hi>U.
                        “Bardaisan and Origen on Fate and the Power of the Stars.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >JECS</hi> 20 (2012), 515–541.</bibl>
                    <bibl>P<hi rend="smallcaps">ossekel, </hi>U. “Die
                        Schöpfungstheologie des Bardaisan von Edessa.” In: <hi rend="italic">Edessa
                            in hellenistisch-römischer Zeit. Religion, Kultur und Politik zwischen
                            Ost und West. Beiträge des internationalen Edessa-Symposiums in Halle an
                            der Saale, 14.–17. Juli 2005</hi>, edited by L. G<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >reisiger</hi> / C. R<hi rend="smallcaps">ammelt</hi> / J. T<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ubach.</hi> Beiruter Texte und Studien 116 (Beirut
                        2009), 219–229.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Possekel</hi>, U. “Bardaisan
                        of Edessa on the Resurrection. Early Syriac Eschatology in its
                        Religious-Historical Context.” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 88
                        (2004), 1–28.</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps">amelli, </hi>I. <hi
                            rend="italic">Bardaisan of Edessa. A Reassessment of the Evidence and a
                            New Interpretation</hi> (Piscataway, NJ 2009).</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps">amelli, </hi>I.
                        “Origen, Bardaiṣan, and the Origin of Universal Salvation.” <hi
                            rend="italic">HTR</hi> 102 (2009), 135–168.</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >amos-</hi>L<hi rend="smallcaps">issón, </hi>D<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Pseudo-Caesarius.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >LThK</hi><hi rend="superscript">3</hi> 8 (1999), 708.</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps">ehm, </hi>B.
                        “Bardesanes in den Pseudoclementinen.” <hi rend="italic">Philologus</hi> 93
                        (1938), 218–247.</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps">eich, </hi>E. “Ein
                        Brief des Severus Sēḇōḵt.” In: <hi rend="italic">Sic itur ad astra. Studien
                            zur Geschichte der Mathematik und Naturwissenschaften. Festschrift für
                            den Arabisten Paul Kunitzsch zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, edited by M. F<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">olkerts</hi> / R.<hi rend="smallcaps"> </hi>L<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">orch</hi> (Wiesbaden 2000), 478–489.</bibl>
                    <bibl>R<hi rend="smallcaps">iedinger, </hi>R. <hi
                            rend="italic">Pseudo-Kaisarios. Überlieferungsgeschichte und
                            Verfasserfrage</hi>. Byzantinisches Archiv 12 (München 1969).</bibl>
                    <bibl>S<hi rend="smallcaps">achau, </hi>E. <hi
                            rend="italic">Inedita syriaca. Eine Sammlung syrischer Übersetzungen von
                            Schriften griechischer Profanliteratur. Mit einem Anhang. Aus den
                            Handschriften des Britischen Museums herausgegeben</hi> (Wien 1870,
                        reprint Hildesheim 1968).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Sachau</hi>, E. <hi
                            rend="italic">Verzeichniss der syrischen Handschriften der Königlichen
                            Bibliothek zu Berlin</hi>. 2 vols. (Berlin 1899).</bibl>
                    <bibl>S<hi rend="smallcaps">chaeder, </hi>H<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>H<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Bardesanes von Edessa in der Überliefer-ung der
                        griechischen und der syrischen Kirche.” <hi rend="italic">ZKG</hi> 51
                        (1932), 21–73.</bibl>
                    <bibl><anchor xml:id="ENREF_4"/><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Tanaseanu-Döbler, I</hi>. “Bemerkungen zu Porphyrios und Bardaiṣan.”
                            <hi rend="italic">ZAC</hi> 19 (2015), 26–68.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Tannous</hi>, J. “You Are What You Read:
                        Qenneshre and the Miaphysite Church in the Seventh Century.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">History and Identity in the Late Antique Near East</hi>,
                        edited by<hi rend="smallcaps"> Ph. Wood</hi> (Oxford
                        2013), 83–102.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Thonemann</hi>, P. “Abercius of Hierapolis:
                        Christianization and Social Memory in Late Antique Asia Minor.” In: <hi
                            rend="italic">Historical and Religious Memory in the Ancient World</hi>,
                        edited by B. Dignas / R. R. R. Smith. (Oxford 2012), 257–282.</bibl>
                    <bibl>V<hi rend="smallcaps">ajda, </hi>G<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi> “Le témoigne de al-Māturidī sur la doctrine des
                        Manichéens, des Dayṣānites et des Marcionites.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Arabica</hi> 13 (1966), 1–38.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">van </hi>E<hi rend="smallcaps">ss, </hi>J.
                            <hi rend="italic">Theologie und Gesellschaft im 2. und 3. Jahrhundert
                            Hidschra. Eine Geschichte des religiösen Denkens im frühen Islam</hi>. 6
                        vols. (Berlin 1991–1995).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">van </hi>R<hi rend="smallcaps">ompay, </hi>L.
                        “Bardaisan and Mani in Philoxenus of Mabbog’s <hi rend="italic">Mēmrē
                            Against Habbib</hi>.” In: <hi rend="italic">Syriac Polemics. Studies in
                            Honour of Gerrit Jan Reinink</hi>, edited by W.
                            J<hi rend="smallcaps">. van </hi>B<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">ekkum</hi> / J. W. D<hi rend="smallcaps">rijvers</hi> /
                        A. C<hi rend="smallcaps">. </hi>K<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >lugkist</hi>. OLA 170 (Louvain 2007), 77–90.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="smallcaps">Villey</hi>, É. “Qennešre et
                        l’astronomie aux VIe et VIIe siècles.” In: <hi rend="italic">Les sciences en
                            syriaque</hi>, edited by É. <hi rend="smallcaps">Villey</hi>. Études
                        syriaques 11 (Paris 2014), 149–190.</bibl>
                    <bibl>W<hi rend="smallcaps">inter, </hi>F. <hi
                            rend="italic">Bardesanes von Edessa über Indien. Ein früher syrischer
                            Theologe schreibt über ein fremdes Land</hi>. Frühes Christentum.
                        Forschungen und Perspektiven 5 (Thaur 1999).</bibl>
                    <bibl>W<hi rend="smallcaps">right, </hi>W<hi
                            rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts in the British
                            Museum</hi>. 3 vols. (London 1870–1872).</bibl>
                    <bibl><anchor xml:id="ENREF_3"/><hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Wright</hi>, W. <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts
                            Preserved in the Library of the University of Cambridge</hi>. 2 vols.
                        (Cambridge 1901).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
