<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Marco Morrigi, ed., <hi rend="italic">A Corpus of Syriac
                    Incantation Bowls: Syriac Magical Texts from Late Antique
                    Mesopotamia</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Erica C. D.</forename>
                        <surname>Hunter</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>School of African and Oriental Studies, London</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n1prhunter</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Erica C. D. Hunter</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: A Corpus of Syriac
                            Incantation Bowls: Syriac Magical Texts from Late Antique
                            Mesopotamia</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1PRHunter.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="241" to="245">241–245</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="13"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Marco Morrigi, ed., <hi rend="italic">A Corpus of Syriac
                            Incantation Bowls: Syriac Magical Texts from Late Antique
                            Mesopotamia</hi> (Leiden, Brill: 2014). Pp. xviii + 278; €139.</ab>
                    <div type="body">

                    <p xml:lang="en">This volume has the principal aim of analysing all published Syriac
                        incantation bowls in order to describe their language and to update Victor
                        Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">Syriac Incantation Bowls</hi> (Ann
                        Arbor, MI, 1971), thus incorporating scholarly literature published
                        thereafter. Forty-nine texts, spanning one hundred and sixty years
                        (1853–2012) have been re-edited and presented in this volume, together with
                        palaeographic charts for each specimen. Grammar, magical practice, drawings,
                        angelic and demonic names, clients’ names and “all other aspects” are not
                        discussed since in Moriggi’s opinion they deserve particular treatment.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi> commences with I.1 <hi rend="italic">The Study of Syriac Incantation Bowls</hi> which
                        provides a chronological overview of publications of Syriac incantation
                        bowls, as well as notes about further specimens – essentially in private
                        hands – that are being prepared for publication. Hence, exempted from this
                        volume are unpublished Syriac incantation bowls that are currently being
                        worked on by other authors. Also excluded are several items with Syriac
                        inscriptions that do not fit the standard definition of incantation bowls. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">I.2 <hi rend="italic">Methodology</hi> clearly shows how
                        carefully and clearly Moriggi has organised the data accompanying each
                        entry. Particular attention is paid to the transliteration of Syriac into
                        Latin, and the vexed question surrounding the reconstruction of text is
                        discussed. Moriggi concludes that the texts must “speak their own language”
                        (p. 5) noting that some grammatical features of Syriac bowls diverge from
                        Classical Syriac, and as a consequence emendation of the text to accommodate
                        standard Classical Syriac grammar has been avoided. This is indeed a sound
                        point to make.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">I.3 <hi rend="italic">Language of Syriac Incantation Bowls</hi>
                        examines previous authors’ comments on the relationship of Syriac to other
                        Aramaic dialects that were in usage in Mesopotamia, noting the various
                        positions that have been adopted over the decades. In particular, Moriggi
                        queries the premise offered by Müller-Kessler that many of the Syriac and
                        Jewish Babylonian Aramaic incantation bowls were translated from Mandaic <hi rend="italic">Vorlagen</hi> and offers three conclusions: (i)
                        that the language of Syriac bowls is not far removed from Classical Syriac,
                        (ii) that non-Classical features may be internal factors of varieties of
                        Syriac found in Mesopotamia, and (iii) that the linguistic traits may allow
                        for some reconstruction of contemporary spoken varieties now found in Near
                        Eastern Neo-Aramaic (NENA). He suggests as a working hypothesis that the
                        language of Syriac incantation bowls be considered as a written non-literary
                        variety, used alongside literary written varieties, i.e., Classical Syriac.
                        This is an entirely sustainable position, and one of the pressing <hi rend="italic">desiderata</hi> in incantation bowls is for a
                        comprehensive analysis of the language, which may reveal various dialects
                        especially if provenance factors are taken into consideration.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">II <hi rend="italic">Palaeography</hi> discusses the two major
                        scripts of the Syriac incantation bowls before presenting a meticulous and
                        carefully worked analysis of the individual characters of both the
                        Estrangela and Manichaean scripts which are treated separately in the
                        following sections.
                        II.2<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Syriac Bowls and Estrangela Script</hi>
                        reviews previous scholarly opinion, then analyses selected diag-nostic
                        characters and variants thereto. These observations have chronological
                        implications, e.g., the <hi rend="italic">Resh</hi> always being
                        written with the upper point. Moriggi does also briefly comment on the
                        application of diacritical points and concludes by refering to the 2011
                        publications of Ayda Kaplan on Syriac typology which he upholds as being
                        applicable to incantation bowls.
                        II.3<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Syriac Bowls and Manichaean Script</hi>
                        presents a long discussion of different scholarly views about the origins
                        and chronology of this Syriac script, before embarking on a detailed
                        analysis of each character as found in the bowls and drawing conclusions
                        about parellels with Aramaic scripts from northern Mesopotamia, Palmyrene
                        Aramaic, and characters that have no direct parallels in contemporary
                        Aramaic scripts from Mesopotamia. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The major part of the volume, III <hi rend="italic">Texts</hi>,
                        is devoted to detailed studies of each the forty-nine bowls. The catalogue
                        material which commences each entry valuably presents: current location,
                        dimensions, remarks (by previous scholars), script, text arrangement, number
                        of lines, drawings and other signs, clients, contents, parallels, editions,
                        notes, and finally photographs and facsimiles. The transliterated text and
                        translated text are conveniently presented side by side. Accompan-ying notes
                        comment on phraseology and language, providing insight into the philological
                        intricacies of the texts, and referring to appropriate parallels. The sum
                        total is a rich contri-bution to our knowledge of Syriac incantation bowl
                        texts and is the culmination of an enormous amount of effort in com-piling,
                        amalgamating, and extrapolating previous scholars’ expertise.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Any volume often stands or falls by the indexes and listings which allow
                        the user multiple access points. Moriggi has compiled a listing of bowls
                        1–49 together with references to the provenance number and author of
                        publication. Such a listing is very helpful, but might have been improved by
                        listing the publications in chronological order, commencing with the 1853
                        incantation bowl which Ellis published. A slight re-arrangement of each
                        entry might be recommended, namely placing the date of publication after the
                        bowl number, e.g., Bowl no. 1 (1912) YBS 2357, <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>: Montgomery 1912a. The Glossary, as Moriggi points
                        out, contains only complete words and words that have been reconstructed
                        with certainty using R. Payne Smith, <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus
                            Syriacus</hi> (1879–1901) for the <hi rend="italic">lemma</hi>
                        where possible. Again the detail supplied provides very valuable entry
                        points to the texts. Various appendices include <hi rend="italic">List of Angels, Deities, Demons and other Entities</hi> with
                        identifiable names in parenthesis following the transliteration, also <hi rend="italic">Lists of Clients and Adversaries</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">Bibliography</hi> is comprehensive. Concluding
                        the volume are the <hi rend="italic">Script Charts</hi> or
                        palaeographic tables for each of the forty-nine specimens, covering both the
                        Edessene Syriac and Manichaean Syriac fonts. These again form a very useful
                        reference point for anyone undertaking serious comparative work on
                        incantation bowls.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In this meticulous publication it was disappointing that the photographic
                        plates sequelled the entries of each of the texts. Some minor
                        re-organisation (perhaps by the publisher) could have addressed this
                        shortcoming. The plate might have been placed alongside the Prolegomena,
                        i.e., <hi rend="italic">before</hi> the transliterated text and
                        translation for each specimen.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In this otherwise very thorough volume, there were two areas that were
                        lacking. Firstly, given the very careful organisation of the volume, it was
                        remarkable that provenance was not designated under a distinct sub-heading,
                        but was incorporated under Remarks. Granted, many bowls are without
                        provenance. However, where the provenance is known, e.g., those from Nippur,
                        this should have been documented. An appendix listing of provenanced
                        incantation bowls should have been supplied. In any concerted reconstruction
                        of the dialects of Syriac used to write the incantation texts (and this also
                        applies to Mandaic and Jewish Babylonian Aramaic) provenance is a key
                        factor. When sufficient bowls with known provenance are published, it might
                        be possible to map various dialects, in the same way that modern NENA
                        studies are now being undertaken. Pinpointing provenance may also enable
                        patterns of transmission of the refrains to be charted, thus providing
                        invaluable data since incantation texts straddle various communities in
                        Sassanian Mesopotamia.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Physical dimensions were given for each specimen. However, a much more
                        detailed physical typology should have been a <hi rend="italic">desideratum</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                            <p rend="footnote text"> As, for example, in Erica C. D. Hunter, “The typology of the Incantation Bowls: Physical Features and Decorative Aspects, ” in J. B. Segal, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue
                                    of theAramaic and Mandaic Incantation Bowls in the British
                                    Museum</hi> (London: British Museum Publications, 2000) 63–204.</p>
                        </note>
                        Incantation bowls were drawn from the repertoire of Sasanian household
                        plain-ware and were not ritually manufactured, but differences between the
                        Mandaic and Jewish Babylonian Aramaic bowls can be discerned. Such
                        perspectives may shed light onto the sociological aspects of the incantation
                        bowls and <hi rend="italic">ab extensio</hi> possible regional
                        differences. At the very least, it would have been worthwhile to have
                        indicated whether the bowls were flat-based or hemispherical (generally
                        approximately 50% in each category) as it is not possible to ascertain this
                        from the photographs. A profile line-drawing and physical description for
                        each specimen (which would not have taken an inordinate amount of time)
                        would have added the finishing dimension to the volume.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Moriggi considers that the volume will provide scholars with the most
                        accurate and complete anthology of published Syriac incantation bowls,
                        providing a secure foundation for further study on the grammar of these
                        texts, and will be useful for subsequent discoveries of incantation bowls.
                        Moriggi’s expertise lies in the philological and also palaeographical
                        aspects, which he has addressed soundly. The volume certainly makes an
                        enormous contribution to furthering studies on Syriac incantation texts, and
                        more generally on incantation bowls. For any scholar who has an interest in
                        incantation bowls, this work is a ‘must’, but one hopes that in future
                        publications both provenance and physical typology will be given the careful
                        treatment that Moriggi has otherwise applied to the forty-nine Syriac
                        specimens upon which he has clearly devoted much time and attention.</p>
                   
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>