<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Field Notes on Syriac Manuscripts II</title>
                <title type="sub">A Philosophical Manuscript <hi rend="italic">Olim</hi> Mosul 35
                        Rediscovered<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            For a first installment see <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> 20.2 (2017),
                            419–434. The research leading to this article has received funding from
                            the European Research Council under the European Union’s Seventh
                            Framework Programme (FP7/2007–2013) / ERC Grant Agreement n. 679083 as
                            part of the research project “Transmission of Classical Scientific and
                            Philosophical Literature from Greek into Syriac and Arabic” (HUNAYNNET),
                            carried out at the Austrian Academy of Sciences.</p>
                    </note>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Grigory</forename>
                        <surname>Kessel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austian Academy of Sciences / University of Manchester</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Nicolás</forename>
                        <surname>Bamballi</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n1kessel</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Grigory Kessel</author>
                        <title level="a">Field Notes on Syriac Manuscripts II: A Philosophical
                            Manuscript <hi rend="italic">Olim</hi> Mosul 35 Rediscovered</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1Kessel.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="21" to="42">21-42</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="2"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Manuscripts</term>
                    <term>Philosophy</term>
                    <term>Aristotle</term>
                    <term>Bar ʿEbroyo</term>
                    <term>Translation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-05">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <pb n="21"/>
                <p xml:lang="en">The second installment deals with an East Syriac philosophical
                    manuscript known as Mosul 35 preserved at the collection of the Chaldean
                    Patriarchate. Besides a somewhat imprecise description by A. Scher there is no
                    proper study of the manuscript and its content. The first part of the codex
                    includes works related with Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Organon</hi>
                    (including two short lives of Aristotle), while the second part contains the
                    <pb n="22"/>philosophical compendium <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> by Gregory Bar
                    ʿEḇrōyō. A preliminary examination demonstrates that the manuscript is one of
                    the earliest East Syriac philosophical manuscripts produced in the early modern
                    period. Moreover, it is highly likely that it served as a model for at least
                    three manuscripts (Sachau 226, Sachau 211 and Vat. sir. 593/III). </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.1" xml:lang="en">
                
                <p xml:lang="en">The manuscript <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 needs no
                    special introduction as it has been known to specialists of Syriac philosophy
                    for a long time. The manuscript was described by <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Scher-Addai">Addai Scher</persName> (1867–1915) in his
                    catalogue of the Syriac manuscripts preserved in the collection of the Chaldean
                    Patriarchate in <placeName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mosul">Mosul</placeName>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. Scher, “Notice sur les manuscrits syriaques
                            conservés dans la bibliothèque du Patriarcat chaldéen de Mossoul,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des bibliothèques</hi> 17 (1907), 227–260, here
                            237. Scher’s catalogue covers 116 manuscripts. However, it seems that
                            already at the time when Scher examined the collection it was much
                            larger.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Over the course of the 20th century the manuscript was steadily
                    mentioned either as inaccessible or even as lost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Cf., for instance, H.
                            Hugonnard-Roche, “Le commentaire syriaque de Probus sur l’Isagoge de
                            Porphyre. Une étude préliminaire,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                graeco-arabica</hi> 2 (2012), 230.</p>
                    </note> Moreover, some
                    inaccuracies in Scher’s description (see below) led to confusion among scholars
                    with regard to its content.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> See below the description of item 3.</p>
                    </note> To
                    the best of our knowledge, the only scholar who was able to use it in his
                    research was <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Voobus-Arthur">Arthur Vööbus</persName> (he probably possessed a microfilm copy) in his study
                    of the scholarly activity of the <placeName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Nisibis-School-of">School of Nisibis</placeName>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of the School of Nisibis</hi>, CSCO 266, Subsidia 26
                            (Louvain: Secrétariat du Corpus SCO, 1965).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">With the exception of some manuscripts, the collection of the
                    Chaldean Patriarchate was transferred to Baghdad in mid-20th century together
                    with the office of the Chaldean <pb n="23"/>patriarch. The manuscripts were examined in
                    Baghdad by William Macomber who was even planning to produce a new catalogue but
                    this plan never reached fruition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> W. F. Macomber, “New Finds of Syriac Manuscripts
                            in the Middle East,” in <hi rend="italic">XVII. Deutscher
                                Orientalistentag vom 21. bis 27. Juli 1968 in Würzburg</hi>,
                            Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft, Supplementa I,
                            Vorträge Teil 2, hrsg. von W. Voigt (Wiesbaden: Franz Steiner, 1969),
                            475–476.</p>
                    </note> Another catalogue of that collection was prepared by
                    the Chaldean Patriarch <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bidawid-Raphael-I">Raphael I Bidawid</persName> (1922–2003) but never went to press.
                    Reportedly, it was destroyed during military operations against the Kurds in
                        1961.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> D.
                            Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical Organisation of the
                                Church of the East, 1318–1913</hi>, CSCO 582, Subsidia 104 (Louvain:
                            Peeters, 2000), 11–12.</p>
                    </note> The collection of manuscripts remained
                    in Baghdad until the year 2013 when after the rise of ISIS it was heroically
                    safeguarded by a Dominican priest Najeeb Michaeel O.P. who while risking his own
                    life brought the manuscripts to <placeName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Qaraqosh">Qaraqosh</placeName> and a year later to <placeName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Arbela">Erbil</placeName> in Iraqi
                    Kurdistan. While in Erbil, the manuscripts were digitized by the Centre
                    numérique des manuscrits orientaux (CNMO) in collaboration with the Hill Museum
                    &amp; Manuscript Library. A cataloguing of the collection is underway and
                    eventually all of the digitized manuscripts will be available at the <hi rend="italic">vHMML</hi> Reading Room (<ref target="www.vhmml.org">www.vhmml.org</ref>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For a brief account about the
                            digitization of the collection see an article of E. Reisinger in <hi rend="italic">Illuminations</hi> 2017/Spring, 4–7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The learned Chaldean bishop Addai Scher briefly presented the
                    content of the codex while overlooking one text (no. 3) and not identifying the
                    final one (no. 9). The philosophical miscellany <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                    Mosul 35 includes Prōḇā’s commentary on <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Porphyry">Porphyry</persName>’s <hi rend="italic">Isagoge</hi> (no. 1), three commentaries dealing with the first part (up to
                    <hi rend="italic">Prior Analytics</hi> I 7) of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Organon</hi> (nos. 5–8), the Syriac version of the <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi> by <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yaqub-of-Edessa">Jacob of Edessa</persName> (no. 3), two lives of Aristotle (no. 2),
                    a Syriac version of <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dionysius-Thrax">Dionysius Thrax</persName>’ Τέχνη γραμματική (no. 4) and, finally, the
                    philosophical compendiumv<pb n="24"/><hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> by <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Bar-Ebroyo-Grigorios">Gregory Bar
                    ʿEḇrōyō</persName> (the text is lacking the title and was not identified by Scher).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Each of the texts present in the manuscript is attested also by
                    other manuscript witnesses, but it is worth high-lighting that there is a group
                    of manuscripts that has a very similar content and one can argue that all of
                    these derive from <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35. The most noteworthy
                    manuscript is Sachau 226 that was produced approximately in 1882.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A digital copy of
                            the manuscript is available at
                            &lt;http://resolver.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/SBB0001EC4F00000000&gt;
                            [accessed on February 20, 2018].</p>
                    </note> This manuscript is basically
                    a mirror copy of the Mosul manuscript with the exception of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā </hi>that does not feature
                    in Sachau 226. According to a scribal note (Sachau 226, f. 90v), two persons
                    were involved in the manuscript’s production:
                    <hi rend="italic">kāṯōḇā </hi>Elīyā Hōmō<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Elīyā Hōmō (1856–1932), a
                            prolific Chaldean scribe. Among many other manuscripts, he copied also a
                            manuscript in the private collection of Bishop Jāk Isḥāq that was
                            presented in the first installment of the “Field Notes” (G. Kessel,
                            “Field Notes on Syriac Manuscripts I: Two Medical Manuscripts Digitized
                            by the Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript Library,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> 20.2 [2017], 421).</p>
                    </note> and
                    a<hi rend="italic"> maḵtḇānā </hi>Ēramyā. Thanks to the
                    clarification of Sachau we learn that the manuscript was commissioned by
                    Jeremiah Shāmīr on behalf of Sachau. Jeremiah Shāmīr was an industrious Chaldean
                    book and manuscript trader and scribe who was active in the second half of the
                    19th century in Mosul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Rifaat Ebied and Nicholas Al-Jeloo published a
                            number of letters Jeremiah sent to Sachau that shed light on the
                            activity of Jeremiah (R. Ebied, “A Collection of Letters in Syriac and
                            Arabic Addressed to Eduard Sachau (1845–1930),” <hi rend="italic">ARAM</hi> 21 [2009], 79–105; R. Ebied and N. Al-Jeloo, “Some
                            Further Letters in Syriac, Neo-Aramaic and Arabic Addressed to Eduard
                            Sachau by Jeremiah Shāmīr,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Assyrian
                                Academic Studies</hi> 24 [2010], 1–45).</p>
                    </note> Many manuscripts
                    from the local collections were copied either by him or for him on behalf of
                    Western scholars and collectors. Given the virtual identity of <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 <pb n="25"/>and Sachau 226 it is highly likely that the former
                    served as a model for the latter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> There is a mention of a manuscript copy of the <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> in one of the letters from
                            Jeremiah to Sachau — it most probably refers to Sachau
                    211.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As mentioned earlier, Sachau 226 lacks only the <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> in comparison with <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul
                    35. As it turns out, the treatise features in another manuscript of the Berlin
                    collection, namely Sachau 211. The manuscript contains only the <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> with exactly the same lacunae as <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 and thus may very well have been copied
                    directly from the Mosul codex. Unfortunately, there are no scribal notes that
                    could help to contextualize the manuscript, although Sachau himself says that
                    the manuscript was produced “wahrscheinlich in Mosul oder Umgegend um
                        1888.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> E.
                            Sachau, <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss der syrischen Handschriften der
                                Königlichen Bibliothek zu Berlin</hi>, Die
                            Handschriften-Verzeichnisse der Königlichen Bibliothek zu Berlin 23, Bd.
                            1 (Berlin: A. Asher &amp; Co., 1899), 340.</p>
                    </note> Given the
                    similarity of the handwriting, it seems that the scribe, following the request
                    of Jeremiah Shāmīr, copied the content of <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35
                    in two separate volumes (perhaps to get more profit), which are now Sachau 226
                    and Sachau 211.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As a matter of fact, <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 may very
                    well have been used as a model for two other manuscripts. First of all, Baghdad
                    Chaldean Monastery 174 (<hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Notre-Dame des
                    Semences/Vosté 55)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> B. Ḥaddād and J. Isḥāq, <hi rend="italic">al-Makhṭūṭā</hi>t <hi rend="italic">al-suryāniyya wa-l-ʿarabiyya fī
                                khizānat al-rahbāniyya al-kaldāniyya fī Baghdād (Syriac and Arabic
                                Manuscripts in the Library of the Chaldean Monastery Baghdad)</hi>,
                            part 1. Syriac Manuscripts (Baghdād, 1988), 85; Jac.-M. Vosté, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue de la bibliothèque syro-chaldéenne du
                                Couvent de Notre-Dame des Semences près d’Alqosh (Iraq)</hi>
                            (Rome–Paris, 1929), 24.</p>
                    </note> copied in the first quarter of the
                    19th century, which contains items 5–9. Unfortunately, we are not aware of the
                    circumstances of the production of that manuscript. And secondly, Vat. sir.
                    593/III copied by an assiduous Syrian Orthodox scribe Mattai Bar Paulos in Mosul
                    <pb n="26"/>contains items 2–5, 7 and 9.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A digital copy of the manuscript is available at
                            https://digi.vatlib.it/view/MSS_Vat.sir.593 [accessed on February 20,
                            2018].</p>
                    </note> Due to the shared lacunae at the beginning of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā </hi>and elsewhere as well
                    as the identical marginal annotations (see, for example, item 4 below) there can
                    be almost no doubt that Vat. sir. 593/III derived
                    from<hi rend="italic"> olim</hi> Mosul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The text of the <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi> breaks off in Vat. sir. 593/III
                            earlier than in the Mosul manuscript.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Considering the value of the manuscript <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                    Mosul 35 as a witness it is worth stressing that for three texts (viz. the first
                    life of Aristotle and nos. 5 and 7) it is the oldest extant copy, while for the
                    others unless there are copies (usually of Syrian Orthodox provenance)
                    originating from <placeName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Suryan-Dayr">Dayr al-Suryān</placeName>, the manuscript witnesses are much younger
                    (usually of East Syriac provenance) and <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35
                    takes the pride of place among those being the oldest one.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As far as
                    the<hi rend="italic"> Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā </hi>is concerned, the
                    presence of the treatise has not been known to scholars because Scher did not
                    manage to identify the text. In fact, although the manuscript does not belong to
                    the early witnesses of the text it nevertheless appears to be one of the oldest
                    East Syriac copies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Another early East Syriac copy, <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mardin/Scher 61 is now available under the project number
                            CCM 382 at <hi rend="italic">vHMML</hi> (dated to the 16th century
                            according to Scher).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">All in all, <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 belongs to the
                    oldest philo-sophical manuscripts produced during the early modern period. And
                    given the fact that most of the texts are either not edited at all or edited
                    based on a smaller number of witnesses that one is aware of today, it deserves
                    to be taken into consideration by any student of Syriac philosophy.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In what follows we provide a description of the manuscript while
                    indicating the presence of the text in Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Sachau 226 (<hi rend="bold">B</hi>) and Vat. sir. 593/III (<hi rend="bold">V</hi>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="27"/>
                <p rend="Heading">Baghdad, Chaldean Patriarchate</p>
                <p rend="Heading 2">CPB 223</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35, <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                    Baghdad 522<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The
                            shelfmark is documented also in Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                School of Nisibis</hi>, 331.</p>
                    </note>, <hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                    Codex 52.2<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> All
                            three shelfmarks can be found in the manuscript.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Paper</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">264 fols.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">1 col., 20 lines per page</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">22 × 16 × 10 cm</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">East Syriac handwriting without vocalization</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Syriac foliation on the verso side and modern Arabic foliation on
                    the recto side.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Condition</hi>: the manuscript is damaged
                    (I–2, XIII–2, XIV–1, XXI+1, XXVII–2) and some of the leaves are torn; in its
                    original form it most probably consisted of 27 quires, all of which are present
                    with just a few folios wanting; the first quire could be originally a
                    quaternion.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Catalogue description</hi>: Scher, A. “Notice
                    sur les manuscrits syriaques conservés dans la bibliothèque du Patriarcat
                    chaldéen de Mossoul.” <hi rend="italic">Revue des bibliothèques</hi> 17 (1907):
                    237. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Date</hi>: the colophon is lost; the
                    manuscript was dated back to the 16th century by Scher (one can, most probably,
                    narrow it down to the second half) but the first half of the 17th century cannot
                    be excluded as well.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="28"/>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Contents</hi>:</p>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2a" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Prōḇā, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Porphyry’s</hi> Isagoge</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">1. ff. 1v–14v</hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        4v–12v]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܝܣܓܘܓܐ܆ ܦܣܘܩܐ ܬܪܝܢܐ܆ ܡܛܠ ܕܦܣܘܩܐ ܩܕܡܝܐ ܠܐ ܐܫܟܚܬ
                        ܒܐܨܚܬܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܥܕܡܐ ܠܗܪܟܐ ܐܠܦ ܠܢ ܦܪܦܘܪܝܘܣ܆ ܕܡܘܢ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ ܓܢܣܐ ܘܐܕܫܐ. ܘܦܘܪܫܢܐ
                        ܘܕܝܠܝܬܐ ܘܓܕܫܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܡ̇ܪ ܕܝܢ ܦܪܦܘܪܝܘܣ܆ ܕܐܝܬ ܫܘܬܦܘ̈ܬܐ ܘܦܘܪ̈ܫܢܐ ܐܚܪ̈ܢܐ ܠܗܠܝܢ ܚܡܫ
                        ܒܢ̈ܬ ܩ̈ܠܐ܆ ܣܛܪ ܡܢ ܗܠܝܢ ܕܡܢܢ ܐܬܐܡܪ. ܐܠܐ ܣܦܩܢ ܘܗܠܝܢ ܕܣܡܢܢ܆ ܠܘܬ ܒܘܚܢܐ ܗܢܐ.
                        ܘܗܟܢܐ ܡܫܠܡܝܢܢ ܠܦܪܓܡܛܝܐ ܗܕܐ. ܒܝܕ ܥܘܕܪܢܐ ܕܐܠܗܐ ܡܪ ܟܠ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܣܘܟܠܐ ܘܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܐܝܣܣܓܘ̈ܓܐ ܕܦܪܦܘܪܝܘܣ ܦܝܠܣܘܦܐ. ܕܥܒܝܕ ܠܦܪܘܒܐ
                        ܐܢܫ ܚܟܝܡܐ ܩܫܝܫܐ ܐܪܟܝܐܛܪܘܣ ܘܐܪܟܝܕܝܩܘܢ ܕܐܢܛܝܟܝܐ ܕܣܘܪܝܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed.</hi>: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Baumstark, A. <hi rend="italic">Aristoteles bei den Syrern vom
                            5. bis 8. Jahrhundert. Syrische Texte, herausgegeben, übersetzt und
                            untersucht. I. Band: Syrisch-arabische Biographien des Aristoteles.
                            Syrische Kommentare zur ΕΙΣΑΓΩΓΗ des Porphyrios</hi>. Leipzig: Teubner,
                        1900, 4*–12* (based on <hi rend="bold">B</hi>).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit.</hi>:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S. “The Commentator Probus: Problems of Date and
                        Identity.” In <hi rend="italic">Interpreting the Bible and Aristotle in Late
                            Antiquity. The Alexandrian Commentary Tradition between Rome and
                            Baghdad</hi>, ed. J. Lössl and J. W. Watt. Farnham–Burlington, VT:
                        Ashgate, 2011, 195–206.</bibl>
                        <pb n="29"/>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “Le commentaire syriaque de Probus sur
                        l’Isagoge de Porphyre. Une étude préliminaire.” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                            graeco-arabica</hi> 2 (2012): 227–243.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Suermann, H. “Anmerkungen zur Sprache der Übersetzungen und
                        Kommentare von Aristoteles und Porphyrios bei Probus.” In <hi rend="italic">VI Symposium Syriacum, 1992: University of Cambridge, Faculty of
                            Divinity, 30 August–2 September 1992</hi>, Orientalia Christiana
                        Analecta 247, ed. R. Lavenant. Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 1994,
                        393–400.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The manuscript contains only the second section of Prōḇā’s <hi rend="italic">Commentary</hi>, pertaining to the common and proper
                        features of the <hi rend="italic">quinque voces</hi> (Porph. <hi rend="italic">Isag</hi>. 13.9–22.12 Busse). According to the indication
                        that was incorporated into the title, the first section was already missing
                        in the model of <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35. British Library Add.
                        17215 and Dayr al-Suryān, Syr. Fragment no. 88 contain fragments of the
                        first section of the text which complement each other; the two sections of
                        the text are preserved complete in Mingana Syr. 606 and in three manuscripts
                        from Baghdad, Chaldean Monastery 169, 170, 171 (<hi rend="italic">olim</hi>
                        Notre-Dame des Semences 51, 52 and 53), for the relationship among which as
                        well as for further information on this work see Hugonnard-Roche, “Le
                        commentaire syriaque de Probus.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                            <p rend="footnote text"> Hugonnard-Roche (“Le commentaire syriaque de
                                Probus” 230 n. 16) conflates the title of the work as supplied
                                artificially by Baumstark in his edition (but not in his translation
                                on p. 148) with the actual title of <hi rend="bold">B</hi>, which
                                nowhere has “fragments du commentaire de l’<hi rend="italic">Isagoge</hi> composé par Proba d’Antioche”.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2b" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Two lives of Aristotle</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">2. ff. 14v–16v </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        13r–14r <hi rend="bold">V</hi> 155rv]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">General title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܓܡܛܝܐ ܕܡܠܝܠܘܬܐ ܕܥܒܝܕܐ ܠܐܪܝܣܛܛܠܝܣ ܦܝܠܣܘܦܐ ܦܪܝܦܛܛܝܩܘܣ</p>
                    <pb n="30"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">First life. Title:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܟܣܝܣ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܝܠܗ ܕܐܪܣܛܛܠܝܣ ܢܝܩܘܡܐܟܘܣ ܐܪܟܝܛܪܘܣ ܛܝܓܪܝܣ
                        ܕܥܒܝܕܐ ܠܐܡܘܢܝܣ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܨܐ ܩܕܡܝܬ ܕܢܒܥܐ ܐܬܪܗ ܘܢܣܝܡ ܓܢܣܗ ܘܗܠܝܢ ܕܫܪܟܐ ܢܥܩܒ ܐܟܚܕܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܣܡܘ ܐܢܘܢ ܒܕܘܟܬܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܠܝܬܐ ܡܬܩܪܝܐ ܗܘܬ. ܒܗ̇ܝ ܕܐܦ ܡܛܠ
                        ܡܚܫܒܬܐ ܡܬܟܢܫܝܢ ܗܘܘ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Second life. Title:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܚܪܬܐ ܦܪܟܣܝܣ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܠܝܣ ܒܪܐ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ ܗ̣ܘܐ܆ ܕܢܝܩܘܡܐܟܘܣ ܐܣܝܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܚܝܐ ܕܝܢ ܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܗܠܝܣ ܫܢ̈ܝܐ ܫܬܝܢ ܘܬܡܢܐ </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡܬ ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܕܘܒܪܐ ܕܐܪܝܣܛܛܠܝܣ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Both texts were fully transcribed from <hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        in Sachau’s <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss der syrischen Handschriften</hi>,
                        Bd. 1, 335–336, which goes unmentioned in Düring’s treatment of the Syriac
                        lives in <hi rend="italic">Aristotle in the Ancient Biographical
                            Tradition,</hi> 183–189.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">First life:</p> 
                    <bibl>Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Aristoteles bei den
                            Syrern</hi>, 2* (based on <hi rend="bold">B</hi>).</bibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Second life:</p> 
                    <bibl>Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Aristoteles bei den
                            Syrern</hi>, 2*–3* (based on <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and <hi rend="bold">V</hi>).</bibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">An English translation of the Syriac lives is provided in
                        Düring,
                        <hi rend="italic">Aristotle in the Ancient Biographical Tradition, </hi>185–188
                        but its source text is not absolutely clear.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Düring, I. <hi rend="italic">Aristotle in the Ancient
                            Biographical Tradition</hi>, Studia Graeca et Latina Gothoburgensia V;
                        Acta Universitatis Gothoburgensis. Göterborgs Universitets Årsskrift LXIII,
                        2. Göteborg: Almqvist &amp; Wiksell, 1957, 183–246.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gutas, D. “The Spurious and the Authentic in the Arabic Lives
                        of Aristotle.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Aristotle in the Middle Ages. The </hi>Theology<hi rend="italic"> and Other Texts</hi>,
                        Warburg Institute Surveys and Texts XI, ed. J. Kraye, W. F. Ryan and C. B.
                        Schmitt. <pb n="31"/>London: The Warburg Institute, 1986, 15–36 = id. <hi rend="italic">Greek Philosophers in the Arabic Tradition</hi> (Variorum Collected
                        Studies Series CS698), Aldershot, Hampshire–Burlington, VT: Ashgate, 2000,
                        no. vi.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2c" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Jacob of Edessa’s Version of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">3. ff. 16v–64v </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        14r–45v <hi rend="bold">V</hi> 155v–175v]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܩܐܛܐܓܘܪܝܣ ܕܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܠܝܣ ܦܝܠܣܘܦܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܡܘܢܘ̈ܡܐ ܐܘ ܟܝܬ ܫܘ̈ܝܝ ܫܡܐ ܡܬܐܡܪܝܢ܆ ܕܗܢܘܢ ܕܫܡܐ ܒܠܚܘܕ ܕܓܘܐ܇
                        ܡܠܬܐ ܕܝܢ ܕܐܘܣܝܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܥܠܘܗܝ ܕܫܡܐ ܐܚܪܬܐ ܗ̣ܝ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܗܠܝܢ ܕܝܢ ܕܡܥܝܕܝܢ ܕܢܬܐܡܪܘܢ ܟܢܝܫܐܝܬ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܡܢܝܢ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܟܬܒܐ ܕܩܛܗܓܘܪܝܣ ܕܥܒܝܕ ܠܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܠܝܣ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Georr, Kh. <hi rend="italic">Les Catégories d’Aristote dans
                            leurs versions syro-arabes. Édition de textes précédée d’une étude
                            historique et critique et suivie d’un vocabulaire technique</hi>.
                        Beyrouth: Institut Français de Damas, 1948, 253–305 (based on BNF syr. 248
                        and, partially, on BNF syr. 354 that is extant only up to 11b1) (cf. the
                        review by G. Furlani, in <hi rend="italic">Rivista degli studi
                            orientali</hi>25 [1950]: 101–104).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schüler, S. <hi rend="italic">Die Uebersetzung der Categorieen
                            des Aristoteles von Jacob von Edessa (nach einer Handschrift der
                            Bibliothèque nationale zu Paris und einer der Königl. Bibliothek zu
                            Berlin) herausgegeben, mit einer Einleitung versehen und mit den
                            griechischen Handschriften verglichen</hi>. Inaugural-Dissertation,
                        Erlangen 1896. Berlin, 1897, 21–31 (up to 3b32 only; based on <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and BNF syr. 248).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “Sur les versions syriaques des <hi rend="italic">Catégories</hi> d’Aristote.” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            Asiatique</hi> 275 (1987): 205–222 = id. <hi rend="italic">La logique
                                d’Aristote du grec au syriaque. Études sur la transmission des <pb n="32"/>textes de
                            l’</hi>Organon<hi rend="italic"> et leur interprétation philosophique</hi>,
                        Textes et Traditions 9. Paris: Vrin, 2004, 23–37.</bibl>
                    <bibl>King, D. <hi rend="italic">The Earliest Syriac Translation of
                            Aristotle’s Categories: Text, Translation and Commentary</hi>,
                        Aristoteles Semitico-Latinus 21. Leiden: Brill, 2010.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Scher overlooked this item in his description of the contents
                        of the codex. This omission generated some bibliographical confusion. In <hi rend="italic">GSL</hi> 251 n. 4. Baumstark (followed by Georr, <hi rend="italic">Les Catégories d’Aristote dans leurs versions
                            syro-arabes</hi>, 27) includes the Mosul manuscript among the extant
                        copies of Jacob of Edessa’s version of Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi>. And therefore King (<hi rend="italic">The Earliest
                            Syriac Translation</hi>, 283 n. 2) suggests that Baumstark was led to
                        assume that Scher’s description of item no. II of his catalogue (p. 237) as
                        “πραγματεία de la Logique composée par Aristote, philosophe” due to its
                        position in the codex after the <hi rend="italic">Isagoge</hi>, actually
                        meant the <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi>. It seems rather to be the case
                        that Baumstark correctly inferred that the <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi>
                        was present in the manuscript and followed the lives of Aristotle in Mosul
                        35 relying on the evidence provided by <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and <hi rend="bold">V</hi> (cf. the following statement in his <hi rend="italic">Aristoteles bei den Syrern</hi>, 2: “Den Überlieferungszweig der
                        griechischen γένη vertreten zwei syrische Lebensskizzen dieser Art die als
                        Vorsatzstücke einer Übersetzung der Κατηγορίαι auf uns gekommen sind”).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">For further information on the manuscript tradition of Jacob of
                        Edessa’s version of the <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi> — including a list
                        of extant witnesses, a partial study of the relation between them, and
                        corrections to Georr’s text — see King, <hi rend="italic">The Earliest
                            Syriac Translation</hi>, 283–296. Manuscripts <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and
                            <hi rend="bold">V</hi> are not represented in King’s stemma on p. 288.
                        As we noted above, <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and <hi rend="bold">V</hi> are in
                        all likelihood apographa of our codex — and therefore not copies of one of
                        the Notre-Dame des Semences manuscripts as King says on p. 288. The
                        establishment of the proper stemmatic position of <hi rend="italic">olim</hi> Mosul 35 remains hence a desideratum.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2d" xml:lang="en">
                    <pb n="33"/>
                    <head>Syriac Version of the Τέχνη γραμματική ascribed to Dionysius Thrax</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">4. ff. 64v–79r </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        46r–55v <hi rend="bold">V</hi> 175r–181r]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܡܐܡܪܐ ܕܚܣܝܐ ܘܡܝܬܪ ܒܟܠ. ܪܒܢ ܡܪܝ ܝܘܣܦ ܗܘܙܝܐ. ܕܥܠ ܢܝܫܐ
                        ܕܓܪܐܡܡܛܝܩܘܬܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܪܢܢ ܗܟܝܠ ܚܟܝܡ̈ܝܗܘܢ ܕܝܘܢܝ̈ܐ. ܕܡܬܐܡܪܢܘܬܐ ܡ̇ܢ ܐܝܬܝܗ̇܆ ܡܢܬܐ
                        ܙܥܘܪܬܐ ܕܪܘܟܒܗ̇ ܕܡܠܬܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܢ ܗ̣ܘ ܕܡܬܚܙܝܐ ܠܟܘܢ ܕܫܘ̈ܝܢ ܕܐܦ ܠܡܫܡܥܬܐ ܕܐܚܪ̈ܢܐ ܢܬܝ̈ܒܠܢ ܐܘ ܕܠܐ
                        ܢܬܝ̈ܒܠܢ܆ ܗܕܐ ܠܒܘܚܪܢܟܘܢ ܚܬܝܬܐ ܬܬܝܗܒ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܡܡܠܠܐ ܕܥܠ ܐܘܡܢܘܬܐ ܡܠܝܠܬܐ ܕܓܪ̈ܐܡܡܛܝܩܘ. ܕܥܒܝܕ ܠܪܒܢ ܡܪܝ ܝܘܣܦ
                        ܗܘܙܝܐ. ܡܩܪܝܢܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܪܒܢ. ܡܪܝ ܢܪܣܝ ܡܦܫܩܢܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Merx, A. <hi rend="italic">Historia artis grammaticae apud
                            Syros</hi>, Abhandlungen für die Kunde des Morgenlandes Bd. IX, 2.
                        Leipzig, 1889, 50*–72* (based on British Library, Add. 14620, Add. 14658 and
                            <hi rend="bold">B</hi>).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Contini, R. “Considerazione interlinguistiche sull’adattamento
                        siriaco della Τέχνη γραμματική di Dionisio Trace.” In <hi rend="italic">La
                            diffusione dell’eredità classica nell’età tardoantica e medievale. Il
                            Romanzo di Alessandro e altri scritti. Atti del seminario internazionale
                            di studio, Roma–Napoli, 25–27 settembre 1997</hi>, L’eredità classica
                        nel mondo orientale 2, a cura di R. B. Finazzi e A. Valvo. Alessandria:
                        Edizioni dell’Orso, 1998, 95–111.</bibl>
                    <bibl>King, D. “Elements of the Syriac Grammatical Tradition as these
                        Relate to the Origins of Arabic Grammar.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            <pb n="34"/>Foundations of Arabic Linguistics. Sībawayhi and Early Arabic
                            Grammatical Theory</hi>, Studies in Semitic Languages and Linguistics
                        65, ed. A. E. Marogy. Leiden: Brill, 2012, 189–209.</bibl>
                    <bibl>King, D. “Grammar and Logic in Syriac (and Arabic).” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi> 58.1 (2013): 101–120.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">On f. 64v one comes across a pejorative remark of Chaldean
                        patriarch Joseph VII Audo (1847–1878) on this grammatical treatise claiming
                        that the work “deserves neither to be read nor to be copied.” The same note
                        is present also in <hi rend="bold">V</hi>. In all likelihood, the remark was
                        penned by the Catholicos himself.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The Syriac version of the Τέχνη γραμματική does not include the
                        first ten of the twenty sections of the work, beginning only with section 11
                        (22.3 sqq. Uhlig: Περὶ λέξεως. Λέξις ἐστὶ μέρος ἐλάχιστον τοῦ κατὰ σύνταξιν
                        λόγου κτλ.).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Despite being younger than British Library Add. 14658, Merx
                        argued that Add. 14620 preserves an older recension than the former. Merx
                        was provided with a copy of <hi rend="bold">B</hi> by Richard Gottheil when,
                        as Merx mentions, his work was already in advanced stage and therefore he
                        made only limited use of the manuscript.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The attribution of the translation to <persName ref="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yawsep-Hazzaya">Joseph Hūzāyā</persName> appears
                        only in the Mosul manuscript (and its apographs) and was considered by Merx
                        as non-authentic, whereas Contini treated is as tenable.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2e" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Prōḇā, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Aristotle’s</hi> Prior Analytics I
                        2–7</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">5. ff. 79v–90v </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        55v–63v <hi rend="bold">V</hi> 181r–186r]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܦܘܫܩܐ ܕܦܣܘܩܐ ܕܬܪܝܢ ܕܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܢܐܠܘܛܝܩܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܬܠܬ ܐܝܬܝܗܝܢ ܕܗܦ̈ܟܢ. ܐܦܘܦܐܣܝܣ ܟܘܠܝܬܐ. ܩܐܛܐܦܐܣܝܣ ܟܘܠܢܝܬܐ.
                        ܩܐܛܐܦܐܣܝܣ ܡܢܬܝܬܐ</p>
                    <pb n="35"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܟܠ ܚܝܘܬܐܓܚܘܟܬܐ. ܘܡܬܟܢܫ܆ ܠܐ ܟܠ ܒܪܢܫܐ ܓܚܘܟܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܦܘܫܩܐ ܕܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܢܐܠܘ̈ܛܝܩܐ ܕܡܦܫܩ ܠܦܪܘܒܐ ܚܟܝܡܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>van Hoonacker, A. “Le traité du philosophe syrien Probus sur
                        les <hi rend="italic">Premiers Analytiques</hi> d’Aristote.” <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi> 9<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
                        série, 16 (1900): 70–166, here 104–122.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “Un cours sur la syllogistique d’Aristote à
                        l’époque tardo-antique: le commentaire syriaque de Proba (VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle) sur les <hi rend="italic">Premiers
                            Analytiques</hi>. Édition et traduction du texte, avec introduction et
                        commentaire.” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 7 (2017):
                        107–170, here 140–152.</bibl>
                    <bibl>See no. 7 infra.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2f" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Severus Sēbokht, <hi rend="italic">Discourse on Syllogisms in Aristotle’s
                    </hi>Prior Analytics</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">6. ff. 90v–111r</hi> &gt;[<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        63v–79r]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܡܐܡܪܐ ܕܒܙܥܘܪ̈ܝܬܐ ܡܚܘܐ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܪܫܡ ܡܛܠ ܣܘܢܠܘܓܝ̈ܣܡܘ ܕܒܐܢܐܠܘܛܝܩܐ
                        ܩܕ̈ܡܝܐ ܕܐܪܝܣܛܘܛܗܠܝܣ ܕܥܒܝܕ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܡܛܟܣ ܢܗܝܐܝܬ ܐܝܟ ܕܡܨܝܐ ܠܣܒܘܟܬ ܐܢܫ ܕܡܬܟܢܐ
                        ܣܘܪܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܢܝܫܐ ܐܝܬ ܠܢ ܒܡܐܡܪܐ ܗܢܐ ܕܠܚܘܐ ܐܝܟ ܕܒܙܥܘܪ̈ܝܬܐ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܢܪܫܘܡ ܡܛܠ
                        ܙܢܝ̈ܐ ܕܣܘܢܠܘܓܝ̈ܣܡܘ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܗ̇ܝ ܕܐܝܟ ܡܠܝܠܘܬܐ ܦܠܛܘܢܝܬܐ ܐܘܟܝܬ ܬܚܘܡܐ. ܕܡܝܘܬܐ ܐܝܬܝܗ̇ ܕܒܐܠܗܐ
                        ܐܝܟ ܕܡܨܝܐ ܠܒܪܢܫܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܠܡܟܬܒ ܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܢܠܘܛܝܩܐ ܕܡܛܟܣ ܣܝܡ ܣܓܝ ܢܗܝܪܐܝܬ ܐܝܟ
                        ܕܡܨܝܐ ܠܣܒܘܟܬ ܕܐܬܟܢܝ ܣܘܪܐ</p>
                    <pb n="36"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: not edited</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Baumstark, A. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der syrischen
                            Literatur, mit Ausschluß der christlich-palästinensischen Texte</hi>.
                        Bonn: A. Marcus und E. Weber, 1922, 246 and n. 11.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S. “The Syriac Commentary Tradition.” In <hi rend="italic">Glosses and Commentaries on Aristotelian Logical Texts:
                            The Syriac, Arabic and Medieval Latin Traditions</hi>, Warburg Institute
                        Surveys and Texts XXIII, ed. Ch. Burnett. London: The Warburg Institute,
                        1993, 3–18, here 14 §4.2.2 = id. <hi rend="italic">From Ephrem to Romanos:
                            Interactions Between Syriac and Greek in Late Antiquity</hi>, Variorum
                        Collected Studies Series CS664. Aldershot, Hampshire–Brookfield, VT:
                        Ashgate, 1999, no. xiii.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2g" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Prōḇā, <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Aristotle’s</hi> Prior Analytics I
                        1</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">7. ff. 111v–124r </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        79r–87v <hi rend="bold">V</hi> 186r–192v]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܟܬܒܐ ܕܐܢܐܠܘܛܝܩܐ. ܕܥܒܝܕ ܠܦܪܘܒܐ ܚܟܝܡܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܥܐ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܩܗܦܐܠܗ̈ܐ ܕܩܕܡ ܟܠ ܟܬܒܐ ܙ̇ܕܩ ܕܢܬܬܣܝܡܘܢ ܐܝܟ ܕܝܠܦܢܢ
                        ܟܬܒܐ ܗ̇ܘ ܕܩܕܡ ܗܢܐ </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܢܗܘܐ ܫܘܐ ܠܗ̇ܘ ܕܣܝܡ ܐܘ ܕܢܗܘܐ ܡܝܬܪ ܡܢܗ. ܕܢܗܘܐ ܕܝܢ ܒܨܝܪ ܡܢܗ܆ ܘܠܐ
                        ܟܠ ܟܠܗ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܠܡܟܬܒ ܦܘܫܩܐ ܕܦܣܩܐ ܩܕܡܝܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>van Hoonacker, A. “Le traité du philosophe syrien Probus sur
                        les <hi rend="italic">Premiers Analytiques</hi> d’Aristote.” <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi> 9<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>
                        série, 16 (1900): 70–166, here 83–104 (based on a manuscript from Bedjan’s
                        private collection and <hi rend="bold">B</hi>).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “Un cours sur la syllogistique d’Aristote à
                        l’époque tardo-antique: le commentaire syriaque de Proba (VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle) sur les <hi rend="italic">Premiers
                            Analytiques</hi>. Édition et traduction du texte, avec introduction et
                        commentaire.” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-<pb n="37"/>arabica</hi> 7 (2017):
                        107–170, here 128–140 [based on van Hoonacker’s edition as well as <hi rend="bold">B</hi> and <hi rend="bold">V</hi>].</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Suermann, H. “Anmerkungen zur Sprache der Übersetzungen und
                        Kommentare von Aristoteles und Porphyrios bei Probus.” In <hi rend="italic">VI Symposium Syriacum, 1992: University of Cambridge, Faculty of
                            Divinity, 30 August–2 September 1992</hi>, Orientalia Christiana
                        Analecta 247, ed. R. Lavenant. Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 1994,
                        393–400.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S. “The Commentator Probus: Problems of Date and
                        Identity.” In <hi rend="italic">Interpreting the Bible and Aristotle in Late
                            Antiquity. The Alexandrian Commentary Tradition between Rome and
                            Baghdad</hi>, ed. J. Lössl and J. W. Watt. Farnham–Burlington, VT:
                        Ashgate, 2011, 195–206.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2h" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Letter of Severus Sēbokht to Aitalāhā regarding προτάσις in Aristotle’s De
                        Interpretatione</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">8. ff. 124r–128v </hi> [<hi rend="bold">B</hi>
                        87v–90v]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܓܪܬܐ ܕܝܠܗ ܟܕ ܕܝܠܗ ܕܣܐܘܪܐ ܣܐܒܘܟܬ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܟܬܒܗ ܠܘܬ ܐܝܬܐܠܗܐ. ܐܢܫ
                        ܐܦܣܩܘܦܐ ܠܡ ܕܢܝܢܘܐ. ܕܒܗ ܡܛܠ ܦܪܘܛܐܣܝܣ ܕܒܟܬܒܐ ܕܦܪܝܪܡܢܣ ܡܡܠܠ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܕܐܦܝܣܬ ܣܟܘܠܬܢܘܬܐ ܕܐܚܘܬܟ ܪܘܚܢܝܬܐ܆ ܕܐܥܒܕ ܠܗ̇ ܦܘܪܫܐ ܐܝܟ
                        ܕܒܙܥܘܪ̈ܝܬܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܕܗ̇ܝ ܕܝܬܝܪ ܚܣܝܡܐ ܐܡ̇ܪ ܐܢܐ. ܐܘ ܕܠܚܘܒܟ ܐܠܗܝܐ ܡܫܝܛ ܐܢܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Final rubric</hi>:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡܬ ܐܓܪܬܐ ܕܡܛܠ ܦܪܘܛܐܣܝܣ ܕܒܦܪܝܪܡܢܝܐܣ ܕܣܘܪܐ ܣܐܒܘܟܬ ܐܦܣܩܘܦܐ ܠܡ
                        ܕܩܢܫܪܝܢ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: </p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “L’épître de Sévère Sebokht à Aitilaha sur
                        le <hi rend="italic">Peri Hermeneias</hi>. À propos des propositions
                        métathétiques <pb n="38"/>et privatives, et de l’existence du possible.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">Labor limae. Atti in onore di Carmela Baffioni, </hi>a
                        cura di A. Straface, C. De Angelo e A. Manzo, Studi Magrebini, 12–13.
                        Napoli: Università degli Studi di Napoli ‘L’Orientale’, Dipartimento Asia
                        Africa e Mediterraneo (in preparation).</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H. “Questions de logique au VIIe siècle. Les
                        épîtres syriaques de Sévère Sebokht et leurs sources grecques.” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 5 (2015): 53–104.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The text deals with some philosophical notions and expressions
                        in Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">De Interpretatione</hi>; it can be
                        productively compared with many other texts of the commentary tradition.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.2i" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Gregory Bar ʿEḇrōyō, <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="bold">9. ff. 129v–264v </hi> [<hi rend="bold">V</hi>
                        192v–234v]</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Author</hi>: &lt;Gregory Bar ʿEḇrōyō&gt;</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Title</hi>: &lt;<hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ
                            teḡrāṯā</hi>&gt;</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Incipit mut</hi>. (introduction to the
                        treatise):</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܬ ܗܘ ܓܝܪ ܝܡܐ ܕܛܝ̈ܒܘܬܐ ܕܠܐ ܡܬܬܓܝܫ܆ ܘܬܗܘܡܐ ܕܫܘ̈ܟܢܐ ܕܠܐ
                        ܡܬܬܡܝܫ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Desinit mut</hi>. (Book 4, ch. 4):</p>
                    <p xml:lang="syr">ܘܗ̇ܢܝܢ ܥܬܝ̈ܕܬܐ ܐܢ ܐܝܟ ܕܐܝܬܝܗܝܢ ܦܝ̈ܫܢ ܗܘ ܚܙܘܐ</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ed</hi>.: The text remains unedited with the
                        exception of a few fragments.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit</hi>.:</p>
                    <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Takahashi, H. “Barhebraeus und seine islamischen Quellen. <hi rend="italic">Têḡrat</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic normalweight">̲</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">têḡrāt</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic normalweight">̲</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">ā</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Tractatus tractatuum</hi>) und
                        Ġazālīs <hi rend="italic">Maqāṣid al-falāsifa.</hi>” In <hi rend="italic">Syriaca: Zur Geschichte, Theologie, Liturgie und Gegenwartslage der
                            syrischen Kirchen. 2. Deutsches Syrologen-Symposium (Juli 2000,
                            Wittenberg)</hi>, Studien zur Orientalischen <pb n="39"/>Kirchengeschichte 17, hrsg.
                        von M. Tamcke. Münster: LIT, 2002, 147–175.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Takahashi, H. <hi rend="italic">Barhebraeus. A
                            Bio-Bibliography</hi>. Piscataway, N.J.: Gorgias Press, 2005,
                        254–256.</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Both the beginning and end are wanting and there are some
                        lacunae within the text. The text begins on the verso side of a folio with
                        the recto side deliberately left blank. It suggests that the scribe had at
                        his disposal a defective copy and decided to leave the space for the missing
                        portion of the text. The end of the treatise (that must have occupied the
                        two folios missing in the quire) is wanting due to a damage that occurred to
                        the manuscript.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā </hi>(<hi rend="italic">Tractatus tractatuum</hi>) is one out of three
                        philosophical compendia of Bar ʿEḇrōyō that has not received so far the
                        scholarly attention it deserves. This compendium consists of three books:
                        logic (f. 129v), natural sciences (f. 172r) and metaphysics (f. 219r).
                        According to Hidemi Takahashi, Bar ʿEḇrōyō draws extensively on Ghazālī’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Maqāṣid al-falāsifa</hi>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">This copy of
                        <hi rend="italic">Teḡraṯ teḡrāṯā </hi>escaped scholarly
                        attention because it was not identified by Scher. Being one of the oldest
                        East Syriac copies of the treatise, one wonders if it was copied from an
                        older East Syriac copy or from a Syrian Orthodox one. A close comparison of
                        its text against the extant Syrian Orthodox copies might shed some light on
                        the reception and transmission of the treatise in the East Syriac
                        milieu.</p>
                </div>
               <div> 
                   <pb n="40"/><p xml:lang="en">[page left blank intentionally]</p>
                    </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n1kessel.3" xml:lang="en">
                <pb n="41"/>
                <head>Images:</head>
<p>
    <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV21N1Kessel_image1.png" rend="center">
                        <desc>CPB_00223_001v.jpg</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Plate 1. CPB 223, f. 1v</hi></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Published with the permission of the Chaldean Patriarchate.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The image is supplied by the Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript
                    Library.</p>
                <p>
                    <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV21N1Kessel_image2.png" rend="center">
                        <desc>CPB_00223_114v.jpg</desc>
                    </graphic>
                </p>
                <pb n="42"/>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Plate 2. CPB 223, f. 114v</hi></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Published with the permission of the Chaldean Patriarchate.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The image is supplied by the Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript
                    Library.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>