<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Incarnational Theology and Spirituality of John the Solitary
                    of Apamea</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Seely J.</forename>
                        <surname>Beggiani</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Independent Scholar</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n2beggiani</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Seely J. Beggiani</author>
                        <title level="a">The Incarnational Theology and Spirituality of John the
                            Solitary of Apamea</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N2Beggiani.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="139" to="169">139-169</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="6"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>John of Apamea</term>
                    <term>John the Solitary</term>
                    <term>Theology</term>
                    <term>Spirituality</term>
                    <term>Incarnation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-11-01">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">John the Solitary of Apamea, a fifth-century Syriac writer,
                    presents an early synthesis of theology and spirituality founded primarily on
                    the Incarnation and based on Scripture. John teaches that humans are created in
                    the image and likeness of the preexistent Christ, and this image is the basis of
                    their spiritual nature. Therefore, the incarnate Christ is the paradigm of human
                    existence in this life, and the risen Christ is the vehicle of transformation of
                    resurrected humanity. John develops the various levels of spiritual progress in
                    this life culminating in silent prayer, which is a foretaste of communing with
                    the wisdom and love of Christ in the world to come.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body xml:lang="en">
            <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.1" xml:lang="en">
                <p xml:lang="en">The Syriac religious writings of the first four Christian centuries
                    with their almost exclusive reliance on Scripture as a source represent a unique
                    approach to theology and spirituality. Ephrem and Aphrahat, early
                    representatives of this tradition, expressed their teachings within a biblical
                        world-<pb n="391"/>view.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            xml:lang="en"> The term “biblical world-view” is used to describe how
                            the biblical writers pictured and ordered reality. In contrast to the
                            classical world, biblical thought gives priority to faith and
                            revelation.</p></note> Early Syriac culture did interact with Greek
                    philosophy and science. Ephrem was aware of Greek philosophy and science and
                    made use of the theory of the four elements in his teaching.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> Ute Possekel, “Syriac Theology,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">Oxford Handbook to the Reception History of
                                Christian Theology</hi>, ed. by S. Coakley and R. Cross
                            (forthcoming), 2-7. See also Possekel, <hi rend="italic">Evidence of
                                Greek Philosophical Cocnepts in the Wrtiting of Ephrem the
                                Syrian</hi>, CSCO 580 (Leuven: Peeters, 1999).</p></note> It was in
                    the latter part of the fifth century that Greek philosophy and theology gained
                    more prominence and integration in Syriac scholarship. The substantial writings
                    on the spiritual life attributed to John the Solitary of Apamea,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p xml:lang="en"> The principal published
                            works attributed to John the Solitary are: <hi rend="italic">Brief von
                                Johannes dem Einsiedler</hi>, Lars Rignell, trans. (Lund: Hakan
                            Ohlssons, 1941), summarized by Irenée Hausherr, “Un grand auteur
                            spiritual retrouvé: Jean d’Apamée,” OCA 183 (Rome: 1969), 181–216; <hi
                                rend="italic">Drei Traktate von Johannes dem Einsiedler (Johannes
                                von Apamea),</hi> L.G. Rignell, ed, trans. (Lund, 1960), the first
                            Tractate is translated into English by Dana Miller in <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Ascetical Homilies of Saint Isaac the Syrian</hi> (Boston: Holy
                            Transfiguration Monastery, 1981), 461–6; <hi rend="italic">Johannes von
                                Lycopolis, Ein Dialog über die Seele und die Affekte des
                                Menschen</hi>, ed. Sven Dedering (Uppsala, 1936), translated by Mary
                            Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary on the Soul</hi>
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias, 2013), also translated by Irenée Hausherr, <hi
                                rend="italic">Dialogue sur l’âme et les passions des hommes</hi>,
                            OCA 120 (Rome, 1939); <hi rend="italic">Sechs Gesprache mit Thomasios,
                                Der Briefweschel zwischen Thomasios und Johannes und drei an
                                Thomasios gerichtete Abband lungen</hi>, Werner Strothmann, ed.,
                            trans. (Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 1972), translated by René Levenant,
                                <hi rend="italic">Jean d’Apamée. Dialogues et Traités</hi>, Sources
                            Chrétiennes 311 (Paris: Editions du Cerf, 1984); Sebastian Brock,
                            trans., “John the Solitary, On Prayer,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                Theological Studies</hi> 30 (1979), 84–101; Sebastian Brock, trans.,
                            “Letter to Hesychius” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Fathers on Prayer
                                and the Spiritual Life</hi> (Kalamazoo: Cistercian, 1987), 81–98;
                            Sameer Maroki, “Jean le Solitaire (d’Apamée), Quatre Lettres inedités,
                            Textes Syriaques et Traduction française,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                                l’Orient</hi> 35 (2010), 477–506. </p></note> which probably date
                    from the first half of the fifth century, are more similar to earlier examples
                    of Syriac literature than later writings in this regard. <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en"> Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony observes:
                            “The role of the Bible in his spirituality, a sort of continual
                            meditation on Scripture, is central, and his patterns of thought are
                            easily characterized as typically Semitic.” Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony,
                            “‘More interior than the Lips and the Tongue’: John of Apamea and Silent
                            Prayer in Late Antiquity,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian
                                Studies</hi> 20 (2012): 321.</p></note> John the Solitary knew Greek
                    but hardly used Greek terminology in his writings. Irénée Hausherr observes that
                    John’s views are closer to those of Ephrem than to early Christian philosophers
                    such as Gregory of Nyssa or<pb n="392"/> Evagrius of Pontus.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"> See: Bitton-Ashkelony, “John of
                            Apamea,” 321-2.</p></note> He shows no influence from Evagrius who
                    greatly influenced many subsequent Syriac writers. In terms of sources other
                    than Scripture, he refers only to Ignatius of Antioch.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p xml:lang="en"> Irenée Hausherr, “Un grand auteur
                            spiritual retrouvé: Jean d’Apamée.” OCA 183 (1969): 213; Brock, <hi
                                rend="italic">Syriac Fathers</hi>, 78.</p></note> He mentions in
                    passing Eusebius of Caesarea’s <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>. He
                    rejects by name the teachings of the Valentinians,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p xml:lang="en">
                            <hi rend="italic">Quatrième Dialogue avec Thomasios sur l’extrême
                                variété des êtres créés par Dieu, su tout ce qu’il a opéré dans la
                                nature et hors de la nature. Et d’autres sujets</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 79–80. </p></note> and in his writings
                    he also rejects docetism, Arianism, and Apollinarism.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Most of John’s published writings consist of spiritual direction
                    in the form of dialogues, tracts, and letters in response to queries from monks
                    and solitaries of the region. It is possible that his monastery was near
                    Nikertai where Theodoret lived as a monk prior to becoming bishop of Cyrrhus in
                        423.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p xml:lang="en"> Sebastian
                            Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Fathers on Prayer and the Spiritual
                                Life</hi>, (Kalamazoo: Cistercian, 1987): 78. </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> This article seeks to outline John’s incarnational theology and
                    its application to his spiritual doctrine based on a close reading of John’s
                    densely written tracts and dialogues. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>THEOLOGY</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">John the Solitary sees creation as a wondrous manifestation of the
                    glory of God. The vast range of God’s creativity extends from the highest rank
                    of angels to the lowest material entity. Each being in creation has significance
                    in celebrating the glory of God. God’s “economy of salvation” includes all
                    spiritual beings, both angels and humans. Human beings are a microcosm of
                    spiritual and material creation. John locates spirit in humans in the deepest
                    part of the soul. Both in this life and in eternity, the body is an integral
                    part of the human self.</p>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Centrality of the Incarnation in Creation</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">John’s view of God’s plan of salvation incorporates all of
                        creation including both angels and humans. John seems to take for granted
                        that the incarnation of Christ was essential to this plan from the
                        beginning, since the resurrected humanity of<pb n="393"/> Christ is an
                        integral part of bringing about the transformation of humanity. In his <hi
                            rend="italic">Third Treatise on the mystery of the economy of Christ our
                            Lord</hi>, John declares that the Scriptures manifest the authenticity
                        of Christ’s economy of salvation because they do not confess his divinity
                        without associating it with his humanity, or his humanity without his
                        divinity. According to John, they teach the unique person of the only Son of
                        God in exaltation and humiliation. To those who refuse to confess Christ’s
                        corporeity, St. Paul teaches that He is of the line of David according to
                        the flesh. To those who do not speak of his being the only Son of the
                        Father, Paul declares that in the fullness of time God sent his son born of
                        a woman. To those who distinguish two sons, the Gospels announce that the
                        Savior is the only Son of God. John affirms the mystery of the divine will
                        to imprint on the human soul the image of the only Son of God.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Lettre to Thomasios</hi>, Levanant, Dialogues,
                                166–68.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Created in the image and likeness of Christ, humans can only reach
                        fulfillment in Christ</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">For John human beings were created not only in the image of God
                        but in the image of the Word made flesh. He declares: “By his foreknowledge,
                        God had predestined, chosen, sanctified and fashioned us in the image of His
                        Son, so that after having lost and forgotten our grandeur, dignity and glory
                        that we had received in our creation, we are, thanks to Christ, renewed,
                        rendered perfect and receive life, truth, and wisdom of the mysteries of God
                        in his holy world.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p xml:lang="en"
                                > Ibid., 138.</p></note> The Son of God had created all living
                        beings perfect according to his image. From the beginning of their
                        existence, he was their “knowledge, life, light, true repose, holy kingdom
                        and place of peace.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 137. </p></note> He had prepared and
                        sanctified this present world with all its splendors in preparation for the
                        perfect world to come. This plan of salvation prepared from the beginning of
                        the world is invisible and exists invisibly in the world and was executed
                        visibly through the actions of Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12"
                            n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 136–8.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The ideal is for the spiritual soul and body to exist in
                        perfect harmony. However, since the body’s senses and passions can go
                        astray, the soul can only arrive at mastery of<pb n="394"/> the body through
                        long discipline. On one level the soul relies on its bodily senses for its
                        natural knowledge and on its passions to act in the secular world. But by
                        nature, the soul seeks understanding through intellectual activity. The
                        spiritual part of humans is called to a higher understanding and activity.
                        In the present world the spirit has difficulty functioning, since it is part
                        of the soul which in turn relies on the body and sense knowledge. John
                        compares this condition to a complete embryo with all its senses, arms and
                        legs, but unable to act as long as it is in its mother’s womb. In the same
                        way, while the spiritual soul is in the physical world it cannot operate
                        until it rises to the spiritual world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                            n="13"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 36–7; <hi rend="italic">Premier
                                    Dialogue de Mar Jean le Solitaire avec le bienheureux Thomasios
                                    sur l’expérance future</hi>, 54–5 in René Levenant, trans,, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Jean d’Apamée. Dialogues et Traités</hi>, Sources
                                Chrétiennes 311 (Paris: Editions du Cerf, 1984). </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Reflecting the teachings of St. Paul, John states that on the
                        level of the material world, God has chosen to teach humans through the
                        splendor of his works and his wisdom in creation. We can come to some
                        understanding of God’s works, but not of God in himself. Creation manifests
                        the grandeur of God’s marvelous skill. However, God chooses often in
                        Scripture to show His plans not in grand gestures but in small ways. Since
                        God cannot be known in himself, humans use the highest names available in
                        referring to him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p xml:lang="en"
                                    ><hi rend="italic"> Cinquième Dialogue du meme Mar Jean le
                                    Solitaire sur ce thème: pourquoi malgré la transformation si
                                    grande and si élevé dont elle doit bénéficier, la nature humaine
                                    a-t-elle d’abord été créé en ce monde avec un corps composé?
                                </hi>in Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Jean d’Apamée</hi>, 104–6; <hi
                                    rend="italic">Réponse de Mar Jean le Solitaire à Thomasios qui
                                    l’avait interrogé sur le mystère de l’économie du Christ qui a
                                    eu lieu pour tous: Premier Traité</hi>, ibid., 132.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In his <hi rend="italic">Letter to Hesychius</hi>, John offers
                        the following advice to the solitary:</p>
                    <quote><p xml:lang="en">When evening comes, collect your thoughts and ponder
                            over the entire course of the Day: observe God’s providential care for
                            you; consider the grace he has wrought in you throughout the whole span
                            of the day; consider the rising of the moon, the joy of daylight, all
                            the hours and moments, the divisions of time, the sight of different
                            colors, the beautiful adornment of creation, the course of the sun, the
                            growth of<pb n="395"/> your own stature, how your own person has been
                            protected; consider the blowing of the winds, the ripe and varied
                            fruits, how the elements minister to your comfort, how you have been
                            preserved from accidents, and all the other activities of grace. When
                            you have pondered all of this, wonder of God’s love towards you will
                            well up within you, and gratitude for his acts of grace will bubble up
                            inside you.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p xml:lang="en">
                                    Brock, <hi rend="italic">Syriac Fathers</hi>, 94–5.</p></note>
                        </p></quote>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.3" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The invisible and the visible</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">A key in articulating his theology and found throughout his
                        writings is John’s distinction between the invisible and the visible.
                        Invisible reality is the realm of God. God’s activity in creating, in
                        revealing, and in the working out of the plan of salvation introduces the
                        invisible into visible reality. The human soul, which in its depths is
                        spirit stamped in the image of God, represents the meeting point between the
                        invisible and the visible. Human beings in their earthly condition are able
                        to know and function by way of visible things, but the invisible realities
                        embedded in material creation can be grasped only partially and with
                        difficulty. For John, since the God is unknowable and unattainable, humans
                        cannot attain God through knowledge, because they become lost in mystery.
                        The human will is wearied in its unlimited searching, and it is only
                        Christ’s presence that can give it rest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                            n="16"><p xml:lang="en"> Sameer Maroki, “Jean le Solitaire (d’Apamée),
                                Quatre Lettres inedités, Textes Syriaques et Traduction française,”
                                    <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 35 (2010), 481, and
                                “Lettere: Sur le Mystère du Christ,“ 497. </p></note> Nevertheless,
                        it is in God’s plan of salvation that human beings will recover their
                        original state allowing the spirit to function in the realm of the
                        invisible. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John speaks of creation containing “two mysteries: its outward
                        appearance and the creative workmanship of God which lies within it.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en"> Mary Hansbury, <hi
                                    rend="italic">John the Solitary on the Soul</hi> (Piscataway:
                                Gorgias, 2013):5</p></note> The eyes can only see material things
                        whereas the intellect can know the invisible. Human beings are essentially
                        spirit in matter with the realization that finitude is a<pb n="396"/> part
                        of their nature. The ability to know is limited by their material senses and
                        the limitations of their intellect, will and spirit. Yet, human beings with
                        their double substance manifested in the body and concealed in the soul are
                        called to delight in seeing God’s hidden wisdom shining forth in the amazing
                        beauties of creation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 6.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John states that since “God conceals within the inner members
                        a nature having senses more subtle than all the bodies,”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid.</p></note> the human
                        intellect is able to go beyond one’s external senses. “Now because of the
                        subtleness of its stirrings, this nature searches out the hidden wisdom of
                        the things created by the Lord of all.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                            n="20"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 6</p></note> John encourages his readers
                        to strive for a purity of intellect which is the “only true wisdom that God
                        has put in human nature in this life.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
                            n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 156.</p></note> John advises that humans
                        pray that “God might make the light of His knowledge to shine in us that the
                        virtues which He has put in us at the creation of our soul might be
                        visible.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid.,
                                106. </p></note> As such, humans should devote themselves to study
                        so that their intellects would turn within and focus on their interior
                        selves.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Thus in John’s anthropology, the spiritual soul and body
                        constitute the complete human being both in this world and the next. In this
                        world, spirit element is limited in its activity because of its reliance on
                        the soul, and the soul’s intellectual activity is restrained by the body.
                        God provides instruction through his wisdom found hidden in the works of
                        creation and through Scripture adapted to humans’ limited understanding. The
                        goal is to seek the spiritual reality that lies within humanity.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.4" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Divine revelation: the Word expressed in “speech”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> The English term “voice” is also
                                used depending on the conext.</p></note></head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Furthermore for John, the Word of God is the divine expression
                        and divine image, yet hidden and mysterious in the realm of silence. In
                        revelation the “word” is expressed in human “speech,” yet speech is hardly
                        adequate to the task. No human words can represent the Word.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter sent to Eutropius and Eusebius </hi>in
                                Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,” 209–10.</p></note> If God had chosen
                            to<pb n="397"/> be understood, he would have chosen the way of knowledge
                        and not of faith. He would have chosen philosophers as his disciples, not
                        fishermen. Even when He reveals himself to humans, it is according to human
                        ability to comprehend.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Maroki, “Lettre: sur le Mystère,”
                        497–8.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> According to John, physical expression whether through the
                        prose, poetry, figures or allegories of Scripture or the preaching of
                        prophets and ministers is the only way to communicate with human intellects
                        in the present world. It is in the spiritual world to come that humans are
                        able to see the mysteries themselves without figures. At the present time
                        humans are in communion with God through the mysteries of the Church. The
                        future majesty shall be revealed not in figures, enigmas, similitudes and
                        parables, but shall be given to those who have guarded purely the pledge of
                        the Spirit.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> While on earth humans are a composite of body and soul, where
                        the corporeal side is expressed in voice or speech. The “word” or “logos” is
                        not corporeal. “Word” is to be understood as that part of the soul that is
                        in the image and likeness of God, and “speech” is the soul expressed in its
                        corporeal form. The word is expressed in speech as long as the soul is
                        dependent on the body. The external senses are unable to consider hidden
                        things. Hidden things can only be studied through contemplation.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Lettre to Eutropius and Eusebius</hi>, in
                                Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,” 203–4.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John also uses this distinction between word and “voice” when
                        comparing the human condition in this life with that of the world to come.
                        He cites Ignatius of Antioch’s <hi rend="italic">Letter to the Romans</hi>
                        urging his readers not to deter his desire to witness to Christ in
                        martyrdom. His hope through death for the faith is to become a “word” of
                        God. If the Romans would want him to hang on to his earthly body, he would
                        remain a “voice” of God. He would rather his readers not love the life he
                        has on earth more than his entering the life of the spirit. John continues
                        that when Ignatius says that he shall be a word of God, he means that in the
                        future world, humans shall live the life of the spirit and know the truth
                        through wisdom, which cannot be known from human speech. Making use of a
                            Pauline<pb n="398"/> metaphor, humans will no longer see an image of the
                        truth in a mirror, but face to face without intermediary.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter sent to Eutropius and Eusebius</hi> in
                                Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,” 200-3..</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Incarnation as Word become “Voice”</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">John applies the distinction between word and voice in his
                        teaching about the Incarnation. In this regard, John cites John the Baptist
                        who refers to himself as a voice crying in the wilderness, but who refers to
                        Christ as the Word. Christ is designated as the word because he is the
                        prophet on behalf of the Father. Christ put on a body as the word puts on
                        voice. The body as voice is not just an outer robe but expresses the word
                        which is unreachable because of the Lord’s “unlimited rationality.”
                        Therefore, God the Word in his plentitude is to be found in his perfect
                        humanity. The Word expresses himself in voice in order to be heard by human
                        ears. However, God the Word is always in the presence of the Father. He
                        takes a perfect body to be seen and revealed to the human family, otherwise
                        he would not be known. The mixture of the word in voice is not confused, but
                        is combined in a single power and humans perceive a sole expression all the
                        while understanding two powers, the power of the voice and the power of the
                        word. The power of the voice connotes a body and the power of the word a
                        soul. It is impossible to separate the two. The same can be applied to the
                        mixture of divinity and humanity in Christ. “[M]ore (intimate) than the
                        mixture and communion of word proceeding from intelligence and voice from
                        the body, is the true communication…of the divinity and humanity in
                            Christ.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 206. See also: 205–7.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John emphasizes the limitations on divine revelation to
                        rational creatures: “When God speaks to us, He speaks in our language and
                        not in His. God is unknowable even to the angels. Our concepts of Him are
                        analogous, not univocal…The silence of God speaks to us in a voice without
                        becoming voice.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 209</p></note> What God shows in visions is not his essence.
                        No created comparison approaches God. “No word expresses His Word. We know
                        only that He exists.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 209-10.</p></note> The goal of humans in this
                        life is to arrive at silence, to progress through the ranks of<pb n="399"/>
                        voice, word and silence, to a knowledge of the truth known in itself without
                        symbols, to a knowledge of the new life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                            n="31"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 211.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.6" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Humans went astray by choosing the material world and ignorance over
                        wisdom </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In John’s theology, human beings have distanced themselves from
                        God and rendered themselves strangers to Him. They have lost all trace of
                        the perfect and true life, and dissipated the treasures hidden in them. They
                        have chosen to be amazed no longer “at the invisible riches which are in all
                        the worlds and in the celestial multitudes, of their glorious and perfect
                            beauties.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Troisième Traité du meme sur le mystè de
                                    l’économie du Christ notre Seigneur</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 159.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Deprived of the knowledge of God, humans had fallen “into the
                        profound darkness of ignorance and became darkness themselves, enveloped in
                        the fog of error and incapable of knowing themselves.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Deuxième Traité du même sur le mystère du
                                    Christ</hi>, Levanent, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>,
                                154.</p></note> Captivated by the flesh, “creatures had gone outside
                        their nature in turning toward the exterior world, having lost knowledge of
                        themselves and of the dignity received at creation, and forgotten the
                        invisible action of God hidden in them.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                            n="34"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Reponse à Thomasios</hi>, Levanent, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 136-7,</p></note> With the
                        corporeal world as their only source of knowledge, a barrier hindered access
                        to their inner self. Wandering far from God, each evil passion became an
                        obstacle hindering the soul from seeing anything other than the corporeal.
                        The evil powers brought it about that humans were without knowledge of their
                        creator or of creation, did not understand themselves and were unaware of
                        where or how they were. The original harmony and concord that God had placed
                        in creatures was broken by rebellion and error.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Lettre de Mar Jean à Thomasios</hi>, 125.
                            </p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.7" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Invisible Word became the visible Christ to be teacher, exemplar and
                        redeemer</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">John declares that Christ uniquely is the whole content of the
                        mystery of the Gospel. When God chose to reveal this plan of salvation
                        through the intermediary of His Son, the Son chose<pb n="400"/> poverty and
                        smallness to manifest the glory of His wisdom.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Cinquième Dialogue,</hi> Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 106.</p></note> Divine
                        intervention was needed to break all barriers to enable human souls to see
                        the mystery of the other world. Since they had lost the light of knowledge,
                        they lived on the level of the body and did not realize they were more than
                        flesh and blood. Throughout the years God sent messengers, seers, and
                        helpers. Since no one else could deliver them, the one who is invisible and
                        hidden in himself went out of the invisible to the visible to render himself
                        visible to creatures. Since humans were not persuaded that this mystery was
                        given to them by God, Christ clothed himself visibly to teach them. He
                        limited his infinite light, power, and wisdom into a single human form.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Deuxième Dialogue avec Thomasios sur la
                                    transformation dont bénéficiera l’homme dans le vie future: dans
                                    le monde futur il sera spiritual. Et d’autres sujets</hi>,
                                Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 64; <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Deuxième Traité</hi>, 148; <hi rend="italic">Troisième
                                    Traité</hi>, 167.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In a letter to a young monk named Hesychius, John gives this
                        advice:</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">Now it is only when your mind is wrapped in meditation
                        on the incarnation of our</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">Lord – at whose good will and pleasure you have been
                        held worthy to perform</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">good works – that pride will not be sown within you. For
                        without his self-</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">abasement, we should have been far too low down for
                        those beautiful qualities of</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">his, and not even a distant recollection of them would
                        have entered our minds.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                                xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter to Hesychius</hi>, translated by Sebastian
                                Brock in <hi rend="italic">Syriac Fathers</hi>, 83.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Christ was sent as a messenger and came as a physician, as a
                        brother and spoke as a teacher. He was poor with the poor, tempted with
                        those who are tempted and liberated his friends from captivity, while he was
                        led to death. His lowliness is seen in the body he took from us, while his
                        human actions are attributed to his divinity to which he is indivisibly
                            united.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p xml:lang="en"><hi
                                    rend="italic"> Troisième Traité</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 168–70.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> According to John, Christ fought against Satan and his
                        temptations as an example to humans. Humans had not been convinced of God’s
                        invisible mystery that those who fight against Satan and triumph over
                        temptations to evil will be worthy of the mysteries known to the angels. The
                        Son of God<pb n="401"/> abased himself thus teaching humans how far they had
                        fallen from their true dignity. He accepted crucifixion to teach humans how
                        they are captive to their passions and plunged in the darkness of error. In
                        his humanity Christ demonstrates the internal spiritual battle that humans
                        must wage against temptations to vainglory, pride and arrogance. He
                        fashioned humans in his image, restored life, light and intelligence,
                        reconciled, enabled humans to participate in his grandeur, and raised them
                        to his world of truth and his kingdom of peace, the new world.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Réponse à Thomasios</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 139; <hi rend="italic">Deuxième
                                    Traité</hi>, 150, 155–6.</p></note> Through his work of
                        salvation, Christ bestows a wisdom that was not attainable by the righteous
                        who lived before his coming.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>,
                                130–2; Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 39.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Christ by his will saves invisibly by guiding, reconciling,
                        affirming and sanctifying human beings. John declares that Christ “elevates
                        and traces the image and structure of the new man in resemblance to his
                        knowledge and in the image of his wisdom and in according to the form of his
                        living and vivifying way of understanding. He operates in the interior self
                        and by his all-powerful force.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                                xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic"> Troisième Traité</hi>, Levenant,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 162–3.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John teaches that the words of Christ are portrayed in his
                        works. He advises his reader that if he wishes to put on the image of
                        Christ, he should accomplish his works. “For where there exist works, there
                        also is his image. And where there is his image, there is his
                        perceptibility, and where there is his perceptibility there is his
                        communion. His communion is union with the Father and union with the
                            Spirit.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Maroki, “Lettre,” in “Jean le Solitaire,” 501–2.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.2.8" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The wisdom of Christ gives hope for the future resurrection</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The wisdom that comes from communion with Christ enables humans
                        to attain their hope unimpeded. John emphasizes the fact that Christ teaches
                        that the ultimate destiny of human beings is their future resurrection and a
                        new life similar to that of the angels. Christ offers this hope of
                        resurrection to those who are baptized and seek a life of virtue according
                        to His teachings. The truth that humans seek cannot be found through human
                        effort or from the wisdom of the world. It is<pb n="402"/> only God’s
                        revelation and God’s grace that can raise them above their human nature.
                        Humans live through faith which hopes in God, “who in his mercy makes us
                        worthy of this hope by communion in his spiritual mysteries. “<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Quatrième Dialogue</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 99; Also “Introduction,”
                                28–29.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> According to John, Christ’s plan of salvation extends to all
                        rational creatures. It is adapted to beings on high and humans below
                        according to their capacity. Regarding celestial beings he elevates them,
                        enriches them and brings renewal in understanding. To earthly beings he
                        grants resurrection, life and participation in his grandeur. To rebellious
                        Principalities and Powers he brings humiliation of their pride, a
                        liquidation of their activity and an annihilation of their power.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Réponse à Thomasios</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 142; <hi rend="italic">Troisième
                                    Traité</hi>, 163.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In his <hi rend="italic">Third Treatise on the Mystery of the
                            Economy of Christ Our Savior,</hi> John declares that all he has exposed
                        on the richness of the mysteries of Christ is but a small stone from a high
                        mountain or a grain of sand from the shore. Humans know only of the
                        salvation he brought to them, but not of the other worlds, nor “of the
                        renewal accomplished among the angels, his action regarding the Powers, his
                        power among the Dominations, his lordship over the Principalities, his
                        wisdom regarding the Seraphim, his knowledge regarding the Cherubim, his
                        grandeur, his richness, his perfection and his truth before the
                            Father.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 159-60.</p></note> John
                        declares that Christ’s mystery “lives in all, is hidden in all, is mingled
                        and united in all and adorned by all.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                            n="47"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 160.</p></note> John teaches that the
                        power of Christ resides hidden in all orders, powers and rational creatures.
                        He “holds in his hand the end of all ends, the heights of the heights, the
                        depth of the depths…The force of divine wisdom of Christ envelopes all the
                        worlds, is extended to all and acts in all. It renders all things great and
                        it enriches the knowledge of each of the orders.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 161-2.</p></note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>THE SPIRITUAL LIFE</head>

                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Baptism</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Initiation into the life of the spirit begins with baptism.
                        John observes that just as the power of Christ in His miracles was<pb
                            n="403"/> not revealed to humans before Christ’s baptism, so the
                        knowledge of the divine mysteries is not manifested to humans before
                        receiving baptism. Baptism involves not only visible baptism, but also
                        plunging completely beyond this visible world. “Just as after his baptism
                        our Lord manifested signs and prodigies, likewise man now possesses
                        perfectly the holy power of baptism, while he is adorned of the divine
                            gifts.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Deuxième Traité</hi>, Levenant, Dialogues,
                                149.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The reception of baptism enrolls humans in the great mystery
                        of achieving communion with God. John claims that in a sense remission of
                        sins is a secondary result of baptism. Otherwise, he asks what would be the
                        reason to baptize infants. “The principal effect of baptism is to make us
                        children of God for the liberty of the new life in the name of the glorious
                            Trinity.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter to Theodolus and companions </hi>in
                                Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,” 189.</p></note> Infants were born into
                        servitude, because the transgression of the first man reigns over all
                        humans. Christ drew a figure of the reality to come by the mystery of his
                        baptism, which served as a type of his death and Resurrection. Just as He
                        rose from the tomb, humans ascend from the baptismal font into a spiritual
                        life. Christ has produced in humans a hope of a new life. It is not the
                        water that renews but the “incubation of a secret force.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 191-2.</p></note> For the
                        baptized it is no longer the Law which is their teacher, but the baptismal
                        mystery which becomes the master which guides the baptized. The freedom that
                        Christ confers means that humans will not be dealing with the Law or further
                        moral combat in the heavenly Jerusalem.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                            n="52"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 192.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Before the revelation of Christ humans knew only of Divine
                        Providence. When Christ manifested himself as a light which chases the
                        darkness, the true knowledge of the new life dissipated the obscurity of
                        error. The Jerusalem on high will receive humans according to the measure of
                        their growth in the knowledge of the new man.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid.,190.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Baptism operates secretly in this present life and will be
                        manifested fully in the future life. John offers examples from the
                        Scriptures. Jeremiah was consecrated prophet in his mother’s womb, but his
                        vocation appeared only in his public life. David received his royal
                        anointing long before he was<pb n="404"/> recognized as king. Joseph
                        received his gift of interpreting dreams as a youth, but exercised it later
                        when imprisoned by Pharaoh.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 192.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> For John, there are two resurrections. The first is at baptism
                        when one is introduced to the spiritual life. The second is when one rises
                        to eternity. If human conduct after baptism is without fault, one is already
                        in the new life, but not in its understanding. This life in the spirit can
                        give a partial anticipation of the contemplation proper to the future life.
                        Nevertheless, the future life begins here on earth.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p xml:lang="en"> Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,”
                                211–2.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Hope</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In John’s theological system, divine revelation culminating in
                        the teachings and actions of the incarnate Christ marks a significant
                        milestone in God’s plan of salvation. However, the destiny of humanity and
                        all of creation awaits the completion of the divine plan. Relying on the
                        promises of Jesus Christ believers confidently hope that the fulfillment
                        will take place. For John, hope is the key virtue that consistently urges
                        humans to strive for that goal. According to Irenée Hausherr, the letters of
                        John “show us a sentiment of the goods to come, a waiting on God, becoming
                        here below a source of freedom, knowledge, joy of heart beyond the struggle
                        with resolutions and of intellectual discourse. The future glory already
                        appears as a dawn to the eyes of faith. The mysticism of John consists of
                        living eternity in time…(It is a) science of the mysteries of the other
                        world, of a knowledge illumined by the hope of God. …It is charity which
                        enables other virtues to grow, a charity nourished by being attached to
                        future goods.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 212–3.</p></note> According to John the hope promised by
                        Christ includes the resurrection of the dead, communion with God, life with
                        the angels, ineffable blessings, promises, life, diverse revelations,
                        spiritual knowledge, wisdom, a peace exempt of any struggle with thoughts,
                        and a true rest from combat against sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57"
                            n="57"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Troisième Traité</hi>, Levenant, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Dialogues</hi>, 163–4.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <pb n="405"/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.3" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Progress in the Spiritual Life</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">John depicts the spiritual life as a long struggle with
                        passions and temptations which must be overcome by seeking the truth. John
                        speaks of three levels or orders of the spiritual life, the level of the
                        body, of the soul, and of the spirit. This threefold approach was adopted by
                        many Syriac writers including Isaac of Nineveh and Joseph the
                            Visionary.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Brock, <hi rend="italic">Syriac Fathers</hi>, 79.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Using the term “level” does not mean that there are three
                        discrete stages in the spiritual life wherein one completes the first stage
                        to proceed to the next. Nor does it mean that when one is operating on the
                        level of the soul that the level of the body is no longer an issue. Rather
                        John is trying to delve into the human composite which in its earthly
                        existence is made up of the earthly body with its senses and passions, the
                        soul with its interior senses and intellectual and volitional activity, and
                        the spiritual nature which is located at the depths of the soul. When one is
                        given over primarily to the secular world and the waywardness of the
                        physical passions, one’s lifestyle or way of life is on the corporeal level.
                        When one has disciplined the urges of the body, the soul becomes focused on
                        the aspirations of the intellect to seek knowledge and wisdom. However, even
                        at this level the soul must function through the senses and passions now
                        under control. While it is difficult in this life, humans strive to reach
                        the level of the spirit. However, here again the spirit must work with its
                        earthly intellect, will, and senses. This is why John notes constantly that
                        living according to the spirit for an extended time is rare in this life.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.4" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Corporeal Level </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The level of the body is the condition where one is inclined
                        toward the desires of the body and is absorbed with evil thoughts. Since the
                        soul is joined to the body, there is a life-long struggle between the body’s
                        will and that of the soul. At this level one is subject to jealousy,
                        contention and divisions. In his discussion on the passions, John speaks of
                        three divisions of passions. There are those that arise through the body’s
                        activity, those that arise from the soul’s activity through the body, and
                        those that arise from activity on the level of the<pb n="406"/> soul.
                        Passions that arise from the body include those that lead to anger, envy,
                        malice, hatred, boastfulness, vanity and pride.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p xml:lang="en"> Levenant, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Dialogues</hi>, 40; Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">On the
                                    Soul</hi>, 98–102. </p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John refers often to the rebellious Principalities and Powers
                        who in their arrogance and love of vainglory wish to control the world and
                        subject it to their power. He cites St. Paul’s Epistle to the Ephesians:
                        “For our struggle is not with flesh and blood, but with the principalities,
                        with the powers, with the world rulers of this present darkness, with the
                        evil spirits in the heavens.” These Powers knew that humans were possessed
                        of a glorious nature from their creator that lay dormant in their souls and
                        were led only by their bodily senses. Men interested only in the visible
                        were seduced and became subject to their will. By use of visions, plants,
                        stones, reptiles, and animals, these Powers delude humans into thinking that
                        they have power over the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                                xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic"> Réponse à Thomasios</hi>, Levenant,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 135–6.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> However, John notes that the demon is unable to touch the soul
                        directly since it is invisible to him. However, because the soul is attached
                        to the body, especially to the heart and brain, he is able to cause
                        confusion. He is unable to see or touch the soul, but only the organs in
                        which are hidden the soul’s vigor. If he were able to affect the soul, he
                        would be able to do so after the soul leaves the body. But since he cannot
                        see the soul, he has no power over it, because his power is stopped at the
                            body.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p xml:lang="en"><hi
                                    rend="italic"> Sixième Dialogue</hi>, Levenant, Dialogues,
                                117–8.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Those living on the corporeal level seek power, honors and
                        desire to accumulate material things. Some persons remain at this level
                        because they have no fear of judgment nor do they care for instruction.
                        Their prayer is filled with distractions and they have an anthropomorphic
                        view of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>,
                        30–2.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> However, others reach a point where they begin resisting
                        improper desires. When they begin to achieve a harmony between soul and
                        body, they experience a salutary fear of judgment and of provoking of God’s
                        wrath. At this point the soul realizes that this fear that it will be
                        “deprived of true wisdom and become a stranger to the mysteries of God”
                        arises from its own true nature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 172.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <pb n="407"/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Level of the Soul</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">On the level of the soul one must practice asceticism by
                        fasting, vigil, detachment from earthly things, patience, and fear of God.
                        John teaches that by nature the human soul seeks to arrive at truth and
                        therefore when the soul is liberated from the urges of the body it pursues
                        its love for instruction. As the soul strives for recollection, the struggle
                        with bad thoughts continues. By avoiding the way of iniquity, it walks on
                        the way to truth. In getting rid of hateful conduct, it gains access to
                        divine knowledge. Passions of the soul include ignorance, forgetfulness,
                        conceit and unbelief. However, the soul can persevere in not giving in to
                        them by keeping distant from all earthly things, by stillness, by love, and
                        “by the nurturing of the knowledge of the truth.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p xml:lang="en"> Mar John the Solitary “An
                                Epistle on Stillness,” L. Rignel, ed., transl., <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Drei Traktate von Johannes dem Einsiedler</hi>, transl. into
                                English by Dana Miller, <hi rend="italic">The Ascetical Homilies of
                                    Saint Isaac the Syrian</hi> (Boston: Holy Transfiguration
                                Monastery, 1984): 461–2.</p></note> It is the soul’s nature to be on
                        a higher level than the body, but is subject to evil temptations because of
                        its association with the body. The needs of living in the world offer many
                        distractions when one is seeking to meditate on God. To achieve this goal
                        one must strive to arrive at a higher level.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p xml:lang="en"> Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John
                                    the Solitary</hi>, 32–4; </p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John observes that “in this life there is nothing more
                        excellent than virtuous conduct by a faith which hopes in God. In his mercy
                        he will render us worthy of this hope by communion with his mysteries.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Quatrième Dialogue</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 99.</p></note> Detouring from
                        virtuous conduct leads to error. John declares that the Epicureans strayed
                        from honest conduct by deciding to go no further than the body and thinking
                        there is nothing beyond this world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"
                                ><p xml:lang="en"> Levanant, <hi rend="italic">Premier
                                Dialogue</hi>, 53. </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> At the level of the soul, one is called to practice charity
                        and mercy. Charity is manifested in the zeal to bring those who err to the
                        knowledge of the truth. The commandment of Christ to love one’s enemies
                        means that those engaged in the spiritual life must not only express their
                        love exteriorly, but also purify their interior senses and attitudes. Mercy
                        consists not only in giving alms and performing the corporal works of mercy,
                            but<pb n="408"/> also to show compassion and forgiveness. It seeks to
                        teach those who lack purpose, and to preach hope to the hopeless.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p xml:lang="en"> Hansbury, <hi
                                    rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>, 14, 176.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.5.1" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Humility</head>
                        <p xml:lang="en">According to John, and many spiritual writers before and
                            after him, humility is the key to the way of life of the interior
                            person. Humility involves self-emptying of the love of money, followed
                            by emptying oneself of the love of praise. Humility should in no way be
                            manifested exteriorly. It consists of a pure transparence of the soul to
                            the love of God. One can arrive at a point of loving without fear, free
                            from any attachment which is not God. In true humility one attains the
                            perfection of loving God uniquely for himself.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 14; Levenant, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 25, 30.</p></note>
                        </p>
                        <p xml:lang="en"> John speaks of self-emptying on several levels. There is
                            the self-emptying of the body by abandoning of possessions, of the soul
                            by turning away from its passions, and of the spirit by ridding itself
                            of opinions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p xml:lang="en">
                                    Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary,
                                </hi>176.</p></note></p>
                        <p xml:lang="en"> In meditating on Christ’s humility, John explains that one
                            can attain an inner sight which can see beyond corporeal things and is
                            able to understand that Christ’s humbling of Himself is the door to His
                            mysteries. John declares that insofar as one has sanctified oneself, he
                            will become rich in discernments. And, insofar as one has multiplied his
                            humiliations, he shall be worthy of a knowledge of the Holy
                                Trinity.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p xml:lang="en">
                                    Maroki, “Lettre,“ in “Jean le Solitaire,” 504–5.</p></note></p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.5.2" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Stillness (Tranquility)</head>
                        <p xml:lang="en">Prayer is a principal characteristic of living on the level
                            of the soul. However, at this stage it is not free of all distractions
                            or is continual. Since in John’s worldview the realm of the divine to
                            which humans are destined is marked by silence, a primary goal of the
                            spiritual life is to arrive at a state of tranquility or stillness. John
                            teaches tranquility consists in the heart and mind’s not being troubled
                            and divided by thoughts, and the will not quarrelling with itself. It is
                            a state of serenity and gentleness of soul. Later, on the level of the
                            spirit, tranquility will consist of a mind undivided concerning the
                            truth and a<pb n="409"/> soul not confused by opinions. It is a state of
                            unity and harmony of the worlds.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"
                                    ><p xml:lang="en"> Hansbury, 178, 190.</p></note></p>
                        <p xml:lang="en"> To reach tranquility one must deprive oneself of anything
                            that would captivate the intellect. John says that during prayer one
                            should renounce the exercise of the external senses. The soul cannot
                            perceive its true self if it is bound by the impulses of the body. It
                            should seek a continual abiding within itself in stillness so that it
                            can overcome wandering thoughts and empty recollections. Along with
                            stillness, there should be further instruction in the knowledge of the
                            truth through study of the Sacred Scriptures, insight into the mysteries
                            of the natures of created things, and by narrations of God’s
                            revelations. “Little by little [one] begins to be enlightened and to
                            perceive the good that lies in his own nature. Thus he is formed in the
                            image of his Maker and made to resemble his beauty…The longer one
                            perseveres in stillness, the more his passions weaken; and the more the
                            passions weaken, the more he becomes strong and finds peace.”<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p xml:lang="en"> “An Epistle on
                                    Stillness,” in <hi rend="italic">Asectical Homilies of Saint
                                        Isaac</hi>, 463-4.</p></note> John teaches that “when we see
                            one another, we see ourselves, because our image and our seal (stamp)
                            are found in each other; and we are supported by each other as we are
                            supported by the knowledge of ourselves.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., 464.</p></note></p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.5.3" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Purity and Luminosity of Soul </head>
                        <p xml:lang="en">As noted above, the soul must go through a long process to
                            arrive at this level. One should strive for serenity and mental
                            awareness. One must have perfect love of God and of human beings.
                            Through these things a person approaches purity of soul. Purity of soul
                            is expressed in a life of good deeds and of chanting praise to God. It
                            is only after a long process of purification that one arrives at
                            luminosity of soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                                    xml:lang="en"> John the Solitary, <hi rend="italic">On the
                                        Soul</hi>, Sebastian Brock, trans., <hi rend="italic">Syriac
                                        Fathers</hi>, 80. </p></note> John describes this state of
                            perfection with the Syriac word, <hi rend="italic">shafyuta</hi>,
                            “luminosity” or “limpidity” of soul. It can also be translated as
                            “integrity” since the soul recovers its original purity. Paul Harb,
                            citing Irenée Hausherr, distinguishes between <hi rend="italic"
                                >dahyuta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">shafyuta</hi>. While both refer
                            to the purity of the soul, <hi rend="italic">dahyuta </hi>refers<pb
                                n="410"/> to the beginning of the process, and <hi rend="italic"
                                >shafyuta</hi> is its crown.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"
                                    ><p xml:lang="en"> Paul Harb, “Doctrine spirituelle de Jean Le
                                    Solitaire, Jean d’Apamée,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                                        l’Orient</hi> 2 (1971): 243.</p></note> Robert Kitchen
                            observes that “the path to Perfection necessarily begins in this life,
                            for the Christian must first achieve the level of purity and only then
                            graduate up to luminosity and finally to Perfection.”<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p xml:lang="en"> Robert Kitchen, “In Search
                                    of Lost Apophthegmata in John the Solitary of Apamea,” 13-14
                                    www.academia.edu/1176465. </p></note> According to René
                            Levenant, the term <hi rend="italic">shafyuta</hi> has the meaning of
                            “total purification which gives access to divine intimacy and renders
                            the senses of the soul capable of perceiving the mysteries of the world
                            to come.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p xml:lang="en">
                                    Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 42.</p></note> The
                            soul is now open totally to the future hope. One can arrive at this
                            state only through divine aid. Faith is a necessary condition for this
                            purification. Christ himself is the model. The soul transcends not only
                            evil passions but also the life of virtue in the body. The soul operates
                            exclusively on the level of spirit. In this state of integrity, the
                            opacity of the body gives way to transparency. This new condition is
                            invisible to humans and to Satan. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.6" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The Level of the Spirit</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Having gone beyond the struggle with evil passions of the body,
                        and the distractions and wanderings of the intellect and will, the soul
                        enters a place of peace in divine love. It receives through revelation a
                        vision of the mysteries. On the level of the spirit, one is beyond earthly
                        thoughts. One seeks the wisdom of God and nothing else.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic"> Premier
                                    Dialogue</hi>, Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 55;
                                Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>, 34.</p></note>
                        In a prayer offered to God John declares the following:</p>
                    <quote><lg xml:lang="en">
                            <l> What wonders has your love effected!</l>
                            <l> When someone is still alive </l>
                            <l> he has left this world:</l>
                            <l> though his bodily condition remains</l>
                            <l> with the world’s bodily condition,</l>
                            <l> yet his spirit has been raised up towards you,</l>
                            <l> so that for a period of time</l>
                            <l> he is where he knows not,</l>
                            <l> being totally raptured and drawn towards you.<note place="foot"
                                    xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p xml:lang="en"> Brock, <hi rend="italic"
                                            >Syriac Fathers</hi>, 346.</p></note>
                            </l>
                        </lg></quote>
                    <pb n="411"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John’s <hi rend="italic">Epistle on Stillness</hi> opens with
                        the statement: “The perfection of the truth that is fulfilled in the
                        knowledge of the Divinity is understood by knowledge through the perception
                        of perfect wisdom. This is the ‘full stature’ and the ‘light of knowledge’:
                        knowledge which is the vision of him who promised through prophecy that he
                        would appear to those who love him and keep his commandments.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p xml:lang="en"> “Epistle on
                                Stillness,” 461.</p></note> In the <hi rend="italic">Letter to
                            Hesychius</hi>, John advises: “Consider that your true wealth lies in
                        truth; for truth consists in the love of God, the awareness of his wisdom,
                        and the fulfilling of his will.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Brock, <hi rend="italic">Syriac Fathers</hi>,
                            93.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> On the level of spirit, knowledge of the mysteries is totally
                        invisible without any exterior effect. True revelations of the world to come
                        take place only in the soul which is above the turmoil of thoughts. The soul
                        understands God’s revelations not through hearing since God speaks to humans
                        without the sound of a voice but invisibly. He establishes an intimate
                        relationship with the interior person.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83"
                            n="83"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Sixième Dialogue, </hi>Levenant, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Dialogues</hi>, 118-9.</p></note> John cites St. Paul to the
                        Ephesians asking that God grant a spirit of wisdom and revelation enabling
                        knowledge of Him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 114.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Knowledge of the mysteries of the future world leads to
                        perfect charity in the love of others and total humility. One’s love for
                        others is a prerequisite for love of God. On the level of the spirit, one
                        loves God uniquely for himself. Furthermore, one can only truly love others
                        when there is an insight into the mysteries of love. Perfect love is to love
                        all persons like God. The love of Christ gathers together into one the sons
                        of light, enables them to have harmony among themselves and makes them to
                        dwell in one another. John urges his readers to implant the love of Christ
                        in themselves. Without becoming perfect in the love of Christ, one is not
                        able to arrive at a knowledge of him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85"
                            n="85"><p xml:lang="en"> Hansbury<hi rend="italic">, On the Soul</hi>,
                                42–6, 188; <hi rend="italic">Letter À Thomasios</hi>. Levenant,
                                    123<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                            </p></note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.3.7" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Silent Prayer</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">According to John the Solitary the goal of the spiritual life
                        while on earth is to break through, at least on rare occasions, into the
                        life of the world to come. The means to approach this intimacy with God is
                        through the perfecting of one’s prayer.<pb n="412"/> John considers the
                        Incarnation of the Word entering humanity as the paradigm for its approach
                        to God. Humans retrace his steps to ascend to the realm of the Word. Indeed,
                        as noted above, the resurrected humanity of Christ is the vehicle of future
                        communion with the divine. Therefore, in prayer humans are called to
                        transcend not only the corporeal character of prayer with spoken words, but
                        also to go beyond the interior prayer of the mind and heart. Ultimately
                        prayer reaches its completion in the realm of God where all is silence
                        beyond words or expression. Just as in the Incarnation the Word departed
                        from the realm of silence to become voice, so those who have put on Christ
                        are called through this union to go from voice to the silence of the
                        Word.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John advises that “spiritual prayer does not reach its
                        fullness as a result of either learning or the repetition of words.” Since
                        one is addressing God who is Spirit, one should pray in spirit. John
                        continues: </p>
                    <quote><p xml:lang="en">[S]piritual prayer is more interior than the tongue,
                            more deeply interiorized than anything on the lips, more interiorized
                            than any words, and beyond vocal song. When someone prays this kind of
                            prayer he has sunk deeper than all speech, and he stands where spiritual
                            beings and angels are to be found; like them, he utters ‘holy’ without
                            any words.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p xml:lang="en">
                                    Sebastian Brock, transl. in “John the Solitary on Prayer,” <hi
                                        rend="italic">The Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 30
                                    (1979) 97. </p></note></p></quote>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The person who worships by chanting with his tongue night and
                        day is considered one of the “just.” But one who goes deeper and chants in
                        intellect and the spirit is called “spiritual.” To arrive at spiritual
                        prayer is a long process. It involves extended periods of prayer, chanting
                        the psalms, observing vigils, fasting and abstaining, and meditation on the
                        God’s judgment in fear and trembling. One’s practice of humility should
                        reach a point where he considers others even great sinners as better than
                            himself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 98. Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony observes that the distinction
                                between the “just” and the “spiritual” could be a reflection of a
                                similar distinction in the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>.
                                See: “More interior than the lips and the Tongue,”
                            324-325.</p></note></p>
                    <pb n="413"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John explains that silent prayer does not consist merely in
                        silencing one’s tongue. This type of silence along with the quieting of
                        thought is a pre-requisite before the interior tongue of the intellect can
                        express itself. John describes five types of silence: the silence of the
                        tongue, the silence of the body, the silence of the soul, the silence of the
                        intellect and the silence of the spirit. The silence of the tongue is
                        achieved when one avoids evil speech. The silence of the body is when the
                        senses are inactive. The silence of the soul occurs when there are no evil
                        thoughts. The silence of the intellect is when one is not reflecting on
                        harmful or distracting knowledge. “The silence of the spirit is when the
                        intellect ceases even from stirrings caused by created spiritual beings and
                        all its movements are stirred solely by Being [the Existent One], at the
                        wondrous awe of the silence which surrounds Being.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p xml:lang="en"> Brock, “John the Solitary on
                                Prayer, 99.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony distinguishes John the Solitary’s
                        understanding of silent prayer from Evagrius’ teaching on pure prayer. Where
                        “Evagrius’s concept of pure prayer centered on the inner dynamic of the
                        mind, thus a major part of his descriptions is devoted to the nature and
                        experience of the mind itself, whereas John’s concept of silent prayer
                        centered on the entire self.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Bitton-Ashkelony, “Silent Prayer,” 321-2.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> John concludes the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Prayer</hi> by
                        teaching that prayer is not an end in itself. Here on earth one’s very self,
                        spirit, soul and body should become the words we have prayed. Prayer should
                        become embodied and result in virtuous deeds. In other words, the highest
                        form of prayer should become incarnate in deeds. John observes that as a
                        result “you are seen in the world to be a man of God.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p xml:lang="en"> Brock, “John the Solitary on
                                Prayer,” 87–8.</p></note> In a sense one is imitating on a
                        creaturely level the Word of God who emerges from the realm of divine
                        silence and dwells among us to carry out the work of salvation. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>THE NEW WORLD</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">As noted above, the promise of the spiritual life begins with
                    baptism. In baptism one is sanctified for a future glory, but its manifestation
                    will take place only in the world to come.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91"
                        n="91"><p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic"> Letter to Theodoulos </hi>in
                            Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,” 192.</p></note> Earthly baptism is a “type”
                    of the new birth after the<pb n="414"/> resurrection. John claims that the
                    mystery of baptism, of resurrection and of luminosity is one process. He cites
                    the example of the veil covering a fetus. Just as physical birth involves going
                    through the veil into earthly existence, so the birth of the true person goes
                    beyond luminosity into the new world. Limpidity is an intermediate state for the
                    virtuous person to go out into the spiritual world where the mind achieves true
                    understanding. Again, it is rare in this life for one to reach this state of
                    perceiving the wisdom of the new world. Above luminosity is the new life of the
                    new person not in doing works but in knowledge. No one has lived this new life
                    here on earth but Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p
                            xml:lang="en"> Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>,
                            122–6.</p></note>
                </p>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.4.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>The New Person in the World to Come</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">As noted above, some are able to have intimations of the new
                        person in the present life. They begin to receive the future gifts and begin
                        to live the new life at least on rare occasions. From his study of the
                        Scriptures John in his writings attempts to describe some of the features of
                        the world to come.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> As long as the soul is in its earthly body its own interior
                        senses are not able to operate on the spiritual level. Revelations which
                        directed to the level of the spirit can be communicated only in corporeal
                        images. But once the soul arises completely from the body and enters into
                        the spiritual world, and its thought is no longer enclosed in the body, then
                        its spiritual senses begin to operate efficaciously on spiritual things.
                        Along with the change in the body is a change in how the soul understands
                        itself. Its knowledge and understanding go beyond itself. The body itself is
                        transformed by the resurrection to constitute with the soul a spiritual
                        unity. It operates within the spiritual man and is circumscribed by him.
                        John cites Paul’s letter to the Corinthians that what is sown as a natural
                        body is resurrected a spiritual body. Humans become like the angels who are
                        not exteriorly corporeal and interiorly spiritual, but their spirituality is
                        all of the same order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Premier<hi rend="italic"> Dialogue</hi>,<hi
                                    rend="italic"> Leve</hi>nant, 54–6; <hi rend="italic">Letter to
                                    Eutropius and Eusebius </hi>in Hausherr, “Un grand auteur,”
                                197.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In the new world the mind seeks communion with the wisdom of
                        God in the knowledge of His mysteries. There is a thirst for the spiritual
                        mysteries which gives delight to the new<pb n="415"/> person in the new
                        life. In this state of spiritual awareness, the intellect “emanates from the
                        wisdom of God.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Hansbury, <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary</hi>, 134; See also:
                                138, 146, 148, 192.</p></note> The soul experiences joy and divine
                        love. The soul is elevated to the sublime majesty where it becomes aware of
                        its own smallness. At this level one does not judge those who have gone
                        astray nor consider oneself better than others.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter to Eutropius and Eusebius </hi>in Hausherr,
                                “Un grand auteur,” 197.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> “After the resurrection of the body, God gives us true
                        knowledge. Humans are new persons without sin or evil thoughts.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Letter to Theodoulos </hi>in Hausherr, “Un grand
                                auteur,” 190.</p></note> Their sole concern is God’s will with an
                        attitude free of abstract thinking and where soul and body are in harmony
                        and equilibrium. The earthly world was made of lifeless elements which
                        nevertheless manifest the wisdom of God. The world to come is living,
                        constituted by living beings, the angels and the just. There is no need for
                        intellectual searching. The saints know God by revelation, by an interior
                            perception.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Ibid., 190-1.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Hope in the new world is manifested in an understanding
                        different from what one presently possesses, “to have our thoughts
                        completely transformed and our deficient movements replaced by perfect ones.
                        We do not know how our understanding will be or how we will know God.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Lettre à Thomasios, </hi>Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 121.</p></note> Humans are called
                        to turn to God in love and faith and will learn in a divine manner. John
                        explains that in the new world one will be able to see the invisible by an
                        invisible thought without the need of form or intermediary and according to
                        one’s capacity. The divine mysteries are known without image, form or
                            color.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p xml:lang="en"><hi
                                    rend="italic"> Sixième Dialogue</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 112–3.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In a response to Thomasios, John prays that “Christ who is the
                        true form and true body, the image and beauty of all the worlds to act in us
                        by his grace, to reveal his invisible mystery, to illumine our intelligence,
                        to make us understand the depth of his invisible wisdom, to purify the
                        operations of our thought, so that we are able to see the multiple beauties
                        which compose the image of his mystery.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100"
                            n="100"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Réponse à Thomasios</hi>, Levenant, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>, 131.</p></note> Yet, God’s wisdom
                        is incomprehensible and without limit. While one may know the<pb n="416"/>
                        forms under which it manifests itself, we are unable to explain its mystery,
                        but only know that it is. God is known in the new world by a new vision that
                        is unknowable to humans and which reduces them to silence. It is beyond
                        words and thoughts. One exults in a knowledge that he cannot understand in
                        the bosom of the mystery of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"
                                ><p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic"> Deuxième Dialogue avec
                                    Thomasios</hi>, Levenant, <hi rend="italic">Dialogues</hi>,
                                59.</p></note> John’s view is reflected in this prayer: “the more a
                        person has loved you, the more you will manifest the wondrous sight of you.
                        Not that you refuse to manifest yourself here, only that here this takes
                        place by means of the revelation of mysteries, whereas at the end of time it
                        will be by means of a glorious vision of you. Not everyone will behold you
                        there equally but each in accordance with his capability.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p xml:lang="en"> Brock, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Syriac Fathers</hi>, 347.</p></note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2beggiani.5" xml:lang="en">
                <head>CONCLUSION</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">John the Solitary offers a spiritual doctrine based primarily on
                    Scripture. While his writings are focused on spiritual direction, they reflect a
                    developed and consistent theology based on a biblical world-view. John views
                    creation as a manifestation of God’s glory. All creatures spiritual and
                    material, animate and inanimate were created for a purpose, and all of creation
                    is destined for transformation and fulfillment. While John does not know the
                    shape or form of this ultimate stage, he relies on Scripture to project what
                    future may await human beings and the rest of creation.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> John does not separate spirit from soul, but rather describes the
                    spiritual component as invisible and embedded in the depths of the soul. John
                    declares that the spirit is stamped with the image and likeness of the
                    preexistent Word of God made flesh. This understanding forms the basis of his
                    spiritual doctrine. It is also the approach of other Eastern spiritual writers
                    including Isaac of Nineveh. The whole human person constituted of spirit, soul
                    and body was intended from the beginning to grow towards perfection in this
                    world. This process of maturation would reach its completion in the
                    transformation of the human person in the resurrection. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In attempting to describe the bridging of the divide between the
                    divine and the created John uses the terms “invisible” and “visible.” Echoing
                    Paul, John states that God reveals himself in material creation. For him this
                    means a true<pb n="417"/> presence but invisible by nature. In the same way,
                    God’s revelation, the Incarnation, the actions of the Holy Spirit and grace, all
                    partake of invisible reality. The image and likeness of God constituent of human
                    beings is also invisible to human knowledge.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In John’s view, the Word of God becoming human was a necessary
                    part of God’s plan for the world. Constituted of soul and body, humans do not
                    have the capacity on their own to deal with the spiritual way of life to which
                    they are called. Their limited capacity became even more obstructed by sin.
                    God’s revelation in the Scriptures and in the coming of Christ was the only way
                    to teach and guide humans toward the spiritual way of life. Christ carried out
                    the role of teacher and physician. He extended his divinizing activity on earth
                    by instituting baptism, the Eucharist and the other mysteries of the Church.
                    Ultimately, he was the ideal example of achieving the life of the spirit by his
                    life, death and resurrection. The resurrected and transformed humanity of Christ
                    becomes the vehicle of future transformation for humans. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> John’s spiritual direction addresses how human beings are to
                    conduct themselves in the present world to arrive at fulfillment in communion
                    with the resurrected Christ. His approach is to deal with the human condition as
                    he finds it. His method is to address the particular characteristics of the
                    body, the soul and the spirit, and provide direction on their purification. This
                    threefold analysis differs from the threefold approach of purification,
                    illumination and contemplation found in Evagrius and other spiritual writers. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> For John a way of life focused on the body is a condition where
                    the urgings of the body dominate the intellect and will. The spiritual life is
                    not a concern and there is no attempt at asceticism. The way of the soul
                    describes those who are aware of God’s teachings as expressed in the human
                    language of Scripture. At this level, one strives to obey the commandments,
                    practice asceticism to achieve harmony between soul and body, pray publicly and
                    privately, and perform good works. Humility and self-denial are essential for
                    progress. Ultimately, one seeks to arrive at purity and luminosity of soul.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The level of the spirit is rarely achievable on a regular basis in
                    this life. It represents a foreshadowing of the life to come. One experiences
                    communion with the resurrected Christ and insights into his wisdom. The result
                    is an overflow of charity<pb n="418"/> towards others. John presents a
                    description of this high point of the spiritual journey in his teaching on
                    silent prayer. In quelling all activity of the body and soul, one’s spirit is
                    released from all of its ties to the created world and enters the silence of the
                    divine.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In John the Solitary we find a spirituality founded on the premise
                    that humans having been created in the image and likeness of the incarnate God
                    are destined to be in union with his resurrected humanity and sharing in his
                    wisdom and love for all creation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="syr">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <bibl>Bitton-Ashkelony, Brouria. “More Interior than the Lips and the Tongue: John
                    of Apamea and Silent Prayer in Late Antiquity.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        Early Christian Studies</hi> 20 (2012): 303-331.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Book of Steps: The Syriac Liber Graduum</hi>. Translated,
                    with an Introduction and Notes by Robert A. Kitchen and Martien F. G.
                    Parmentier. Kalamazoo: Cistercian Press, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bradley, Bruce. “Jean le Solitaire.” <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de
                        Spiritualité</hi> 8 (1974): cols. 764-72.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Fathers on Prayer and the
                        Spiritual Life.</hi> Kalamazoo: Cistercian Publications, Inc., 1987. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Spirituality in the Syriac Tradition</hi>.
                    Kottayam: St. Ephrem Research Institute, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl>de Halleux, André. “Christologie de Jean de Solitaire.” Le Muséon 94 (1981):
                    5-36.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian: Select Poems</hi>. Translation,
                    introduction and notes, Sebastain P. Brock and and George A. Kiraz . Provo,
                    Utah: Brigham Young University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Harb, Paul. “Doctrine spirituelle de Jean Le Solitaire, Jean d’Apamée.” Parole
                    de l’Orient 2 (1971): 225-60. </bibl>
                <pb n="419"/>
                <bibl>Hausherr, Irenée. “Un grand auteur spiritual retrouvé: Jean d’Apamée.” OCA 183
                    (1969): 181–216. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Dialogue sur l’âme et les passions des
                    hommes</hi>. OCA 120. Rome, 1939.</bibl>
                <bibl>John the Solitary. <hi rend="italic">Brief von Johannes dem Einsiedler</hi>.
                    Translated by Lars Rignell, Lund: Hakan Ohlssons, 1941.</bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Drei Traktate von Johannes dem Einsiedler
                        (Johannes von Apamea)</hi>. Translated and edited by L.G. Rignell. Lund,
                    1960.</bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . “An Epistle on Stillness.” Translated by Dana Miller. In <hi
                        rend="italic">The Ascetical Homilies of Saint Isaac the Syrian</hi>. Boston:
                    Holy Transfiguration Monastery, 1981: 461–6.</bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Jean d’Apamée. Dialogues et Traités.</hi>
                    Translated by René Levenant. Sources Chrétiennes 311. Paris: Editions du Cerf,
                    1984. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . “Jean le Solitaire (d’Apamée), Quatre Lettres inedités, Textes
                    Syriaques et Traduction Française.” By Sameer Maroki. <hi rend="italic">Parole
                        de l’Orient</hi> 35 (2010): 477–506. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Johannes von Lycopolis, Ein Dialog über die Seele
                        und die Affekte des Menschen</hi>. Edited by Sven Dedering. Uppsala, 1936. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . “Letter to Hesychius.” Translated by Sebastian Brock. In <hi
                        rend="italic">The Syriac Fathers on Prayer and the Spiritual Life.</hi>
                    Kalamazoo: Cistercian, 1987: 81–98. </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">John the Solitary on the Soul</hi><hi>. Translated
                        by Mary Hansbury. Piscataway: Gorgias, 2013.</hi>
                </bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . “On Prayer.” Translated by Sebastian Brock, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 30 (1979): 97-100. Reprinted in In <hi
                        rend="italic">The Ascetical Homilies of Saint Isaac the Syrian</hi>. Boston:
                    Holy Transfiguration Monastery, 1981: 466-8. </bibl>
                <pb n="420"/>
                <bibl>_______ . <hi rend="italic">Sechs Gesprache mit Thomasios, Der Briefweschel
                        zwischen Thomasios und Johannes und drei an Thomasios gerichtete Abband
                        lungen</hi>, Translated and edited by Werner Strothmann. Berlin: Walter de
                    Gruyter, 1972. </bibl>
                <bibl>Kitchen, Robert. <hi rend="italic">In Search of Lost Apophthegmata in John the
                        Solitary of Apamea</hi>. <ref target="http://www.academia.edu/1176465"><hi
                            style="font-family:Garamond;font-size:12pt"
                            >www.academia.edu/1176465</hi></ref></bibl>
                <bibl>_______ . “Youhannan Ihidaya,” <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic
                        Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</hi>. Edited by Sebastian P. Brock, Aaron
                    M. Butts, George A. Kiraz, Lucas Van Rompay. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press,
                    2011. </bibl>
                <bibl> Possekel, Ute, “Syriac Theology,” in <hi rend="italic">Oxford Handbook to the
                        Reception History of Christian Theology</hi> (forthcoming). <ref
                        target="http://www.academia.edu/27635980"><hi
                            style="font-family:Garamond;font-size:12pt"
                            >www.academia.edu/27635980</hi></ref></bibl>
                <bibl>Possekel, Ute. <hi rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical Cocnepts in
                        the Wrtiting of Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, CSCO 580. Leuven: Peeters,
                    1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>_______. “Syriac Theology,” in <hi rend="italic">Oxford Handbook to the
                        Reception History of Christian Theology</hi> (forthcoming).
                    www.academia.edu/27635980</bibl>
                <pb n="4421"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
