<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Preliminary Considerations on Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī's Islamic
                    Sources</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Bert</forename>
                        <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>KU Leuven</orgName>
                        <orgName>The Louvain Centre for Eastern and Oriental Christianity
                            (LOCEOC)</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n2jacobs</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Bert Jacobs</author>
                        <title level="a">Preliminary Considerations on Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī's
                            Islamic Sources</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N2Jacobs.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="357" to="389">357-389</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="5"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Qurʾān</term>
                    <term>Translation</term>
                    <term>Alphonse Mingana</term>
                    <term>Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī</term>
                    <term>Christian-Muslim apologetics</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-11-01">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Though Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī (d. 1171) wrote his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Disputation Against the Arabs</hi> during the so-called ‘Syriac
                    Renaissance’ (c. 1026-1318), a period characterized by an increased Christian
                    awareness of Islamic literary culture, to date no sustained appeal has been made
                    for a direct use of Islamic sources in composing this work. This situation seems
                    largely influenced by Alphonse Mingana who categorically rejected Bar Ṣalībī’s
                    knowledge of Islamic literature, particularly the Arabic Qurʾān. This article
                    proposes to take a fresh look at the potential traces of Islamic sources the
                    work displays. Such a reading reveals traces of at least five other Islamic
                    literary genres besides the Qurʾānic excerpts for which the work is well known:
                    Muḥammad’s biography (<hi rend="italic">sīra</hi>), heresiography, exegesis (<hi
                        rend="italic">tafsīr</hi>), prophetic traditions (<hi rend="italic"
                        >ḥadīth</hi>), and the so-called ‘stories of the prophets’ (<hi
                        rend="italic">qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʾ</hi>). To prepare the way for a closer
                    assessment of Bar Ṣalībī’s Islamic sources, the aim of this paper is to survey
                    the various allusions to and quotations of the material<pb n="357"/> reminiscent of these
                    five additional literary genres, and to reflect on their significance with
                    regards to Bar Ṣalībī’s interculturality. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.1" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">Though the earliest interactions between Syriac Christians and Muslims
                within the nascent Islamic empire may have been characterized by more hybridity and
                ill-defined borders than was once suspected,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"
                        ><p xml:lang="en">* This article presents some intermediary results of my
                        current PhD project on the apologetic theology and sources of Dionysius Bar
                        Ṣalībī’s <hi rend="italic">Disputation Against the Arabs</hi>, particularly
                        his use of the Qurʾān and other Islamic texts. I thank the FWO for
                        generously supporting my research. I also wish to thank James E. Walters for
                        his patience with me and for checking my English.</p><p xml:lang="en"> Thus
                        the thesis of Michael P. Penn, <hi rend="italic">Envisioning Islam: Syriac
                            Christianity and the Early Muslim World</hi> (Pennsylvania: University
                        of Pennsylvania Press, 2015).</p></note> the religious borderlines soon
                became increasingly delineated. An activity particularly instrumental to this
                development was the production of apologetic/polemic texts on both sides clearly
                manifesting the depths of the Christian-Muslim theological divide. Though the
                earliest examples of such works on the Christian side were still composed in Syriac,
                such as <hi rend="italic">The Disputation between Patriarch John and an Emir</hi>,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Disputation between a Monk of Bēt</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ḥālē and a Muslim</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">The Disputation between Timothy I
                    and the Caliph al-Mahdī</hi>, from the early ʿAbbāsid period onwards the use of
                Syriac as the primary literary language of theological discourse and debate
                gradually declined in favor of the official language of the Caliphate, Arabic.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> For overviews of the Syriac
                        apologetic texts in response to Islam, see Sidney H. Griffith, “Disputes
                        with Muslims in Syriac Christian Texts: From Patriarch John (d. 648) to Bar
                        Hebraeus (d. 1286),” in <hi rend="italic">Religionsgespräche im
                            Mittelalter</hi>, Wolfenbütteler Mittelalter-Studien 4, ed. B. Lewis and
                        F. Niewöhner (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1992), 251-273; id., <hi
                            rend="italic">Syriac Writers on Muslims and the Religious Challenge of
                            Islam</hi> (Kottayam: SEERI, 1995); Barbara Roggema, “Pour une lecture
                        des dialogues islamo-chrétiens en syriaque à la lumière des controverses
                        internes à l’islam,” in <hi rend="italic">Les controverses religieuses en
                            syriaque</hi>, Études syriaques 13, ed. F. Ruani (Paris: Geuthner,
                        2016), 261-294. For early Muslim polemics against Christianity, see e.g.
                        David Thomas, <hi rend="smallcaps">“</hi>Early Muslim Responses to
                        Christianity,” in <hi rend="italic">Christians at the Heart of Islamic Rule:
                            Church Life and Scholarship in </hi><hi rend="italic">ʿAbbasid
                        Iraq</hi>, The History of Christian-Muslim Relations 1, ed. D. Thomas
                        (Leiden: Brill, 2003), 231-254.</p></note> In the period of the so-called
                ‘Syriac<pb n="358"/> Renaissance’ (c. 1026-1318), however, one more Syriac work specifically
                devoted to refuting Islam would appear. Of all Syriac refutation texts, this one
                perhaps most sharply draws the lines between the truth of Christianity and the
                falsehood of Islam: <hi rend="italic">The Disputation Against the Arabs</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italic">ōruʿutō luqbal ʿamō d-Arābōyē</hi>) composed by Dionysius Bar
                Ṣalībī (d. 1171), the West Syrian Metropolitan of Amīd (present-day
                    Diyarbakir).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p xml:lang="en"> A critical
                        edition based on five manuscripts together with an English translation was
                        published in 2005 by Joseph Amar, <hi rend="italic">Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī: A
                            Reponse to the Arabs</hi>, CSCO 614-615 (Leuven: Peeters, 2005). I have
                        checked Amar’s edition against the oldest manuscript from the year 1207, <hi
                            rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate 160</hi> (ff. 245a-278b).
                        Amar’s translation is the basis for the citations occuring in this paper,
                        but I regularly applied changes were deemed necessary. For Bar Ṣalībī’s
                        bio-bibliography, see Stephan D. Ryan, <hi rend="italic">Dionysius bar
                            Salibi's Factual and Spiritual Commentary on Psalms 73-82</hi>, Cahiers
                        de révue biblique 57 (Paris: J. Gabalda et Cie, 2004), p. 1-14. On the
                        period of the ‘Syriac Renaissance’, see Herman Teule, “The Syriac
                        Renaissance,” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Renaissance</hi>, Eastern
                        Christian Studies 9, ed. H. Teule <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> (Leuven:
                        Peeters, 2010), 1-30. Other writers of this period engaged Islam as well in
                        their theological writings, but none of them is credited for having composed
                        a seperate work in response to Islam. Some studies on these author’s
                        apologetics are Herman Teule, “Jacob bar Šakkō, the Book of Treasures and
                        the Syrian Renaissance,” in <hi rend="italic">Eastern Crossroads. Essays on
                            Medieval Christian Legacy</hi>, Gorgias Eastern Christianity Studies 1,
                        ed. J.-P. Monferrer-Sala (Piscataway, NJ: Georgias Press, 2007), 143-154;
                        Salam Rassi, <hi rend="italic">Justifying Christianity in the Islamic Middle
                            Ages: The Apologetic Theology of ʿAbdīshōʿ bar Brīkhā (d. 1318)</hi>
                        (PhD diss., University of Oxford, 2015); Bert Jacobs, “Unveiling Christ in
                        the Islamicate World: Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī's Prophetology as a Model for
                        Christian Apologetics in Gregory Bar ʿEbrōyō’s Treatise on the Incarnation,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of the Islamicate World</hi>
                        6/1&amp;2 (2018), 187-216.</p></note></p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Part of a larger encyclopedic work that also includes a theological
                compendium and disputations against the Jews, Nestorians, Chalcedonians, and
                Armenians, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi> is a quite significant hallmark
                in the history of Christian-Muslim relations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"
                        ><p xml:lang="en"> See my PhD dissertation for a discussion of the larger
                        literary context. On the content and significance of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Disputation Against the Arabs</hi>, see also the overviews of Syriac
                        apologetic texts in nr. 2, as well as Sidney H. Griffith<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >,</hi> “Dionysius bar Ṣalībī on the Muslims,” in <hi rend="italic">IV
                            Symposium Syriacum: Literary Genres in Syriac Literature</hi>,
                        Orientalia Christiana Analecta 229, ed. H. Drijvers <hi rend="italic">et
                            al</hi>. (Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1987), p.
                        353-365; Herman Teule, “Dionysius Bar Ṣalibi,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Christian-Muslim Relations: A Bibliographical History </hi>3 (Leiden:
                        Brill, 2011), 665-70, p. 667-70.</p></note> It is not only the latest
                disputation against Islam to<pb n="359"/> be composed in Syriac, but also the lengthiest and most
                comprehensive work of its kind, covering all the major issues of Christian-Muslim
                controversy in thirty chapters divided over three <hi rend="italic">mimrē</hi> or
                tracts. The primary topics of dispute, the doctrines of the Trinity and Incarnation,
                are most prominently present, though various secondary themes have their place as
                well. <hi rend="italic">Mimrō</hi> I (chs. 1-8) is principally devoted to refuting
                Muslim objections against Trinitarian doctrine, but also has an introductory chapter
                on the origins and teachings of Islam, and one on the divisions in the early Muslim
                community. The doctrine of the Incarnation is the central theme of <hi rend="italic"
                    >mimrō</hi> II (chs. 9-24), but several chapters also discuss Muḥammad’s
                prophetic status, the legitimacy of Christian spiritual practices, the scriptural
                integrity of the Bible and the Qurʾān, and the proper conception of Paradise. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> In these first two <hi rend="italic">mimrē</hi>, Bar Ṣalībī relies on
                four types of arguments to uphold the veracity of Christianity. Besides the usual
                use of arguments from ‘nature and scripture’, he also presents testimonies from the
                pagan sages,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī
                        provides two such testimony lists: in chapter 8 concerning the Trinity, and
                        in chapter 19 for the Incarnation. Only the latter list was studied in
                        Sebastian P. Brock, ”A Syriac Collection of Prophecies of the Pagan
                        Philosophers,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica</hi> 14
                        (1983): 203-246; id., “Some Syriac Excerpts from Greek Collections of Pagan
                        Prophecies,” <hi rend="italic">Vigilae Christianae</hi> 38 (1984):
                        77-90.</p></note> and more importantly, arguments from the Qurʾān, which is
                cited in a Syriac translation. Conforming to a widespread Christian approach to the
                Qurʾān, his quotes serve either to demonstrate the Qurʾān’s flawed character or
                conversely, to find support in it for Christian teachings.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p xml:lang="en"> On early Christian approaches to the
                        Qurʾān, see Mark Beaumont, “Early Christian Interpretation of the Qurʾān,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Transformation</hi> 22/4 (2005): 195-203; Sidney H.
                        Griffith, “The Qurʾān in Arab Christian Texts; the Development of an
                        Apologetical Argument: Abū Qurrah in the <hi rend="italic">Maǧlis</hi> of
                        al-Maʾmūn,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 24 (1999): 203-233;
                        id., <hi rend="smallcaps">“</hi>Christians and the Arabic Qurʾān:
                        Prooftexting, Polemics, and Intertwined Scriptures,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Intellectual History of the Islamicate World</hi> 2 (2014): 243-266;
                        Clare E. Wilde, <hi rend="a-size-large"><hi rend="italic">Approaches to the
                                Qur’an in Early Christian Arabic Texts</hi> (750CE-1258 CE)
                        (</hi>Palo Alto, California: <hi rend="a-size-large"> Academica Press,
                            2014)</hi>.</p></note> This reading of the Qurʾān is fully<pb n="360"/> developed in
                    <hi rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III (chs. 25-30), undoubtedly the most original
                part of the work. In these final six chapters, Bar Ṣalībī divides the pages into two
                sections: one containing excerpts from the Qurʾān and the other section providing
                his commentary, i.e. his apologetic and polemic interpretations of the cited
                material. The themes that are discussed in the six chapters are revelation and
                creation (25), Adam (26), Noah (27), the Patriarchs (28), Mary and Jesus (29), and
                concludes with a chapter clustering Qurʾānic verses on a wide range of topics
                (30).</p></div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>The Issue of the Sources</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Like other writers of the Syriac Renaissance, Bar Ṣalībī’s favored
                    method of composition, as displayed in <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                    is to compile previous works and combine, edit, and shape them to his own
                    purposes. The identification of his sources and the assessment of how he makes
                    uses of them, however, is still largely uncharted territory. That he principally
                    draws, as might be expected, on Syriac and Christian Arabic sources has recently
                    received some initial attention.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            xml:lang="en"> See Martin Heimgartner, <hi rend="italic">Timotheos I.,
                                Ostsyrischer Patriarch: Disputation mit dem Kalifen Al-Mahdī,
                            </hi>CSCO 631-2 (Leuven: Peeters,<hi rend="smallcaps"> 2011), </hi>tr.,
                            p. xxvii (nr. 105); Shabo Talay, “Aus dem polemischen Genre des
                            Syrischen: Die luqbal-Schriften von Bar Ṣalībī und Bar Šūšan,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana, Festschrift für Hubert Kaufhold
                                zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, ed. P. Bruns and H. O. Luthe(Wiesbaden:
                            Harrassowitz, 2013), 511-521, p. <hi rend="smallcaps">517-8</hi>. On Bar
                            Ṣalībī’s use of the now lost <hi rend="italic">Chronicle </hi>of
                            Dionysius of Tell-Maḥrē (d. 845) in the opening chapter of the <hi
                                rend="italic">Disputation</hi>, see Bert Jacobs, “Tentative
                            Reconstruction of Dionyius of Tell-Maḥrē’s Account of the Rise of Islam
                            through Three Dependant Texts,” forthcoming.</p></note> However, whether
                    he also made use of Islamic sources, a marked trait of<pb n="361"/> Syriac Christian writers
                    during his period,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p xml:lang="en"> See
                            Teule, “The Syriac Renaissance,” p. 23-8.</p></note> remains completely
                    elusive to date. Despite the fact that several recent studies have called
                    attention to the originality of Bar Ṣalībī’s knowledge of Islamic history and
                    the Qurʾān, little to no appeals for a direct reliance on Arabic Islamic sources
                    have been made so far. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> This state of affairs appears to be largely indebted to the first
                    modern scholar to have dealt with the text, Alphonse Mingana (1878-1937), who in
                    1925 not only rejected Bar Ṣalībī’s knowledge of the Arabic Qurʾān, but also of
                    Islamic literature altogether. Basing his argument solely on <hi rend="italic"
                        >mimrō</hi> III, Mingana was arguing for Bar Ṣalībī’s reliance on a late
                    seventh or early eighth-century Syriac translation of a pre-standardized
                    recension of the Qurʾān, or as he called it, “an ancient Syriac translation of
                    the Ḳurʾān [sic] exhibiting new verses and variants.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en"> Alphonse Mingana, “An Ancient Syriac
                            Translation of the Ḳurʾan Exhibiting New Verses and Variants,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Bulletin of the John Rylands Library</hi> 9/1 (1925):
                            188-235; reprinted with minimal corrections and additions in Manchester:
                            Manchester University Press, 1925, 3-50. The current paper cites from
                            Mingana’s final version. Recently, Mingana’s study has been reprinted in
                            a volume seeking to challenge the Qurʾān’s traditional status in Islam,
                                <hi rend="a-size-large"><hi rend="italic">Which Koran?: Variants,
                                    Manuscripts, Linguistics</hi>, ed. </hi>Ibn Warraq<hi
                                rend="a-size-large"> (</hi>Amherst, Prometheus Books<hi
                                rend="a-size-large">, 2008; 2011). </hi>Mingana’s study and
                            translation of the quotation section of <hi rend="italic">mimrō </hi>III
                            was based on a single manuscript, <hi rend="italic">Mingana Syriac
                                89</hi> (1715 AD). After completion of his study, he was able to
                            compare this manuscript with <hi rend="italic">Harvard Syriac 91</hi>
                            (1898 AD), the results of which he described in a supplementary note
                            appended to the paper.<hi rend="a-size-large"> </hi></p></note> It was
                    in the context of postulating a dependence on such a translation that Mingana
                    provided several arguments for why Bar Ṣalībī could not himself have translated
                    the Qurʾānic excerpts from the Arabic. His boldest move occurs at the very end
                    of the paper, where he argues that Bar Ṣalībī simply was unqualified for the
                    task, due to his seemingly “extremely meagre” knowledge of Islamic works.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p xml:lang="en"> Mingana<hi
                                rend="smallcaps">, “</hi>An Ancient Syriac Translation,” p.
                            29-30.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Though Mingana’s claim of having unearthed evidence of a
                    non-canonical Qurʾān was soon rejected by prominent contemporary Qurʾānic
                    scholars such as Gotthelf Bergsträβer,<pb n="362"/> Theodore Nöldeke, and Arthur Jeffery, and
                    largely ignored by Islamicists ever since, to date no conclusive alternative
                    account for the provenance of the Qurʾānic translations in Bar Ṣalībī’s work has
                    been advanced.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p xml:lang="en">
                            Gotthelf Bergsträβer<hi rend="smallcaps">, </hi>“Die Geschichte des
                            Qurāntexts,” in T. Nöldeke, F. Schwally, G. Bergsträβer, and O. Pretzl,
                                <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Qurāns</hi>, <hi rend="st">3 vols.
                                (Leipzig: Dieterich’sche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 1909, 1919, 1938),
                                Vol. 3, </hi>p. 100-2. For Nöldeke’s brief epistolary response from
                            April 13, 1925, see ibid., p. 102 (nr. 1). Bergsträβer’s view that the
                            variants presented by Mingana are unrelated to the non-canonical
                            variants known from Muslim sources was endorsed by Arthur Jeffery, <hi
                                rend="italic">Materials for the History of the Text of the Qur’an:
                                The Old Codices</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1937), p. 14-15 (nr
                        1).</p></note> Yet one interesting hypothesis worthy of further exploration
                    has already been put forth a while ago by Sidney Griffith, who suggested that
                    Bar Ṣalībī himself “made the translations to suit his own apologetic/ polemic
                    purposes, and that the variants are to be explained as distortions, rather than
                    as evidence of ‘an ancient Syriac translation’.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> Griffith, <hi rend="italic">Syriac
                                Writers on Muslims</hi>, p. 25.</p></note> Before reexamining Bar
                    Ṣalībī’s potential translation work, however, it may be wise to first clarify
                    the more fundamental issue of his interculturality, as someone with no affinity
                    whatsoever with Islamic literary culture is indeed not very likely to be a
                    Qurʾānic translator. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> As we shall see, Mingana’s ‘extremely’ low estimation of Bar
                    Ṣalībī’s interculturality was not only founded on a flawed manuscript basis, but
                    a fresh reading of the work brings to light traces of at least five other
                    Islamic literary genres in addition to the Qurʾān. Some of these materials had
                    been noted by Mingana and were (mistakenly) interpreted as “new verses and
                    variants [from the Qurʾān],” other materials he missed due to his neglect of
                    both <hi rend="italic">mimrē</hi> I-II and the commentary section of <hi
                        rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            xml:lang="en"> See my PhD for a full assessment of Mingana’s proposals.
                        </p></note> For the sake of convenience, these materials will be surveyed
                    according to their characteristic literary genres, though one has to bear in
                    mind that none of the materials under review are limited to works of one
                    particular genre alone.</p><pb n="363"/>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Classification of Islamic Material by Literary Genre </head>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Sīra</hi></head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Although not the first trace of Muslim literature in the work,
                        we begin our survey with a passage in the commentary section of chapter 25
                        dealing with works on Muḥammad’s life, since the first half of it was the
                        sole basis for Mingana’s claim that Bar Ṣalībī’s knowledge of Islamic works
                        was “extremely meagre.” According to Mingana’s reading of the passage, Bar
                        Ṣalībī would have thought that Muslims have <hi rend="italic">only</hi> two
                        books in addition to the Qurʾān, the <hi rend="italic">Maghāzī</hi> and the
                            <hi rend="italic">Mukhtāra</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"
                                ><p xml:lang="en"> Mingana<hi rend="smallcaps">, “</hi>An Ancient
                                Syriac Translation,” p. 29-30: “[…] his own knowledge of Muslim
                                religious and historical books seems to have been extremely meagre.
                                […] Of the innumerable Muslim works of <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth
                                </hi>and history, preceding the twelfth century, the author had
                                apparently heard only of the <hi rend="italic">Maghāzi</hi> and the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Mukhtāra </hi>(<hi rend="italic">!</hi>), and
                                even these he had not seen and read; he was aware of their existence
                                only through hearsay: ‘the Muslims say that they have …’ A man of
                                this calibre would hardly be able to translate the Ḳurʾān [sic] or
                                to use the early works of tradition in a controversial work between
                                Christians and Muslims.” (Mingana’s italics)</p></note> If that were
                        what he actually believed, one could indeed rightly criticize him for being
                        in a complete state of ignorance of the ambient Muslim culture. What Mingana
                        fatally overlooked, however, is that the single manuscript he is relying on
                        displays a large gap in the passage under consideration.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. </hi><hi rend="Footnote_Text_Char"><hi
                                        rend="italic">Mingana Syriac </hi>89, f. 76a</hi>. This
                                manuscript is nowadays easily consultable online, see
                                http://vmr.bham.ac.uk/Collections/Mingana/ Syriac_89.</p></note>
                        This lacuna appears to be of an early date, since it is also present in all
                        the manuscripts consulted by Amar.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"
                                ><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the
                                    Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 111; tr. 103. Amar’s manuscripts include <hi
                                    rend="italic">Harvard Syriac 91</hi>, the manuscript which
                                Mingana later used for comparison in his supplementary notes.
                            </p></note> Fortunately, the oldest manuscript, <hi rend="italic">Ms.
                            Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate</hi> 160 from the year 1207 AD, fills in
                        the missing relative clause qualifying Bar Ṣalībī’s statement (see
                        italics):</p><pb n="364"/>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">The Muslims say that they have two other books in
                        addition to the Qurʾān <hi rend="italic">by which the lifespan of Muḥammad
                            is known </hi>(<hi rend="italic">da-b-hūn metīdaʿ yubōlō d-Mwḥmd</hi>):
                        the <hi rend="italic">Maghāzī</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܡܓܐܙܝ</foreign>), which records the actions of Muḥammad in battle, and
                        (also) at the end of the book which they call the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mukhtāra</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܘܟܬܪܐ</foreign>), they report
                        on the lifespan (<hi rend="italic">yubōleh</hi>) of Muḥammad.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate </hi>160, f.
                                271a-b. Cf. Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                                ed. p. 111, tr. p. 103-4. Also the word <hi rend="italic"
                                    >yubōleh</hi> occuring at the end of this passage appears to be
                                a better reading than <hi rend="italic">yuqneh</hi>, ‘his image’,
                                the reading attested in the manuscripts consulted by Amar.
                            </p></note></p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Thus, the mentioned “two other books” do not at all refer to
                        Muslim literature in general, as Mingana understood it, but only to <hi
                            rend="italic">particular</hi> works narrating the life of Muḥammad.
                        Apparently, Bar Ṣalībī acquired this knowledge from Muslim informants,
                        presumably orally or through a writing. As for the first work refered to,
                        there are numerous Islamic writings entitled <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                            al-Maghāzī</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Book of Expeditions</hi>) reporting
                        on Muḥammad’s raids and military campagns during the Medinan period, such as
                        those of Ibn Isḥāq (d. c. 770) and al-Wāqidī (d. 823), to name only two
                        important writers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p xml:lang="en">
                                See the works surveyed by F. Sezgin, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                                    des arabischen Schrifttums</hi>, Vol. 1 (Leiden: Brill, 1967),
                                237-56, 275-302; and more generally M. Hinds, “Al-Maghāzī,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">EI</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">2</hi> 5
                                (1986): 1161-6. </p></note> The writing that answers to the name <hi
                            rend="italic">Mukhtāra</hi> is more doubtful. One possibility is that it
                        refers to a <hi rend="italic">sīra</hi> work that has <hi rend="italic"
                            >al-mukhtār</hi>, ‘the chosen one’, in its title, such as for instance
                        al-Baghawī’s (d. 1117) <hi rend="italic">Kitāb al-Anwār fī shamāʾil al-Nabī
                            al-Mukhtār</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Book of Elucidations on the Good
                            Qualities of the Chosen Prophet</hi>).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Although Bar Ṣalībī only refers to <hi rend="italic">sīra</hi>
                        works the Muslims say they have in their possession, without claiming any
                        direct affinity with them, he does appear to be familiar with the basic
                        Muslim narrative of Muḥammad’s early years as seen from the account that
                        follows immediately thereafter, which was completely ignored by Mingana:</p><pb n="365"/>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">They also call him Aḥmad (cf. Q 61:6), as if it is the
                        same as Muḥammad, son of ʿAbdallāh, son of ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib. When his father
                        died, his uncle Abū Ṭālib raised him, and his foster mother was called
                        ḥalīma. When he was forty years old, he went around saying that two angels
                        had come, tied up his stomach, washed his heart, and restored it to his
                        body. He also saw along the road a tree and a rock that greeted him. One day
                        he saw an angel who tried to strangle him three times, saying to him:
                        ‘Recite in the name of your Lord, who made man from clay. Recite by your
                        honorable Lord, who instructed with the pen that wrote’ (Q 96:1-4).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 111, tr. p. 103-4.
                                Amar misread several proper names at the beginning of this passage.
                                The oldest manuscript has an additional sentence which adds a
                                somewhat polemical twist to the narrative: “Muḥammad and his foster
                                mother put him [the angel] down, as he [the angel] was about to
                                choke him with the pen that wrote”, see <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac
                                    Orthodox Patriarchate </hi>160, f. 271b.</p></note>
                    </p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Very similar descriptions of Muḥammad’s genealogy, his
                        upbringing as an orphan, the miraculous events prefiguring his prophetic
                        mission, and the first revelation said to be brought to him by the angel
                        Gabriel at mount ḥirāʾ, are readily found in the <hi rend="italic">sīra</hi>
                            literature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p xml:lang="en">
                                See e.g. Alfred Guillaume, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Muḥmmad: A
                                    Translation of Ibn Isḥaq’s </hi>Sīrat rasūl Allāh (Oxford:
                                Oxford University Press, 1982), p. 69-72 (on his birth, foster
                                mother, and the washing of his heart by two men in white when he was
                                an infant); p. 79 (Abū Ṭālib becomes Muḥammad’s guardian after the
                                death of his grandfather); p. 104-106 (on the stones and trees
                                greeting him and the first revelation he received, i.e. Q 96:1-5).
                                Note the slight discrepancy that Abū Ṭālib became Muḥammad’s
                                guardian after the death of his grandfather ʿAbd al-Muṭṭalib, not
                                after the death of his father, as Bar Ṣalībī wrote.</p></note> The
                        Islamic character of this account is further emphasized by the fact that a
                        very different, much more polemic portrayal of Muḥammad’s career, drawn from
                        the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of Dionysius of Tell-Maḥrē (d. 845),
                        was included in Bar Ṣalībī’s opening chapter.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> See n. 7 for my forthcoming
                                study on this chapter.</p></note>
                    </p><pb n="366"/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Heresiography</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The earliest trace of Islamic literature in the work is found
                        as early as chapter two, which discusses the divisions that arose in the
                        early Muslim community. Bar Ṣalībī writes that “approximately 73 heresies
                            (<hi rend="italic">heresīs</hi>)” belonging to four principal sects
                        sprang up among Muḥammad’s people after his death. These four ‘mother’ sects
                        call themselves <hi rend="italic">al-Shīʿa, al-Khawārij, al-Muʿtazila</hi>,
                        and <hi rend="italic">al-Sunna</hi>, but their opponents call them
                        respectively <hi rend="italic">al-Rawāfiḍ, al-Ḥarūriyya, al-Qadariyya, and
                            al- al-Murjiʾa</hi>. For all of these Arabic appelations Bar Ṣalībī also
                        provides Syriac equivalents.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> See Talay, “Aus dem polemischen Genre,” p.
                            516-7.</p></note> This terminological overview then proceeds with a
                        sketch of the enmity and discord among them concerning the issues of
                        rightful leadership and divine providence. During this discussion, Bar
                        Ṣalībī also quotes some Qurʾānic verses and <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi>
                        said to be used against one another by these four sects. <note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 5-8, tr. p. 2-9. In his Arabic
                                Chronicle, Bar ʿEbrōyō includes a similar but more elaborate account
                                of early Islamic schisms, undoubtedly borrowed from (a) Muslim
                                source(s), see Bar ʿEbrōyō, <hi rend="italic">Taʾrīkh mukhtaṣar
                                    al-duwal</hi>, ed. Ṣalhānī, p. 164-7. </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The originality of this account among Syriac Christian texts
                        on Islam has been pointed out by scholars as Sidney Griffith, Herman Teule,
                        and Barbara Roggema.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> See the works cited in nr. 2 and 4.</p></note> What
                        is yet to be explored, however, are the remarkable parallels with works of
                        Islamic heresiography, such as those written by al-Nawbakhtī (d. 912),
                        al-Ashʿarī (d. 936), al-MalaṬī (d. 987), al-Baghdādī (d. 1037), and
                        al-Shahrastānī (d. 1153), to name only some of the most prominent. Following
                        explicitly or implicitly a <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> about the division
                        of the <hi rend="italic">umma</hi> into 72 or 73 sects, all the named
                        authors classify, just as Bar Ṣalībī did, the various sects of Islam under
                        the four headings of <hi rend="italic">Shīʿa</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Khawārij</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Muʿtazila</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Murjiʾa</hi>, and discuss their internal disputes.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en"> Henri Laoust, “La classification
                                des sectes dans le <hi rend="italic">Farq</hi> d’al-Baghdādī,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Revue des Études Islamiques</hi> 29 (1961): 19-59;
                                reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Pluralismes dans l'islam</hi> (Paris,
                                1983), 135-75; id. “La classification des sects dans
                                l’hérésiographie ashʿarite,” <hi rend="italic">Arabic and Islamic
                                    Studies in Honor of Hamilton A. R. Gibb</hi>, ed. G. Makdisi
                                (Leiden 1965), 377-86.; id., “L'hérésiographie musulmane sous les
                                Abbassides,” <hi rend="italic">Cahiers de civilisation
                                    médiévale</hi> 38 (1967), 157-178; Dominique Sourdel, “Les
                                classification des sects islamiques dans le <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                                    al-Milal</hi> d’al-Šahrastānī,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Islamica</hi> 31 (1970): 239-247; Claude Gilliot, “Islam,
                                ‘sectes’ et groups d’opposition politico-religieux (VIIe-XIIe
                                siècles),” <hi rend="italic">Rives nord-méditerranéeennes </hi>10
                                (2002): 1-13.</p></note> At least one<pb n="367"/> major scholar of Islamic
                        heresiography has recently drawn attention to the apparent influence of this
                        literature on Bar Ṣalībī’s presentation of the sects of Islam.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="en"> Josef van Ess, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Der Eine und das Andere. Beobachtungen an
                                    islamischen haresiographischen Texten</hi>, 2 vols (Berlin/New
                                York: De Gruyter, 2011), Vol. 1., p. 77.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> According to al-Shahrastānī, the divisions between Muslims
                        boil down to four fundamental issues: (1) the divine attributes (<hi
                            rend="italic">ṣifāt Allāh</hi>); (2) faith and eschatology; (3) divine
                        determinism (<hi rend="italic">qadar</hi>); and (4) the issue of rightful
                        leadership (<hi rend="italic">imāma</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                            n="27"><p xml:lang="en"> Laoust<hi rend="smallcaps">,
                                </hi>“L'hérésiographie musulmane sous les Abbassides,” p. 171.
                             </p></note> In Bar Ṣalībī’s account, however, only the final two topics
                        appear to be of interest and most of all the issue of divine determinism. He
                        goes to some lengths to describe the four sects’ opinion on whether good and
                        evil come from God or from human freedom. This information has a distinct
                        purpose in his discourse, as it allows him to thereafter refute Sunnī
                        determinism and reaffirm the proper Christian understanding of divine
                        providence and human free will. It is not surprising to encounter this theme
                        this early in the work. In the aftermath of the shocking Zangid destruction
                        of the ‘blessed city’ of Edessa in 1144 and 1146, making sense of divine
                        providence was a very heavily debated topic within the West Syrian
                        community, a debate in which Bar Ṣalībī played a prominent role, although
                        still only a deacon at the time.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Teule, “Dionysius Bar Ṣalibi,” p. 665. The <hi
                                    rend="italic">Disputation</hi> as a whole may even be written in
                                response to the Muslim destruction of Edessa. After having upheld
                                the doctrines of the Trinitiy and Incarnation to his own
                                satisfaction, Bar Ṣalībī somewhat triumphantically writes that,
                                through his efforts, “the proclamation of Christianity has achieved
                                victory over the people that has overpowered us because of our sins
                                    (<hi rend="italic">ʿamō d-men ʿelat ḥṭōhayn etʿašan
                                ʿlayn</hi>)”. This important allusion to the fall of Edessa was
                                mistrans-lated by Amar, see Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against
                                    the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 81, tr. p. 74.</p></note>
                    </p><pb n="368"/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3.3" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Tafsīr</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In the commentary section of <hi rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III,
                        Bar Ṣalībī twice refers to opinions of Qurʾānic commentators, whom he calls
                            <hi rend="italic">mfashqōnē</hi>. His first reference to Islamic
                        exegetical literature is on the subject of the odd so-called ‘disconnected
                        letters’ (<hi rend="italic">al-ḥurūf al-muqaṭṭaʿa</hi>) occuring at the
                        beginning of the second sūra: “Alif Lam Mim. That is the Book, wherein is no
                        doubt, a guidance to the godfearing” (Q 2 :1-2, Arberry)<hi rend="italic"
                            >.</hi> In commen-ting on these verses, Bar Ṣalībī writes:</p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">(The Qurʾān reads here) ‘that’ (<hi rend="italic"
                            >haw</hi>) book and not ‘this’ (<hi rend="italic">hōnō</hi>) book.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī may
                                allude here to the fact that although Muslim exegetes usually
                                interpret <hi rend="italic">dhālika l-kitāb</hi> (Q 2:2) to mean
                                ‘this book’, i.e. the Qurʾān, it literally says ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                    >that</hi> book’. This sentence was not included in Amar’s
                                translation, though it is present in his edition. </p></note> What
                        sort of book is this? Their exegetes (<hi rend="italic">mfashqōnē
                            dīlhūn</hi>) interpret these letters in many different ways. Some of
                        them say that these letters are the numbers of the years of Muḥammad[‘s
                            community]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p xml:lang="en"> My
                                emendation.</p></note>. And there are those who interpret them
                        according to the name of their God. Therefore he wrote and added after the
                        letters, saying: ‘That is the great tablet (<hi rend="italic">lawḥō
                            rabtō</hi>) which is in heaven, raised up before the eyes of the angel
                        Michael’, which they call in Arabic (<hi rend="italic">b-Ṭayyōyōʾīt</hi>),
                        the ‘Preserved Tablet’ ([<hi rend="italic">al-</hi>] <hi rend="italic">lawḥ
                            al-maḥfūẓ</hi>, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܚ ܐܠܡܚ[ܦ]ܘܕ</foreign>).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 112, tr. p. 104.
                            </p></note></p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Muslim exegetical literature reports a wide range of possible
                        interpretations for the ‘disconnected letters’ appearing at the beginning of
                        some 29 sūras.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en"> On
                                the large spectrum of interpretations within Sunnī <hi rend="italic"
                                    >tafsīr</hi>, see Martin Nguyen, “Exegesis of the <hi
                                    rend="italic">ḥurūf al-muqaṭṭaʿa</hi>: Polyvalency in Sunnī
                                Traditions of Qur’ānic Interpretation,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                    Qurʾānic Studies</hi> 14/2 (2012): 1-28.</p></note> Within this
                        large spectrum of<pb n="369"/> views one finds the very same opinions voiced by Bar
                        Ṣalībī. With some discontent, al-Ṭabarī mentions a report to the extent that
                        a group of Jews had heard the recitation of <hi rend="italic">alif lām
                            mīm</hi> and said that the numerical value of these letters (1+30+40)
                        indicate the number of years Muḥammad’s community would last. When they
                        thereafter heard the recitation of other letters carrying each time a higher
                        numerical value, they in the end had to conclude that the matter was
                            ambiguous.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p xml:lang="en">
                                al-Ṭabarī, <hi rend="italic">Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy
                                    al-Qurʾān</hi>, ed. Cairo, p. 210.</p></note> Among the
                        interpretations al-Ṭabarī is more supportive of, he refers to the view that
                        the letters refer to God’s greatest name (<hi rend="italic">al-ism
                            al-aʿẓam</hi>); to an abbreviation of one of God’s names, e.g. <hi
                            rend="italic">alm</hi> means <hi rend="italic">al-raḥīm</hi>; or to
                        multiple names of God, i.e. <hi rend="italic">alif</hi> stands for <hi
                            rend="italic">Allāh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">lām</hi> for <hi
                            rend="italic">al-Laṭīf</hi> (‘the Gentle’), and <hi rend="italic"
                            >mīm</hi> for <hi rend="italic">al-Majīd</hi> (‘the Glorious’).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p xml:lang="en"> Ibid., p.
                                204-228.</p></note> Other commentators interpret the letters as one
                        of the names of the Qurʾān and say that it refers to God’s statement: “I
                        revealed this book [i.e. the Qurʾān] to you from the ‘Preserved Tablet’ (<hi
                            rend="italic">al-lawḥ al-maḥfūẓ</hi>)”, i.e. from the heavenly Book (cf.
                        Q 85:21-2).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en">
                                al-Qurṭubī, <hi rend="italic">al-Jāmiʿ li-aḥkām al-Qurʾān</hi>, ed.
                                Beirut, p. 241. See Daniel A. Madigan, “Preserved Tablet,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">EQ</hi> 4 (2004): 261-3. </p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate 160</hi> has preserved an
                        additional sentence to Bar Ṣalībī’s comment which may contain his motive for
                        adducing this information on Muslim exegesis. In it, Bar Ṣalībī appeals to
                        the authority of Muḥammad to appropriate the contents of the ‘Preserved
                        Tablet’ to Christianity: “The things he [i.e. the angel Michael] recites
                        here, he [i.e. Muḥammad] says, are Christians things.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate </hi>160, f.
                                271b: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܠܝܢ ܕܬ̇ܢܐ ܗܪܟܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܕܝܠܢ ܟܖ̈ܝܣܛܝܢܐ
                                    ܐܡܪ݂.</foreign>
                            </p></note> In other words, what the angel Gabriel is reciting from the
                        Preserved Tablet is not the Qurʾān in Bar Ṣalībī’s opinion, but things
                        (texts?) related to Christianity.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The second reference to Muslim exegesis occurs in his comment
                        on Q 69:17 about the so-called <hi rend="italic">ḥamlat al-ʿarsh</hi>, the
                        angels bearing the Throne of God who are also mentioned in<pb n="370"/> Q 40:7. Although
                        in the citation provided by Bar Ṣalībī, “They bear the Throne of your Lord
                        above them <hi rend="italic">on the eighth day </hi>(<hi rend="italic"
                            >b-yawmō tmīnōyō</hi>),”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                                ed. 110, tr. p. 103.</p></note> the reference to the amount of
                        angels was obscured possibly as a result of misunderstanding the elliptic
                        ending of the Arabic “they will bear the Throne of your Lord above them <hi
                            rend="italic">on that Day, eight [of them] </hi>(<hi rend="italic"
                            >yawmaʾidh thamāniya</hi>),” Bar Ṣalībī clearly is aware of Muslim
                        interpretations of this verse: “Their exegetes say that four angels bear the
                        Throne of God, but then they add (<hi rend="italic">awsefw</hi>) another
                        four which makes eight. Perhaps, the first four grew tired?”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate </hi>160, f.
                                272b. The manuscripts consulted by Amar read ‘to add’ in the
                                singular (<hi rend="italic">awsef</hi>) which is taken to mean that
                                it is the Qurʾān that adds four angels, see Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. 113, tr. p. 106.
                                Mingana derived a rather bizarre argument against Bar Ṣalībī’s
                                translatorship from this comment, see Mingana, “An Ancient Syriac
                                Translation,” p. 6-7<hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                            </p></note> In this piece of rhetoric, Bar Ṣalībī appears to ridicule
                        Muslim exegetes who acknowledge four Throne bearers but later double their
                        number. To harmonize the fact that Q 69:17 mentions eight angels while some
                            <hi rend="italic">ḥ</hi><hi rend="italic">adīth</hi> report only four,
                        some exegetes indeed have taken the position that the Throne is currently
                        carried by four angels, but on the Day of Resurrection by eight.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p xml:lang="en"> Stephen R. <hi
                                    rend="a-size-extra-large">Burge, <hi rend="italic">Angels in
                                        Islam: Jalāl al-Dīn al-Suyūtī's</hi> al-Ḥabāʾik fī akhbār
                                    al-malāʾik, Culture and Civilization in the Middle East 31
                                    (Oxon: Routledge, 2012), p. 43-4.</hi>
                            </p></note> A specific <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> is often adduced in
                        support of this view: “Four carry Him today, eight (will carry God) on the
                        Day of Resurrection.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> al-Ṭabarī, <hi rend="italic">Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan
                                    taʾwīl āy al-Qurʾān</hi>, ed. Cairo, p. 229; <hi
                                    rend="a-size-extra-large">Burge, <hi rend="italic">Angels in
                                        Islam</hi>, </hi>p. 146.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The reason why Bar Ṣalībī found such a doubling of angels
                        absurd is obviously determined by the Biblical lens through which he reads
                        the Qurʾān. As such, he certainly knew that in Ezekiel’s vision only four
                        creatures carry the divine Throne (Ezek 1). He thus indirectly appears to be
                        criticizing Muslim exegetes, and by extension the Qurʾān, for contradicting
                        the Bible, a polemic made repeatedly in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Disputation</hi>.</p><pb n="371"/>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3.4" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Ḥadīth</hi></head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Three direct citations of prophetic sayings of Muḥammad
                        recorded in the major Sunnī <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> collections occur
                        among the Qurʾānic excerpts in <hi rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III. Among the
                        verses dealing with creation in chapter 25, Bar Ṣalībī quotes a well-known
                            <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> transmitted in various forms about what
                        God created first:</p>
                    <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Disputation</hi>, XXV</cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Sunan Abū Dāwūd</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>And when he [i.e. Muḥammad] wished to speak of
                                creation, he said: “First He created the pen of the scribe (<hi
                                    rend="italic">qnayō d-sōfrō</hi>). He said to the pen: ‘Walk and
                                write!’ But the pen answered: ‘What should I write?’. He said:
                                ‘Write concerning what will happen until the end’.<note place="foot"
                                    xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                            rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 110, tr. p.
                                        102. </p></note></cell>
                            <cell>[…] I heard the Messenger of God (peace be
                                upon him) say: ‘The first thing God created was the pen (<hi
                                    rend="italic">al-qalam</hi>)’. He said to it: ‘Write!’ It asked:
                                ‘What should I write, my Lord?’ He said: ‘Write what was decreed
                                about everything until the Last Hour’ […].<note place="foot"
                                    xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p xml:lang="en">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sunan Abū Dāwūd</hi>, ed. <hi
                                            rend="italic">Dār al-salām, </hi>Vol. 5, book 42, 4700,
                                        p. 213 (translation slightly adapted). For other versions,
                                        see ‘creation’ in A. J. Wensinck, <hi rend="italic">A
                                            Handbook of Early Mohammadan Tradition</hi> (Leiden:
                                        Brill, 1927), p. 49.</p></note></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The reason why Bar Ṣalībī found this saying important enough to
                        include is seen from his commentary, in which he makes the error of
                        Muḥammad’s teaching apparent by contrasting it with the Biblical account of
                        creation:</p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">Moses wrote: ‘In the beginning, God
                            created heaven and earth’ (Gen 1:1). He said this before [writing that]
                            (God) created the <hi rend="italic"
                            >qalam</hi>, that is, the pen (<hi
                            rend="italic">qnayō</hi><hi
                           >) of the scribe! And how is God in need of
                            writing, unless he fears to forget something?!</hi><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī<hi rend="italic">,
                                    Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 113, tr. p. 105. Note Bar
                                Ṣalībī’s use of the Arabic term for pen, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >qalam</hi>. </p></note>
                    </p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> On another occasion, in chapter 30, Bar Ṣalībī introduces a
                        saying of Muḥammad concerning his community with the words ‘Muḥammad
                        said’:</p><pb n="372"/>
                    <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Disputation</hi>, XXX</cell>
                            <cell>Ṣaḥīḥ al-Bukhārī</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Muḥammad said: ‘My community is among the
                                nations as a white spot on a black ox (<hi rend="italic">ūmtō dīly
                                    baynōtʿammē ak ōtōḥwōrtō b-tawrō ukōmō</hi>)’.<note place="foot"
                                    xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                            rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 128, tr. p.
                                        122.</p></note></cell>
                            <cell>[…] (Muḥammad) said: ‘My community is among
                                the nations as a white hair on a black ox (<hi rend="italic">inna
                                    ummatī fī l-umamk-al-shaʿara al-bayḍāʾ fī l-thawr
                                    al-aswad</hi>)’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                                        xml:lang="en">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Ṣaḥīḥ al-Bukhārī</hi>, ed. <hi
                                            rend="italic">Dār al-salām</hi>, Vol. 8, book 81, 6529,
                                        p. 287 (translation slightly adapted).</p></note></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Muḥammad’s apparent admittance of the insignificant position of
                        his community apparently was of value to Bar Ṣalībī’s polemics, for this is
                        what one reads in his commentary: “Your own prophet testifies that (Muslims)
                        are few in the world. Christians, however, are numerous and this is why they
                        are strong.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar
                                Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 135, tr. p.
                                130.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> With the words “Prayer of the <hi rend="italic">Ṭayyōyē</hi>,”
                        Bar Ṣalībī cites one final <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> in chapter 30. This
                        prayer is the well-known ‘Abrahamic prayer’ (<hi rend="italic">al-ṣalāt
                            al-Ibrāhīmiyya</hi>) reported in various <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi>
                        collections, which serves as the closing supplication of the five-daily
                        Muslim prayer:</p>
                    <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Disputation</hi>, XXX</cell>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Sunan Abū Dāwūd</hi></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Prayer of the Muslims: ‘O God, pray (<hi
                                    rend="italic">ṣalō</hi>) for Muḥammad and the sons of his
                                people. And bless (<hi rend="italic">barek</hi>) Muḥammad and the
                                sons of his people as you prayed for (<hi rend="italic">ṣlayt</hi>),
                                blessed (<hi rend="italic">barekt</hi>), and had mercy (<hi
                                    rend="italic">w-ḥōnt</hi>) on Abraham and the sons of his
                                people. For he [i.e. Muḥammad] is praiseworthy and exalted (<hi
                                    rend="italic">mshabḥō wa-mraymō</hi>)’.<note place="foot"
                                    xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                            rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 132, tr. p.
                                        127. Mingana was unable to identify this passage, perhaps
                                        because he read <hi rend="italic">ʿameh</hi>, ‘his people’
                                        as <hi rend="italic">ʿamhu</hi>, Arabic for ‘his paternal
                                        uncle’, see Mingana, “An Ancient Syriac Translation,” p. 45
                                        (nr. 3) </p></note></cell>
                            <cell>[…] So he [i.e. Muḥammad] said: ‘O God, send
                                your <hi rend="italic">ṣalāt</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ṣalli</hi>)
                                upon Muhammad, and the family of Muḥammad, as you have sent your <hi
                                    rend="italic">ṣalāt</hi> (<hi rend="italic">ṣallayta</hi>) upon
                                Abraham. And send your bless-ings (<hi rend="italic">bārik</hi>)
                                upon Muhammad, and the family of Muḥammad, as you have sent your
                                blessings (<hi rend="italic">bārakta</hi>) upon the family of
                                Abraham. Indeed, you are the praiseworthy (<hi rend="italic"
                                    >ḥamīd</hi>), the glorious (<hi rend="italic">majīd</hi>)’.<note
                                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p xml:lang="en">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Sunan Abū Dāwūd</hi>, ed. Dār al-salām,
                                        Vol. 1, book 177/8, 976, p. 571-2 (translation slightly
                                        adapted).</p></note></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table><pb n="373"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Though Bar Ṣalībī provides no comment for this quotation, his
                        motive for including it most likely is linked to an earlier debate on the
                        meaning of Christ’s prayer and the Muslim’s prayer for Muḥammad, in which
                        Bar Ṣalībī argued that “because you pray for your prophet, you seem to be
                        better than he is since you petition God to forgive him his
                            wrongdoing”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs, </hi>ed. p. 72, tr.
                                p. 65. </p></note> This polemic background may also explain
                        (assuming that Bar Ṣalībī is the translator at work) why the Arabic verb <hi
                            rend="italic">ṣallā</hi>, which can mean ‘to pray’ or ‘to bless’
                        (usually the latter in this context) is rendered by its Syriac cognate
                        having only the meaning ‘to pray’. Even more pertinent, this background
                        could also provide an explanation for the distorted concluding doxology
                        which addresses the prayer not to God, but to Muḥammad. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In addition to these three direct quotations of prophetic <hi
                            rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi>, Bar Ṣalībī also twice alludes to Muslim
                        traditions on the collection of the Qurʾān. In chapter 23, in response to
                        the Muslim critique that the Gospels are unreliable since they were written
                        by the apostles and not by Christ himself, Bar Ṣalībī retorts by arguing
                        that such a critique applies as well to the Qurʾān, which was not written
                        down by Muḥammad himself, but was collected for the first time into a single
                        codex by his cousin ʿAlī ibn Abū Ṭālib: </p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">Against them we say: Consider that when Muḥammad died,
                        the Qurʾān was neither written down. So his cousin ʿAlī ibn Abū Ṭālib –
                        others of them say: ʿUthmān ibn ʿAffān – swore that he would not put on the
                        cloak (<hi rend="italic">marṭūṭō</hi>) until their scripture was collected
                        and its parts joined together. For they were scattered here and there among
                        various individuals during the life of Muḥammad. So ʿAlī collected it and
                        made it into<pb n="374"/> a single codex (<hi rend="italic">ktōbō</hi>), and he called it
                        ‘Qurʾān’ because he joined, that is, bound together (<hi rend="italic"
                            >aqrana awkīt dabaq</hi>) (the fragments). Therefore ‘Qurʾān’ means:
                        ‘volume and collection of disparate fragments’.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 98, tr p. 90-1. Amar misread the
                                part on the swearing, reading it as though ʿAlī swore that ʿUthmān
                                would not put on the cloak. Note that Bar Ṣalībī implies that the
                                term ‘Qurʾān’ is etymologically derived from the Arabic verb <hi
                                    rend="italic">aqrana</hi>, ‘to join together, to combine’, from
                                the root <hi rend="italic">q-r-n</hi>, rather than from the root <hi
                                    rend="italic">q-r-</hi>ء<hi rend="italic">, </hi>‘to read, to
                                recite’, which is the standard explanation. Though Bar Ṣalībī’s take
                                on it is manifestly polemical, this alternative etymology is not as
                                “fanciful” as Amar suggested, for the root <hi rend="italic"
                                    >q-r-n</hi> is discussed by Arab lexicographers among the
                                possible meaning of ‘Qurʾān’, see Anne-Sylvie Boisliveau, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Le Coran par lui-même: Vocabulaire et
                                    argumentation du discours coranique autoréférentiel
                                </hi>(Leiden: Brill, 2014), p. 41-3.</p></note></p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Although the standard Muslim account ascribes the first
                        collection of the Qurʾān to the initiative of Caliph Abū Bakr, several
                        traditions recorded in both Sunnī and Shīʿī sources indeed contain reports
                        that it was ʿAlī who first collected the Qurʾān after Muḥammad’s death.
                        Interestingly enough, such reports also mention ʿAlī’s act of swearing not
                        to put on the cloak, that is, not to leave the house, until the Qurʾān was
                        fully collected. For instance: </p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">ʿAbd Khayr reported from ʿAlī that when he saw people in
                        despair and frustration at the death of the Prophet, he swore that he would
                        not wear his cloak on his back until he had collected the Qurʾān. Then he
                        sat in his house and collected the Qurʾān. So it was the first <hi
                            rend="italic">muṣḥaf</hi> in which the Qurʾān had been collected –
                        collected from his heart and this [<hi rend="italic">muṣḥaf</hi>] is with
                        the descendants of Jaʿfar.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Quoted in Shehzad Saleem, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Collection of the Qurʾān: A Critical and Historical Study of
                                    Al-Farāhī’s View</hi> (PhD diss., University of Wales Lampeter,
                                2010), p. 239. For the narratives of ʿAlī’s collection of the
                                Qurʾān, see ibid.<hi rend="italic">, </hi>p. 236-279; Seyfeddin
                                Kara, “The Suppression of ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib’s Codex: Study of the
                                Traditions on the Earliest Copy of the Qurʾān,” <hi rend="st"><hi
                                        rend="italic">Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi></hi> 75/2
                            (2016): 267-289.</p></note></p></quote></cit><pb n="375"/>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī also remarks that Muslims differ on who collected
                        the Qurʾān for the first time: was it ʿAlī ibn Abū Ṭālib, or as “others of
                        them say” ʿUthmān ibn ʿAffān? This ambiguity is also reflected in Islamic
                        sources, although there not only a difference is to be noted on whether the
                        first collection of the Qurʾān was made by ʿAlī or ʿUthmān, but “each of the
                        first four caliphs is reported to have been the first person to collect the
                        Ḳurʾān [sic].”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Welch, “Ḳurʾān,” <hi rend="italic">EI</hi><hi
                                    rend="italic superscript smallcaps">2</hi> 5 (1986), p. 405. See
                                also John Burton, <hi rend="italic">The Collection of the
                                    Qurʾān</hi> (Cambrigde: Cambridge University Press, 1977), p.
                                138-159.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> According to the most widespread Sunnī account, the final
                        consonantal text was established during the reign of Caliph ʿUthmān who was
                        confronted with the need of uniting the Muslim community around one unified,
                        official text. The Caliph obtained the Qurʾānic collection commissioned by
                        Abū Bakr now in the possession of ḥafṢa, and appointed a commission to copy
                        it into several volumes which then were sent to the main cities of the
                        empire. Due to ʿUthmān’s initiative in the establishment of an official,
                        unified text, it came to be called <hi rend="italic">al-muṣḥaf
                            al-ʿUthmānī</hi>, ‘the ʿUthmānic Codex’. Bar Ṣalībī also seems to know
                        of this subsequent stage of the Qurʾān’s textual history. To refute the
                        Muslim claim that the revelation of the Qurʾān is similar to that of the Law
                        and the Gospel, Bar Ṣalībī points out that, unlike Moses’ writing of the Law
                        and the apostles’ writing of the Gospel, Muḥammad did not write down the
                        Qurʾān himself, but ʿUthmān did it, which is why the book is called the
                        ʿUthmānic Codex (<hi rend="italic">ktōbō</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ʿUthmānī</hi>): </p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">As for you, from where was the scripture revealed to
                        your prophet, although he [i.e. Muḥammad] died without writing (it)? Abū
                        Bakr ruled after him and did not write anything down, neither did ʿUmar
                        write the scripture. ʿUthmān collected (<hi rend="italic">kanesh</hi>) your
                        scripture which had been collected by your elders (<hi rend="italic"
                            >sōbē</hi>) and he made them swear to say whatever they heard from the<pb n="376"/>
                        prophet. He wrote this down, and it was called ‘the ʿUthmānic Codex’ (<hi
                            rend="italic">ktōbō</hi><hi rend="italic">ʿUthmānī</hi>).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 111, tr. p. 103.
                                Note Bar Ṣalībī’s use of the <hi rend="italic">nisba </hi>adjective
                                    <hi rend="italic">ʿUthmānī</hi>. </p></note></p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> The oldest manuscript has also here preserved an additional
                        sentence, in which reference is made to other Muslim works narrating the
                        Qurʾān’s textual history: “The Muslims say they have two other books [in
                        which] the story of the codices is written (<hi rend="italic">Ōmrīn</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Ṭayyōyē d-īt l-hūn trēn ktōbē ḥrōnē. Ktīb sharbō
                            da-ktōbē</hi>).”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p
                                xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate </hi>160, f.
                                271b. </p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.3.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ</hi></head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">As the Qurʾān narrates the lives and deeds of the prophets
                        before Muḥammad only in a very cursory manner, Muslim commentators soon
                        began to reconstruct the narratives by drawing on Jewish and Christian
                        traditions, the so-called <hi rend="italic">Isrāʾīliyyāt</hi>,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p xml:lang="en"> On this term, see
                                    <hi rend="italic">Roberto Tottoli</hi><hi rend="st"><hi
                                        rend="italic">,</hi> “Origin and Use of the Term
                                </hi>Isrāʾīliyyāt in Muslim Literature,” <hi rend="italic">Arabica
                                </hi>46 (1999): 193-209.</p></note> which led to the emergence of
                        collections of ‘stories of the prophets’ (<hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ
                            al-anbiyāʾ</hi>). These collections were included in the early sections
                        of Muslim historiographies, or were transmitted in separate works of <hi
                            rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʾ</hi>. Though the latter works were
                        produced from early on, it was in the eleventh century, just before Bar
                        Ṣalībī’s lifetime, that major works were composed, such as those by Abū
                        Isḥaq al-Thaʿlabī and Muḥammad ibn ʿAbdallāh al-Kisāʾī. Both were very
                        popular, comprehensive collections of traditions on the prophets, ordered
                        chronologically from creation to the time of Jesus.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p xml:lang="en"> On this genre in general, see
                                Tilman Nagel, <hi rend="italic">Die Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ. Ein Beitrag
                                    zur Arabischen Literaturgeschichte</hi> (PhD diss., University
                                of Bonn, 1967); Roberto Tottoli, <hi rend="italic">Biblical Prophets
                                    in the Qurʾan and Muslim Literature</hi>, Routledge Studies in
                                the Qur'an (London/New York: Routledge, 2001).</p></note> There are
                        two passages in <hi rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III that recall the often
                        rather legendary character of the <hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ</hi>
                        genre. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In the context of the Adam narratives of chapter 26, Bar
                        Ṣalībī quotes a peculiar account of Adam’s creation according<pb n="377"/> to which he
                        would have laid soulless on the earth for forty years. A very similar
                        tradition was already reported by al-Ṭabarī (d. 923) in both his <hi
                            rend="italic">Tafsīr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">History</hi>:</p>
                    <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                            <cell><hi rend="italic">Disputation</hi>,
                                XXVI</cell>
                            <cell>Ṭabarī, <hi rend="italic">Tafsīr/Ta</hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">ʾrīkh</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Adam was formed and lay on the earth for forty
                                years without a soul. The angels passed by him and saw him.<note
                                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī,
                                            <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 115,
                                        tr. p. 108. Note that the mention of the angels’ fear is
                                        absent from Bar Ṣalībī’s version, possibly because it was
                                        irrelevant to the point he seeks to make.</p></note></cell>
                            <cell>So God shaped Adam into a human being, and he
                                remained a figure of clay for forty years, corresponding to the day
                                of Friday. The angels passed by him and were seized with fear by
                                what they saw, and <hi rend="italic">Iblīs</hi> felt fear most.<note
                                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p xml:lang="en"> al-Ṭabarī,
                                            <hi rend="italic">Jāmiʿ al-bayān ʿan taʾwīl āy
                                            al-Qurʾān</hi>, ed. Cairo, p. 459; Franz Rosenthal, <hi
                                            rend="italic">The History of al-Tabari</hi>, <hi
                                            rend="italic">Vol. 1:  General Introduction and From the
                                            Creation to the Flood</hi> (Albany: Suny Press, 1989),
                                        p. 262. On the proces of the creation of Adam, see Cornelia
                                        Schöck, <hi rend="italic">Adam im Islam. Ein Beitrag zur
                                            Ideengeschichte der Sunna</hi> (Berlin: Klaus Schwarz
                                        Verlag, 1993), p. 74-8. This aspect of the creation of Adam
                                        was not discussed in Kisters’ study of Adamic legends in
                                        Islam, see M. J. Kister, “<hi rend="Footnote_Text_Char"
                                            >Ādam: A Study of Some Legends in <hi rend="italic"
                                                >Tafsīr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ḥadīṯ</hi>
                                            Literature,” <hi rend="italic">Israel Oriental
                                                Studies</hi> 13 (1993):
                                113-74.</hi> </p></note></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The idea behind this waiting period appears to be that a
                        certain time was needed for Adam’s clay body to dry before God could breathe
                        a soul into it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p xml:lang="en">
                                Schöck, <hi rend="italic">Adam im Islam</hi>, p. 75. </p></note>
                        Such a time interval is, of course, totally alien to Bar Ṣalībī’s biblical
                        frame of reference, which is exactly the point he draws out in his
                        commentary:</p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">Although scripture says that Adam was
                            created on the sixth day (cf. Gn 1:26-31), this scripture says that Adam
                            was formed and was lying without a soul in the dust of the earth for
                            forty years!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                                ed. p. 116, tr. p. 109.</p></note>
                    </p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In chapter 27 on Noah and the flood, Bar Ṣalībī at one point
                        interrupts the flow of Qurʾānic verses with a lengthy report on a giant
                        named Og, son of ʿAnaq (ʿ<hi rend="italic">Awg/ʿŪg bar<pb n="378"/> ʿAnaq</hi>), said to
                        have survived the flood and who was later killed by Moses. The purpose of
                        this report, as his comment shows, is clearly to ridicule the silly stories
                        given credence by Muslims.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                                xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                                ed. p. 119, tr. p. 112: “Observe that also this story is
                                unbelievable, dull, and very foolish”.</p></note> As the many
                        legendary embellishments in this Og story very specifically points to a <hi
                            rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʾ</hi> work, it is worth quoting in full: </p>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">(God) did not set apart men, except Noah and those who
                        were with him in the ark, and Og, son of ʿAnaq, as the readers of the
                        scriptures (<hi rend="italic">qōryay ktōbē</hi>) say. Og was the son of
                        Sayhan and his mother ʿAnaq, and Og was a giant. As he was created by God,
                        his stature was so great in creation that no one was able to describe it.
                        And he was an enemy of the Muslims (<hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">ʿeldbōbō d-mashlmōnē</hi>) and those who are like them.
                        His mother, ʿAnaq, was a woman of the daughters of Adam, and, as they say,
                        she was beautiful to behold. But the readers of the scriptures say that at
                        his birth he was already huge, in a way that is impossible to relate. On the
                        waist of the giant there was a belt, and he used to stretch out his hand
                        into the sea to take hold of a big fish from the bottom of the sea and he
                        would hold it up to the sun to roast and eat it. He lived for 3600 years. He
                        was born in the days of Adam, and lived until (the time of) Moses who killed
                        him. </p></quote></cit>
                    <cit><quote><p xml:lang="en">They say that he was killed as such: The giant looked
                        from a distance upon the Children of Israel (<hi rend="italic">bnay
                            Īsrōʾīl</hi>) as they were praying in their camp, and determined that
                        the circumference of the camp was about two hours away. So the giant
                        approached a big mountain and broke off a rock as big as the circumference
                        of the camp. He put it above his head intending to hurl it on them to kill
                        them then and there. But immediately, God sent a common bird, a hoopoe, to
                        show His<pb n="379"/> power to His servant. And it took hold of a palm branch and a rock
                        the size of the head of the giant. And when the hoopoe pierced the rock, it
                        fell on the giant’s neck who collapsed to the ground.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p xml:lang="en"> Bar Ṣalībī, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Against the Arabs</hi>, ed. p. 118-119, tr. p.
                            111-2.</p></note></p></quote></cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> In the Old Testament, Og is only scantly mentioned as the
                        Amorite king of Bashan, a last descendant of a race of giants who was
                        defeated by Moses (cf. Nu 21:33-35; Dt 1:4; 3:11; 4:47). In early rabbinic
                        writings, these disparate verses gave rise to legendary elaborations which
                        later found their way to Muslim sources.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                            n="63"><p xml:lang="en"> B. Heller and S.M. Wasserstrom, “Ūdj,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">EI</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">2</hi> 10
                                (2000): 777-8. See also Admiel Kosman, “The Story of a Giant Story:
                                The Winding Way of Og King of Bashan in the Jewish Haggadic
                                Tradition,” <hi rend="st"><hi rend="italic">Hebrew Union College
                                        Annual</hi> 73 (2002): 157-190; </hi>Ján Pauliny, “ʿŪg ibn
                                ʿAnāq, ein sagenhafter Riese: Untersuchungen zu den islamischen
                                Riesengeschichten,” <hi rend="italic">Craecolatina et Orientalia
                                </hi>5 (1973): 249-268.</p></note> In the story itself, as cited by
                        Bar Ṣalībī, clues are found that it was indeed taken from a Muslim source,
                        namely the reference to “the readers of the scriptures” which is how <hi
                            rend="italic">ahl al-kitāb</hi>, the Muslim designation for Jews and
                        Christians, is usually translated in the <hi rend="italic">Disputation</hi>;
                        the appellation of Moses’ people as <hi rend="italic">bnay Īsrōʾīl</hi>, the
                        cognate of the Qurʾānic appelation <hi rend="italic">banū Isrāʾīl</hi>; and
                        the fact that the giant is portrayed as “an enemy of the Muslims”.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p xml:lang="en"> Gutmann remarks
                                that Og, who was among the earliest biblical figures depicted in
                                Islamic art, fascinated Muslims “as he symbolized the accursed, evil
                                infidel who is vanquished by such true believers as Moses”, see
                                Joseph Gutmann, “More about the Giant Og in Islamic Art,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Bulletin of the Asia Institute</hi> 3 (1989):
                                107-114, p. 111.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> Indeed, very similar narratives, including specific details
                        are reported in popular works of <hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʾ</hi>
                        such as those by al-Thaʿlabī and al-Kisāʿī’.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p xml:lang="en"> al-Thaʿlabī, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Arāʾis al-majālis fī qiṣas al-anbiyāʾ</hi>, tr. Brinner, p.
                                99-100, 399-403; al-Kisāʾī, <hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyā</hi>,
                                ed. Eisenberg p. 233-5, tr. Thackston, p. 251-3.</p></note> The
                        enduring popularity of the story of Og and Moses is further testified by the
                        fact that historiographical works from the Mongol and later periods<pb n="380"/>
                        sometimes include illustrations of scenes of the narrative.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p xml:lang="en"> Joseph Gutmann and
                                Vera B. Moreen “The Combat between Moses and Og in Muslim
                                Miniatures,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Asia Institute</hi> 1
                                (1987): 111-21. On the important place of the story of Og in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ</hi> manuscripts from the
                                sixteenth century, see <ref
                                    target="https://www.google.be/search?hl=nl&amp;tbo=p&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=inauthor:%22Na%27ama+Brosh%22"
                                    >Naʿama Brosh</ref> and <ref
                                    target="https://www.google.be/search?hl=nl&amp;tbo=p&amp;tbm=bks&amp;q=inauthor:%22Rachel+Milstein%22"
                                    >Rachel Milstein</ref>, <hi rend="italic">Biblical Stories in
                                    Islamic Painting</hi> (Jerusalem: Israel Museum, 1991), p.
                                39-40, 97-9; Rachel Milstein, Karin Rührdanz, and Barbara Schmitz,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Stories of the Prophets: Illustrated
                                    Manuscripts of Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ</hi> (California: Mazda
                                Publishers, 1999), p. 131, 191.</p></note> An early example is found
                        in Zakariyyā al-Qazwīnī’s (d. 1283) <hi rend="italic">ʿAjāʾib al-Makhlūqāt
                            wa-gharāʾib al-mawjūdāt</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Marvels of Creatures and
                            Strange Things Existing</hi>):</p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic
                            url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV21N2Jacobs1.png"
                            rend="center">
                        </graphic>
                    </figure>
                    <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="bold">Image: </hi><hi rend="italic">Ms.
                            Walters 659</hi>, f. 143b<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                                xml:lang="en">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ms. Walters 659</hi>, f. 143b,
                                https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/
                                File:Muhammad_ibn_Muhammad_Shakir_Ruzmah-%27i_Nathani__The
                                _Demon_%27Uj_ibn_%27Unuq_Carries_a_Mountain_with_which_to_Kill_Moses_and_His_Men_-_Walters_W659143B_-_Full_Page.jpg</p></note></p><pb n="381"/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2jacobs.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Concluding Remarks</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Almost a century after Mingana’s paper on the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Disputation Against the Arabs</hi>, a new start was made in the present
                    article in tracing the potential Islamic sources Bar Ṣalībī relied upon in
                    composing the work. Mingana’s swift claim that Bar Ṣalībī’s knowledge of Islamic
                    works was “extremely meagre” has proven to be ‘extremely’ inaccurate, not only
                    because it rests on a flawed textual basis, but also because it combines with a
                    highly selective reading of the text. The fact that little of the material
                    discussed above is paralleled in other known Syriac (or Christian Arabic) texts
                    leads one to suspect very strongly that Bar Ṣalībī was drawing directly on
                    Islamic sources, incorporating material as he saw fit to his apologetic and
                    polemic purposes at hand. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> However, one should not fall in the opposite extreme of saying
                    that his knowledge of Islamic sources was ‘extremely rich’. Given the fact that
                    one finds in many Islamic works material on Muḥammad’s life, the sects of Islam,
                        <hi rend="italic">tafsīr</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi>, and the
                    stories of the prophets, a limited number of <hi rend="italic">Vorlagen</hi>
                    could already suffice to account for all the material under review. The
                    specificity of the material of the heresiography and <hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ
                        al-anbiyāʾ</hi> genres may warrant first and foremost further exploration
                    along these lines. Particularly the prospects of a reliance on a work of <hi
                        rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyāʾ</hi> seems promising, as the use of such a
                        <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> not only could explain the origin of his
                    legendary accounts on Adam’s creation and Og the giant, but potentially also
                    account for his notices on Muḥammad’s life and Muslim exegesis as well as his
                    direct citations of <hi rend="italic">ḥadīth</hi> material. Even more
                    fascinating – to go already one step further – it may possibly also go to some
                    lengths in explaining where the thematically arranged collection of Qurʾānic
                    excerpts included in <hi rend="italic">mimrō</hi> III came from in the first
                    place. All of this, however, is a subject for some other time. </p><pb n="382"/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Bar Ṣalībī, Dionysius, <hi rend="italic">Against the Arabs</hi>,
                    ed. and tr. Joseph P. Amar, <hi rend="italic">Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī: A Response
                        to the Arabs</hi>, CSCO 614-615. Leuven: Peeters, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Beaumont, Mark I. “Early Christian Interpretation of the Qurʾān.”
                        <hi rend="italic">Transformation</hi> 22/4 (2005): 195-203.</bibl>
                <bibl>Boisliveau, Anne-Sylvie, <hi rend="italic">Le Coran par lui-même:
                        Vocabulaire et argumentation du discours coranique autoréférentiel</hi>.
                    Leiden: Brill, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brinner, William M., ʿArāʾis al-Majālis fī Qisas al-Anbiyāʾ <hi
                        rend="italic">or “Lives of the Prophets” as recounted by Abū Isḥāq Aḥmad Ibn
                        Muḥammad Ibn Ibrāhīm Al-Thaʿlabī</hi>, Studies in Arabic Literature 24.
                    Leiden: Brill, 2002</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian P., “A Syriac Collection of Prophecies of the
                    Pagan Philosophers.” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica</hi> 14
                    (1983): 203-246.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “Some Syriac Excerpts from Greek Collections of Pagan
                    Prophecies.” <hi rend="italic">Vigilae Christianae</hi> 38 (1984): 77-90.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brosh,<hi rend="italic"> Naʿama and Rachel Milstein, Biblical
                        Stories in Islamic Painting</hi>. Jerusalem: Israel Museum, 1991. </bibl>
                <bibl>Burge, Stephen R., <hi rend="italic">Angels in Islam: Jalāl al-Dīn
                        al-Suyūtī's</hi> al-Ḥabāʾik fī akhbār al-malāʾik, Culture and Civilization
                    in the Middle East 31. Oxon: Routledge, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Burton, John, <hi rend="italic">The Collection of the Qurʾān</hi>.
                    Cambrigde: Cambridge University Press, 1977.</bibl><pb n="383"/>
                <bibl>Gilliot, Claude, “Islam, ‘sectes’ et groups d’opposition
                    politico-religieux (VIIe-XIIe siècles).” <hi rend="italic">Rives
                        nord-méditerranéeennes</hi> 10 (2002): 1-13.</bibl>
                <bibl>Griffith, Sidney H, “Dionysius bar Ṣalībī on the Muslims.” In <hi
                        rend="italic">IV Symposium Syriacum: Literary Genres in Syriac
                        Literature</hi>, Orientalia Christiana Analecta 229, ed. H. Drijvers et al.
                    Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1987, 353-365.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “Disputes with Muslims in Syriac Christian Texts: From
                    Patriarch John (d. 648) to Bar Hebraeus (d. 1286).” In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Religionsgespräche im Mittelalter</hi>, Wolfenbütteler Mittelalter-Studien
                    4, ed. B. Lewis and F. Niewöhner. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1992, 251-273.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , <hi rend="italic">Syriac Writers on Muslims and the
                        Religious Challenge of Islam</hi>. Kottayam: SEERI, 1995.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “The Qurʾān in Arab Christian Texts; the Development of
                    an Apologetical Argument: Abū Qurrah in the Maǧlis of al-Maʾmūn.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 24 (1999): 203-233.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “Christians and the Arabic Qurʾān: Prooftexting,
                    Polemics, and Intertwined Scriptures.” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of
                        the Islamicate World</hi> 2 (2014): 243-266.</bibl>
                <bibl>Guillaume, Alfred, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Muḥammad: A
                        Translation of Ibn Isḥaq’s</hi> Sīrat rasūl Allāh. Oxford: Oxford University
                    Press, 1982.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gutmann, Joseph and Vera B. Moreen “The Combat between Moses and Og
                    in Muslim Miniatures.” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Asia Institute</hi> 1
                    (1987): 111-21.</bibl><pb n="384"/>
                <bibl>Gutmann, Joseph, “More about the Giant Og in Islamic Art.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin of the Asia Institute</hi> 3 (1989): 107-114.</bibl>
                <bibl>Heimgartner, Martin, Timotheos I., <hi rend="italic">Ostsyrischer
                        Patriarch: Disputation mit dem Kalifen Al-Mahdi</hi>, CSCO 631-2. Leuven:
                    Peeters, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Heller, B. and S. M. Wasserstrom, “Ūdj,” <hi rend="italic">EI<hi
                            rend="sup">2</hi></hi> 10 (2000): 777-8.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hinds, M. “Al-Maghāzī,” <hi rend="italic">EI<hi rend="sup"
                        >2</hi></hi> 5 (1986): 1161-6.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jacobs, Bert, “Unveiling Christ in the Islamicate World: Fakhr
                    al-Dīn al-Rāzī's Prophetology as a Model for Christian Apologetics in Gregory
                    Bar ʿEbrōyō's Treatise on the Incarnation.” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual
                        History of the Islamicate World</hi> 6/1&amp;2 (2018), 187-216.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “Tentative Reconstruction of Dionysius of Tell-Maḥrē’s
                    Account of the Rise of Islam through Three Dependant Texts.” Forthcoming.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jeffery, Arthur, <hi rend="italic">Materials for the History of the
                        Text of the Qurʾan: The Old Codices</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1937.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kara, Seyfeddin, “The Suppression of ʿAlī ibn Abī Ṭālib’s Codex:
                    Study of the Traditions on the Earliest Copy of the Qurʾān.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Near Eastern Studies</hi> 75/2 (2016): 267-289.</bibl>
                <bibl>Al-Kisāʾī, <hi rend="italic">Qiṣaṣ al-anbiyā</hi>, ed. Isaac
                    Eisenberg, <hi rend="italic">Vita Prophetarum auctore Muḥammad ben ʿAbdallāh
                        al-Kisāʾī ex codicibus, qui in Monaco, Bonna, Kygd. Batav. Lipsia et Gothana
                        Asservantur</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1922; tr. William M. Thackston, <hi
                        rend="italic">Tales of the Prophets of Al-Kisaʾi</hi>. Library of Classical
                    Arabic literature 2. Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1978.</bibl><pb n="385"/>
                <bibl>Kister, M. J., “Ādam: A Study of Some Legends in Tafsīr and Ḥadīṯ
                    Literature.” <hi rend="italic">Israel Oriental Studies</hi> 13 (1993):
                    113-74.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kosman, Admiel, “The Story of a Giant Story: The Winding Way of Og
                    King of Bashan in the Jewsih Haggadic Tradition.” <hi rend="italic">Hebrew Union
                        College Annual</hi> 73 (2002): 157-190.</bibl>
                <bibl>Laoust, Henri, “La classification des sectes dans le Farq
                    d’al-Baghdādī.” <hi rend="italic">Revue des Études Islamiques</hi> 29 (1961):
                    19-59; repr. in H. Laoust, <hi rend="italic">Pluralismes dans l'islam</hi>.
                    Paris: Geuthner, 1983, 135-75. </bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “La classification des sects dans l’hérésiographie
                    ashʿarite.” In <hi rend="italic">Arabic and Islamic Studies in Honor of Hamilton
                        A. R. Gibb</hi>, ed. G. Makdisi. Leiden: Brill, 1965, 377-86.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “L'hérésiographie musulmane sous les Abbassides.” <hi
                        rend="italic">Cahiers de civilisation médiévale</hi> 38 (1967): 157-178.</bibl>
                <bibl>Madigan, Daniel A., “Preserved Tablet,” <hi rend="italic">EQ</hi> 4
                    (2004): 261-3.</bibl>
                <bibl>Milstein, R., K. Rührdanz and B. Schmitz, <hi rend="italic">Stories
                        of the Prophets: Illustrated Manuscripts of</hi> Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ.
                    California: Mazda Publishers, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mingana, Alphonse, “An Ancient Syriac Translation of the Ḳurʾan
                    Exhibiting New Verses and Variants.” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the John
                        Rylands Library</hi> 9/1 (1925): 188-235; repr. in Manchester: Manchester
                    University Press, 1925, 1-50; repr. in <hi rend="italic">Which Koran?: Variants,
                        Manuscripts, Linguistics</hi>, ed. Ibn Warraq. Amherst: Prometheus Books,
                    2008; 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nagel, Tilman, <hi rend="italic">Die Qiṣaṣ al-Anbiyāʾ. Ein Beitrag
                        zur Arabischen Literaturgeschichte</hi>. Unpubl. PhD diss., University of
                    Bonn, 1967.</bibl><pb n="386"/>
                <bibl>Nöldeke, T., F. Schwally, G. Bergsträβer, and O. Pretzl, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte des Qurāns</hi>, 3 vols. Leipzig: Dieterichsche
                    Verlagsbuchhandlung, 1909, 1919, 1938.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nguyen, Martin, “Exegesis of the ḥurūf al-muqaṭṭaʿa: Polyvalency in
                    Sunnī Traditions of Qur’ānic Interpretation.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        Qurʾānic Studies</hi> 14/2 (2012): 1-28.</bibl>
                <bibl>O’Shaughnessy, Thomas J. “God’s Throne and the Biblical Symbolism
                    of the Qurʾān.” <hi rend="italic">Numen</hi> 20/4 (1973): 202-221. </bibl>
                <bibl>Pauliny, Ján, “ʿŪg ibn ʿAnāq, ein sagenhafter Riese: Untersuchungen
                    zu den islamischen Riesengeschichten.” <hi rend="italic">Craecolatina et
                        Orientalia</hi> 5 (1973): 249-268.</bibl>
                <bibl>Penn, Michael P., <hi rend="italic">Envisioning Islam: Syriac
                        Christianity and the Early Muslim World</hi>. Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania
                    University Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rassi, Salam, <hi rend="italic">Justifying Christianity in the
                        Islamic Middle Ages: The Apologetic Theology of ʿAbdīshōʿ bar Brīkhā (d.
                        1318)</hi>. PhD diss., University of Oxford, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Roggema, Barbara, “Pour une lecture des dialogues islamo-chrétiens
                    en syriaque à la lumière des controverses internes à l’islam.” In <hi
                        rend="italic">Les controverses religieuses en syriaque</hi>, Études
                    syriaques 13, ed. F. Ruani. Paris: Geuthner, 2016, 261-294.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rosenthal, Franz, <hi rend="italic">The History of al-Tabari, Vol.
                        1: General Introduction and From the Creation to the Flood</hi>. Albany:
                    Suny Press, 1989.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ryan, Stephan D. <hi rend="italic">Dionysius bar Salibi's Factual
                        and Spiritual Commentary on Psalms 73-82</hi>, Cahiers de révue biblique 57.
                    Paris: J. Gabalda et Cie, 2004.</bibl><pb n="387"/>
                <bibl>Saleem, Shehzad, <hi rend="italic">Collection of the Qur’ān: A
                        Critical and Historical Study of Al-Farāhī’s View</hi>. PhD diss.,
                    University of Wales Lampeter, 2010. </bibl>
                <bibl>Sezgin, F. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des arabischen
                        Schrifttums</hi>, Vol. 1. Leiden: Brill, 1967.</bibl>
                <bibl>Schöck, Cornelia, <hi rend="italic">Adam im Islam. Ein Beitrag zur
                        Ideengeschichte der Sunna</hi>. Berlin: Klaus Schwarz Verlag, 1993.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sourdel, Dominique, “Les classification des sects islamiques dans
                    le Kitāb al-Milal d’al-Šahrastānī.” <hi rend="italic">Studia Islamica</hi> 31
                    (1970): 239-247.</bibl>
                <bibl>Talay, Shabo, “Aus dem polemischen Genre des Syrischen: Die
                    luqbal-Schriften von Bar Ṣalībī und Bar Šūšan.” In <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                        Christiana, Festschrift für Hubert Kaufhold zum 70. Geburtstag</hi>, ed. P.
                    Bruns and H. O. Luthe. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2013, 511-521.</bibl>
                <bibl>Teule, Herman, “Jacob bar Šakkō, the Book of Treasures and the
                    Syrian Renaissance.” In <hi rend="italic">Eastern Crossroads. Essays on Medieval
                        Christian Legacy</hi>, Gorgias Eastern Christianity Studies 1, ed. J.-P.
                    Monferrer-Sala. Piscataway, NJ: Georgias Press, 2007, 143-154.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “The Syriac Renaissance.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                        Syriac Renaissance</hi>, Eastern Christian Studies 9, ed. H. Teule et al.
                    Leuven: Peeters, 2010, 1-30.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , “Dionysius bar Ṣalibi,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Christian-Muslim Relations: A Bibliographical History</hi> 3, ed. D. Thomas
                    et al. Leiden: Brill, 2011, 665-670.</bibl>
                <bibl>Thomas, David, “Early Muslim Responses to Christianity.” In <hi
                    rend="italic">Christians at the Heart of Islamic Rule: Church Life and<pb n="388"/>
                        Scholarship in ʿAbbasid Iraq</hi>, The History of Christian-Muslim Relations
                    1, ed. D. Thomas. Leiden: Brill, 2003, 231-254.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tottoli, Roberto, “Origin and Use of the Term Isrāʾiliyyāt in
                    Muslim Literature,” <hi rend="italic">Arabica</hi> 46 (1999): 193-209.</bibl>
                <bibl>_________ , <hi rend="italic">Biblical Prophets in the Qur'an and
                        Muslim Literature</hi>. Routledge Studies in the Qurʾan. London: Routledge,
                    2001.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Ess, Josef, <hi rend="italic">Der Eine und das Andere.
                        Beobachtungen an islamischen haresiographischen Texten</hi>, 2 vols. Berlin:
                    De Gruyter, 2011.</bibl>
                <bibl>Welch, A.T., “Ḳurʾān,” <hi rend="italic">EI<hi rend="sup"
                        >2</hi></hi> 5 (1986): 400-29.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wensinck, A.J., <hi rend="italic">A Handbook of Early Mohammadan
                        Tradition</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1927.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wilde, Clare E., <hi rend="italic">Approaches to the Qurʾān in
                        Early Christian Arabic Texts (750CE-1258 CE)</hi>. Palo Alto: Academica
                    Press, 2014.</bibl><pb n="389"/>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
