<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Gišeroy kcʿurdkʿ (Hymns of the Night)</title>
                <title type="sub">Seven Madrāše of Ephrem the Syrian Preserved in Armenian</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jesse Siragan</forename>
                        <surname>Arlen</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of California, Los Angeles</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n2arlen</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Jesse Siragan Arlen</author>
                        <title level="a">Gišeroy kcʿurdkʿ (Hymns of the Night): Seven Madrāše of
                            Ephrem the Syrian Preserved in Armenian</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N2Arlen.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="15" to="66">15-66</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="3"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Ephrem the Syrian</term>
                    <term>Armenian</term>
                    <term>Hymns</term>
                    <term>Madrāše</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-11-01">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">

        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p xml:lang="en">This paper treats the collection of fifty-one hymns (madrāše) of
                    Ephrem the Syrian that survive in Armenian translation (Arm. kc‘urdk‘), with a
                    particular focus upon one cycle of seven, the Hymns of the Night (Gišeroy
                    kc‘urdk‘), which treat the topic of vigil. After a brief discussion of the
                    collection as a whole, an annotated English translation of the Hymns of the
                    Night (kc‘urdk‘ 10-16) is made for the first time. Following this is a
                    commentary that discusses linguistic, historical and thematic evidence that
                    supports the attribution to Ephrem and points towards a fifth-century date for
                    the translation from Syriac to Armenian.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <pb n="267"/>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> I would like to
                            thank my doctoral advisor, Peter Cowe, for his close guidance throughout
                            the process of writing and revising this article and the translations
                            therein, which was carried out in the course of a year-long seminar on
                            Armenian Ephremica at UCLA. This article and the translations would have
                            been much poorer without his careful and thorough assistance. I would
                            also like to thank Jeffrey Wickes, who, both via email and in person at
                            the 2017 NAPS meeting (where an earlier version of this paper was
                            presented), offered suggestions and helped me with some of my questions
                            regarding Ephrem and his fourth-century context, while pointing me to
                            relevant bibliographical sources that I made use of in this paper. All
                            shortcomings in this article and any errors in translation are entirely
                            my own responsibility. A note on transliteration: Armenian has been
                            transliterated according to the Hübschmann-Meillet standard as applied
                            in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Études Arméniennes</hi>, and Syriac
                            has been transliterated according to the standard used by the Library of
                            Congress (<ref target="https://www.loc.gov/catdir/cpso/roman.html"><hi
                                    rend="underline color(0000FF)"
                                    >https://www.loc.gov/catdir/cpso/roman.html</hi></ref>. Accessed
                            20 March 2018). This has not been strictly maintained for the names of
                            modern Armenian writers, in cases where their names are conventionally
                            rendered into Latin characters with a different spelling, or for
                            bibliographic references classified according to a different
                            transliteration system (such as Library of Congress). For the vowel
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">ու</foreign>, I follow the convention of
                            transliterating it as ‘u’ instead of ‘ow.’ Thus: <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >կցուրդ</foreign> is rendered as <hi rend="italic">kc‘urd</hi> and
                            not <hi rend="italic">kc‘owrd</hi>. Transliterated words in both
                            languages are marked off in italics, except for personal and place
                            names.</p></note></head>
                <p>Among the profuse corpus of extant Armenian texts attributed to Ephrem the Syrian
                    are fifty-one pieces called <hi rend="italic">kc‘urd</hi> (<foreign
                        xml:lang="hy">կցուրդ</foreign>), the Armenian rendering of the Syriac <hi
                        rend="italic">madrāšā</hi>. Although traditionally translated into English
                    as ‘hymn,’ <hi rend="italic">madrāšā </hi>might be better
                    rendered as ‘teaching song,’ which captures the twin components of this Syriac
                    genre, at the nexus betwen didactic literary work and liturgical hymn.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> This is the
                            nomenclature of scholars such as Andrew Palmer and Kees den Biesen. See
                            Andrew Palmer, “A Single Human Being Divided in Himself: Ephraim the
                            Syrian, the Man in the Middle,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of
                                Syriac Studies</hi> 1:2 (1998): 119-163; Kees den Biesen, <hi
                                rend="italic">Simple and Bold: Ephrem’s Art of Symbolic
                            Thought</hi>, Gorgias Dissertations 26, Early Christian Studies 6
                            (Piscataway, NJ, 2006).</p></note> The Syriac root <hi rend="italic"
                        >drš</hi>, ‘to tread out (a path)’ with its derived meaning of ‘to train,
                    instruct,’ indicates the didactic origin of the genre,<pb n="268"/> immediately
                    bringing to mind as well the Hebrew tradition of <hi rend="italic">midraš</hi>,
                    and its association with interpretation and debate. It is likely that at the
                    earliest stage the <hi rend="italic">madrāšā</hi> genre was a purely literary
                    one (i.e. not sung), and probably prose rather than poetry.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> On the <hi rend="italic"
                                >madrāšā</hi> genre, see Kathleen McVey, “Were the earliest <hi
                                rend="italic">madrāšē</hi> songs or recitations?” in <hi
                                rend="italic">After Bardaisan. Studies on Continuity and Change in
                                Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professor Han J.W. Drijvers</hi>,
                            eds. G.J. Reinink and A.C. Klugkist, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 89
                            (Louvain, 1999): 185-199; Edmund Beck, “Ephräms des Syrers Hymnik,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">Liturgie und Dichtung. Ein interdisziplinäres
                                Kompendium. Gualtero Duerig annum vitae septuagesimum feliciter
                                complenti</hi>, eds. H. Becker and R. Kaczynski (St. Ottilien,
                            1983), vol. 1: 345-379.</p></note> Ephrem himself cites the
                    second/third-century figure Bardaiṣan as the one responsible for transforming
                    this prose genre into measured verse with melodies.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies</hi> 53.5.1-5 in Edmund Beck,
                                <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra
                                Haereses</hi>, Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 169/170,
                            Scriptores Syri 76/77 (Louvain, 1957). See Kathleen McVey, “The earliest
                                <hi rend="italic">madrāšē</hi>,” 187-188.</p></note> Ephrem,
                    following Bardaiṣan’s lead, became the most celebrated composer of <hi
                        rend="italic">madrāše</hi>, employing it for his own instructive and
                    polemical purposes. The combination of verse and song made for an effective
                    means of polemics in the contested religious environment of the fourth century
                    in addition to providing a means of edification for hearers and a fit medium for
                    Ephrem’s poetic and symbolically rich thought world and theological method.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> On Ephrem’s
                            theological method, see den Biesen, <hi rend="italic">Simple and
                                Bold</hi>, as well as two recent dissertations: Jeffrey Wickes, “Out
                            of Books, a World: The Scriptural Poetics of Ephrem the Syrian’s Hymns
                            on Faith,” PhD diss., University of Notre Dame, 2013; Carmen Maier,
                            “Poetry as Exegesis: Ephrem the Syrian’s Method of Scriptural
                            Interpretation Especially as Seen in his Hymns on Paradise and Hymns on
                            Unleavened Bread,” PhD diss., Princeton Theological Seminary,
                        2012.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p> By the time of the fifth century — the earliest possible period at which the <hi
                        rend="italic">madrāše</hi> of Ephrem could have been translated into
                    Armenian, due to the invention of Armenian letters in the fifth century — <hi
                        rend="italic">madrāšā</hi> referred to a type of liturgical hymn, already
                    present in all Syriac traditions, of<pb n="269"/> isosyllabic lines arranged in
                    strophes sung by a soloist, with a short refrain sung by a choir, the singers
                    often being women.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > On the performance context of Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">madrāše</hi>,
                            see Andrew Palmer, “Ephrem of Nisibis,” in <hi rend="italic">The Wiley
                                Blackwell Companion to Patristics</hi>, ed. Ken Parry (Chichester,
                            2015): 126–140 at 127.</p></note> The Armenian term <hi rend="italic"
                        >kc‘urd</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="hy">կցուրդ</foreign>), like the
                    fifth-century <hi rend="italic">madrāšā</hi>, refers to strophic, often
                    antiphonal liturgical poetry, usually sung in connection with the celebration of
                    a feast-day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">
                            NBHL, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="hy">կցուրդ</foreign>.</p></note> It is
                    derived from the verb <hi rend="italic">kc‘em</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                        >կցեմ</foreign>), meaning “to join, unite, tie,” and could refer either to
                    the joining together of syllables and words into metric verse, or the joining
                    together of voices in song.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> It likewise carries a derivative meaning of “to
                            play (an instrument)” or “to sing.” See NBHL, s.v. <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">կցեմ</foreign>.</p></note> In connection with this,
                    the standard word for hymn in Armenian, <hi rend="italic">šarakan</hi> (<foreign
                        xml:lang="hy">շարական</foreign>) from the root <hi rend="italic"
                        >šar</hi>/<hi rend="italic">šarem</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                        >շար</foreign>/<foreign xml:lang="hy">շարեմ</foreign>) shares this sense of
                    ‘ordering, arranging.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> NBHL, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >շարական</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                        >շարեմ</foreign>.</p></note></p>
                <p> The complete collection of Ephrem’s fifty-one <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>
                    were first published in a diplomatic edition by Nersēs Akinian of the Vienna
                    Mekhitarist order of scholar-monks in 1957.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10"
                        n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> Nersēs Akinian, <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘
                                S. Ep‘remi Xorin Asorwoy</hi> [=<hi rend="italic">Ephräm des Syrers
                                51 Madrasche in Armenischer Ubersetzung</hi>], Texte und
                            Untersuchungen der Altarmenischen Literature, Bd. 1.3 (Vienna,
                            1957).</p></note> A few years later this text was reproduced by Louis
                    Mariès and Charles Mercier along with an introduction and annotated translation
                    into Latin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Louis Mariès and Charles Mercier, <hi rend="italic">Hymnes de Saint
                                Ephrem conservées en version arménienne</hi>, Patrologia Orientalis
                            XXX, fascicle 1 (Paris: Firmin-Didot, 1961). For earlier publications
                            see Edward Mathews, “Armenian Hymn IX, <hi rend="italic">On
                                Marriage</hi> by Saint Ephrem the Syrian,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                                of the Society for Armenian Studies</hi> 9 (1999): 55-63, at 56-57,
                            n. 7; and Mariès and Mercier, <hi rend="italic">Hymnes</hi>,
                        10-11.</p></note> Corrections and further variant readings from manuscripts
                    not consulted by Akinian were added by Levon Tēr-Petrosian in a later
                        study.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Levon Tēr-Petrosian, “Kc‘urdk‘ S. Ep‘remi Xorin Asorvoy: Bnagrakan
                            Čšgrtumner [<hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> of Ephrem the Syrian:
                            Text-Critical Emendations],” <hi rend="italic">Handēs Amsoreay</hi> 92
                            (1978): 15-48.</p></note> Over the years,<pb n="270"/> there have been a
                    number of scattered translations of individual hymns, often with brief studies
                    accompanying them, in French and English.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13"
                        n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> The following <hi rend="italic"
                                >kc‘urdk‘</hi> have been translated into English or French: <hi
                                rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 2-7, 9 in François Graffin, “Hymnes
                            inédites de S. Ephrem sur la virginité” <hi rend="italic">L’Orient
                                Syrien </hi>6 (1961): 213–42; <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 4-5 in
                            Edward Mathews, “Saint Ephrem the Syrian: Armenian Dispute Hymns between
                                <hi rend="italic">Virginity</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                                >Chastity</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des études
                                arméniennes </hi>28 (2001/2): 143–69;
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd </hi>9 in Edward
                            Mathews, “Armenian Hymn IX, On Marriage, by Saint Ephrem the Syrian,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society for Armenian Studies </hi>9
                            (1996/7 [1999]): 55–63;
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>14-15 in Louis
                            Mariès, “Deux Antiphonae de Saint Ephrem,” <hi rend="italic">Recherches
                                de Science Religieuse</hi> 45 (1957), 396-408;
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd </hi>46 in Robert Murray,
                            “‘A Marriage for all eternity’: The Consecration of a Syrian bride of
                            Christ,” <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review </hi>11
                            (1989): 65–8; <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 47-51 in Bernard
                            Outtier, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lettre aux amis de Solesmes</hi> 18 (avril-juin 1979): 3-9 and
                            Idem, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie II” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lettre aux amis de Solesmes</hi> 22 (avril-juin 1980): 3-8 and
                            Idem, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie III”
                            <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux amis de Solesmes </hi>(1981:1):
                            14-18 and Idem, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie IV” <hi
                                rend="italic">Lettre aux amis de Solesmes</hi> (1981:3): 3-7 and
                            Idem, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie V” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Lettre aux amis de Solesmes</hi> (1982:2): 3-5;
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd </hi>48 in Louis Mariès,
                            “Une Antiphona de Saint Ephrem sur l’eucharistie,” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Recherches de Science Religieuse</hi> 42 (1954), 395-403;
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd </hi>49 in Sebastian
                            Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Harp of the Spirit: Poems of Saint Ephrem
                                the Syrian</hi>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> ed., The Institute
                            for Orthodox Christian Studies (Cambridge, 2013): 119-123. Robert Murray
                            also treats the dispute hymns
                            (<hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>4-5, 9) in Robert
                            Murray, “Aramaic and Syriac Dispute-Poems and Their Connections,” in
                            M.J. Geller, J.C. Greenfield, M.P. Weitzmann, eds., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Studia Aramaica: New Sources and New Approaches</hi>, Journal of
                            Semitic Studies, Supplement 4, (Oxford, 1995): 157-187.</p></note></p>
                <p> Akinian’s diplomatic Armenian text is largely derived from two manuscripts:
                    Matenadaran 821 and Nicosia (Cyprus) 8 (now Antelias 85).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> Akinian, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urdk‘</hi>, ix-xviii and Mariès and Mercier, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hymnes</hi>, 8-18. I summarize their description of the manuscripts
                            in my account which follows, also making use of Ō. Eganyan, A.
                            Zeytʻunyan, Pʻ. Antʻabyan, eds., <hi rend="italic">Mayr tsʻutsʻak
                                hayerēn dzeṛagratsʻ Mashtotsʻi Anuan Matenadarani</hi> [=Grand
                            Catalogue of the Armenian Manuscripts of the Matenadaran named Maštoc‘],
                            Erevan, 1984—, vol. III, s.v. 821. In fact, for <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 16-51, Akinian actually uses Vienna 257 as his base
                            text, which is a derivative of Matenadaran 821.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 16-51 are provided from the former and 1-15 from
                    the latter. Matenadaran 821 is a religious<pb n="271"/> miscellany (<foreign
                        xml:lang="hy">ժողովածոյ</foreign>) copied in 1313 at the monastery of Akner
                        (<foreign xml:lang="hy">Ակներ</foreign>) in Cilicia.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Eganyan et al., <hi
                                rend="italic">Mayr tsʻutsʻak</hi>, vol. III, s.v. 821. The full
                            texts of the Matenadaran manuscript catalogues (now up to nine volumes,
                            which covers manuscripts 1-3000) are available at the Matenadaran
                            website: http://www.matenadaran.am/.</p></note> It contains only <hi
                        rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 16-51 because the initial pages of the
                    manuscript are missing, resulting in the loss of the first 15 <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kc‘urdk‘</hi>. Occasional pages or portions of pages are also missing or
                    damaged (as well as some being out of order), leading to lacunae in later <hi
                        rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>. The manuscript was already in a defective state
                    when it was repaired in 1596 at T‘lkuran (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                        >Թլկուրան</foreign>) near Edessa, as is clear from the colophon of the
                    renewer who begged the reader’s forgiveness for the missing initial pages and
                    their mixed-up order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The full colophon of the renewer reads as follows:
                            Ի թվին ՌԽԵ (1596) ամին նորոգեցաւ դարձեալ վերստին սուրբ գիրքս ի
                            գեաւղաքաղաքն ի Թլկուրան, ի դուռն Սուրբ Կարապետին, ի հայրապետութեան
                            տէր Պետրոս քաջ րաբունապետին մերոյ, եւ ի առաջնորդութեանն տէր Կարապետին եւ
                            աստուածաբան վարդապետին, ձեռամբ անարժան Թումայի աշակերտի։ Եւ որք
                            ընթեռնուք եւ ուսանիք, Աստուած ողորմի ասացէք, եւ Աստուած ձեզ եւ մեզ
                            ողորմեսցի. ամէն։ Դարձեալ, կրկին, աղաչեմ, չլինել մեղադիր մեզ վասն
                            պակասութեան գրոցս եւ խարնիխուրն լինելոյ, քանզի յոյժ աշխատ եղաք եւ ոչ
                            կարացաք գտանել զպակասն սորա, եւ այլ օրինակ ոչ գոյր, բայց զայն, որ յայտնի
                            գոյ ի գիրքս՝ ուսցիս եւ զմեզ անպարսաւ թողցես. եւ Քրիստոսի փառք յաւիտեանս.
                            ամէն։ </p><p rend="footnote text">In the year 1045 (=1596 CE) this holy
                            book was yet again restored in the town of T‘lkuran, at the door of Holy
                            Karapet, during the patriarchy of Father Petros our excellent pontiff,
                            and during the prelacy of Father Karapet, theological doctor [<hi
                                rend="italic">vardapet</hi>], by the hand of the unworthy disciple
                            T‘umay. And you who read and study it, say “May God have mercy,” and may
                            God have mercy upon you and us. Amen. Again, a second time, I beg you
                            not to blame us on account of the defectiveness of this book and its
                            mixed-up state, because we made great effort and yet were unable to find
                            its missing pages, and there was no other exemplar, except that which is
                            present in this book. May you study, and leave us irreproachable. And to
                            Christ glory forever. Amen. Eganyan et al., <hi rend="italic">Mayr
                                ts‘uts‘ak</hi>, vol. III, s.v. 821.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p> From this we can conclude that by 1313 when the manuscript was copied, it
                    contained all 51 <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> of Ephrem<pb n="272"/> as a
                    single collection. Unfortunately however, all the manuscripts derived from this
                    copy were undertaken after it had become defective. In 1939 on a trip to Cyprus,
                    Akinian discovered Nicosia 8 (now Antelias 85), which contained the missing
                    initial fifteen <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> 47-51 (it therefore lacks numbers 16-46).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"> Nersēs Akinian, <hi
                                rend="italic">Tsʻutsʻak hayerēn dzeragratsʻ Nikosiayi i Kipros</hi>
                            [=Katalog der armenischen Handscriften in Nikosia auf Cyprus], Vienna,
                            1961, 36-41. The manuscripts of Nicosia, Cyprus are now held in
                            Antelias, Lebanon at the Armenian Catholicosate of Cilicia. Nicosia 8 is
                            now Antelias 85, and is also described in Anoushawan Vardapet Tanielian,
                                <hi rend="italic">Mayr tsʻutsʻak hayerēn dzeṛagratsʻ Metsi Tann
                                Kilikioy Katʻoghikosutʻean</hi> [=Catalogue of the Armenian
                            Manuscripts in the Collection of the Armenian Catholicosate of Cilicia],
                            (Antelias, 1984), 319-322.</p></note> It is a collection of religious
                    texts, compiled mostly from the lives and writings of the Fathers, and was
                    copied in the fourteenth century. It is in a deteriorated state, but nonetheless
                    for the most part filled the gaps of Matenadaran 821 by supplying the texts
                    (with some lacunae) of the first fifteen <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>. </p>
                <p> It is highly unlikely that the fifty-one <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> of
                    Ephrem surviving in Armenian were all derived from an original cycle of
                    fifty-one <hi rend="italic">madrāše</hi> put together as such in the fourth
                    century by Ephrem, but rather were pulled together at some point, presumably by
                    the Armenian translator(s), from different Syriac originals. The surviving
                    fifty-one <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> treat a variety of different topics,
                    but can be broken down into at least three major sub-groupings, perhaps
                    representative of three originally separate cycles of <hi rend="italic"
                        >madrāše</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>1-9
                    treat virginity and holiness;
                    <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>10-16 all contain the
                    superscript <foreign xml:lang="hy">Գիշերոյ կցուրդ</foreign> (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi>, “Teaching Song of the Night”) and have to do with
                    vigil; <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>17-51 in one way or
                    another all treat the topic of eating, in particular the Lord feeding his
                    creatures, with topics derived from everyday life and the Scriptures, including
                    the Lord feeding his creatures through mysteries (<hi rend="italic">rāze</hi>),
                    such as the Eucharist
                    (<hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ </hi>47-51). These three larger
                    themes likely reveal the taste of the Armenian translator(s),<pb n="273"/> who
                    chose these particular hymns for their relevance to the Armenian ecclesiastical
                    context.</p>
                <p> Most scholars have assumed an early date for the translation of these texts,
                    supposing that they come from the initial translation movement of Maštoc‘ and
                    his students in the fifth century. No scholars who have worked on the <hi
                        rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> have found grounds for questioning either the
                    authenticity of their attribution to Ephrem or the early date of
                        translation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > For example, according to Edward Mathews, “Language, style, and the
                            themes treated in these poems clearly reflect those found in the genuine
                            Syriac hymns of Ephrem,” in Mathews, “Armenian Dispute Hymns,” 148.
                            Robert Murray, in the brief introduction to his translation of <hi
                                rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 46 says, “Though this poem comes to us in
                            Armenian, a number of significant expressions clearly represent Syriac
                            terms which are familiar both from St. Ephrem and from his contemporary
                            Aphrahat,” in Murray, “Marriage for all eternity,” 65. For further
                            examples, see the studies in note 10 above.</p></note> There has however
                    been very little effort to give concrete evidence for either of these two
                    suppositions. In light of recent studies of Edward Mathews demonstrating that
                    many of the works translated from Syriac into Armenian — both those attributed
                    to Ephrem and as well as the works of other writers — actually date from the
                    Cilician period (especially the twelfth–thirteenth centuries) when there was a
                    sizeable Syriac community living within the Armenian realm, as opposed to the
                    fifth-century provenance that previous scholars had simply assumed for most
                    Syriac works in Armenian, it seemed worthwhile to investigate the attribution
                    and provenance of these texts by examining the concrete linguistic evidence of
                    the texts as well as some historical and thematic evidence.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> On the dating and authorship
                            of Syriac translations into Armenian, see Edward G. Mathews, “Syriac
                            into Armenian: The Translations and their Translators,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac
                                Studies</hi> 10 (2010): 20-44.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p> After conducting my investigation into this question, I believe the evidence
                    strongly favors the view to date that these texts issue from authentic Syriac
                    originals of Ephrem rendered into Armenian in the fifth century. This article
                    focuses on the cycle of seven <hi rend="italic">Gišeroy kc‘urdk‘</hi> that treat
                    the topic of vigil, providing an annotated translation as well as a commentary
                        <pb n="274"/> providing mostly linguistic evidence that supports their
                    authentic attribution to Ephrem. A translation of all fifty-one <hi
                        rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> into English is currently under preparation.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Annotated Translation<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> I am following the text found in Mariès and
                            Mercier, <hi rend="italic">Hymnes</hi>, 76-80, which is the same as that
                            of Akinian, <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>, 26-28. Since this is a
                            diplomatic edition, at times I translate from more preferable readings
                            found in the apparatus or among the additional manuscript witnesses
                            found in Tēr-Petrosian, “Kc‘urdk‘.”</p></note></head>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 10 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 1]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Blessing, Hymn of the First Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">O Son, glorified by the sleepless ones; blessing to
                    You from those keeping watch.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">1 O watchers, be like Moses, the chief of the
                    Hebrews,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">He who estranged himself from sleep during the days in
                    which he stood on the mountain;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The following account of Moses’ behavior on Mount
                            Sinai differs in many respects from the narrative in Exodus (which
                            commences in chapter 19 and continues to the end of the book). Ephrem
                            likely makes use of extracanonical, including oral traditions native to
                            early Syriac Christian and perhaps Rabbinic traditions of Mesopotamia
                            related to Moses, as he expands the biblical narrative with his own
                            interpretation. This is of course one of the aspects of the poetic,
                            exegetical method of his <hi rend="italic">madrāše</hi> that align them
                            with their Hebrew counterpart, <hi rend="italic"
                    >midraš</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">But from the hour that he became a [seer of] god<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> The text reads
                            reads simply <foreign xml:lang="hy">աստուած</foreign> (“god”). Akinian
                            suggested correcting <foreign xml:lang="hy">աստուած</foreign> to
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">աստուածատես</foreign> (“a seer of God”).
                            Although there are no manuscript witnesses to support his emendation, it
                            is logically sound and I have followed it in the English translation.
                            The compound <foreign xml:lang="hy">աստուածատես</foreign> (“a seer of
                            God”) is found among fifth-century writers. See NBHL, s.v. <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">աստուածատես</foreign>.</p></note> and his face was
                    illumined,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Sleep feared to approach his eyes, which had put on<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text"> Literally,
                            “clothed, dressed” (<foreign xml:lang="hy">զգեցան</foreign>).</p></note>
                    glory.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">5 For the veil of Moses was limiting the vision of all
                        the<pb n="275"/> people,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Who would remain outside all the walls, and did not have
                    the temerity to pass from outside the veil to be with him.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod 34:29-35.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Although sleep was hovering near to Moses within the
                    veil,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">If he were to enter [sc. into sleep], he would be killed
                    by the glory right away.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Since even without the glory, he had banished the sleep
                    of eighty nights,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ephrem derives the number eighty by combining the
                            two accounts of Moses being on the mountain for forty days and forty
                            nights, as mentioned in Exod 24:18 and Exod 34:28.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">10 After he had put on<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26"
                        n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Literally, “clothed, dressed” (<foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">զգեցաւ</foreign>).</p></note> glory, how much more
                    would he banish it!</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">But so that the people would not err and think that he
                    was not a man,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">He would doze off lightly, in order to teach them that
                    he is earthly and not celestial.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Literally, “lower (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >ներքին</foreign>) and not upper (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >վերին</foreign>).”</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And because he had trained himself and had become a
                    watcher by a little effort of his will,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Behold, he estranged himself from sleep, from the days
                    of our Lord up until now.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">15 Concerning his coming to Tabor,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"> Ephrem is referring to Moses’
                            appearance at the transfiguration. See Matt 17:1-8 with parallels in
                            Mark 9:2-8 and Luke 9:28-36. </p></note> Scripture says,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> The subjectless
                                “<foreign xml:lang="hy">ասէ</foreign>” in the Armenian text is
                            usually used to introduce a quote from Scripture, although here it could
                            refer to Tradition more broadly, or an early written or oral souce that
                            falls outside of canonical Scripture.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">“Afterwards he slept no more, but he stands with the
                    sleepless ones in sleep.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> None of the gospel passages mention directly
                            Moses’ lack of sleep, so presumably Ephrem is drawing on an
                            extra-canonical source. The Lukan account does mention the disciples
                            sleepiness during the event. Ephrem seems to distinguish in this passage
                            between two kinds of sleep: one that is lower (terrestrial) and one that
                            is upper (celestial). The latter is a kind of intelligible, cognizant
                            sleep of eternal rest.</p></note></p>
                <pb n="276"/>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And Joshua son of Nun<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                        n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> Joshua is regularly named along with his
                            patronymic, since the Syriac for Joshua and Jesus are the same (as in
                            Hebrew and Greek). The form found in the Armenian bible for “Joshua, Son
                            of Nun” is normally <foreign xml:lang="hy">Յեսու որդի Նաւեայ</foreign> ,
                            as in Exodus 33:11, Numbers 11:28, 13:16/17, Joshua 1:1, and elsewhere.
                            The unusual form here (<foreign xml:lang="hy">Յեսու Նաւեանց</foreign> )
                            is a kind of Armenization of the patronymic, treating it gramatically
                            how Armenian <hi rend="italic">naxarar</hi> family names are treated.
                            The same form is also found in the beginning of a commentary on Joshua
                            and Judges by the fifth-century author <hi rend="italic">Ełišē</hi>
                                (<foreign xml:lang="hy">Մեկնութիւն Յեսուայ եւ Դատաւորաց</foreign>):
                                “<foreign xml:lang="hy">Կոչեցաւ Յեսու Նաւեանց ի Տեառնէ առաջնորդ
                                Իսրայելի</foreign> ...” in Ełišē Vardapet, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Matenagrut‘iwnk‘</hi>, Venice, 1859, 167.</p></note> was a dweller
                    in the tent of meeting, as it is written.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                        n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod 33:11.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Through his dwelling in the holy place, he banished the
                    sleep of his eyes,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And the desire of his body parts, and the dozing and
                    sleep of his pupils. </p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">20 Modesty dwelt in his heart, and wakefulness in his
                    eyelids.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Sleep and desire are natural, and both were conquered by
                        Hoshea.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Hoshea was the name of Joshua before Moses changed his name: see Num
                            13:8 and Num 13:16/17. The Armenian form here (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >Հոշայէ</foreign>) is derived from the Syriac (<hi rend="italic"
                                >hušā‘</hi> ), and not from the Greek (<foreign xml:lang="gr"
                                >Αυση</foreign>), even though the form found in the Armenian bible
                                (<foreign xml:lang="hy">Աւսեայ</foreign>, appearing only in the
                            genitive) is derived from the Greek.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Because he who conquers desire of the body is able to
                    conquer sleep of the eyes.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">He submitted himself to sleep for a little, but to
                    desire not ever at all.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Sleep was struck off from his eyes, and desire did not
                    rule in his heart.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">25 Along with this same example, Elijah banished
                        sleep<pb n="277"/> from his eyes,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Because for forty nights his eyelids fasted from
                        sleep.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> 1
                            Kgs 19:8.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And because he trained himself in watching in his
                    journey on Mount Horeb,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 1 Kgs 19.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">That watching of a short time made him a watcher
                        forever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">
                            This seems to be another allusion to the transfiguration, as was made
                            with Moses above.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Job was awake in his testing to seek and receive from
                    his Lord</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">30 Thanksgiving instead of complaining and blessing
                    instead of blasphemy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Job 1:20-22; 2:9-10.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Jonah kept watch during the nights in which he was in
                    the womb of the fish;</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">He was buried in the fish and the sea, but sleep did not
                    reign over his eyes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Jonah 1:17-2:10.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">The wakefulness of the son of Amathias surprised and
                    amazed the big fish,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Because he did not even want to bend his knee so long as
                    he was in the belly of the fish.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">35 Jonah fled from God because he thought in his
                    ignorance</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">That the Holy One and Glorious One dwells only in the
                    land of Promise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > Jonah 1:3.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">But when he descended into the floor of the sea, he
                    learned from his own experience </p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">That not only on the earth is that Holy One, but also in
                    the abyss of the depths of the sea.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Jonah 2.</p></note></p>
                <pb n="278"/>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Jeremiah was awake in the pit to make prayers for his
                    murderers;</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">40 Through his occupation with God, he estranged himself
                    from the foul pit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Jer 38:6-13.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">Ezekiel banished his sleep for four hundred and thirty
                        days,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text"> Ezek
                            4:4-8.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">For he fasted from sleep, as he fasted from food.</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">By the same measure [with which he measured] his food,
                    he measured the sleep of his eyes,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And since his food was little, he would only moisten his
                        palate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Ezek 4:9-17.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">45 By the [measure of the] little water which he would
                    drink, he would lead eye to eye for a short time,</p>
                <p style="text-align:left;">And before having slept, right on the spot he would wake
                    up.</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 11 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 2]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Second Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Blessed is the one who comes and makes glad the
                    watchers at his appearance.</p>
                <p>1 Be sober a little while, O virtuous ones, lifting up the heaviness of
                    darkness.</p>
                <p>Because behold, a little while<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The language here of “a little while” hearkens to
                            Jesus’ farewell discourse in the gospel of John (see John 16:16).
                            Immediately following this discourse is the incident at Gethsemane,
                            where Jesus tells the disciples to watch and they fall asleep. This is
                            brought up in the verses of this <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> that
                            immediately follow. Thus, Ephrem encourages his watchers not to fall
                            asleep as the disciples did.</p></note> and [night] has completed its
                    hours, and morning comes and makes us glad.</p>
                <p>At night, the disciples kept watch, yet because they<pb n="279"/> dozed off,</p>
                <p>Out of wrath, the teacher severely reproached the twelve.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> Matt 26:36-46 with parallels
                            in Mark 14:32-42, Luke 22:40-46.</p></note></p>
                <p>5 The establisher of that nature would not have compelled them [sc. to stay
                    awake],</p>
                <p>If he had not known that humanity is able to conquer sleep;</p>
                <p>And he would not have laid down a commandment again,</p>
                <p>If he had not known that [sleep] could be conquered.</p>
                <p>Scripture says, “Be watchers, to guard the hour of the bridegroom who is to
                        come.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text"> This
                            appears to be a reference to the parable of the bridegroom, although
                            this exact language is not found in the gospel passages (see Matt
                            25:1-13). Ephrem may also have in mind Mark 13:32-37.</p></note></p>
                <p>10 He gave us four watches<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The four watches of the night are mentioned in
                            Mark 13:35 (evening, midnight, cockcrow, and dawn).</p></note> to guard,
                    throughout all the nights of our life,</p>
                <p>So that in whichever of them he comes, he will find his church awake.</p>
                <p>Although he hid his day and his hour, and did not reveal the hour of his
                    dawning,</p>
                <p>Yet behold, he foretold through the four parts that in the night his revelation
                    is made.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text"> Mark
                            13:32-37.</p></note></p>
                <p>Let us keep therefore the hour of the groom, as we received a commandment,</p>
                <p>15 Because even if he does not come in our days, his trustworthiness will not
                    defraud us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Ephrem’s point is that even if the Second Coming does not occur in their
                            days, they will still get a reward for having kept watch.</p></note></p>
                <p>“As you will be found, you will be led,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> This doesn’t seem to correspond to any
                            canonical biblical passage, so it likely derives from an extra-canonical
                            source.</p></note> said the teacher<pb n="280"/> to his disciples.</p>
                <p>Let us chase away sleep from our eyes, to be ready at his coming.</p>
                <p>Unexpectedly, the lightning flashes; thunder cracks and causes fright.</p>
                <p>Unexpectedly, the firstborn hastens, and he stirs the powers of the heavens.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"> For thunder,
                            lightning, and other celestial activity in regards to the return of
                            Christ, see Matt 24: 27-31 and Luke 17:24.</p></note></p>
                <p>20 The violence of lightning flashes and the terrors of all thunderings</p>
                <p>Are as a breath and as nothing in the eyes of the revelation of Christ.</p>
                <p>The sun grows dark from his [sc. Christ’s] face, and the moon is obstructed from
                    the face of his glory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Matt 24:29.</p></note></p>
                <p>Darkness is erased and diminished through the dawning of the great sign.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text"> Matt
                        24:30.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sleep and slumber of the eyes falls away, and desire of body parts is
                    removed,</p>
                <p>25 And one wakefulness spreads out, which does not diminish.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"> Ephrem here seems to envision
                            a vigilance enveloping everyone and everything. This vigilance is single
                            and whole, and will continue without ceasing, allowing for a pure
                            continuity of consciousness. On animals keeping watch, see for example
                            the reference to the wild beasts keeping watch with Daniel in the den at
                                <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 13.2.</p></note></p>
                <p>Everyone who keeps<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Following mss C: <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >պահէ</foreign> instead of <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                            >պատմէ</foreign>.</p></note> the hours of the groom, he makes glad at
                    his appearance.</p>
                <p>Because those who remove the heaviness from their life are right to put to sleep
                    their body parts.</p>
                <p>Let us keep watch as much as we are able, and not less<pb n="281"/> than our
                    ability.</p>
                <p>Our laziness is reproached by the strong ones who toil among us, for we did not
                    keep watch in the evening. </p>
                <p>30 Let us by no means be half-awake,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">ծանրարթունք</foreign>, literally “heavily-awake,”
                            perhaps a reference to keeping watch in a hypnagogic state.</p></note>
                    for there is one who keeps watch the whole night; let us keep watch at least
                        half.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Ephrem indicates that his group keeping watch is not the most extreme
                            ascetically, keeping vigil as they do for around half the night. There
                            are others who shun sleep even longer, keeping watch throughout the
                            entire night.</p></note></p>
                <p>What benefit is it that we slept yesterday, since we will sleep again today?</p>
                <p>Watchers abound in prayers, while sleepers are numbered by their dreams.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"> Here begins a
                            contrast between the praying of watchers and the dreaming of sleepers.
                            Dreams are regarded as empty and evanescent at best, with the dangerous
                            potential to induce passions and sin through deceptive and foul visions
                            (dreams). Furthermore, there is no lasting benefit brought from sleep or
                            its attendant dreams, as one simply becomes tired again the next day.
                            Watching with prayer on the other hand, brings both present and lasting
                            benefit to the practitioner, purifying them in and through the act of
                            watching, while storing up future benefits and recompense that will be
                            reaped at the revelation of Christ.</p></note></p>
                <p>The breaths of watchers are purified and their minds become chaste,</p>
                <p>While in the breath of sleepers the error of deceptive visions is gathered.</p>
                <p>35 The breath of watchers is glorified through their occupation with God,</p>
                <p>While the breath of sleepers is a game for the Evil One.</p>
                <p>In their dreams, they are befouled through their visions, and passions seize
                    power over them,</p>
                <p>And sleep, which they thought was rest, became entirely disturbed.<pb n="282"
                    /></p>
                <p>They wander through many places and roam, and they suffer to no benefit.</p>
                <p>40 In all directions they soared and returned, although they were not removed
                    from their bodies.</p>
                <p>Because they were not engaged in the watching of God, Satan seized power over
                    their visions.</p>
                <p>Because they did not gather at the door of their Lord, they were dispersed
                    through their visions to their souls’ harm.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59"
                        n="59"><p rend="footnote text"> This section likely serves as a warning to
                            those of Ephrem’s community who have skipped the vigil for sleep (or
                            were tempted to do so).</p></note></p>
                <p>The benefits of watchers were multiplied unto them, while the dreams of sleepers
                    were multiplied unto them.</p>
                <p>The toil of watchers is preserved, while the accumulation of dreams turns to
                    nothing.</p>
                <p>45 May there be a memorial for me among you, O watchers,</p>
                <p>Who lifted up the heaviness, because others did not keep watch.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> The very communal idea
                            expressed here and alluded to also in verse 1 of this <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urd</hi> is that those keeping watch lift the heaviness for
                            those who did not keep vigil. On the idea of the vigil of some making up
                            for the neglect or sin of others, see also <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>
                            16.38.</p></note></p>
                <p>Behold I exhort the multitude, that they may become awake.</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 12 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 3]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Third Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">May the watchers, who became worthy to become a
                    companion of the holy seraphim, thank You.</p>
                <p>1 Do not grant authority to sleep to reign over your body<pb n="283"/> parts;</p>
                <p>Hear the calamities, which it worked on earth; shudder with fear, and flee from
                        it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> In the
                            following <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>, Ephrem brings forth a number of
                            examples from figures in the Hebrew Bible, who had bad things happen to
                            them in their sleep. As is often the case with Ephrem, his
                            interpretation and presentation of some of these passages is often
                            unique and atypical when compared with late antique Greek and Latin
                            exegetes and commentators of Scripture. See, for example, his
                            presentation of Adam in lines 3-4 and Lot and his daugthers in lines
                            7-8.</p></note></p>
                <p>Adam was plundered in sleep, by the rib that was taken from him.</p>
                <p>In wakefulness, he was one; when he slept, he was divided, and turned into
                        two.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text"> Gen
                            2:21-22. </p></note></p>
                <p>5 Noah was greatly ridiculed through his sleep, by the one who was born from
                    him;</p>
                <p>In wakefulness he was sober and temperate; in his sleep, he became naked and was
                    exposed to shame.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Gen 9:20-27.</p></note></p>
                <p>Lot also, through his sleep, was plundered and did not sense it.</p>
                <p>The wakeful ones became wealthy from his treasure, and from his seed they turned
                    into nations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Gen 19:30-38.</p></note></p>
                <p>For if sleep worked this against the just, and they did not sense it while it was
                    robbing them,</p>
                <p>10 How much more ought we sinners to fear sleep so that it not reign over us!</p>
                <p>The firstborn of Egypt died in sleep, and that misfortunate one [sc. Pharaoh] did
                    not sense it;</p>
                <p>But after he awoke and got up, then he felt his blow.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod 12:29-30.</p></note><pb
                        n="284"/></p>
                <p>Sisera, who through his gigantic strength slaughtered the nation of the
                    Hebrews,</p>
                <p>Became as great in his wakefulness, as he was weakened through sleep.</p>
                <p>15 For Jael rose up against him and drove a stake through his jaws;</p>
                <p>Sleep made him into a disgrace, for by the hand of a woman it killed him.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text"> Judg
                            4:12-22.</p></note></p>
                <p>Samson,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> The
                            story of Samson is told in Judg 13-16.</p></note> who had taken an
                        oath,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text"> Judg
                            13:2-7 and Judg 16:17.</p></note> who from the womb had been clothed
                    with gigantic strength,</p>
                <p>Who had burned Philistia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 15:4-5.</p></note> — through a woman, the
                    Philistines blinded his eyes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 16:18-22.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>He who killed that lion<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 14:5-6.</p></note> and with foxes burned
                        Philistia,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Judg 15:4-5.</p></note></p>
                <p>20 Sleep duped and robbed him, and in the daytime tied him to a millstone.</p>
                <p>At night, Midian was pillaged by the wakeful ones, who were with Gideon.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text"> This episode is
                            narrated in Judg 7.</p></note></p>
                <p>At the sound of the trumpets, Midian was roused and woke up, arose and struck
                    itself with the sword.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 7:19-23.</p></note></p>
                <p>The hands of the wakeful ones were not smeared in the blood of the drowsy
                    sleepers.</p>
                <p>By the lanterns and shouts of the wakeful one, it was polluted in its own
                    blood.</p>
                <p>25 Gideon was vigilant in prayer,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 7:15.</p></note> and dreams were making
                    Midian flow.<pb n="285"/></p>
                <p>They prophesied victory to it, but defeat came to it.</p>
                <p>Saul was plundered in sleep, for he lost the hem of his robe.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam 24:1-8.</p></note></p>
                <p>Through the hem which [David] cut, he took the royal rule from him. </p>
                <p>And because he [sc. Saul] did not shudder in fear from it [sc. sleep], he
                    continued and slept again.</p>
                <p>30 He remained deprived of his weapon, because his spear was taken from him.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam
                            26:1-12.</p></note></p>
                <p>Life after that sleep, David granted to him as a gift;</p>
                <p>For after that sleep which was in the cave, he slept an eternal sleep. </p>
                <p>And because the Rabshakeh blasphemed and slept, an angel smashed his army,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text"> The narrative
                            involving the Rabshakeh of Assyria is told in 2 Kgs
                    18-19.</p></note></p>
                <p>And the seed that he sowed in the day, he reaped in the night. </p>
                <p>35 Behold the Rabshakeh was sleeping on his couch, while Hezekiah was awake in
                        prayer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Judg 19:14-34.</p></note></p>
                <p>The sleepless one descended at the prayers of the wakeful one, and slaughtered
                    the camps of the sleepers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Judg 19:35.</p></note></p>
                <p>Sion was full of prayers, and the camp of Assyria with dead people.</p>
                <p>The watchers made the sleepers who blasphemed slumber in an eternal sleep.</p>
                <p>In the night, Babylon was pillaged by the Medes, who were vigilant.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan
                        5:30-31.</p></note><pb n="286"/></p>
                <p>40 Sleep handed over the marvelous one [sc. Babylon] to death along with the
                    whole country.</p>
                <p>For he who sleeps along with the wakeful one — they are one, and they are not
                    one.</p>
                <p>The rest of sleep does not endure, but the recompense of prayers is stored
                    up.</p>
                <p>This labor which is in our body parts, multiplies for us benefit in the
                    heights.</p>
                <p>Our labor passes away, but our reward endures forever.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text"> The last few verses of this
                                <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> reiterate the latter half of <hi
                                rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 11.</p></note></p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 13 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 4]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Fourth Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Blessed is He who made worthy the sons of Adam to sing
                    psalms with the angels.</p>
                <p>1 Blessed are the watchers, who in all nights are arrayed against sleep. </p>
                <p>Daniel was awake in the den, and the wild beasts were keeping watch with
                        him;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan
                            6:19-23.</p></note></p>
                <p>The night was too short to give thanks for his salvation that came about for
                    him.</p>
                <p>Darius also drove away sleep; he estranged himself also from delicacies.</p>
                <p>5 He did not give rest to his body because of his love for Daniel.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan
                        6:18.</p></note></p>
                <p>Throughout that time in which Daniel fasted from the delicacies of the
                    kingdom,</p>
                <p>He was sober in all his hours for he was awake in all his hours.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan
                        1:8-17.</p></note></p>
                <p>He drove away sleep from his pupils, in order to call on<pb n="287"/> his God,</p>
                <p>In order that by sign and manifestation, insults might be blocked from his
                    people.</p>
                <p>10 Through vigil he persuaded God to show him the dream of the king.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text"> The reference is
                            to Daniel receiving the interpretation of King Nebuchadnezzar as
                            narrated in Dan 2. Dan 2:19 specifically mentions that the
                            interpretation to the dream was given to Daniel in a vision at night.
                        </p></note></p>
                <p>And through his and his companions’ vigil, [God] revealed to him [sc. Daniel] the
                    dream and His [sc. God’s] interpretation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87"
                        n="87"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan 2:17-19.</p></note></p>
                <p>The Chaldaeans and sorcerers entered and were confounded, because they did not
                    comprehend it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Dan 2:1-11.</p></note></p>
                <p>The watcher entered and told the dream, and along with the dream its
                    interpretation.</p>
                <p>Because that which the king saw as he was sleeping in the house of his
                    kingdom,</p>
                <p>15 The prayers of the watchers made vividly clear before the king and his
                    companions. </p>
                <p>The Chaldeans were saved by the vigil that the youths kept,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="footnote text"> Dan 2:24.</p></note></p>
                <p>Because vigil shone upon it and revealed the dream that was concealed from the
                    sorcerers. </p>
                <p>Through wakefulness and soberness, you are similar to the sleepless ones on
                    high,</p>
                <p>And to the prophets through your halleluias, and to the Seraphim through your
                        holinesses,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Perhaps a reference to an early form of the Trisagion. For the
                            association with Seraphim, cf Isa 6:2-3.</p></note></p>
                <p>20 To the assembly that blessed in Ephrath<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91"
                        n="91"><p rend="footnote text"> i.e. Bethlehem; see Gen 35:19, for the
                            association of these two places.</p></note> at night at<pb n="288"/> the
                    dawning of our Savior.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Luke 2:13-14.</p></note></p>
                <p>Behold, may your hosts resemble<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Corrected <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >նմանեցին</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                            >նմանեսցին</foreign>.</p></note> them through the blessing<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text"> Corrected
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">աւրհնութեան</foreign> to <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">աւրհնութեամբ</foreign>.</p></note> that your mouths
                    are thundering. </p>
                <p>The Magi who had sensed concerning the only-begotten Son because they had
                    banished the sleep of their eyes,</p>
                <p>Were hastening throughout all the nights, with the illuminating star guiding
                        them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="footnote text"> Matt
                            2:1-10.</p></note></p>
                <p>The apostles kept watch the whole night to catch fish, but did not find any.</p>
                <p>25 In the morning their minds rejoiced at the great catch they had found.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text"> John
                            21:3-11.</p></note></p>
                <p>Our Lord passed the night in prayer once it became evening, in order to be an
                    example to watchers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See, for example, Matt 14:23. Here and to the end
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>, Christ is presented as the watcher
                                <hi rend="italic">par excellence</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p>Blessed are you, who studied with that teacher, the firstborn son who taught
                    you.</p>
                <p>He is Lord of both — wakefulness and sleepiness — if he came into both, since
                    both are for us.</p>
                <p>As he slept for us, so also he kept watch for us.</p>
                <p>30 Through sleep he alluded to his body, and through watching he banished our
                    bouts of sleepiness. </p>
                <p>Because he came into the world, which is subject to wakefulness and to
                    sleepiness,</p>
                <p>He subjected himself to both, since he was close to both.</p>
                <p>Because if watchfulness were not good, then the Son would not have become an
                    example of it;<pb n="289"/></p>
                <p>Without keeping watch, no one is able to alienate oneself from all evils.</p>
                <p>35 Let us become disciples of Him rightly, so that his life may become perfected
                    in us.</p>
                <p>Let us not become disciples half-heartedly, lest we become sleepers and not
                    watchers.</p>
                <p>The Son, who was not in need of keeping watch, became a watcher for our sake.</p>
                <p>He fashioned it as a weapon and gave it to us, so that our discipleship would
                    bear fruit in virtue. </p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 14 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 5]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Fifth Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Blessing to the Son, who makes glad the watchers by
                    His dawning.</p>
                <p>1 King David, who thought to build a temple for God,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text"> This <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urd</hi> along with the following one treat the Biblical episode
                            of David intending to build a house (temple) for God, and being told by
                            God through the prophet Nathan that he will not be able to. In this and
                            the following <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>, Ephrem’s driving motivation
                            is to explain why David was not allowed by God to build the temple. The
                            relevant biblical passages are 2 Sam 6-7 and especially Ps 131(132),
                            upon which Ephrem is more dependent than the narrative in 2 Sam,
                            although as usual he elaborates upon the biblical narrative. It is also
                            possible that he is drawing upon extra-canonical texts or oral
                            traditions in his interpretation.</p></note></p>
                <p>Made a voluntary covenant to not give sleep to his eyes.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text"> Ps 131(132):
                    2-5.</p></note></p>
                <p>He distanced himself from his own house, because he saw that far away </p>
                <p>That ark, which was full of the mystery of Christ,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text"> Heb 9.</p></note> had been
                        neglected.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > 2 Sam 6:2.</p></note></p>
                <p>5 The king estranged himself from his own house and<pb n="290"/> from the mattress
                    of his bed;</p>
                <p>He pitched for himself a tent instead of a house, and spread out sackcloth on the
                    ground. </p>
                <p>And so that his body would not become heavy, he gave it food in moderation.</p>
                <p>He deprived himself of everything, so that he would be capable of fulfilling his
                    covenant.</p>
                <p>From his house and his bed David was able to estrange himself, </p>
                <p>10 While from his sleep, how was he able to estrange himself?</p>
                <p>He wanted to know the place, and he had set his desire on building the temple. </p>
                <p>And he made a covenant for this reason, and he actualized it through his oath. </p>
                <p>He swore to the Lord and made a covenant with him to not give sleep to his eyes, </p>
                <p>Nor slumber to his eyelids until he find the place of the Lord.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p rend="footnote text"> Ps 131(132):
                        2-5.</p></note></p>
                <p>15 He descended into great humility until he saw that place;</p>
                <p>And in the hour that he learned of the place, the covenant of his mouth was
                    fulfilled.</p>
                <p>He did not want to offer anything other than things from that place,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p rend="footnote text"> The episode
                            recounted in this stanza perhaps refers to 2 Sam 24:15-25.
                            Alternatively, it could be a reference to 2 Sam 6:17.</p></note></p>
                <p>So he offered what was found from the same and from the same place.</p>
                <p>The king’s oxen were found in the same place, and it was not lacking wood.</p>
                <p>20 With the wood and oxen that were of that place, he sacrificed to the Lord of
                    that place.<pb n="291"/></p>
                <p>And because it was a prodigious oath, the Lord worked in him greater things. </p>
                <p>Because through the fire from above, his sacrifice became acceptable.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="footnote text"> This could be
                            a reference to Solomon’s sacrifice at the dedication of the temple in 1
                            Kgs 8 and 2 Chr 7:1.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>God showed him the place that he sought, and he blocked death from his nation. </p>
                <p>And why did [God] not allow him to build the house?</p>
                <p>25 The great things that are not worked, the Lord his benefactor worked for
                        him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Perhaps a reference to 2 Sam 7:8-13.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>And God prohibited him who was smaller than all,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam 16:11.</p></note>
                    because of his transgressions. </p>
                <p>And what actually was his transgression, which prohibited him from building the
                    house?</p>
                <p>“You shed much blood, and it is not fitting,” says Scripture, “that you should
                    build it.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text"> 1
                            Chr 22:8; 1 Chr 28:3; see also 1 Kgs 5:3.</p></note></p>
                <p>The first blood was Goliath’s,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam 17.</p></note> and after him the
                        Amalekites’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam 30.</p></note></p>
                <p>30 And yet not without God did he slaughter the former and the latter. </p>
                <p>He would ask Him [sc. God], and then he would go up against the nation against
                    whom he would rampage.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam 23:2-4; 1 Sam 30:8; 2 Sam 2:1; 2 Sam
                            5:19-23.</p></note></p>
                <p>His slaughter is less than that one who slaughtered the thirty-two kings.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p rend="footnote text"> See Josh
                            12:7-24, although the biblical passage mentions thirty-one.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>He did not shed blood among his people, except for the blood of Uriah,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p rend="footnote text"> 2 Sam
                        11.</p></note><pb n="292"/>
                </p>
                <p>And Uriah himself was Hittite and not Hebrew.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113"
                        n="113"><p rend="footnote text"> 2 Sam 11:3.</p></note></p>
                <p>35 He did not make a demand on Nabal due to his insult because Abigail beseeched
                        him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p rend="footnote text"> 1
                            Sam 25.</p></note></p>
                <p>And he had pity on Saul for the sake of God and Jonathan,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text"> See the episodes recounted
                            in 1 Sam 24-26.</p></note></p>
                <p>He who spared his killer from the murder of the men who were with him,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam
                            24:1-7.</p></note></p>
                <p>How was he unjust with regard to killing vainly the sons of his own nation?</p>
                <p>Could it be that perhaps this same transgression stayed and remained until
                    Nathan?</p>
                <p>40 And that Nathan nullified his covenant in this way, when he said to him, “you
                    will not build it.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 2 Sam 7.</p></note></p>
                <p>But so that heaviness should not be compounded upon David’s body when he grew
                    old,</p>
                <p>He postponed his punishment after him, so that the old man would be in peace.</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 15 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 6]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Sixth Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Why was David prevented from building the house? And
                    whether it was because he shed much blood that [God] prohibited him.</p>
                <p>1 If it was because David slaughtered the nations that it was not lawful [for
                    him] to build the house,</p>
                <p>Then everyone who slaughters like him, is under blame like him.</p>
                <p>If that is so, then Abraham is blameworthy, who slaughtered the five kings,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p rend="footnote text"> Gen
                            14:8-16.</p></note><pb n="293"/></p>
                <p>And Moses who slaughtered Midian<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Perhaps a reference to Num 25:16-18.</p></note>
                    and Joshua who slaughtered Canaan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See throughout the book of Joshua.</p></note></p>
                <p>5 Asa is blameworthy who slaughtered the Indians,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p rend="footnote text"> In the biblical account,
                            Asa slaughtered the Ethiopians. See 2 Chr 14:9-13.</p></note> and
                    Hesechiah who slaughtered Assyria,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 2 Kgs 19.</p></note></p>
                <p>And the Maccabees who slaughtered Ionia,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123"
                        n="123"><p rend="footnote text"> i.e. the Seleucids; this is recounted in
                            1-2 Mac.</p></note> and Zerubbabel who slaughtered Macedonia.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p rend="footnote text"> The biblical
                            account regarding Zerubbabel, who appears in Hag 1-2, does not mention
                            him slaughtering Macedonia.</p></note></p>
                <p>Yet if they are not blamed for the blood of those peoples which they shed,</p>
                <p>Why is only David blamed because of this?</p>
                <p>If the others were blameworthy, [God] would not let Moses fail to mention it.</p>
                <p>10 Moses — he is great in reproaches, for he carries the reproaches of the
                        rock.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Presumably a reference to Num 20:8-12. </p></note></p>
                <p>Moses slaughtered one of his people, and was not blamed.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod
                    32:25-29.</p></note></p>
                <p>Neither was Elijah, who with his own hand slaughtered the prophets of Baal.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Kgs
                            18:40.</p></note></p>
                <p>Although Moses slaughtered the Hebrews, his face was radiant with glory.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod
                            34:29-35.</p></note></p>
                <p>And Elijah who slaughtered the pagan priests, was taken up in a chariot to
                        heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129"><p rend="footnote text"> 2
                            Kgs 2:9-12.</p></note><pb n="294"/>
                </p>
                <p>15 To Jehu who slaughtered the prophets of Baal,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p rend="footnote text"> For Jehu, see 2 Kgs 9-10.
                            The slaughtering in question here is mentioned in 2 Kgs 10:11 and 2 Kgs
                            10:18-27.</p></note> [God] gave the equipment of the cult,</p>
                <p>When [God] ordained that for four generations the crown be for his
                        offspring.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > 2 Kgs 10:30.</p></note></p>
                <p>Yet David, who is equal with his companions, why did [God] discriminate him from
                    his companions?</p>
                <p>And if he did not discriminate him, then why did he deprive him of building the
                    temple?</p>
                <p>His companions received the good news, and for him [sc. David] a heap of
                    murders.</p>
                <p>20 Moses made the tent of meeting,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Exod 33:7-11.</p></note> but [God] prohibited him
                    [sc. David] from building the house.</p>
                <p>[God] did not deprive him on account of the nations, who were numbered among the
                    holy ones,</p>
                <p>But rather, [God] spared him from the hardship of the oath, by hastening to
                    dissolve the oath.</p>
                <p>If [David] had not hastened to swear, he would have built the temple.</p>
                <p>The oath, which he swore on account of the temple — <hi rend="italic">it</hi>
                    deprived him of building it.</p>
                <p>25 For he swore greater than his ability: that he would not enter into his
                    house,</p>
                <p>And that he would not go up to his bed, and that he would not give sleep to his
                        eyes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133"><p rend="footnote text"> Ps
                            131(132): 2-5.</p></note></p>
                <p>Now so that he would not be in weariness until he had completed the structure</p>
                <p>Before he even began the structure, [God] brought to fulfillment his oath by the
                    prohibition.</p>
                <p>[God] wanted to grant good things to him for the sake<pb n="295"/> of his
                    trustworthiness,</p>
                <p>30 So [God] prohibited him under the guise of blame, since he [sc. David] is far
                    from slander.</p>
                <p>Because if on account of blame [God] would have prohibited him from building
                    it,</p>
                <p>Then Uriah would have been before Him [sc. God] to remind Him at that time.</p>
                <p>But Uriah was nowhere to be found in order for [God] to remember, because David
                    had been pardoned through Nathan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> 2 Sam 12:13.</p></note></p>
                <p>The blame of the righteous ones hastened to Him [sc. God], who surrounded Him
                    [sc. God] and were not blamed. </p>
                <p>35 Or was he who had received along with the temple the Spirit of holiness,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135"><p rend="footnote text"> 1 Sam
                            16:13</p></note></p>
                <p>And had been glorified and become worthy of the Spirit, was he unworthy to build
                    the temple?</p>
                <p>And if it was said to him in earnest, then why did [God] demand of him [sc.
                    David]</p>
                <p>That which was not demanded from a single one of the righteous?</p>
                <p>And if all the righteous who had slaughtered — whether from the people or from
                    the nations — were not blamed,</p>
                <p>40 How could [God] have blamed David? On the contrary, he is blessed and without
                    blame like his companions.</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 16 [<hi rend="italic"
                        >Gišeroy kc‘urd</hi> 7]</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">Hymn of the Seventh Night</p>
                <p style="text-align:center;">[Title and beginning lost]<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn136" n="136"><p rend="footnote text"> The title and first few
                            lines of this <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> are lost.</p></note><pb
                        n="296"/></p>
                <p>1 …as the number of his years is prolonged.</p>
                <p>Keeping watch, which is heavy for everyone, is very light for them.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137"><p rend="footnote text"> This <hi
                                rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> involves an extended comparison between
                            the vigil of groomsmen or wedding guests of an earthly groom who stay up
                            late to celebrate the wedding, with the vigil of the groomsmen of the
                            heavenly groom (Christ), i.e. those keeping vigil for whom Ephrem writes
                            this <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p>You are groomsmen, who were invited to the wedding of the groom who does not
                    die.</p>
                <p>Let us drive away sleep from our pupils through the blessing of our lips.</p>
                <p>5 For if they become joyful there, by the joy that compunction gives to souls</p>
                <p>How much more should they become joyful here, by the joy that gathers its seed a
                        hundredfold!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> There is a reference here to the Parable of the
                            Sower, found in Matt 13:1-9, Mark 4:1-9, and Luke 8:4-8.</p></note></p>
                <p>And if there — soundings of trumpets, here — harps of psalms;</p>
                <p>There — accursed shoutings to the Evil One, while here — blessings to God.</p>
                <p>There they repeat the hateful passions, which desire works among humankind,</p>
                <p>10 While here they repeat the blessed passions, which the Lord and his servants
                    bore.</p>
                <p>For if through the trumpet and harp they remove sleep from the eyes of
                    humans,</p>
                <p>And if the clashing of cymbals dispels that which rebels against all [sc.
                    sleep];</p>
                <p>Then here, because the Spirit of holiness resounds in the mouth of David his
                    harp,</p>
                <p>How much more will wakefulness reign among us, so that through the power of his
                    words we may become wise!<pb n="297"/></p>
                <p>15 If sleep, driven out by revelries, is defeated, and licentiousness was able to
                    conquer it,</p>
                <p>Then how much more will modesty conquer it!</p>
                <p>The earthly<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Literally “lower” (<foreign xml:lang="hy">ներքին</foreign>).</p></note>
                    groom becomes happy in watching<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> i.e. staying up late at the wedding party. Here
                            and throughout this <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi>, the same word is used
                            by the translator to refer to the staying up late of the groomsmen of
                            the earthly groom at the wedding party. It is the same word he uses for
                            the keeping watch of the groomsmen of the heavenly groom: <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">հսկումն</foreign>. </p></note> instead of
                    mourning;</p>
                <p>The celestial<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Literally “upper” (<foreign xml:lang="hy">վերին</foreign>).</p></note>
                    groom becomes happy through the pure watching of holy mourners.</p>
                <p>He who is defeated by the heavines of this sleep of limbs</p>
                <p>20 Is reproached by the temporal groomsman who drove away sleep from his eyes. </p>
                <p>There wakefulness is without recompense, and watching is without a promise,</p>
                <p>But glory is prepared for our watching, and a paradise of delight is
                    promised.</p>
                <p>If in that watching there is festivity, behold, modesty in this watching. </p>
                <p>And since that one is full of all harm, it is also thickened through slipping. </p>
                <p>25 That watching passes, O brothers, yet all its stains are retained,</p>
                <p>While although this watching ceases, the treasure of its life remains. </p>
                <p>In the great dawning of the Son of God, the eternal groom,</p>
                <p>They will expose the hidden sins, which were accumulated in the watching of the
                    temporal groom.</p>
                <p>Because there everyone is prepared to scandalize the one who listens to him,<pb
                        n="298"/></p>
                <p>30 While here everyone is prepared to help the one who listens to him.</p>
                <p>There everyone shows his face to his friend to harm him,</p>
                <p>While here, behold through a veil, brothers have warned each other.</p>
                <p>They summon desire upon themselves through the sound which enters their ears,</p>
                <p>While here they hear the voice of the Spirit, who cleanses their minds.</p>
                <p>35 There everyone is hardened to sin against his companion,</p>
                <p>While here everyone strives to earn himself and his friend.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn142" n="142"><p rend="footnote text"> i.e. earn their
                            salvation</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>There they go in revelry and laughter, while here they come in weeping and
                    mourning. </p>
                <p>The debts that they accumulated there, they expiate by this<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn143" n="143"><p rend="footnote text"> Corrected <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">այնու</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >այսու</foreign>. </p></note> watching.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn144" n="144"><p rend="footnote text"> Here, as well as in <hi
                                rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 11.46 is the idea that those keeping vigil
                            are also bringing benefit to those who are not. </p></note></p>
                <p>If the watching that is full of such dangers is lovable and light,</p>
                <p>40 Then how much more should our watching of manifold benefit be enjoyed by the
                    sleepless ones!</p>
                <p>Let us take for ourselves a good example from that licentious watching.</p>
                <p>Let us resemble each other through wakefulness, but estrange ourselves from their
                    thoughts.</p>
                <p>And since their thoughts are similar to the exclamations that fall in their
                    ears,</p>
                <p>Our thoughts should be similar to the exclamations of the Spirit that we have
                    heard. </p>
                <p>45 The revelry ceased, but its harm remains; the watching passed, yet its
                    lawlessness remains.<pb n="299"/></p>
                <p>Sayers and hearers died, but the judgement is kept for the awful tribunal. </p>
                <p>We are one here and there, yet we are not equal; here, weary and dejected in
                    mind;</p>
                <p>For whatever is without benefit is light for the ones who do it,</p>
                <p>While everything that comes about by hope, one performs with toil.</p>
                <p>50 As the Evil One urges and hastens people to the watching that harms the
                    watchers,</p>
                <p>So also here he has his effect<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Following the suggestion of Mariès, who corrected
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">անդաստէ</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >անդ ազդէ</foreign> ; cf Mariès et Mercier, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hymnes</hi>, 254-255, n. 222.</p></note> upon those who keep watch
                    for the sake of benefit.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Commentary</head>
                <p>The commentary will be limited to three major foci. First, I will provide
                    evidence for a Syriac original to the Armenian text. Second, I will provide
                    evidence for an early date of translation. Third, I will show how the teaching
                    and practice of vigil in the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> aligns with what we
                    know about Ephrem’s views on vigil from the authentic Syriac works of Ephrem. </p>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.3.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Evidence for a Syriac Original</head>
                    <p>Prose far outweighs poetry in quantity in early Armenian literature, and
                        early Armenian prose is indebted to ideals of Greek rhetoric for its
                        compositional standards. Fifth-century Armenian prose is marked by balance
                        and repetition in phraseology, lexical surplusage, complex syntactical
                        constru-ctions, a prevalent use of compound verbal adjectives, and the use
                        of rhetorical tropes and figures derived from Greek models. The <hi
                            rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> of Ephrem on the other hand are marked by
                        simple syntactical constructions, lexical paucity, and an overall plain
                        style of composition that owes little to Greek<pb n="300"/> rhetorical
                        models. Although they were originally composed in Syriac verse, the Armenian
                        translator has made no consistent effort to render them into Armenian verse,
                        apart from marking where the original Syriac lines ended. In the fifth
                        century, Armenian poetic forms were still primarily oral and employed
                        varying syllabic counts, and therefore were unlike the fixed syllabic counts
                        of Ephrem’s verse forms.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146"><p> Mary
                                Boyce, “The Parthian ‘Gōsān’ and Iranian Minstrel Tradition,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great
                                    Britain and Ireland</hi>, No. 1/2 (April 1957): 10-45 at 44 note
                                5.</p></note> Concrete examples of linguistic evidence for a Syriac
                        original are given below, first looking at phonology and then syntax and
                        morphology.</p>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.3.2" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Phonology</head>
                        <p>The immediate place to look for evidence of a Syriac original in the
                            realm of phonology is with the rendering of names in the texts. The vast
                            number of names appearing in the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> forbids
                            bringing forth every example, but the examples drawn from the chart
                            below are representative of the way that the translator often preserves
                            a Syriac rendering of a name over and against a Greek one. The Armenian
                            biblical text contains portions translated from both Greek and Syriac,
                            and therefore names from biblical figures are rendered in the Armenian
                            Bible as well as Armenian literature in different forms depending on
                            whether they come from a Syriac or Greek original.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p rend="footnote text"> On the Armenian
                                    Bible, see S. Peter Cowe, “The Bible in Armenian” in <hi
                                        rend="italic">The New Cambridge History of the Bible, Volume
                                        2: From 600 to 1450</hi>, eds. Richard Marsden and E. Ann
                                    Matter (Cambridge, 2012): 143-161; Idem, “The Two Armenian
                                    Versions of Chronicles: their Origin and Translation Technique,”
                                        <hi rend="italic">Revue des études arméniennes</hi> 22
                                    (1990–1): 53–96.</p></note> Therefore, by looking at the names
                            in the Armenian text, we can gain an indication as to whether the text
                            issues from a Syriac or Greek original, based on how the translator
                            renders the names.</p>
                        <pb n="301"/>
                        <table rend="rules">
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Name in English</hi></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Place in Text</hi></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Arm form from
                                    Syriac</hi></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><p style="text-align:center;"
                                        ><hi rend="smallcaps">Form in </hi></p><p
                                        style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Syriac</hi></p></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><p style="text-align:center;"
                                        ><hi rend="smallcaps">Form in </hi></p><p
                                        style="text-align:center;"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                                        >Greek</hi></p></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Arm form from
                                    Greek</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center">Hoshea (a name of Joshua)</cell>
                                <cell rend="center">10.21 [X.28]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148"
                                        n="148"><p rend="footnote text"> The line numbers in
                                            brackets refer to the numbering of the Armenian text in
                                            Mariès et Mercier, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Hymnes</hi>.</p></note></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Հոշայէ</foreign> (gen.)</cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܘܫܥ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Αυση</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Աւսեայ</foreign> (gen.)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center">Philistines</cell>
                                <cell rend="center">12.18 [XII.31]</cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Փղշտացիք</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܠܫ̈ܬܝܐ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁι ἀλλόφυλοι</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Այլազգիք</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149"
                                        n="149"><p rend="footnote text"> Although the Armenian bible
                                            does know the form <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                                >Փղշտացիք</foreign>, it employs <foreign
                                                xml:lang="hy">Այլազգիք</foreign> in the vast
                                            majority of cases, following the Greek (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁι
                                            ἀλλόφυλοι</foreign>).</p></note></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center">Saul</cell>
                                <cell rend="center">12.27 [XII.47]</cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Շաւուղ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܐܘܠ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Σαουλ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Սաւուղ</foreign></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center">Joshua</cell>
                                <cell rend="center">15.4 [XV.7]</cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Յեշով</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܫܘܥ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἰησοῦς</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Յեսու</foreign></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="center">Jehu</cell>
                                <cell rend="center">15.15 [XV.23]</cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Յահով</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܗܘ</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">Ιου</foreign></cell>
                                <cell rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Յէու</foreign></cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p><lb/>The Armenian versions of the names in the above chart all follow
                            Syriac forms over and against the form in Greek, which provides strong
                            evidence for the presence of a Syriac original. Although in a number of
                            cases, the Armenian version of a name in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> follows a Greek form over and against a Syriac one,
                            this can be explained by the fact that the former became predominant
                            over time, and a translator or later copier would be more likely to
                            prefer a Greek form to its Syriac variant, especially in the case of a
                            common or renowned biblical figure. Conversely, the names of less common
                            or renowned figures would have been more likely to retain their original
                            form from the Syriac.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> None of the personages in the above chart
                                    are especially renowned in the Armenian Christian tradition. For
                                    more examples of names used in the texts, see: Akinian, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>, xxii-xxiii.</p></note></p>
                        <pb n="302"/>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head xml:id="hv21n2arlen.3.3" xml:lang="en">Syntax and Morphology</head>
                        <p>The syntax of the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> exhibits throughout
                            constructions that are unusual or awkward in Armenian grammar, because
                            they are closely following an original Syriac. A number of
                            representative examples will be brought forth below. </p>
                        <p> 10.3 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Բայց</foreign>
                            <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">ի ժամէն</foreign>, զի</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">եղեւ նա աստուած[ատես]</foreign> (But <hi
                                rend="underline">from the hour that</hi> he became a [seer of] god).
                            In normal Armenian syntax, <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի ժամէն</foreign>
                            <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">զի</foreign></hi> would be
                            rendered as <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի ժամէն</foreign>
                            <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">յորում</foreign></hi>, with
                            the use of the relative pronoun in the locative. However, here it seems
                            that the translator preferred to use the particle <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >զի</foreign> as it more closely matches with the Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕ</foreign>, which is
                            evidently the underlying form here.</p>
                        <p> 10.7 [X.9]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> The line numbers in brackets refer to the
                                    numbering of the Armenian text in Mariès et Mercier, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Hymnes</hi>.</p></note>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">Դարձեալ կայր քունն Մովսիսի</foreign>
                            <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">ի ներքս քան
                                զնա</foreign></hi> (Although sleep was hovering near to Moses <hi
                                rend="underline">within it</hi> [sc. the veil]). <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">Ի ներքս քան</foreign> + <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >զ</foreign> + acc. is very awkward and unusual in Armenian. A more
                            common Armenian rendering would be <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >ներքոյ</foreign> + gen. or <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի
                                ներքոյ</foreign> + abl. It seems to be rendering an underlying
                            Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܓܘ
                            ܡܢ</foreign><hi style="font-size:14pt">. </hi>Armenian
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի</foreign> correlates with <foreign
                                xml:lang="syr">ܠ</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="hy">ներքս</foreign>
                            correlates with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘ</foreign>; and <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">քան</foreign> correlates with <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                                >ܡܢ</foreign>.</p>
                        <p> 10.43 [X.59] <foreign xml:lang="hy">Նովին կշռով կերակրոյ իւրոյ կշռեաց
                                զքուն աչաց իւրոց</foreign> (By the same measure [<hi
                                rend="underline">with which he measured</hi>] his food, he measured
                            the sleep of his eyes). Ellipsis is a prevelant feature of Syriac prose,
                            when words or phrases may be supplied from corresponding clauses, as
                                here.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> See Theodor Nöldeke, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Compendious Syriac Grammar</hi>, tr. James A. Chrichton
                                    (London, 1904): §332, 374, 382.</p></note> The same construction
                            is not a regular feature of Armenian syntax.</p>
                        <p> 11.29 [XI.45-46] <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">Ժիրք
                                    որ</foreign></hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">վաստակին ի միջի մերում</foreign>
                            <hi style="font-size:11pt">, </hi><hi
                                rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">նոքաւք</foreign></hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">կշտամբի վատութիւն մեր</foreign> (<hi
                                rend="underline">The strong ones who</hi> toil among us, <hi
                                rend="underline">by them</hi> our laziness is reproached). The
                            syntax of this phrase is unmistakeably Syriac, with its expansion,
                            periphrasis, and use of antecedent and pronominal reference,<pb n="303"/>
                            the underlying portion being represented by something like: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܝܠܬܢ̈ܐ
                                ܕ...ܒܗܢܘܢ</foreign> where a fronted focused subject noun is introduced,
                            then expanded into a relative by means of the pronoun <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕ</foreign>, and
                            then itself is the antecedent of a pronoun in the following phrase.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153"><p rend="footnote text"> See
                                    Takamitsu Muraoka, <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac: A Basic
                                        Grammar with a Chrestomathy, 2</hi><hi
                                        rend="italic superscript"
                                    >nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> rev. ed., Porta Linguarum Orientalium: Neue Serie</hi>
                                    (Wiesbaden, 2005): §91; Aaron Butts, “The Classical Syriac
                                    Language,” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World</hi>, ed.
                                    Daniel King (Routledge, forthcoming in 2018); Gideon Goldenberg,
                                    “On Some Niceties of Syriac Syntax” in <hi rend="italic">Studies
                                        in Semitic Linguistics: Selected Writings</hi> (Jerusalem,
                                    1998): 579-590.</p></note> Nothing like this is found in native
                            Armenian writing.</p>
                        <p> 11.35 [XI.57-58] <foreign xml:lang="hy">Փառաւորի շունչ հսկեցողաց
                                զբաղմամբ իւրեանց <hi rend="underline">որ</hi> ընդ Աստուծոյ</foreign>
                            (The breath of watchers is glorified, through their occupation <hi
                                rend="underline">which is</hi> with God). There is nothing in the
                            Armenian syntax which requires the use of the relative pronoun <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">որ</foreign> here, and it would read much smoother
                            without it. However, it likely renders a Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                                >ܕ</foreign>, which in Syriac is preferable in the above
                            construction. </p>
                        <p> 11.31 [XI.51-52] <foreign xml:lang="hy">Զի՞նչ աւգուտ է զի ննջեցաքն
                                երէկ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="hy">զի</foreign>
                            <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">յաւելցուք
                                    ննջեսցուք</foreign></hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">այսօր</foreign>>։ (What benefit is it that we
                            slept yesterday, since <hi rend="underline">we will sleep again</hi>
                            today?). In Syriac, the verb <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܣܦ</foreign> ‘to
                            add, increase,’ when paired with another verb, takes on an adverbial
                            function meaning ‘more’ or ‘again.’ In this line, the translator calqued
                            the idiom into Armenian using the corresponding Armenian verb in this
                            line, and again at 12.29 [XII.51-52]: <foreign xml:lang="hy">եւ զի ոչ
                                քասքնեաց նա յայնմանէ, <hi rend="underline">եւ յաւել միւսանգամ
                                    ննջեաց</hi></foreign> (And because Saul did not shudder in fear
                            from it [sleep], <hi rend="underline">he continued and slept
                            again</hi>). </p>
                        <p> 12.28 [XII.49-50] <hi rend="underline"><foreign xml:lang="hy">ի ձեռն
                                    տտնոյն</foreign></hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">զոր եհատ, առ զթագաւորութիւնն ի նմանէ</foreign>
                                (<hi rend="underline">Through the hem</hi> which he cut, he took the
                            royal rule from him). <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ի ձեռն</foreign> + gen. to
                            render an instrumental represents another calque of a Syriac idiom
                                (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܕ</foreign>). This idiom is used very
                            frequently throughout the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>. While it is
                            not uncommon in native Armenian due to influence<pb n="304"/> most
                            especially from the Bible (the LXX and NT also employ this Semitic
                            construction), it is much more frequently found in Armenian translated
                            from Syriac.</p>
                        <p> The above examples of Armenian syntactical and morphological usage
                            closely following Syriac usage over and against standard Armenian
                            syntactical practice are meant to serve as representative (and by no
                            means exhaustive) examples, that provide strong evidence for a Syriac
                            original to the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.4" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Evidence for a Fifth-Century Date of Translation</head>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.4.1" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Linguistic</head>
                        <p>Certain syntactic features in the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> are
                            also indicative of early Armenian usage. Two representative examples are
                            presented below. </p>
                        <p> 12.32 [XII.57-58]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> The line numbers in brackets refer to the
                                    numbering of the Armenian text in Mariès et Mercier, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Hymnes</hi>.</p></note>
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">Զի յայնմ քնոյ որ <hi rend="underline">յայրի
                                    անդ</hi></foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="hy">քուն յաւիտենից ննջեաց
                                նա</foreign> (For after that sleep which was <hi rend="underline">in
                                the cave</hi>, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> slept an eternal sleep).
                            This line has two features characteristic of early Armenian prose. The
                            first is the use of the local adverb (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >անդ</foreign>) in the place of the deictic suffix (-<foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">ն</foreign>) to define the object of the preposition
                                <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի</foreign> (when used with a sense of
                                motion).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">
                                    <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի</foreign> + acc. + <foreign
                                        xml:lang="hy">անդր</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                        >ի</foreign> + loc. + <foreign xml:lang="hy">անդ</foreign>
                                    (as here); <foreign xml:lang="hy">ի</foreign> + abl. + <foreign
                                        xml:lang="hy">անտի</foreign>.</p></note> In later periods of
                            Armenian, the deictic suffix is more commonly used to define the object
                            in these kinds of grammatical constructions. The second feature here is
                            the otiose usage of the personal pronoun (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
                                >նա</foreign>), which in constructions like the above clause is
                            perceived by later Armenian writers to be redundant and tends to be
                            dropped, since there is no change of subject (and third person singular
                            is indicated already by the verb ending). In early Armenian prose
                            however, there is a greater tendency for an otiose use of personal
                            pronouns. Another example may be found in 12.41 [XII.75-76]: <foreign
                                xml:lang="hy">Զի այն որ ննջէն հանդերձ արթնովն մի են եւ<pb n="305"/>
                                չեն մի <hi rend="underline">նոքա</hi></foreign> (Because he who
                            sleeps along with the wakeful one, <hi rend="underline">they</hi> are
                            one, and <hi rend="underline">they</hi> are not one). </p>
                        <p> The most important linguistic feature of the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> suggesting an early date of translation lies in the
                            realm of morphology. Rather than specific data, it is the lack of data —
                            that is, the striking absence of any influence from the Hellenizing
                            school of translations, which began in the sixth century and affected
                            the morphology of all later Armenian authors and translators to a
                            greater or lesser extent.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> On characteristics features of the
                                    Hellenizing school, particularly in the realm of morphology, and
                                    their effect upon subsequent Armenian compositions, see Abraham
                                    Terian, “The Hellenizing School: Its Time, Place, and Scope of
                                    Activities Reconsidered” in <hi rend="italic">East of Byzantium:
                                        Syria and Armenia in the Formative Period (Dumbarton Oaks
                                        Symposium, 1980)</hi>, eds. Nina Garsoïan, Thomas F.
                                    Mathews, and Robert W. Thomson (Washington, D.C., 1982):
                                    175-186; Gohar Muradyan, <hi rend="italic">Grecisms in Ancient
                                        Armenian</hi>, Hebrew University Armenian Studies 13,
                                    (Leuven, 2012).</p></note> The absence of any influence from the
                            Hellenizing school of translations strongly suggests that the
                            translation of the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> was made before the
                            sixth century.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.4.2" xml:lang="en">
                        <head>Historical</head>
                        <p>Early Armenian Christianity bears witness to Syriac, and in particular
                            Edessene influence, in a variety of areas. These include of course
                            liturgical practices, such as a pre-baptismal anointing (prior to the
                            invention of Armenian letters, Syriac was the liturgical language of
                            certain spheres in the Armenian realm and so the maintenance of
                            specifically Syriac liturgical practices is by no means
                                surprising).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> One may consult the dozens of studies by
                                    Gabriele Winkler that treat Syriac influence on Armenian
                                    liturgical practice.</p></note> Influence is also seen in myths
                            of apostolic foundation, where there was for example a co-opting of the
                            Abgar legend, that turned Abgar into an Armenian king, and the apostolic
                            mission of Addai/Thaddaeus into the realm of Armenia. Syriac influence
                            is also prevelant in other realms of literature and language
                            (particularly in vocabulary in the ecclesiastical domain). Koriwn, the
                                disciple<pb n="306"/> and biographer of Maštoc‘, inventor of the
                            Armenian alphabet, narrates how his master went first to Edessa in his
                            quest to create an alphabet for Armenian, making use of a modified
                            Syriac alphabet for two years before developing the Armenian alphabet.
                            Armenian students were also sent to Edessa to study Syriac so as to be
                            able to translate from Syriac into Armenian. It is then by no means
                            surprising that in the fifth-century translation efforts, Maštoc‘ and
                            his students drew on the works of Ephrem, who besides being renowned in
                            Edessa, had gained fame across the multilingual Christian world,
                            including of course the Armenian realm with its strong Syriac influence. </p>
                        <p> The topics treated in these particular <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi>
                            also fit well with what we know of the interests and the particular
                            ascetic inclinations of Maštoc‘ and his students, which shared much in
                            common with early Syriac asceticism, as can be seen in the works of
                            Koriwn and the
                            <hi rend="italic">Buzandaran </hi>(P‘awstos
                            Biwzand), and thus it is easy to see why they would have been objects of
                                translation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Nina Garsoïan, “Introduction to the
                                    Problem of Early Armenian Monasticism,” <hi rend="italic">Revue
                                        des études arméniennes</hi> 30 (2005-7): 177-236.</p></note>
                            Finally, the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> show no signs of any
                            Christological or Theological language or concepts dating from a period
                            after the fourth century, nor any other historical references after the
                            time of Ephrem. After considering the historical situation, one is led
                            to conclude that it would be much more surprising if the Armenian
                            tradition did not transmit authentic works of Ephrem the Syrian than if
                            it did. </p>
                        <p> If these texts then are authentic, it seems more likely that they were
                            translated in an early period rather than in the medieval period, since
                            no Syriac originals survive, not even in fragmentary form. A counter
                            argument cannot be made from the fact that the earliest extant
                            manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> dates from the
                            thirteenth century, since so few Armenian manuscripts survive from
                            before the tenth century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dickran Kouymjian, “The Archaeology of the
                                    Armenian Manuscript: Codicology, Paleography, and Beyond,” in
                                        <hi rend="italic">Armenian Philology in the Modern Era: From
                                        Manuscript to Digital Text</hi>, ed. Valentina Calzolari
                                    (Leiden, 2014): 5–22.</p></note> The<pb n="307"/> earliest
                            Armenian manuscripts of many renowned early authors — both native
                            Armenian authors and translated authors of an early period — date from
                            the thirteenth century or later.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv21n2arlen.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Vigil in the authentic Syriac works of Ephrem and the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urdk‘</hi></head>
                    <p>In this section, a brief discussion will be advanced to suggest that the
                        teaching and practice of vigil as presented in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> align with the views on vigil that are presented in
                        Ephrem’s authentic Syriac corpus. </p>
                    <p> Ephrem speaks of vigil and watching not as actions undertaken only by human
                        beings, but as something proper to the divine and angelic realms as well. In
                        the divine realm, Christ is presented as the watcher <hi rend="italic">par
                            excellence</hi>, and even referred to as such by that appellation; for
                        example, one of the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Nisibis</hi> is a meditation
                        on Christ the watcher, who descended to Sheol after his crucifixion to
                        awaken the sleepers there.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160"><p
                                rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Nisibis</hi> LXVI. For the Syriac text of
                                the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Nisibis</hi> with German translation
                                and a study, see Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem
                                    des Syrers Carmina Nisibena</hi>, 4 vols. Corpus Scriptorum
                                Christianorum Orientalium 218–9, 240-241 (Louvain, 1961; 1963); a
                                French translation is available in P. Féghali and C. Navarre, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Saint Éphrem: Sur les chants de Nisibe</hi>,
                                Antioche chrétienne 3 (Paris, 1997), and Dominique Cerbelaud, <hi
                                    rend="italic">La descente aux enfers: Carmina Nisibena</hi>,
                                Spiritualité Orientale 89 (Godewaersvelde, 2009). Christ is also
                                referred to by the designation “watcher” at <hi rend="italic">Hymns
                                    on the Nativity</hi> I.61 and VI.23. For the Syriac text of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Nativity </hi>with
                                German translation and a study, see: Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen De Nativitate
                                    (Epiphania)</hi> 2 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum
                                Orientalium 186–7 (Louvain, 1959). A French translation and study
                                may be found in François Cassingena-Trévedy, o.s.b., tr., <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymnes sur la nativité</hi>, Sources Chrétiennes
                                459 (Paris, 2001). An English translation is available in Kathleen
                                McVey, <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns</hi> (New York,
                                1989). Quotations in English will be taken from McVey’s
                                translation.</p></note> In a dense passage from the <hi
                            rend="italic">Commentary on the Diatessaron</hi> referring to Christ’s
                        calming of the storm at sea, Ephrem writes: “He who was sleeping was
                        awakened, and put to sleep the sea, so that by the wakefulness of the sea
                        which had slept, he might<pb n="308"/> demonstrate the wakefulness of his
                        divinity, which never sleeps.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161"><p
                                rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the Diatessaron</hi>, VI.25. See
                                Christian Lange, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ in the
                                    Syriac Commentary on the Diatessaron</hi>, Corpus Scriptorum
                                Christianorum Orientalium 616, Subsidia 118 (Louvain, 2005),
                            83.</p></note> Ephrem likely drew inspiration from the biblical image of
                        God as the one who never sleeps, constantly keeping watch over his
                            creation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> See for example Ps 121.</p></note> Jesus
                        shares in this quality through his divinity which remained “awake” in him
                        even during the incarnation, and hence he is referred to as the “watcher” or
                        “wakeful one.” We find this same teaching in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urdk‘</hi>, most prominently in the latter half of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urd</hi> 13 (lines 26-38), where Ephrem discusses the purpose of
                        Christ’s watching.</p>
                    <p> An important aspect of the mission of Christ the watcher was to come to
                        earth to wake up human creatures, lost in the slumber of sin. In the <hi
                            rend="italic">Hymns on Nativity</hi>, Ephrem writes, “Let us glorify Him
                        Who watched and put to sleep our captor. / Let us glorify the One Who went
                        to sleep and awoke our slumber.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163"
                                ><p rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi> III.19. McVey, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns</hi>, 87.</p></note> The need for human
                        beings to be awakened from their slumber is present in other early Syriac
                        literature, such as the famous <hi rend="italic">Hymn of the
                            Pearl</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> On this text, see P. H. Poirier <hi
                                    rend="italic">L'hymne de la perle des actes de Thomas.
                                    Introduction, Texte-Traduction, Commentaire</hi>,
                                (Louvain-la-Neuve, 1981).</p></note> In a later hymn from this same
                        cycle, Ephrem writes: “The Watcher has come to make us watchers on
                            earth.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165" n="165"><p
                                rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi> XXI.4. McVey, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns</hi>, 174.</p></note> But why the need to
                        watch? In Early Christianity, watching and vigilance had an eschatological
                        reference, involving the anticipation of the Second Coming. The parable of
                        the ten virgins is crucial here. When the bridegroom came, those invited to
                        the banquet would be those who had stayed awake to watch for his coming.
                        Hence, the constant reiteration of the importance of keeping watch, during
                        the four watches of the night, since it is during one of those watches that
                        Christ indicated he will return, as is expressed in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urd</hi> 11.9-13.</p>
                    <pb n="309"/>
                    <p> Watchfulness is also a practice associated with the angelic realm. This is
                        due in part to the fact that watchfulness is associated with holiness and
                        thus bears easy connection with the sinless angels, whereas, by contrast,
                        insentient sleep is associated with death and sin. This dichotomy of
                        wakeful-ness/holiness and sleep/sin is made explicit in the first <hi
                            rend="italic">Hymn on the Nativity</hi>:</p>
                    <p>The watchers rejoice today because the Awakener has come to wake us up;</p>
                    <p>Who will sleep on this night when all creation is awake?</p>
                    <p>Because Adam introduced into the world the sleep of death in sins,</p>
                    <p>The Watcher came down to wake us up from the slumber of sin.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166"><p>
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi> I.61-62. English
                                translation from McVey, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hymns</hi><hi> (n. 6 above) 71.</hi></p></note></p>
                    <p>The purpose of Christ’s coming into the world, as celebrated in the feast of
                        the Nativity, is to wake up humans from the slumber induced by sin. <hi
                            rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 13.18-21 also makes explicit mention of the
                        host of angels keeping vigil on the night of Christ’s birth. In the first
                        line of the above quoted text, the angels are referred to explicitly as
                        “watchers.” In fact, “watchers” (<hi rend="italic">‘īre</hi>) is one of
                        Ephrem’s most frequent designations for angelic beings, and appears
                        throughout his Syriac corpus; this Aramaic appellation for angels is common
                        to both Jewish and Syriac Christian tradition, and goes back all the way to
                        the biblical book of Daniel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn167" n="167"><p>
                                <hi> For example, in the </hi><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Hymns on
                                    Faith</hi><hi> alone, mention of “watchers” is made at: 3.5, 3.9, 4.1, 4.7, 5.1-4, 6.8, 7.10, 8.3, 8.15, 10.4, 10.9-11, 11.7-8, 22.11, 28.1, 29.1, 30.2, 46.8, 51.5, 52.9, 54.2, 61.13, 68.20. For the Syriac text of the </hi><hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith </hi><hi>with German translation and a study, see: Edmund Beck, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de
                                    Fide</hi><hi>, 4 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 154–5; 212–13 (Louvain 1955; 1961). For an English translation and study of the </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns on
                                    Faith</hi><hi>, see: Jeffrey T. Wickes, tr., </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">St. Ephrem the
                                    Syrian</hi><hi>: </hi><hi rend="italic">The
                                    Hymns on
                                    Faith</hi><hi>, The Fathers of the Church 130 (Washington D.C. 2015). This usage of “watchers” is also prevelant in the </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns on the
                                    Nativity</hi><hi>. On the usage of this term in Syriac literature at large, see Robert Murray, “The Origin of Aramaic ‘îr, Angel,” </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >Orientalia</hi><hi> 53 (1984): 303–317; Idem, “Some Themes and Problems of Early Syriac Angelology,” </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                                    Analecta</hi><hi> 236 (1990): 143–153. On its usage in Ephrem as well as some general remarks on the theme of watching and vigil, see: Idem, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early
                                    Syriac
                                    Tradition</hi><hi>, rev. ed. (Piscataway, 2004) 14; Sebastian Brock, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision of
                                    Saint
                                    Ephrem</hi><hi>, Cistercian Studies Series 124 (Kalamazoo, 1992) 139–141; Wickes, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns on
                                    Faith</hi><hi>, 68, note 2 and McVey, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >Hymns</hi><hi>, 229, note 36; Cassingena-Trévedy, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                >Nativité,</hi><hi> 40, note 5.</hi>
                            </p></note> Armenian shares this<pb n="310"/> usage, with its term
                            <foreign xml:lang="hy">զուարթունք</foreign> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >zuart‘unk‘</hi>, “sleepless ones”), used in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kc‘urdk‘</hi> to refer to angels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168"
                            n="168"><p rend="footnote text"> See for example the title of <hi
                                    rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 10,
                                <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd </hi>10.16, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 13.18-21, and Kc<hi rend="italic"
                                    >‘urd</hi> 16.40.</p></note> Like Christ, “watchers” are
                        sleepless, since they stand ceaselessly in the divine presence in perpetual
                        contemplation and praise, and as such serve as models of admiration and
                        imitation. They maintain the continual consciousness of attention on God
                        that the human watcher strives for through the practice of vigil. The
                        watching of angels is twofold, as they stand wakeful not just in God’s
                        presence, but also watch over earthly life, as Ephrem puts it “suffering
                        over the sinners but rejoicing over penitents.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn169" n="169"><p>
                                <hi> See </hi><hi rend="italic">Hymns against
                                    Julian</hi><hi> I.8. Translation in McVey, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >Hymns</hi><hi>, 229. For the Syriac text of the </hi><hi rend="italic">Hymns against Julian </hi><hi>with German translation and a study, see Edmund Beck, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Paradiso
                                    und Contra
                                    Julianum</hi><hi>, 2 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 174–5 (Louvain 1957). English translation in McVey, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                >Hymns</hi><hi>, 229. </hi></p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p> Watchfulness is closely associated with another concept important to Ephrem
                        and early Syriac Christianity, that of <hi rend="italic">íḥiyḍāyā</hi>,
                        a term rich in semantic range, incorporating at least three separate but
                        interconnected fields of meaning: singular, unique, individual;
                        single-minded, not divided in heart; and single in the sense of unmarried,
                            celibate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn170" n="170"><p>
                                <hi> Murray, </hi><hi rend="italic"
                                    >Symbols</hi><hi>, 13–14; Brock, </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">Luminous Eye</hi><hi>, 136.</hi></p></note> The
                        term in its first usage refers above all to Christ, and corresponds to Greek
                            <hi rend="italic">monogenēs</hi>, “only-begotten.” Its connection with
                        watching and vigil is particularly relevant in the second range, that of
                        single-mindedness, in other words not being divided in heart or will.<pb
                            n="311"/> To be watchful is to be in spiritual harmony, to be always
                        attentive and single-minded in one’s devotion to Christ.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn171" n="171"><p>
                                <hi> Brock, </hi><hi rend="italic">Luminous
                                    Eye</hi><hi>, 141.</hi></p></note> It is to maintain a
                        consistent consciousness of attention on God in prayer. This understanding
                        of being single and undivided in conscious vigil and being divided in sleep
                        occurs in the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> as well.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn172" n="172"><p rend="footnote text"> See for example <hi
                                    rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 11.25 and <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Kc‘urd</hi> 11.39-40.</p></note> It also helps one understand
                        the negative portrayal of the creation of Eve during the sleep of Adam in
                            <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 12.3-4. </p>
                    <p> Not all watching is portrayed positively in the works of Ephrem. There are
                        forms of watching that not only are of no benefit but are harmful, such as
                        the vigil of the greedy who stay up late to devise ways to make more money
                        or the worrier who cannot sleep from the anxiety brought on by worries.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn173" n="173"><p rend="footnote text"> Ephrem
                                outlines a whole litany of such people who keep watch to no benefit
                                in <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi>, I.63-82.
                            </p></note> Referring to biblical examples, Ephrem says that even Judas
                        Iscariot kept vigil an entire night to betray Christ, and “even the
                        Pharisees, sons of darkness, were awake an entire night; / the dark ones
                        kept vigil to conceal the incomprehensible light.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn174" n="174"><p rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Nativity</hi>, I.70-72; McVey, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Hymns</hi>, 72.</p></note> Similarly, <hi
                            rend="italic">Kc‘urd</hi> 16 contains a lengthy meditation on the
                        worthlessness of those who stay up late “keeping vigil” at a wedding party.
                        This stands in sharp contrast with the benefits accrued by those who keep
                        vigil in anticipation of the heavenly bridegroom. </p>
                    <p> This brief discussion indicates the consonance of Ephrem’s thought on vigil
                        as expressed in the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> with what we know from
                        the authentic Syriac texts of Ephrem that mention vigil, further reinforcing
                        the linguistic and historical evidence that point to the strong likelihood
                        of the <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> being authentic works authored by
                        Ephrem, and translated in the fifth century.</p>
                    <pb n="312"/>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Akinian, Nersēs, <hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘ S. Ep‘remi Xorin Asorwoy</hi> [=<hi
                        rend="italic">Ephräm des Syrers 51 Madrasche in Armenischer
                    Ubersetzung</hi>], Texte und Untersuchungen der Altarmenischen Literature, Bd.
                    1.3 (Vienna, 1957).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Ts‘uts‘ak hayerēn dzeragrats‘ Nikosiayi i Kipros</hi>
                    [=Katalog der armenischen Handscriften in Nikosia auf Cyprus], Vienna, 1961.</bibl>
                <bibl>Beck, Edmund, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de
                        Fide</hi>, 4 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 154–5; 212–13
                    (Louvain 1955; 1961).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra
                        Haereses</hi>, Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 169/170,
                    Scriptores Syri 76/77 (Louvain, 1957).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Paradiso und
                        Contra Julianum</hi>, 2 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium
                    174–5 (Louvain 1957).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen De Nativitate
                        (Epiphania)</hi> 2 vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 186–7
                    (Louvain, 1959).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Carmina Nisibena</hi>, 4
                    vols. Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 218–9, 240-241 (Louvain, 1961;
                    1963).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Ephräms des Syrers Hymnik,” in <hi rend="italic">Liturgie und Dichtung.
                        Ein interdisziplinäres Kompendium. Gualtero Duerig annum vitae septuagesimum
                        feliciter complenti</hi>, eds. H. Becker and R. Kaczynski (St. Ottilien,
                    1983), vol. 1: 345-379.</bibl>
                <pb n="313"/>
                <bibl>Boyce, Mary, “The Parthian ‘Gōsān’ and Iranian Minstrel Tradition,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and
                        Ireland</hi>, No. 1/2 (April 1957): 10-45.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian, <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision
                        of Saint Ephrem</hi>, Cistercian Studies Series 124 (Kalamazoo, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">The Harp of the Spirit: Poems of Saint Ephrem the
                        Syrian</hi>, 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> ed., The Institute for Orthodox
                    Christian Studies (Cambridge, 2013).</bibl>
                <bibl>Butts, Aaron, “The Classical Syriac Language,” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                        World</hi>, ed. Daniel King (Routledge, forthcoming in 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl>Cassingena-Trévedy, François, o.s.b., <hi rend="italic">Hymnes sur la
                        nativité</hi>, Sources Chrétiennes 459 (Paris, 2001).</bibl>
                <bibl>Cerbelaud, Dominique, <hi rend="italic">La descente aux enfers: Carmina
                        Nisibena</hi>, Spiritualité Orientale 89 (Godewaersvelde, 2009).</bibl>
                <bibl>Cowe, S. Peter, “The Two Armenian Versions of Chronicles: their Origin and
                    Translation Technique,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des études arméniennes</hi> 22
                    (1990–1): 53–96.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “The Bible in Armenian” in <hi rend="italic">The New Cambridge History of
                        the Bible, Volume 2: From 600 to 1450</hi>, eds. Richard Marsden and E. Ann
                    Matter (Cambridge, 2012): 143-161.</bibl>
                <bibl>den Biesen, Kees, <hi rend="italic">Simple and Bold: Ephrem’s Art of Symbolic
                        Thought</hi>, Gorgias Dissertations 26, Early Christian Studies 6
                    (Piscataway, NJ, 2006).</bibl>
                <bibl>Eganyan, Ō., A. Zeytʻunyan, Pʻ. Antʻabyan, eds., <hi rend="italic">Mayr tsʻutsʻak
                        hayerēn dzeṛagratsʻ Mashtotsʻi Anuan Matenadarani</hi> [=Grand Catalogue of
                    the Armenian Manuscripts of the Matenadaran named Maštoc‘], 9 vols., Erevan,
                    1984—.</bibl>
                <pb n="314"/>
                <bibl>Ełišē Vardapet, <hi rend="italic">Matenagrut‘iwnk‘</hi>, Venice, 1859.</bibl>
                <bibl>Féghali, P., and C. Navarre, <hi rend="italic">Saint Éphrem: Sur les chants de
                        Nisibe</hi>, Antioche chrétienne 3 (Paris, 1997).</bibl>
                <bibl>Garsoïan, Nina, “Introduction to the Problem of Early Armenian Monasticism,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Revue des études arméniennes</hi> 30 (2005-7): 177-236.</bibl>
                <bibl>Goldenberg, Gideon, “On Some Niceties of Syriac Syntax” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Studies in Semitic Linguistics: Selected Writings</hi> (Jerusalem, 1998):
                    579-590.</bibl>
                <bibl>Graffin, François, “Hymnes inédites de S. Ephrem sur la virginité” <hi
                        rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien </hi>6 (1961): 213–42.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kouymjian, Dickran, “The Archaeology of the Armenian Manuscript: Codicology,
                    Paleography, and Beyond,” in <hi rend="italic">Armenian Philology in the Modern
                        Era: From Manuscript to Digital Text</hi>, ed. Valentina Calzolari (Leiden,
                    2014): 5–22.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lange, Christian, <hi rend="italic">The Portrayal of Christ in the Syriac
                        Commentary on the Diatessaron</hi>, Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum
                    Orientalium 616, Subsidia 118 (Louvain, 2005).</bibl>
                <bibl>Maier, Carmen, “Poetry as Exegesis: Ephrem the Syrian’s Method of Scriptural
                    Interpretation Especially as Seen in his Hymns on Paradise and Hymns on
                    Unleavened Bread,” PhD diss., Princeton Theological Seminary, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mariès, Louis, “Une Antiphona de Saint Ephrem sur l’eucharistie,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Recherches de Science Religieuse</hi> 42 (1954), 395-403.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Deux Antiphonae de Saint Ephrem,” <hi rend="italic">Recherches de Science
                        Religieuse</hi> 45 (1957), 396-408.</bibl>
                <pb n="315"/>
                <bibl>Mariès, Louis and Charles Mercier, <hi rend="italic">Hymnes de Saint Ephrem
                        conservées en version arménienne</hi>, Patrologia Orientalis XXX, fascicle 1
                    (Paris: Firmin-Didot, 1961).</bibl>
                <bibl>Mathews, Edward, “Armenian Hymn IX, <hi rend="italic">On Marriage</hi> by Saint
                    Ephrem the Syrian,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Society for Armenian
                        Studies</hi> 9 (1996/7 [1999]): 55-63.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Saint Ephrem the Syrian: Armenian Dispute Hymns between <hi rend="italic"
                        >Virginity</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Chastity</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Revue des études arméniennes </hi>28 (2001/2): 143–69.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Syriac into Armenian: The Translations and their Translators,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 10
                    (2010): 20-44.</bibl>
                <bibl>McVey, Kathleen, <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns</hi> (New York,
                    1989).</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Were the earliest <hi rend="italic">madrāšē</hi> songs or recitations?”
                    in <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan. Studies on Continuity and Change in Syriac
                        Christianity in Honour of Professor Han J.W. Drijvers</hi>, eds. G.J.
                    Reinink and A.C. Klugkist, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 89 (Louvain, 1999):
                    185-199.</bibl>
                <bibl>Muradyan, Gohar, <hi rend="italic">Grecisms in Ancient Armenian</hi>, Hebrew
                    University Armenian Studies 13, (Leuven, 2012).</bibl>
                <bibl>Muraoka, Takamitsu, <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac: A Basic Grammar with a
                        Chrestomathy, 2</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                    >nd</hi><hi rend="italic"> rev. ed., Porta Linguarum Orientalium: Neue Serie</hi>
                    (Wiesbaden, 2005).</bibl>
                <bibl>Murray, Robert, “The Origin of Aramaic ‘îr, Angel,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Orientalia</hi> 53 (1984): 303–317.</bibl>
                <pb n="316"/>
                <bibl>_____, “‘A Marriage for all eternity’: The Consecration of a Syrian bride of
                    Christ,” <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review </hi>11 (1989):
                    65–8.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Some Themes and Problems of Early Syriac Angelology,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Orientalia Christiana Analecta</hi> 236 (1990): 143–153.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Aramaic and Syriac Dispute-Poems and Their Connections,” in M.J. Geller,
                    J.C. Greenfield, M.P. Weitzmann, eds., <hi rend="italic">Studia Aramaica: New
                        Sources and New Approaches</hi>, Journal of Semitic Studies, Supplement 4,
                    (Oxford, 1995): 157-187.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac
                        Tradition</hi>, rev. ed. (Piscataway, 2004).</bibl>
                <bibl>Nöldeke, Theodor, <hi rend="italic">Compendious Syriac Grammar</hi>, tr. James A.
                    Chrichton (London, 1904).</bibl>
                <bibl>Outtier, Bernard, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lettre aux amis de Solesmes</hi> 18 (avril-juin 1979): 3-9.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie II” <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux
                        amis de Solesmes</hi> 22 (avril-juin 1980): 3-8.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie III”
                    <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux amis de Solesmes </hi>(1981:1):
                    14-18.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie IV” <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux
                        amis de Solesmes</hi> (1981:3): 3-7.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Hymnes de saint Ephrem sur l’Eucharistie V” <hi rend="italic">Lettre aux
                        amis de Solesmes</hi> (1982:2): 3-5.</bibl>
                <bibl>NBHL = <hi rend="italic">Nor bargirk‘ haygazean lezui</hi>, 2 vols. (Venice
                    1836-7).</bibl>
                <pb n="317"/>
                <bibl>Palmer, Andrew, “A Single Human Being Divided in Himself: Ephraim the Syrian, the
                    Man in the Middle,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 1:2
                    (1998): 119-163.</bibl>
                <bibl>_____, “Ephrem of Nisibis,” in <hi rend="italic">The Wiley Blackwell Companion to
                        Patristics</hi>, ed. Ken Parry (Chichester, 2015): 126–140.</bibl>
                <bibl>Poirier, P. H., <hi rend="italic">L'hymne de la perle des actes de Thomas.
                        Introduction, Texte-Traduction, Commentaire</hi>, (Louvain-la-Neuve,
                    1981).</bibl>
                <bibl>Tanielian, Anoushawan Vardapet, <hi rend="italic">Mayr tsʻutsʻak hayerēn
                        dzeṛagratsʻ Metsi Tann Kilikioy Katʻoghikosutʻean</hi> [=Catalogue of the
                    Armenian Manuscripts in the Collection of the Armenian Catholicosate of
                    Cilicia], (Antelias, 1984).</bibl>
                <bibl>Terian, Abraham, “The Hellenizing School: Its Time, Place, and Scope of
                    Activities Reconsidered” in <hi rend="italic">East of Byzantium: Syria and
                        Armenia in the Formative Period (Dumbarton Oaks Symposium, 1980)</hi>, eds.
                    Nina Garsoïan, Thomas F. Mathews, and Robert W. Thomson (Washington, D.C.,
                    1982): 175-186.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tēr-Petrosian, Levon, “Kc‘urdk‘ S. Ep‘remi Xorin Asorvoy: Bnagrakan Čšgrtumner
                        [<hi rend="italic">Kc‘urdk‘</hi> of Ephrem the Syrian: Text-Critical
                    Emendations],” <hi rend="italic">Handēs Amsoreay</hi> 92 (1978): 15-48.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wickes, Jeffrey T., “Out of Books, a World: The Scriptural Poetics of Ephrem the
                    Syrian’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi>,” PhD diss., University of Notre
                    Dame, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl>_____, <hi rend="italic">St. Ephrem the Syrian</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Hymns
                        on Faith</hi>, The Fathers of the Church 130 (Washington D.C. 2015).</bibl>
                <pb n="318"/>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
