<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">In Memoriam: Robert P. R. Murray, S.J.</title>
                <title type="sub">(8 June 1926 - 24 April
                    2018)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                        <surname>Brock</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n2obit-murray</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Sebastian P. Brock</author>
                        <title level="a">In Memoriam: Robert P. R. Murray, S.J. (8 June 1926 - 24 April
                            2018)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N2Obit-Murray.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="255" to="261">255–261</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>

            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-11-01">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="obituary">
        <body>
            
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <figure><graphic
                        url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV21N2Obit-Murray1.png"
                        rend="center" height="200">
                    </graphic></figure>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">For Syriacists the name of Robert Murray, who died peacefully in
                    the evening of Tuesday 24th April 2018, will always be associated with his <hi
                        rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi> of 1975, which<pb n="255"/> not only
                    offers such a wonderful introduction to the symbolic thought of early Syriac
                    writers, but has also successfully reversed the negative attitude towards Ephrem
                    that had been characteristic of several earlier English scholars of Syriac, one
                    of whom declared, ‘His poems are turgid, humourless and repetitive’, while
                    another had asserted that his popularity as a poet showed ‘a lamentable standard
                    of public taste’.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Robert Murray was born in China, to missionary parents, on 8th June
                    1926, appropriately just in time for the Feast of St Ephrem according to the
                    Western calendar which falls on the following day. In later life he clearly took
                    pride in his Chinese background and our Visitors’ Book somewhere has an entry
                    where he signed his name in Chinese characters; this is also brought out in the
                    expanded dedication to his parents in the revised edition of his <hi
                        rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi> (2004) where he adds that
                    they had ‘served in China the same Lord as did their first predecessors from the
                    Church of the East’. His education, however, was entirely in England, and after
                    leaving school he spent a year studying Persian at the School of Oriental and
                    African Studies in London, with a view to war service. Once the war was over he
                    went to Oxford University where he took his degree in <hi rend="italic">Literae
                        Humaniores</hi> (consisting in Greek and Latin, followed by Philosophy). It
                    was while he was at Oxford that he was received into the Roman Catholic Church,
                    and it was also in Oxford that his lifelong friendship with the family of J.R.R.
                    Tolkien began (he helped proofread drafts of <hi rend="italic">The Lord of the
                        Rings</hi>). He joined the Society of Jesus in 1949 and was ordained ten
                    years later, with further studies in Münster, followed by a doctorate at the
                    Gregorian University in Rome.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">On his return to England in 1963 he was appointed to teach at
                    Heythrop College (then situated in rural Oxfordshire, but from 1970 onwards in
                    London as part of the University of London). He remained at Heythrop College as
                    an inspiring and much appreciated teacher of biblical studies until his
                    retirement in 1999. His interests were wide and his publications cover much more
                    than the studies in the field of<pb n="256"/> Syriac which constitute the focus of attention
                    here. This breadth of interests is well illustrated by another important book
                    which he published, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Cosmic Covenant</hi> (1992;
                    recently reprinted by the Gorgias Press), whose contents range from biblical
                    scholarship to the remarkable medieval abbess, poet and scholar, Hildegard of
                    Bingen, and end with Simone Weil in the twentieth century. This whole book
                    remains of considerable relevance in the context of the current ecological
                    crisis; several of its themes are picked up in a Syriac context in subsequent
                    articles, as will be seen from the listing below. He had plans for another
                    wide-ranging book, this time on Prophecy, but alas this never materialised. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Not surprisingly most of Robert Murray’s articles that deal with
                    Syriac studies concern, like his influential book, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of
                        Church and Kingdom</hi>, different aspects of early Syriac Christianity,
                    often focusing on particular poems by Ephrem: besides providing illuminating
                    introductions and annotation, he also showed himself to be an especially fine
                    translator of Ephrem, for he combined a rare sensitivity to Ephrem’s often
                    allusive thought with a natural feel for the English language (he also wrote
                    poetry himself). His article on ‘Ephrem’s theory of symbolism’ (1975/6) is still
                    the best succinct discussion of that important topic. Of particular significance
                    are his studies of rhetorical patterns in early Syriac literature, drawing
                    attention to features that have their counterpart in Greek Kunstprosa. He also
                    contributed a number of perceptive overviews, such as that on ‘The
                    characteristics of earliest Syriac Christianity’ in <hi rend="italic">East of
                        Antioch</hi> (1982); all of these remain well worth reading, even though on
                    some matters he subsequently changed his mind, as can be seen from his rewritten
                    and updated Introduction to the revised edition of <hi rend="italic">Symbols of
                        Church and Kingdom</hi>. Many of his wider writings reflect his concern with
                    the relationship between Judaism and Christianity, and this is an aspect
                    reflected in a number of his articles in the Syriac realm, including his
                    ‘Aramaic and Syriac dispute poems’ (1995), which provides what remains the best
                    overview of this intriguing genre.</p><pb n="257"/>
                <p xml:lang="en">Robert Murray attended a number of the international Syriac
                    conferences, the most recent being Symposium Syriacum X, held in Granada in
                    2008; he was also present at the conference in Princeton which was held in his
                    honour on the occasion of the publication of the revised edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom</hi>. Those who have had the
                    privilege of knowing him will remember with gratitude his gentle and generous
                    presence. </p>
                <p xml:lang="syr" rend="center">ܢܫܬܘܐ ܠܓܢܘܢ ܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܠܐ ܡܬܚܒܠ</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The following chronological listing provides Robert Murray’s
                    bibliography where it is of relevance to Syriac Studies. A wider bibliography is
                    to be found in <hi rend="italic">The Heythrop Journal</hi> 36:4 (1995), 521-8, a
                    number of the journal which served as a Festschrift in his honour.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"/>
                <p xml:lang="en"/>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>St Ephrem the Syrian on Church unity, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Churches
                            Quarterly</hi> 15 (1963), 164-76.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The Rock and the House on the Rock. A chapter in the ecclesiological
                        symbolism of Aphraates and Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                            Periodica</hi> 30 (1964), 315-62.</bibl>
                    <bibl>A special sense of <hi rend="italic">ṣlota</hi> as absolution or
                        re-admission to ecclesiastical communion, <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                            Christiana Periodica</hi> 32 (1966), 523-7.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Syriac Studies today, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Churches Review</hi> 1
                        (1966/7), 370-73.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reconstructing the Diatessaron, <hi rend="italic">The Heythrop
                            Journal</hi> 10 (1969), 43-9. [On I. Ortiz de Urbina, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Vetus Evangelium Syrorum et exinde excerptum Diatessaron Tatiani</hi>
                        (Madrid, 1967)]</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ephrem Syrus, in J.H. Creehan (ed.) <hi rend="italic">Catholic Dictionary
                        of Theology</hi> (London, 1967), II, 220-23.</bibl><pb n="258"/>
                    <bibl>A hymn of St Ephrem to Christ on the Incarnation, the Holy Spirit, and the
                        Sacraments, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Churches Review</hi> 3 (1970), 42-50.
                        [with complete translation of <hi rend="italic">de Fide</hi> 10].</bibl>
                    <bibl>The features of the earliest Christian asceticism, in P. Brooks (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Christian Spirituality. Essays in Honour of E.G. Rupp</hi>
                        (London, 1975), 65-77</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mary, the Second Eve in the Early Syriac Fathers, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Eastern Churches Review</hi> 3 (1971), 372-84.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The Lance which re-opened Paradise. A mysterious reading in the early
                        Syriac Fathers, <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 39
                        (1973), 224-34.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The exhortation to candidates for ascetical vows at baptism in the ancient
                        Syriac Church, <hi rend="italic">New Testament Studies</hi> 21 (1974),
                        59-80.</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom. A Study in Early Syriac
                            Tradition</hi> (Cambridge, 1975; reprinted with an additional
                        introduction, Piscataway NJ, 2004).</bibl>
                    <bibl>The theory of symbolism in St Ephrem’s theology, <hi rend="italic">Parole
                            de l’Orient</hi> 6-7 (1975/6), 1-20. [with complete translation of de
                        Fide 20; French translation in <hi rend="italic">Lettre de Ligugé</hi> 203
                        (1980),7-25].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Some rhetorical patterns in early Syriac literature, in R.H. Fischer
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">A Tribute to Arthur Vööbus</hi> (Chicago, 1977),
                        109-31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Der Dichter als Exeget: der hl. Ephräm und die heutige Exegese, <hi
                            rend="italic">Zeitschrift für katholische Theologie</hi> 100 (1978),
                        484-94.</bibl>
                    <bibl>A Hymn of St Ephrem to Christ, <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern
                            Churches Review</hi> 1 (1979), 39-50 [with complete translation of <hi
                            rend="italic">de Virginitate</hi> 31].</bibl>
                    <bibl>St Ephrem’s Dialogue of Reason and Love, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review</hi> 2 (1980), 26-40 [with complete
                        translation of <hi rend="italic">de Ecclesia</hi> 9].</bibl><pb n="259"/>
                    <bibl>(By J. Walsh, but based on materials by RM: Divine call and human
                        response: The Syriac Tradition: St Ephrem, <hi rend="italic">The Way:
                            Contemporary Christian Spirituality</hi> 20 (1980), 228-33).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Syriac Christianity as an example of “inculturation” [in Chinese], <hi
                            rend="italic">Collectanea Theologica Universitatis Fujen</hi> 49 (1981),
                        453-63.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The characteristics of the earliest Syriac Christianity, in N. Garsoian,
                        T. Mathews and R.W. Thomson (eds), <hi rend="italic">East of Byzantium.
                            Syria and Armenia in the Formative Period</hi> (Washington DC, 1982),
                        3-16</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ephraem Syrus, in <hi rend="italic">Theologische Realenzyklopädie</hi>
                        IX.5 (1982), 755-62.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hellenistic-Jewish Rhetoric in Aphrahat, in R. Lavenant (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">III Symposium Syriacum</hi> (Orientalia Christiana
                        Analecta 221; 1983), 87-96.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The origins of Aramaic <hi rend="italic">‘ir</hi> Angel, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Orientalia</hi> 53 1984), 303-17.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ephrem of Syria. A marriage for all eternity: the consecration of a Syrian
                        Bride of Christ, <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review</hi> 11
                        (1989), 65-9.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Some themes and problems of early Syriac angelology, in R. Lavenant (ed.,
                            <hi rend="italic">V Symposium Syriacum</hi> (Orientalia Christiana
                        Analecta 236; 1990), 143-53.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Aramaic and Syriac dispute-poems and their connections, in M.J. Geller,
                        J.C. Greenfield and M.P. Weitzman (eds), <hi rend="italic">Studia Aramaica.
                            New Sources and New Approaches</hi> (Journal of Semitic Studies
                        Supplement 4; Oxford, 1995), 157-87.</bibl>
                    <bibl>L’homme et la creation: responsabilité, péché et reconciliation, in <hi
                            rend="italic">Péché et réconciliation, hier et aujourd’hui</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">Patrimoine Syriaque</hi> IV; Antelias, 1997), 92-9.</bibl>
                    <bibl>‘Circumcision of the heart’ and the origins of the Qyama, in G.J. Reinink
                        and A.C. Klugkist (eds), <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on
                            Continuity and Change in Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professor Han
                            J.W. Drijvers</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 89; 1999),
                        201-11.</bibl><pb n="260"/>
                    <bibl>The Ephremic tradition and the theology of the environment, <hi
                            rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> 2:1 (1999), 67-82.</bibl>
                    <bibl>The paradox of God’s hiddenness and accessibility in St Ephrem, <hi
                            rend="italic">New Blackfriars</hi> 996 (2004), 158-62.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
                <p>Reviews of Syriac relevance:</p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Heythrop Journal</hi> 8 (1967), 331-3: L. Leloir, <hi
                            rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe, Commentaire de l’Évangile concordant ou
                            Diatessaron</hi> (1966). </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Clergy Review</hi> 53 (1968), 823-8: R. Lavenant, <hi
                            rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe, Hymnes sur le Paradis</hi>
                        (1968).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Heythrop Journal</hi> 16 (1975), 92-4: W. Strothmann,
                            <hi rend="italic">Johannes von Apamea</hi> (1972).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Eastern Churches Review</hi> 10 (1978), 160-63: R.
                        Macuch, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der spät- und neusyrische
                            Literatur</hi> (1976).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 44 (1978), 523-6:
                        T. Baarda, <hi rend="italic">The Gospel Quotations of Aphrahat the Persian
                            Sage, I. Aphrahat’s Text of the Fourth Gospel</hi> (1975).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 45 (1979), 486-9:
                        T. Kronholm, <hi rend="italic">Motifs from Genesis 1-11 in the Genuine Hymns
                            of Ephrem the Syrian</hi> (1978).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 32 (1981), 260-61:
                        W. Cramer, <hi rend="italic">Der Geist Gottes und des Menschen in
                            frühsyrischer Theologie</hi> (1979).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Journal of Theolical Studies</hi> 35 (1984), 232-5: D.S.
                        Wallace-Hadrill, <hi rend="italic">Christian Antioch</hi> (1982). </bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 45 (1994), 322-6:
                        M-J. Pierre, <hi rend="italic">Aphraate le sage person, Les Exposés,
                            I-II</hi> (1988-9).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 40 (1989), 258-60:
                        W.L. Petersen, <hi rend="italic">The Diatessaron and Ephrem Syrus as Sources
                            of Romanos the Melodist</hi> (1985).</bibl>
                    <bibl><hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review</hi> 16 (1994), 83-8:
                        J.F. Coakley, <hi rend="italic">The Church of the East and the Church of
                            England</hi> (1992). </bibl><pb n="261"/>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
