<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Nikolai N. Seleznyov (ed. and trans.), <hi rend="italic">Liber sessionum sive
                    disputatio inter Eliam metropolitam Nisibenum et vezirum Abū ʾl-Qāsim
                    al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī et Epistola eiusdem Eliae Nisibeni ad vezirum
                    Abū ʾl-Qāsim missa</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Alexander</forename>
                        <surname>Treiger</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Dalhousie University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv21n1prtreiger</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Alexander Treiger</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: Liber sessionum sive
                            disputatio inter Eliam metropolitam Nisibenum et vezirum Abū ʾl-Qāsim
                            al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī et Epistola eiusdem Eliae Nisibeni ad vezirum
                            Abū ʾl-Qāsim missa</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1PRTreiger.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="236" to="240">236–240</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="12"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
           
                <div type="title">
                    <ab type="review-title">Nikolai N. Seleznyov (ed. and trans.), <hi rend="italic">Книга собеседований Илии,
                        митрополита Нисивина, с везиром Абу-л-Ḳасимом ал-Хусайном ибн ʿАли
                            ал-Магриби и
                        Послание митрополита Илии везиру Абу-л-Ḳасиму / Kitāb al-Maǧālis li-Mār Iliyyā muṭrān Nuṣaybīn wa-Risālatuhu ilā l-wazīr
                        al-kāmil Abī l-Qāsim al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī / Liber sessionum sive
                        disputatio inter Eliam metropolitam Nisibenum et vezirum Abū ʾl-Qāsim
                        al-Ḥusayn ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī et Epistola eiusdem Eliae Nisibeni ad vezirum
                        Abū ʾl-Qāsim missa</hi> (Moscow: Grifon, 2017/8). Pp. 210 + <foreign xml:lang="ar">٢٦٨</foreign>. ISBN 978-5-98862-366-3 +
                        978-5-98862-367-0 (two volumes); 978-5-98862-371-7 (one-volume edition).</ab>
                </div>
                   <div type="body">

                    <p xml:lang="en">The East Syriac theologian Elias of Nisibis (975–1046) has been rightly
                        acclaimed as one of the most influential Syriac and Christian Arabic
                        writers. The book under review presents a first complete critical edition
                        and Russian translation of two of Elias’ Arabic treatises: <hi rend="italic">Book of Sessions</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                            al-Maǧālis</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">Epistle to the Vizier Abū l-Qāsim al-Maġribī</hi>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Previous editions of the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi> include
                        Louis Cheikho’s uncritical and abridged edition,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                                Louis Cheikho, “<hi rend="italic">Maǧālis</hi> Īliyya muṭrān Nuṣaybīn,” <hi rend="italic">al-Mašriq</hi> 20 (1922), 33–44, 112–122, 267–272, 366–377, 425–434 (reprint: Louis Cheikho, <hi rend="italic">Trois
                                    traités anciens de polémique et de théologie
                                    chrétiennes</hi>, Beirut, 1923, pp. 26–73). Cheikho presents a collated text with no critical apparatus, based on four manuscripts: Beirut, Bibliothèque Orientale 564 (year 1826, a copy of a copy of Vat. ar. 645, written in 1234) – <hi rend="bold">B</hi> in Seleznyov’s edition; Beirut, Bibliothèque Orientale 676 (year 1715) – <hi rend="italic">Ḅ</hi> in Seleznyov’s edition; an unspecified Beirut manuscript, which Cheikho dated to the thirteenth century (cf. Louis Cheikho, “al-Maḫṭūṭāt al-ʿarabiyya fī ḫizānat kulliyyatinā al-šarqiyya,” <hi rend="italic">al-Mašriq</hi> 6 (1909), 374–378, at p. 376, No. 99); and Aleppo, Maronite Archdiocese 258 (year 1631).</p>
                    </note>
                        Samir Khalil Samir’s editions of Elias’ Introduction and the First, Sixth,
                        and (partially) Seventh Sessions,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Introduction and First Session: Samir Khalil Samir, “Entretien d’Élie de Nisibe avec le vizir Ibn ʿAlī al-Maġribī sur l’Unité et la Trinité,” <hi rend="italic">Islamochristiana</hi> 5 (1979), 31–117 (reprint: Samir Khalil Samir, <hi rend="italic">Foi et culture en
                                    Irak au XI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle</hi>, Aldershot: Variorum, 1996,
                                    Essay VII).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text" style="font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; text-decoration: underline; text-align:both; ">Sixth Session: Samir
                                    Khalil Samir, “Deux cultures qui s’affrontent: une controverse
                                    sur l’iʿrāb au XI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle entre Élie de Nisibe et le vizir Abū l-Qāsim,” <hi rend="italic">Mélanges de
                                    l’Université
                                    Saint-Joseph</hi> 49 (1975–1976), 619–649 (reprint: Samir, <hi rend="italic">Foi et
                                    culture</hi>, Essay XI); Samir Khalil Samir, “Langue arabe, logique et théologie chez Élie de Nisibe,” <hi rend="italic">Mélanges de
                                    l’Université
                                    Saint-Joseph</hi> 52 (1991–1992), 229–367. I was unable to consult Samir Khalil Samir, <hi rend="italic">Iliyyā
                                    al-Naṣībī: Kitāb
                                    al-Maǧālis,
                                    al-Maǧlis al-sādis fī
                                    al-naḥw wa-l-luġa
                                    wa-l-ḫaṭṭwa-l-kalām</hi>, Cairo: n.p., 1975, 53 pages). Samir Khalil Samir, “Bibliographie du dialogue islamo-chrétien,” <hi rend="italic">Islamochristiana,</hi> 3 (1977), 257–286 (reprint: Samir, <hi rend="italic">Foi et
                                    culture</hi>, Essay I), p.
                                    [10]/264 describes it as an “édition polycopiée,” i.e., a
                                    handwritten or typewritten text reproduced by a duplication
                                    machine; no copy of it seems available in major university
                                    libraries.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Seventh Session: Samir Khalil Samir, “La réfutation de l’astrologie par Élie de Nisibe,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                                    Christiana
                                    Periodica</hi> 43 (1977), 408–441 (reprint: Samir, <hi rend="italic">Foi et
                                    culture</hi>, Essay X);
                                    revised edition: Samir Khalil Samir, “Īliyyā al-Nuṣaybīnī
                                    (975–1046 m) wa-l-wazīr Abū l-Qāsim al-Maġribī. II. Iʿtiqād
                                    al-naṣārā fī aḥkām al-nuǧūm,” <hi rend="italic">al-Mašriq</hi> 77 (2003), 83–105.</p>
                    </note>
                        and Martino Diez’s recent edition of the Fifth Session.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Martino Diez, “The Profession of Monotheism by Elias of Nisibis: An Edition and Translation of the Fifth Session of the <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                                    al-majālis</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Islam and
                                    Christian-Muslim
                                Relations</hi> 28.4 (2017), 493–514.</p>
                    </note>
                        The Sixth Session, in particular, has a paramount importance for Syriac
                        Studies in that there Elias offers a detailed comparison between Syriac and
                        Arabic with reference to grammar, lexicography, and script and makes a case
                        for the superiority of Syriac over Arabic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> David Bertaina, “Science, Syntax, and Superiority in Eleventh-Century Christian-Muslim Discussion: Elias of Nisibis on the Arabic and Syriac Languages,” <hi rend="italic">Islam and
                                    Christian-Muslim
                                    Relations</hi> 22.2 (2011), 197–207. On Elias of Nisibis’ contribution to Syriac lexicography, see Adam McCollum, “Prolegomena to a New Edition of Eliya of Nisibis’s <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
                                    al-turjumān fī taʿlīm luġat
                                    al-suryān</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                    Semitic
                                Studies</hi> 58.2 (2013), 297–322.</p>
                    </note>
                        The <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Epistle </hi>was never
                        published before.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">For his edition of the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi>, Seleznyov
                        consulted thirteen manuscripts, five of which were collated systematically
                            (<hi rend="bold">V</hi> = Vat. ar. 143, adopted as the <hi rend="italic">manuscrit de base</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Online: <ref target="HYPERLINK"/>.</p>
                    </note>
                        <hi rend="italic normalweight" style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">Ṽ</hi> = Vat. ar. 155; <hi rend="italic normalweight" style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">Ṿ</hi> = Vat. ar. 180; <hi rend="bold">P</hi> = Paris, BnF ar. 206; <hi rend="bold">K</hi> = Berlin, Staatsbibliothek syr. 115 [Sachau 67] in
                        Garšūnī), and three others partially (<hi rend="bold">H</hi> =
                        Oxford, Bodleian, Huntington 240 [Uri 38]; <hi rend="bold">A</hi>
                        = Aleppo, Salem ar. 274 [Sbath 1080]; <hi rend="bold">S</hi> =
                        Berlin, Staatsbibliothek syr. 114 [Sachau 205]).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The critical apparatus includes only the most significant variant readings (minor variants, e.g., <hi rend="italic">wa-</hi> vs. <hi rend="italic">fa-, are
                                disregarded).</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> Five additional manuscripts of the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi>—including two of the Beirut
                        manuscripts employed by Cheikho—were judged to be unreliable and
                        disregarded. The <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> is edited on the
                        basis of the only accessible manuscript: Aleppo, Salem ar. 318 [Sbath
                            1131].<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> As Seleznyov indicates (p. 29, n. 3), the only other manuscript of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi>—Sbath 1130 (year 1231)—is now kept in a private collection in London. See Peter J. Starr, “The <hi rend="italic">Epistle to
                                    Bišr b.
                                    Finḥās</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Maqālah
                                    ʿamilahā ilā Bišr b. Finḥās</hi>) of Ibn Zurʿah (m. A.H. 398 / A.D.
                                    1008): Edition, Translation, and Commentary,” PhD diss.,
                                    University of Cambridge, Emmanuel College, 2000, p.
                            74.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Seleznyov’s publication breaks new ground in two respects. First, it
                        offers, for the first time, a reliable integral text of the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi>. This is particularly significant for those
                        parts of the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi> that had been
                        hitherto available only in Cheikho’s edition: i.e., the Second, Third, and
                        Fourth Sessions. Crucially, Seleznyov’s edition (pp. <hi style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">٥٢</hi>:9–<hi style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">٦٣</hi>:7) includes an important
                        passage from the Second Session in which Elias discusses the notion of <hi rend="italic">ḥulūl</hi>, “inhabitation,” of the Divine Word
                        in Jesus. (The Christology of the Church of the East, espoused by Elias of
                        Nisibis, is peculiar in that it construes the Divine Word and Jesus as two
                        distinct subjects—divine / uncreated and human / created, respectively—and
                        hence is predisposed to speaking about the Incarnation in terms of
                        “inhabitation” of the former in the latter.) This passage had been omitted
                        in Cheikho’s edition for doctrinal reasons,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Cheikho explains this omission in the introduction to his edition: “We shall print these <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi> in our journal with the exception of the Second Session, of which we shall publish only a short fragment, because [this Session] contains Nestorian heresy [<hi rend="italic">al-bidʿa
                                    al-nasṭūriyya</hi>]
                                    concerning the Incarnation of the Lord Christ, and [if we were
                                    to publish it in full], it [would] necessitate a long rebuttal”
                                    (Cheikho, “<hi rend="italic">Maǧālis</hi>,” p. 34; cf. p. 117, n.
                                    1).</p>
                    </note> and had therefore remained unpublished.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Nikolai N. Seleznyov, “«И вселисѧвъ ны»: Боговселение
                                    (<hi rend="italic">al-ḥulūl</hi>) в
                                    мусульманско-христианском диалоге—Илия Нисивинский и Абу-л-Ḳасим
                                    ал-Магриби” [“‘And
                                    Dwelled in Us’: Divine Inhabitation (<hi rend="italic">al-ḥulūl</hi>) in Muslim-Christian Disputation—Elias of Nisibis and Abū l-Qāsim al-Maġribī”], <hi rend="italic">Христiанскiй Востокъ / Christian
                                    Orient</hi> 8 (14) (2017), 297–312. On the peculiarities of the Christology of the Church of the East in an Arab Christian milieu, see also Alexander Treiger, “The Christology of the <hi rend="italic">Letter from
                                    the People of
                                    Cyprus</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                    Eastern Christian
                                Studies</hi> 65.1–2 (2013), 21–48.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Second, Seleznyov’s publication presents an <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi>.
                        This allows him to reconstruct the relationship between the two works.
                        Seleznyov argues (pp. 12–13) that the <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> was written first, in response to Abū l-Qāsim’s
                            letter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> This letter as well as Abū l-Qāsim’s response to Elias’ <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> are also included in Seleznyov’s publication (pp. <foreign xml:lang="ar">١٦٣</foreign>–<foreign xml:lang="ar">١٦٥</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ar">٢٥٥</foreign>–<foreign xml:lang="ar">٢٥٩</foreign> respectively).</p>
                    </note>
                        After Abū l-Qāsim’s death in 1027, Elias compiled the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi>, which is a reworking of the <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> with several omissions and additions. The
                        division into seven “sessions” is, according to Seleznyov, a literary ploy.
                        Though it loosely reflects the chronology of Elias’ meetings with Abū
                        l-Qāsim, it is doubtful that all the subjects treated in the <hi rend="italic">Sessions</hi> were discussed in these meetings. It is more
                        likely that Elias used this occasion to engage more deeply in various
                        subjects of Christian-Muslim polemic.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Minor shortcomings of the publication include occasional misprints,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For example, <hi rend="italic">wa-ḏālika</hi> on p. <hi style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">٢٤</hi>:4 should be corrected to <hi rend="italic">wa-li-ḏālika</hi> (the reading of Vat. ar. 143, fol. 19r); <hi rend="italic">aw
                                    laysa</hi> on p. <hi style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">٣١</hi>:10 should be corrected to <hi rend="italic">a-wa-laysa</hi> (spelled as one word); <hi rend="italic">kāna l-amr
                                    hāḏā</hi> on p. <hi style="font-family:Arial Unicode MS">٥٢</hi>:5 should be corrected to <hi rend="italic">kāna l-amr
                                    ʿalā
                                hāḏā</hi> (the reading of Vat. ar. 143, fol. 42r).</p>
                    </note>
                        an overly literal translation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For example, the term <hi rend="italic">qawl</hi>, literally “statement” but frequently employed in the sense of “teaching” or “doctrine” (cf. the title of al-Ašʿarī’s heresiographical work <hi rend="italic">Maqālāt
                                    al-islāmiyyīn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Doctrines
                                    of the Muslims),
                                    is translated throughout as “statement” [высказывание] or
                                    “affirmation” [утверждение], though “doctrine” [учение] would
                                    have been more idiomatic and, arguably, more
                            precise.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> and omission of folio numbers of the <hi rend="italic">manuscrit de base</hi> (though the beginning of
                        every manuscript page is helpfully indicated). While it is commendable that
                        the Arabic text is reproduced the way it appears in the manuscripts, some
                        punctuation would have been useful for most readers. Occasionally, it is
                        noticeable that the text diverges slightly from the <hi rend="italic">manuscrit de base</hi> with no explanation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For example, Vat. ar. 143, fol. 19r:4 reads: <hi rend="italic">wa-li-ḏālika ḥaṣala l-ḏāt ġayr ʿaraḍ wa-ġayr qābil
                                li-l-aʿrāḍ</hi>; Seleznyov’s edition, p. <foreign xml:lang="ar">٢٤</foreign>:4–5 has: <hi rend="italic">wa-ḏālika
                                    ḥaṣalat l-ḏāt {bi-muǧarradihā—supplied from
                                    manuscripts P ṾṼ} ġayr ʿaraḍ ġayr
                                    qābila li-l-aʿrāḍ.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Despite these minor deficiencies, Seleznyov’s edition of the <hi rend="italic">Book of Sessions</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Epistle to the Vizier Abū l-Qāsim al-Maġribī</hi>—the first to provide
                        a complete and reliable access to these two works—is certainly a landmark
                        contribution to Syriac and Christian Arabic Studies. It is to be hoped that
                        it will stimulate further research into the thought of Elias of Nisibis, one
                        of the most influential medieval Syriac and Christian Arabic theologians and
                        a central figure in the history of Christian-Muslim polemic.</p>
                    
                </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>