<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of: Syriac Encounters: Papers from the Sixth North American
                    Syriac Symposium, Duke University, 26-29 June 2011</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Blake</forename>
                        <surname>Hartung</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Saint Louis University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/review/hv21n1prhartung</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Blake Hartung</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: Syriac Encounters: Papers from the Sixth North American
                            Syriac Symposium, Duke University, 26-29 June 2011</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1PRHartung.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="246" to="251">246–251</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="14"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Maria Doerfler, Emmanuel Fiano, and Kyle Smith, eds. <hi rend="italic">Syriac Encounters: Papers from the Sixth North American
                            Syriac Symposium, Duke University, 26-29 June 2011</hi>, Eastern
                        Christian Studies 20 (Leuven: Peeters, 2015). Pp. xx + 498; €85.</ab>
                    
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                    
                    <p xml:lang="en">This volume comprises a selection of twenty-four papers given at the Sixth
                        North American Syriac Symposium, held at Duke University in 2011. It offers
                        an impressive and fairly comprehensive look at the current state of Syriac
                        scholarship as it has broadened beyond its origins in Semitic philology and
                        “Oriental” Christian studies. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The initial group of essays, “Poetics and Representation,” begins with a
                        plenary lecture by Susan Ashbrook Harvey, in which she argues that
                        privileging commentary literature has left scholarship with an
                        overwhelmingly negative image of Eve in the Syriac tradition. She contends
                        that a more complex portrait of Eve emerges from the Syriac liturgy, which
                        would have been the setting in which most women and men encountered the
                        figure of Eve. Harvey’s interweaving of literary and visual evidence makes
                        this an especially compelling look at the relationship between form and
                        content in biblical exegesis. The second essay in this section, by Jeffrey
                        Wickes, is narrower in focus, examining a single hymn by Ephrem. Wickes
                        gives a nuanced reading of Ephrem’s “self-representation,” and in particular
                        how he used biblical language and characters to position himself and his
                        poetry in relation to God. In the final essay, Robert Kitchen introduces a
                        previously unknown metrical <hi rend="italic">Life of Jacob of
                            Serug</hi> by the eleventh-century miaphysite Ṣa‘īd bar Ṣabūnī. Kitchen
                        describes its manuscripts and summarizes its contents, with specific
                        attention to how Ṣabūnī constructed the life of Jacob in response to his own
                        context. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The second section of papers, “Language and Identity,” begins with an essay
                        by Christine Shepardson. She draws upon recent scholarship on “linguistic
                        diversity” in northern Syria and argues that John Chrysostom invoked
                        differences between “urban” Greek- and simple, faithful “rural”
                        Aramaic-speakers in order to present a rhetorical challenge to his urban
                        Antiochene audience. This essay is especially valuable in that it draws upon
                        new scholarship on language use in Late Antique Syria and applies it to
                        nuance our understanding of Syriac texts. The second and third papers in
                        this section, by Riccardo Contini and Heleen Murre-van den Berg, were
                        initially delivered as plenary lectures at the Symposium. Contini’s essay
                        offers what the author calls “a first tentative approach” to linguistic
                        thought in (particularly East Syrian) exegetical works (p. 96). He finds
                        that Syriac exegetes tended to be unaware of or give little attention to
                        linguistic issues in the Hebrew Bible. Contini concludes that although they
                        paid great attention to the meaning of words, this linguistic reflection did
                        not develop beyond what might be called “folk linguistics” (p. 112). In her
                        incredibly informative paper, Murre-van den Berg explores the revival of
                        Classical Syriac as a “unified and unifying national language” (p. 120) for
                        the Syriac communities of Iraq in the twentieth century, transcending
                        confessional boundaries. Finally, she identifies Iraqi Kurdistan as the
                        current center of the revitalization of Classical Syriac. With the political
                        turmoil and violence currently endangering even the relative stability of
                        northern Iraq, one can only hope that such trends can continue. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The third section of the volume, “Resurrection and Apokatastasis,” begins
                        with an essay by Charles Stang, focusing upon Evagrius of Pontus’
                        reflections on the act of writing his “Letter to Melania,” with attention to
                        how these reflections connect to his understanding of the <hi rend="italic">apokatastasis</hi>, or “restoration of all things.” Stang
                        argues that for Evagrius, “pure, receptive minds” (p. 158) can become God’s
                        “letters,” receiving divine “writing” without mediation. In the second
                        essay, Nestor Kavvadas examines the apologetic objectives of the
                        little-known treatise
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">On Providence </hi>(now
                        recently published by Kavvadas<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text" style="font-weight: bold; font-style: italic; text-decoration: underline; text-align:both; "> Nestor Kavvadas, ed. and trans., <hi rend="italic">Joseph Hazzaya, On Providence: Text, Translation and
                                    Introduction</hi>, Texts and Studies in Eastern Christianity 8
                                (Leiden: Brill, 2016).</p>
                    </note>) by the eighth-century East Syriac
                        author Joseph Ḥazzaya, arguing that this defensive work was written prior to
                        Ḥazzaya’s condemnation by the ecclesial hierarchy in 786/790. Kavvadas’
                        essay highlights Ḥazzaya’s “pedagogical” interpretation of the Genesis
                        creation accounts, and his careful promotion of the doctrine of the <hi rend="italic">apokatastasis</hi>, which flows out of his
                        understanding of divine pedagogy. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Maria Doerfler’s paper on the reception of Evagrian thought in Syria opens
                        the fourth section, “Nile and Tigris.” She focuses on how Philoxenus
                        “socializes” Evagrius by mediating his ascetic thought through an “orthodox”
                        framework. The second article, by Karel Innemée, takes a very different
                        turn, examining the tenth-century wooden doors of the famous Deir al-Surian
                        (“Monastery of the Syrians”) in Egypt. Innemée provides a detailed
                        description of the doors and explains the recent process of conservation
                        which began in 2010. The final paper, delivered by Amir Harrak as a plenary
                        lecture, looks at the conditions of non-Muslims in the Abbasid caliphate,
                        and the caliphate’s wars with the Byzantines from the standpoint of the
                        writings of the ninth-century Syrian Orthodox Patriarch Dionysius of
                        Tell-Maḥrē. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The fifth section of the volume, “East and West” opens with an essay by
                        Nathanael Andrade. Andrade explores a single Edessene legal document from
                        the third century, highlighting the ways that the document expresses Roman,
                        Syrian identity in the idiom of the Syriac language. The second essay, by
                        Alberto Camplani, focuses upon a particular Manichaean claim about
                        Bardaisanite psychology. This essay, while valuable and well-researched, is
                        poorly organized and difficult to navigate. For example, the author
                        interrupts the paper with a lengthy rebuttal of Ilaria Ramelli’s work on
                        Bardaisan, and the conclusion neglects to address the specific Manichaean
                        characterization that prompted the study. In the final essay, Craig Morrison
                        examines the intercessory prayers in the <hi rend="italic">Acts of
                            Thomas</hi> and their function in the narrative. The subtitle of this
                        essay (“Intercessory Prayer in Early Syriac Literature”) is somewhat
                        misleading, as the work focuses almost solely on the <hi rend="italic">Acts</hi>. It also shows very minimal engagement with
                        other scholarly literature, in stark contrast with the other papers in this
                        volume.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The sixth section of the volume, entitled “Greek and Syriac,” begins with a
                        paper by Alberto Rigolio on Syriac monastic transmission of “secular” Greek
                        literature, specifically six texts by Lucian, Plutarch, and Themistius.
                        Rigolio argues that “the moralizing nature of these pieces played an
                        important role in their translation as well as in their transmission within
                        Syriac manuscripts” (p. 296). The next essay, by Kathleen McVey, situates
                        the <hi rend="italic">Letter of Mara bar Serapion</hi> in the
                        context of the “Second Sophistic” movement of the second and third
                        centuries. In particular, she examines the appearance of the character of
                        Palamedes in the letter, noting that the treatment of the character aligns
                        well with his treatment by Greco-Roman authors of the early imperial period.
                        In her plenary lecture, Alison Salvesen focuses on Jacob of Edessa’s revised
                        version of the Old Testament, suggesting that Jacob produced this enigmatic
                        text for pedagogical purposes, to demonstrate the value of Greek in
                        clarifying the Peshitta. This careful and valuable study draws upon evidence
                        for Jacob’s life, examines the format of the earliest manuscripts of his Old
                        Testament, and draws comparisons with biblical citations in his other works.
                        The final essay in this section, by Ute Possekel, deals with disputes
                        between Chalcedonians and miaphysites through the lens of the eighth-century
                        correspondence between Leo of Harran, a Chalcedonian, and his friend Eliya,
                        a convert to miaphysitism. Possekel takes the friendly correspondence as
                        evidence for the presence of ongoing dialogue (and not simply polemic)
                        between the communities.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Sidney Griffith’s plenary lecture begins the seventh section of the volume,
                        entitled “History and Influence.” This essay offers an excellent overview of
                        the<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> status quaestionis</hi>
                        regarding the relation of Syriac to the study of early Islam and the Qur’an.
                        Specifically, he argues that the “Syriacisms” of the Qur’an and its
                        conscious critiques of Christian theology and practices indicates that the
                        Arabic-speaking Christian “dialogue partners” (p. 393) of the Qur’an emerged
                        from Syriac-speaking traditions known to have existed on the Arabian
                        periphery. In the second essay of this section, Andy Hilkens examines the
                        depiction of the Turks in the twelfth-century Syriac <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of Michael the Great and its two Armenian
                        translations. Hilkens sheds light on the dynamic processes of translation in
                        Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages, arguing that the two Armenian
                        translations are, in fact, independent adaptations. The third essay, by
                        Alessandro Mengozzi, offers an introduction to the <hi rend="italic">Book of Khamis bar Qardaḥe</hi>, including a survey of the
                        scholarship, an overview of its extant manuscripts, and a description of its
                        contents. It is, therefore, an excellent introductory resource for future
                        research.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The final section of the volume, “Text and Object,” begins with an essay by
                        Jeanne-Nicole Mellon Saint-Laurent on “relic discourse” in Syriac
                        hagiographies which present relics as sources of healing, as substitutes for
                        the presence of the saints, and as representations of “friendship with the
                        saint” (p. 446). These aspects of “relic discourse” explain the anxiety
                        which led to episodes of “relic theft” (p. 449), and to ecclesial
                        regulations on their transportation. The second essay, by Stephanie Bolz,
                        examines three particular Syriac magic bowls from Sasanian Persia.
                        Specifically, Bolz argues that the “adjuration formulae” on the bowls are
                        Jewish in origin. The presence of Jewish formulae in Syriac may attest to
                        widespread transmission of magical formulae across religious boundaries.
                        Lucas Van Rompay’s essay, the final paper of the volume, catalogues two
                        Syriac manuscripts held by Duke University: a West Syrian Gospel manuscript,
                        likely from the tenth or eleventh century, and a Maronite divine office,
                        cop-ied sometime between the sixteenth and eighteenth century.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The great weakness of conference proceedings volumes is that the number of
                        authors and diversity of subject matter can often make them feel disjointed
                        or incoherent. Unsurprisingly, this volume occasionally has such an uneven
                        quality. The editors of this volume should therefore be commended for the
                        introduction and mode of organization, by which they attempt to weave
                        together these disparate pieces of research on the basis of common themes.
                        That being said, the greatest benefit of this volume is something akin to
                        that of reading an issue of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi>: one
                        receives a broad sampling of current research across the various
                        sub-disciplines of Syriac scholarship. For this reason, this volume will no
                        doubt be a valuable resource for libraries and scholars for many years to
                        come. </p>
                </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>