<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Review of: Syrische Handschriften. Teil 2: Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung /
                    Syriac Texts from the Berlin Turfan Collection</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Grigory</forename>
                        <surname>Kessel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences / University of Manchester</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2018</date>
                <idno>Volume 21.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/review/hv21n1prkessel</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Grigory Kessel</author>
                        <title level="a">Review of: Syrische Handschriften. Teil 2: Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung /
                            Syriac Texts from the Berlin Turfan Collection</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol21/HV21N1PRKessel.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="21">21</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="218" to="223">218–223</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="9"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-07-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Erica C. D. Hunter and Mark Dickens, eds., <hi rend="italic">Syrische Handschriften. Teil 2: Texte der Berliner Turfansammlung /
                            Syriac Texts from the Berlin Turfan Collection</hi>, Verzeichnis der
                        orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland 5.2 (Stuttgart: Steiner, 2014).
                        Pp. vi + 505. € 84.</ab>
                </div>
            <div type="body">
                    <p xml:lang="en">The catalogue of the Syriac fragments under review has been long awaited
                        and fills one of the major desiderata in the field of Syriac studies. It
                        contains a detailed description of the fragments that were found during the
                        four missions conducted by the German Turfan Expeditions between 1902 and
                        1914 and that are kept at present in three different locations in Berlin:
                        the largest number is at the Staatsbibliothek (shelfmark SyrHT), and two
                        smaller sets are at the division of Turfanforschung of the
                        Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften and the Museum für
                        Asiatische Kunst, respectively.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The volume appeared in the series <hi rend="italic">Verzeichnis
                            der orientalischen Handschriften in Deutschland</hi>, committed to
                        cataloguing the Oriental manuscripts preserved in German collections, and
                        thereby constitutes a sequel to the catalogue of Julius Assfalg.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">J. Assfalg, <hi rend="italic">Syrische
                                    Handschriften: syrische, karšunische, christlich-palästinische,
                                    neusyrische und mandäische Handschriften</hi>, Verzeichnis der orientalischen
                                    Handschriften in Deutschland 5 (Wiesbaden: Steiner,
                                1963).</p>
                    </note> Although the appearance of the catalogue
                        marks the completion of the general enterprise of cataloguing the Syriac
                        manuscripts in Germany, there still remains some work to be done.
                        Particularly indispensable is an up-to-date list of the actual holdings of
                        libraries and collections as many changes took place over the course of the
                            20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. For example, some
                        manuscripts that feature in the catalogue of the Staatsbibliothek (then
                        Königliche Bibliothek) prepared by Eduard Sachau<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">E. Sachau, <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss der syrischen Handschriften der Königlichen
                                    Bibliothek zu
                                Berlin</hi>, 2 vols. (Berlin, 1899).
                            </p>
                    </note> are no longer in Berlin (but, for instance, in Krakow),
                        whereas a large group of manuscripts described by Assfalg (those in Tübingen
                        and Marburg) were returned to Berlin in the 1970s; the private collection of
                        consul C. W. Adam in Goslar forms now a part of the Schøyen collection. The
                        whereabouts of some private collections that once belonged to Syriac
                        scholars in Germany are unknown (for instance, the one of Gustav Bickell).
                        Moreover, some German libraries acquired a number of manuscripts that thus
                        far remain uncatalogued. Likewise, an unknown number of Syriac manuscripts
                        is preserved among the Syriac diaspora (coming mostly from the Tūr ʿAbdīn
                        region), both at churches and in private hands.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The cataloguing of the Syriac Turfan materials was implemented within a
                        project <hi rend="italic">The Christian Library from Turfan</hi>
                        (2008–2011) that was funded by the Arts and Humanities Research Council of
                        the United Kingdom and was based at the School of Oriental and African
                        studies in London under the leadership of Dr. Erica C. D. Hunter. The
                        present catalogue is a companion to other volumes in the same series dealing
                        with Turfan manuscripts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It happens all too seldom that the Syriac ecclesiastical authorities
                        express manifestly their appreciation of an academic research project. That
                        is why it is all the more gratifying to see a formal preface by the late
                        Catholicos of the Church of the East, Mar Dinkha IV (1935–2015). One may
                        hope that this is a valid token of a positive attitude that will lead to
                        mutual cooperation in the future, particularly with regard to the study of
                        manuscript collections and archives that belong to ecclesiastical
                        bodies.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Most of the Syriac fragments were discovered in the ruins of a former
                        monastery of the Church of the East, located at Shuïpang near the village of
                        Bulayïq, about ten kilometers north of Turfan (for other locations see
                        Appendix VI). One should bear in mind that the Berlin fragments form just a
                        part of all the Syriac fragments discovered in the Turfan region. Whereas
                        most of the Syriac fragments were transferred to Berlin, smaller sets were
                        brought to St. Petersburg<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">N. Smelova, “Manuscrits chrétiens de Qara Qoto: nouvelles perspec-tives de recherche,” in P. G. Borbone and P. Marsone, eds., <hi rend="italic">Le
                                    christianisme syriaque en Asie centrale et en Chine</hi>, Études
                                    syriaques 12 (Paris: Geuthner, 2015), 215–36.</p>
                    </note>
                        and other libraries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For example, Dr. Hidemi Takahashi kindly informs me that a few fragments are preserved at the Ryukoku University in Japan.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The volume consists of three parts of uneven length. The Introduction (pp.
                        1–7) provides a historical background to the Syriac manuscript material from
                        Turfan, including its discovery, transfer to Berlin, and scholarship. Then
                        follows a catalogue arranged by current holding institution (pp. 8–424). The
                        authors of the catalogue spared no pains and prepared seventeen informative
                        appendices (pp. 425–496), aimed at effective usage of the material
                        described.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The catalogue is well designed and provides elaborate description of each
                        fragment, taking into consideration all possible aspects of both physical
                        form and content (overview on pp. 8–12). Physical description includes
                        measurements (line spacing, line length, and size of the margins),
                        condition, number of lines, presence of ruling, colour of the inks used for
                        text and punctuation, palaeographic features, system of punctuation, quire
                        marks, rubrics, corrections, etc. (the fragments are grouped according to
                        the presence of some of those physical features in Appendix X).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> For a synthetic survey, see M. Dickens, “Scribal Practices in the Turfan Christian Community,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies </hi>13 (2013),
                            3–28.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The entries follow a sequential order within each of the three collections.
                        The total number of entries amounts to 481 (Staatsbibliothek 388,
                        Turfanforschung 86, Museum für Asia-tische Kunst 7), but some of those
                        occasionally contain more than one fragment. If fragments belonging to the
                        same manuscripts could be identified, this is indicated at the end of the
                        entry (as well as in Appendix XI). Each entry explicitly acknowledges the
                        scholar responsible for the identification of the text (overview in Appendix
                        XVI). Given the fragmentary nature of the material, it is understandable
                        that some fragments remain unidentified (listed in Appendix II). If the text
                        is not identified the authors offer a provisional characterization of its
                        genre.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The main part of the catalogue covers the fragments in Syriac (including
                        those transcribed in Uighur script as well as bilingual, usually
                        Syriac-Sogdian ones) from the Turfan collection, whereas Appendix XV
                        describes the fragments in Sogdian, New Persian and Uighur with embedded
                        Syriac citations and rubrics (33 in total).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The vast majority of the fragments is limited to a page or even a part of
                        it, bifolia are rare (listed in Appendix V), and there is just one single
                        substantial manuscript (MIK III 45) which is considered to be the earliest
                        witness to the text of East Syriac Ḥudra.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The edition has recently been published: E. C. D. Hunter and J. F. Coakley, eds., <hi rend="italic">A Syriac
                                    Service-Book from Turfan. Museum für Asiatische Kunst, Berlin MS
                                    MIK III 45</hi>,
                                    Berliner Turfantexte 39 (Turnhout: Brepols,
                            2017).</p>
                    </note> In terms of ecclesiastical affiliation, the vast
                        majority of the fragments belongs to the Church of the East, whereas one
                        fragment, described as a ‘draft letter to an unnamed Byzantine official’
                        (SyrHT 2), possibly bears traces of Melkite authorship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A possible connection to Melkite tradition was also discerned in the Sogdian material, namely in two fragments from a Psalter in Sogdian script with Greek incipits; see N. Sims-Williams, “A Greek-Sogdian Bilingual from Bulayïq,” in <hi rend="italic">La Persia e
                                    Bisanzio</hi>, Atti dei Convegni Lincei 201 (Rome: Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei, 2004), 623–631; N. Sims-Williams, “A New Fragment of the Book of Psalms in Sogdian,” in D. Bumazhnov, E. Grypeou, T. B. Sailors, and A. Toepel, eds., <hi rend="italic">Bibel,
                                    Byzanz und Christlicher Orient: Festschrift für Stephen Gerö zum 65.
                                Geburtstag</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2011), 461–66.</p>
                    </note>
                        As far as the dating is concerned, none of the fragments contains a
                        colophon, but a range between the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        and 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century is usually accepted
                        (for some fragments a more precise dating is offered).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In terms of genre (overview in Appendix VII), the most frequent one is
                        liturgy. Thus, one finds liturgical Psalters, New Testament lectionaries,
                        Ḥudra and prayer books. There are at least two hagiographic texts (the <hi rend="italic">Life of Mar Barshabba</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Life of Mar George</hi>), as well as calendrical and
                        pharmaceutical fragments. Among the unidentified texts are fragments that
                        appear to belong to a polemic dialogue between a Christian and a Jew, as
                        well as one philosophical text (seemingly related to Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Categories</hi> that might be a paraphrase or a
                        commentary).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Apparently, the critical value of the Syriac material from Turfan lies in
                        its contribution to the study of the East Syriac liturgical tradition. As
                        shown in a number of studies,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> E. C. D. Hunter, “The Christian Library from Turfan: SYR HT 41-42-43, An Early Exemplar of the Ḥuḏrā”, <hi rend="italic">Hugoye:
                                    Journal of Syriac
                                    Studies</hi> 15.2 (2012), 281–291, S. P. Brock and N. Sims-Williams, “An Early Fragment from the East Syriac Baptismal Service from Turfan”, <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
                                    Christiana
                                Periodica</hi> 77.1 (2011), 81–92.</p>
                    </note>
                        the liturgical texts found among the Turfan fragments are the earliest
                        witnesses for some of the East Syriac liturgical books.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The same applies to other genres. As demonstrated by Miklós Maróth,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> M. Maróth, “Eine unbekannte Version der Georgios-Legende aus Turfan,” <hi rend="italic">Altorientalische
                                Forschungen</hi> 18.1 (1991), 86–108.</p>
                    </note>
                        the <hi rend="italic">Life of Mar George</hi> (SyrHT 95, 359, 360,
                        361, 362, 364, 365, 381) represents a previously unattested ancient
                        recension of the text. The prayer-amulets contained in the collection are
                        the ancient predecessors of the much later East Syriac books of charms that
                        were proudced from the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century
                            onwards.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> E. C. D. Hunter, “Traversing Time and Location: A Prayer-Amulet of Mar Tamsis from Turfan,” in Li Tang and D. Winkler, eds., <hi rend="italic">From the
                                    Oxus River to the Chinese Shores: Studies on East Syriac
                                    Christianity in China and Central
                                Asia</hi>, Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 5 (Zürich / Münster: LIT, 2013), 25–41.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Over the course of the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and
                        beginning 21<hi rend="sup">st</hi> century many Syriac
                        fragments have been studied and published (a list with relevant bibliography
                        can be found in Appendix XVII). Nevertheless, much still remains to be done
                        and there can be no doubt that this catalogue will attract scholarly
                        attention and lead to new research. This is all the more feasible now as all
                        the fragments are freely accessible at the website of the International
                        Dunhuang Project (<ref target="HYPERLINK"/>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The catalogue itself is also freely available at <ref target="HYPERLINK"/> (accessed on April 4, 2018).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cataloguing fragments is not a gratifying labour, and the work becomes all
                        the more painstaking if one deals with ancient witnesses to texts that can
                        hardly be compared with the extant (usually more recent or simply different)
                        versions. The Syriac fragments from Turfan is a unique treasure-trove for
                        the study of the missionary activity of the Church of the East, and we all
                        should commend the authors for their responsible work and attention to
                        detail.</p>
                </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>