<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Coat of Arms of Moses of Mardin</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>András</forename>
                        <surname>Mércz</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Pázmány Péter Catholic University<lb/>
                        Avicenna Institute of Middle Eastern Studies</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2019</date>
                <idno>Volume 22.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv22n2mercz</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>András Mércz</author>
                        <title level="a">The Coat of Arms of Moses of Mardin</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol22/HV22N2Mercz.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2019</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="345" to="393">345-393</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="2"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Moses of Mardin</term>
                    <term>Coat of Arms</term>
                    <term>Ferdinand I</term>
                    <term>Catholic</term>
                    <term>Syrian Orthodox</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2019-08-28">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The core of this paper is an edition of
                    Moses of Mardin’s grant of arms, which, accompanied by relevant excerpts from his
                    unpublished Syriac correspondence, provides new information on the life of this
                    16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century Syrian Orthodox monk, who played an
                    important role at the dawn of the European Syriac scholarship. He was not only
                    granted with a coat of arms, but he was also received by Ferdinand I, which shows
                    the importance of his major achievement, the edition of the Syriac New Testament.
                    The paper points out that he lived in the Jesuit college in Vienna with the scions
                    of the most influential noblemen, which illustrates his social milieu. It will be
                    argued that he remained Syrian Orthodox despite his earlier Catholic profession of
                    faith. It will also be argued that Moses acquired the right to bear the described
                    coat of arms without ennoblement, and he probably did not use it.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century Syrian Orthodox monk, Moses of
                    Mardin, is a key figure in the history of European Syriac scholarship, who did
                    pioneering work in several fields. He took on the lion’s share of the <hi
                        rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of the Syriac New Testament, and he was
                    the teacher of the first generation of Syriac scholars in Europe. As a scribe,
                    he copied a vast amount of manuscripts, and as a diplomatic envoy, he worked on
                    the unity between the Syrian Orthodox and the Roman Catholic Churches.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The two most important corpora of sources on him are the scribal inscriptions
                    and colophons of the manuscripts he copied<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Levi della Vida, <hi rend="italic">Ricerche
                                sulla formazione del più antico fondo dei manoscritti orientali
                                della biblioteca vaticana</hi>. Studi e testi 92. (Città del
                            Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1939), 206–215, 415–423, 435;
                            J. Leroy, “Une copie syriaque du Missale Romanum de Paul III et son
                            arrière-plan historique” (Mélanges de l’Université Saint Joseph 46
                            [1970–1971]), 355–382 and P. G. Borbone, ““Monsignore Vescovo di Soria”,
                            also Known as Moses of Mardin, Scribe and Book Collector” (Khristianskii
                            Vostok 8 [2017]), 79–114.</p>
                    </note> and his Syriac correspondence. Ten letters came down to us from the
                    period 1553–1556. Two of these letters were edited and translated into Latin by
                    Andreas Müller, but the rest are still unpublished.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. Müller, “Epistolae duae Syriacae amoebaeae. Una
                            Mosis Mardeni, Sacerdotis Syri, altera Andreae Masii, JCti et Consil.
                            Olim Cliviaci cum versione et notis,” in <hi rend="italic">Symbolae
                                syriacae, </hi>ed. A. Müller (Berolini, 1673), 1–36. Jan Wim
                            Wesselius was planning to publish the rest, but later abandoned this
                            project. Cf. J. W. Wesselius, “The Syriac Correspondance of Andreas
                            Masius : A Preliminary Report,” in <hi rend="italic">V. Symposium
                                Syriacum, 1988: Katholieke Universiteit, Leuven, 29‒31 août
                                1988</hi>, Orientalia Christiana Analecta 236, ed. R. Lavenant
                            (Roma: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1990), 21–29. Pier
                            Giorgio Borbone has recently quoted an excerpt from a letter and
                            announced his intention to publish the whole corpus. Cf. Borbone,
                            Monsignore, 84 n. 26, 113–114. The study and the edition of the letters
                            constitute also the basis of my forthcoming PhD.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Apart from these, Moses’ name pops up sporadically in a great variety of
                    sources. The last two such discoveries challenged earlier conceptions of the
                    beginning of Moses’ career. In 2017, Pier Giorgio Borbone drew attention to a
                    letter written by the Patriarch Ignatius Niꜥamatallah (1557–1576) calling Moses
                    ‘slanderer’ and ‘excommunicated’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> P. G. Borbone, “From Tur ꜥAbdin to Rome: The
                            Syro-Orthodox Presence in Sixteenth-Century Rome,” In Syriac in Its
                            Multi-Cultural Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium,
                            Mardin Artuklu University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April
                            2012, Mardin, Eastern Christian Studies 23, eds. H.G.B. Teule, E.
                            Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru, M.S. Toprak (Leuven: Peeters, 2017),
                            277–288, here 285–287.</p>
                    </note> These words could still be considered as unkind and malignant remarks
                    against someone who might have been his rival in the European market of Oriental
                    scholars. However, another document recently published by Giacomo Cardinali
                    confirms the patriarch’s statements. In a letter sent to Marcello Cervini in
                    1549, two Syrian Orthodox pilgrims warned the cardinal to be cautious with
                    Moses. They claimed that he had been excommunicated by the patriarch<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> This is an intriguing information, because at that
                            time Niꜥamatallah’s predecessor, Ignatius ꜥAbdallah I (1521–1557) sat on
                            the patriarchal throne, who, according to the current state of research,
                            sent Moses to Rome as his envoy. If this letter proves to be accurate,
                            Moses’ mission will need to be revised.</p>
                    </note> and later when he continued his atrocities in Cyprus by forging a letter
                    in the patriarch’s name in order to deceive the Roman Pontiff,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> If Moses did so, it would not be unprecedented. Cf.
                            N. S. Smelova and N. A. Lipatov-Chicherin, “Georgii, arkhiepiskop
                            Damasskii: samozvancheskaia intriga v istorii otnoshenii Maronitskoi
                            Tserkvi i Sviatogo Prestola v seredine XVI v” (Khristianskii Vostok 6
                            [2013]), 244–311.</p>
                    </note> he was chased away from the Syrian Orthodox community.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Cardinali, “Ritratto di Marcello Cervini en
                            orientaliste (con precisazioni alle vicende di Petrus Damascenus, Mosè
                            di Mārdīn ed Heliodorus Niger)” (Bibliothèque d’Humanisme et Renaissance
                            80:1 [2018], 77–98 and 80:2 [2018], 325–343), here 340.</p>
                    </note> This letter raises many questions,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Why did they send the letter from Paris? Was the
                            letter written in Italian? If they, as pilgrims, were only in transit in
                            Rome, how did they learn Italian? Or else, who helped them in the
                            translation? How did they get in contact with the cardinal?</p>
                    </note> but together with Niꜥamatallah’s record, these two independent sources
                    make it worth considering that Moses might have had a bad record in his
                        homeland.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Incidentally, it might happen that Moses himself
                            also referred to his expulsion in one of his manuscripts. In the
                            colophon of the first manuscript he composed in Rome in 1549, he wrote:
                                “<hi rend="italic">Written by the wretched Moses when he took refuge
                                in God in the year 1860 of the Greek Alexander, son of Philip</hi>”.
                            London, British Library, Ms. Harley 5512, f. 178r. Leroy tentatively
                            interpreted the expression ‘refuge in God’ (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܬܓܘܣ
                                ܒܵܐܬܸܘܵܣ</foreign>) as ‘<hi rend="italic">pérégrination en Dieu</hi>’
                            (Une copie syriaque, 367.), but in the light of the newest discoveries
                            it can be understood also literally, i.e. ‘<hi rend="italic">he fled for
                                succour to God</hi>’, since Moses might have been actually chased
                            away from his home.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> While these documents undermine Moses’ reputation, a new source bearing witness
                    to his career came up in the National Archives of Austria, where a draft of a
                    charter granting a coat of arms to Moses has been preserved. This paper aims to
                    study and publish this unique document, which – along with relevant information
                    from his unpublished Syriac letters – enriches our knowledge on Moses’ Viennese
                    life with new elements, e.g. on his relationship with King Ferdinand I, on his
                    dwelling place, and his suspected reordination as a Catholic priest.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1. Description of the document</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Patents of arms or grant of arms (<hi rend="italic">litterae armales</hi>) are
                    elegant diplomas issued on parchment granting the use of a coat of arms to their
                    possessor. The original copy of the diploma was taken by Moses and is likely
                    lost. The document preserved among the Acts of Imperial Ennoblement
                    (Reichsadelsakten–RAA) under the shelfmark 272.57 in the Austrian State Archives
                    is the draft of the diploma. It is written on paper and comprises five folios
                    with the cover. The page in the middle (f. 3) differs from the rest of the
                    document in size and material; it is visibly an addition. The text is full of
                    interlinear and marginal interpolations, many words are blacked out, and almost
                    half of the second page (f. 2v) is crossed out.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Another copy of the text is also preserved in the archives, since, following the
                    chancellery practice, the final version of the grant was copied into a registry
                    (Reichsregisterbuch). This contains only the first part of the document, until
                    the first lines of f. 4r of the draft, concluding: “<hi rend="italic">ac
                        decentibus actibus etc ut in forma communi. Datum Viennae die XV mensis
                        Martii Anno Domini 1556</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> RK Reichsregister Ferdinand I. 7, 249r–250r. I owe
                            this reference to dr. András Oross, who helped my research in the
                            archives a lot, so I would like to express here my deepest gratitude to
                            him.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The number of corrections in the draft version is surprising, especially because
                    the text of the grant followed a standardized template and it could be easily
                    copied out from a formulary.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> L. Biewer and E. Henning, <hi rend="italic">Wappen.
                                Handbuch der Heraldik</hi>, (Köln–Weimar–Wien: Böhlau Verlag, 2017),
                            45–47; Csízi I., “Kora újkori nemesi címerek” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Heraldika</hi>, ed. Kollega Tarsoly I. and Kovács E. (Budapest:
                            Tarsoly Kiadó, 2018), 155–208, here 163–165.</p>
                    </note> It starts by giving the name and the titles of the issuer (<hi
                        rend="italic">intitulatio</hi>). This part in our case is only one word:
                    Ferdinand, since the draft omits the enumeration of his titles. Granting coats
                    of arms was a royal privilege in most European states. In the Holy Roman Empire,
                    the emperor delegated the right to the imperial counts palatin (<hi
                        rend="italic">comites palatini</hi>), in the Habsburg Monarchy they could be
                    donated by the Archduke of Austria, or later by the princes of Tirol as
                        well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Pfeifer, “Wappenbriefe (unter besonderer
                            Berücksichtigung der Tiroler Verhältnisse)” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Quellenurkunde der Habsburgmonarchie (16.-18. Jahrhundert). Ein
                                exemplarisches Handbuch</hi>, ed. J. Pauser, M. Scheutz and Th.
                            Winkelbauer (Wien–München: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, 2004), 291–302, here
                            294–297).</p>
                    </note> Then comes the <hi rend="italic">arenga,</hi> which refers to the
                    magnanimity of the king or emperor and his endeavour to reward merits. This
                    particular document makes reference to the right and just act, that the royal
                    majesty rewards in his munificence not only his subjects but also “aliens and
                    foreigners, whose integrity, moral uprightness and proper knowledge of sciences”
                    (f. 2r) make them commendable. The inscription (<hi rend="italic"
                        >inscriptio</hi>) mentions the recipient of the grant of arms and the
                    narration (<hi rend="italic">narratio</hi>) describes his merits. The
                    disposition (<hi rend="italic">dispositio</hi>) contains the description of the
                    arms and crest along with a long enumeration of the possibilities of
                    application. The <hi rend="italic">narratio</hi> and the description of the arms
                    are the two paragraphs containing personal information, where the scribe could
                    not continue the monotonous copying. It is no wonder that this latter section
                    contains the most corrections in Moses’ document, which will be discussed in
                    detail below. Then comes a threat of punishment (<hi rend="italic">sanctio</hi>)
                    for those who would prevent the recipient from the exercise of the right granted
                    to him. The fine was 25 marks of pure gold, which was to be paid equally into
                    the royal treasury and for the offended side. The corroboration (<hi
                        rend="italic">corroboratio</hi>) emphasizes that the document was issued
                    with the signature and the seal of the king. The closing protocol (<hi
                        rend="italic">eschatocollum</hi>) contains the date and signature, but on
                    this draft understandably only the date is present.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The largest portion of the text follows a pattern, but a few elements are
                    individual to Moses. These will be discussed in the following one by one.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1. Moses and Ferdinand I (<hi rend="italic">narratio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The coat of arms was granted to Moses by Ferdinand I, who was at that time
                    archduke of Austria as well as king of Bohemia, Hungary, and Croatia. Former
                    sources bore witness to their relationship from Moses’ point of view. According
                    to the Latin dedication of the Syriac Gospels, for instance, which Moses copied
                    for the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps </hi>and offered to the king, he
                    reckoned Ferdinand as a benefactor of Syriac Christians and a strong supporter
                    against Muslims and Nestorians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 102–103. The manuscript has
                            been preserved in Vienna (Österreichische Nationalbibliothek, Ms. Syr.
                            1.) and is accessible online: <ref
                                target="http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/100025DA"
                                >http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/100025DA</ref>.</p>
                    </note> One of the most obvious points of significance of this grant of arms is
                    that it is a formal acknowledgement of Moses’ achievements by the king and
                    witness to their relationship from Ferdinand’s side. The king enumerated Moses’
                    merits with the following words:</p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block">Since you, the aforementioned Syriac priest Moses of Mardin,
                    are thoroughly known to us on account of the excellent talents of your
                    intellect, your piety, your conscientiousness and the sanctity of your life
                    thanks to the trustworthy and distinguished testimony of many people, and we
                    have understood to what a great praise you have cared for the Christian republic
                    by setting to type the New Testament and other very holy books in the Syriac
                    language, and finally what labour and diligence you have invested in this
                    effort, we must not only acknowledge all these things with a generous heart, but
                    also remunerate them with an exceptional decoration and indeed with the favour
                    of our munificence. (f. 2r–2v).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Words of appreciation were specific to the grants of arms, but giving such a
                    long account for the motivation of the issue of the document was extremely rare.
                    Such a personalised wording and the familiar tone applied here were fairly
                        exceptional.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Biewer and Henning, Wappen, 45–46; D. Maier,
                            “Überlegungen zum Formular von Wappenbriefen der Reichskanzlei
                            (1338–1500)” (Mitteilungen des Instituts für Österreichische
                            Geschichtsforschung 126 [2018]), 34–52, here 39–40, 42.</p>
                    </note> Departure from the template might suggest a close or special relation
                    between the donator and the grantee. In fact, Moses’ personal acquaintance with
                    the king is attested by another evidence, too.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> One of the most exciting events Moses reported to his main correspondent,
                    Andreas Masius,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Andreas Masius was a Flemish humanist, who learned
                            Syriac from Moses. He was the addressee of eight letters and the sender
                            of one letter. On his figure see A. van Roey, “Les études syriaques
                            d'Andreas Masius” (Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica 9 [1978]), 141–158;
                            R. J. Wilkinson, <hi rend="italic">Orientalism, Aramaic and Kabbalah in
                                the Catholic Reformation. The First Printing of the Syriac New
                                Testament,</hi> (Leiden‒Boston: Brill, 2007), 77–94; <hi
                                rend="italic">idem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Kabbalistic Scholars
                                of the Antwerp Polyglot Bible,</hi> (Leiden‒Boston: Brill, 2007),
                            39–48 and W. François, “Andreas Masius (1514–1573): Humanist, Exegete
                            and Syriac Scholar” (Journal of Eastern Christian Studies 61:3 [2009]),
                            199–244. </p>
                    </note> was undoubtedly his meeting with king Ferdinand I. He proudly described
                    this episode in a letter with the following words: “I would like you to know,
                    oh, my brother, that I wrote the Gospels on parchment (<hi rend="italic">super
                        carta bergamono</hi>). It is a nice script with gold and silver. I offered
                    it to the king. He was delighted and shook hands with me, as it is customary in
                        Germany<hi rend="italic">”.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 26
                            March 1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 16r. <foreign  xml:lang="syr">ܕܥ ܐܘ̄
                                ܐܚܝ ܕܐܢܿܐ ܟܬܒܿܬ ܠܐܘܢܓܠܝܘܢ ܥܠ ܘܪ̈ܩܐ ܕܡܸܫܟܐ </foreign>super carta
                            bergamono<foreign  xml:lang="syr"> ܟܬܝܒܬܐ ܫܦܝܪܬܐ.
                                ܥܡ ܕܗܒܐ ܘܣܹܐܡܐ. ܘܩܪܒܬܗ ܠܡܠܟܐ. ܘܚܕܹܝ ܒܗ ܣܰܓܝܼ ܘܝܗܒ ܠܝ ܐܝܕܗ ܐܝܟ ܥܝܳܕܐ
                                ܕܓܰܪܡܲܐܢܝܲܐ܀</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </note> Unfortunately, the protocols of the royal receptions of this period
                    perished in a fire, so we do not know more about this event, but it had to take
                    place sometime between 10–15 August or 9 October and 9 December 1554, because
                    after that Ferdinand set off to Augsburg.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. von Gévay, <hi rend="italic">Itinerar Kaiser
                                Ferdinanďs I. 1521–1564</hi>, (Wien: Strauhssel. Witwe Und Sommer,
                            1843).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Moses probably gained admittance to the king thanks to Johann Albrecht
                    Widmanstetter, who was, without doubt, one of those trustworthy and
                    distinguished people from whose testimony Ferdinand heard about Moses. He was
                    chancellor of Lower Austria and an intimate counsellor of the king.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> On him see M. Müller, <hi rend="italic">Johann
                                Albrecht von Widmanstetter 1506-1557. Sein Leben und Wirken</hi>,
                            (Bamberg: Verlag der Handels Druckerei, 1907); Wilkinson, Orientalism,
                            137–169 and U. Cecini, “Johann Albrecht Widmanstetter” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Christian-Muslim Relations: A Bibliographical History.
                                Vol. VII. 1500-1600</hi>, eds. D. Thomas and J. Chesworth,
                            (Leiden–Boston: Brill, 2015), 235–239.</p>
                    </note> As one of the few scholars in Europe who had a basic knowledge of
                    Syriac, he was the one who invited Moses to Vienna after an unexpected
                    encounter. Moses enjoyed Widmanstetter’s hospitality for some time and spent
                    altogether two and a half year between 1553 and 1556 in the Habsburg
                        capital.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Giovanni Rignalmo from
                            Vienna, 23 November 1553: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f.
                            21r <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܐ
                                ܣܓܝ ܚܘܒܐ ܡܚܲܘܐ ܠܝܼ. ܗܘ ܘܐܢܬܬܗ</foreign> “<hi rend="italic">What a great
                                love he and his wife showed towards me.</hi>”</p>
                    </note> He bestowed much of his time on the <hi rend="italic">editio
                        princeps</hi>, therefore it is not surprising that his contribution to the
                    printing of the Syriac New Testament had been highlighted as one of his major
                    achievements in the grant of arms. As for the other very holy books in the
                    Syriac language also mentioned in the document, they can be also identified.
                    Moses copied the book of Ezekiel, a Beth Gazo, which is a Syriac liturgical
                    book, and two grammatical treatises of Barhebraeus. Furthermore, he completed a
                    Syriac (Maronite) Missal and composed two Syriac-Arabic dictionaries.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 101–106.</p>
                    </note> All these manuscripts enriched Widmanstetter’s private collection.
                    Apparently, Moses’ and Widmanstetter’s cooperation was mutually beneficial,
                    therefore, keeping in mind Widmanstetter’s influence at the chancellery, it is
                    not unrealistic to suppose that he might have been the initiator of granting
                    Moses a coat of arms.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The granting of the coat of arms on 15 March 1556 could have provided an
                    opportunity to another official reception by the king,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Ferdinand was in Vienna in these days. Cf. Gévay,
                            Itinerar.</p>
                    </note> although Moses did not give a report about it in his correspondence.
                    What we do know is that he was asked to complete a mission, as it becomes clear
                    from the letter he sent to Masius after leaving Vienna: “I arrived in Venice
                    with the books the king sent to our patriarch. These are namely the books of the
                    New Testament we completed in Vienna. And know, oh my brother, that the king
                    ordered 1000 books of the New Testament: he took 500 of them for himself and he
                    sent with me 300 to two patriarchs: to our patriarch and to the patriarch of the
                        Maronites.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Venice, 1
                            August 1556: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 11r <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܝܬ ܠܐܒܼܷܢܸܬܣܝܲܐ ܥܡ
                                ܟܬ̈ܒܐ ܕܫܕܪ ܡܲܠܟܐ ܠܦܛܪܝܪܟܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܗܿܢܘܕܝܢ.ܟܬ̈ܒܐ ܕܚܿܕܬܐ ܕܚܬܼܡܢܢ
                                ܒܿܰܒܼܝܷܐܢܢܲܐ. ܕܰܥ ܐܵܘ̄ ܐܳܚܝ ܕܥܒܼܕ ܡܲܠܟܐ ܐܰܠܦܵܐ ܟܬܵܒܵܐ ܕܚܿܕܬܐ.
                                ܚܲܡܸܫܡܵܐܐ ܡܸܢܗܘܿܢ ܐܷܚܼܕ ܐܢܘܢ ܡܲܠܟܐ. ܘܲܬܠܵܬܡܵܐܐ ܫܕܪ ܠܬܪܝܢ ܦܛܪ̈ܝܪܟܸܐ
                                ܥܲܡܝ. ܠܦܛܪܝܪܟܐ ܕܝܠܢ. ܘܕܡܰܪܽܘ̈ܢܵܝܸܐ..</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </note> As for the grant of arms, he did not mention it. On the contrary, he
                    complained to Masius saying: “He (scil. the king Ferdinand) gave me 200 books
                    after all this weariness. And he did not give me any dinars, but only 20
                    thalers. God knows that I am saying the truth in front of Him and you. From
                    Vienna to Venice, I spent the money on books<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Venice, 1
                            August 1556: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 11r <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܝܲܗܒ ܠܝ ܬܪܝܢ ܡܵܐܐ
                                ܟܬ̈ܒܐ ܡܢ ܒܿܬܪ ܠܸܐܘܬܐ ܣܲܰܓܝܼܺ ܘܕܝܢܪ̈ܐ ܠܐ ܝܲܗܒ ܠܝ ܠܒܲܪ ܡܢ ܥܣܪܝܢ ܛܰܐܠܪ.
                                ܐܠܗܐ ܝܿܕܥ ܕܫܪܪܐ ܐܡܿܪ ܐܢܐ ܩܕܵܡܘܗܝ ܘܩܕܡܝܟ. ܘܐܢܿܐ ܢܸܦܩܸܿܬ ܢܦܩ̈ܬܐ ܥܠ
                                ܟܬ̈ܒܐ ܡܢ ܒܼܝܸܐܢܢܲܐ ܘܥܕܲܡܵܐ ܠܐܰܒܼܷܢܸܬܣܝܲܐ..</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </note> Masius added a note to this on the margin stating that Moses received
                    700 florins for two years. It is not known how Masius was so well-informed.
                    However, if this amount was true, Moses would have been an extremely well-paid
                    person in Vienna. Widmanstetter had a yearly salary of 500 florins as chancellor
                    of Lower Austria, and he obtained 200 florins additionally as commission,
                    probably for his work as superintendent of the university.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Müller, Johann Albrecht von Widmanstetter, 102.</p>
                    </note> Guillaume Postel, who was invited by Widmanstetter to help with the
                    edition of the New Testament with his experience, earned 200 florins a year as a
                    university teacher. With this salary, he was the best-paid professor at the
                    University of Vienna in 1554.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> R. Kink, Geschichte der kaiserlichen Universität zu
                            Wien. Vol I/2, (Wien: Carl Gerold &amp; Sohn, 1854), 164–165.</p>
                    </note> As for the living expenses, food and lodging were around 50–60 florins
                    per year for a student in the middle of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> F. Gall, Alma Mater Rudolphina, 1365–1965. Die
                            Wiener Universität und ihre Studenten, (Wien: Verlag Austria Press,
                            1965), 117.</p>
                    </note> At the Jesuit fraternity house, which was likely Moses’ dwelling place
                    during his Viennese years, as it will be shown below, 26 florins was the yearly
                        fee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> J. A. de Polanco, <hi rend="italic">Vita Ignatii
                                Loiolae et Rerum Societatis Jesu Historia, IV Vols</hi> (Matriti:
                            Augustinus Avrial, 1896), Vol. IV, 250.</p>
                    </note> so with 350 florins a year one could be well-off. In the light of these
                    data, the 20 thalers mentioned by Moses is also an unrealistic amount to be his
                    total salary, and it was probably money for the journey he received before
                    departure.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Nevertheless, Moses apparently hoped to receive extra recognition for his work
                    at the end of his sojourn in Vienna and he imagined a more palpable and
                    exchangeable reward than the king’s appreciative words in the grant of arms. His
                    initial enthusiasm towards Ferdinand evaporated and he left Vienna somewhat
                    disappointed, with a bitter taste in the mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2. The patent of arms in the light of the Ottoman wars (<hi rend="italic"
                        >narratio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">According to the document, the king decided to present Moses with this grant,
                    “…in order that he can transmit the memory of his right acts, life and diligence
                    confirmed by our testimony and authority to the ones coming after, and (in
                    order) others be inflamed and incited to a good and right way of life by virtue
                    of his example. (f. 2v)” Why did Ferdinand want Moses’ example to be followed?
                    Beyond the fact that referring to the grantee’s exemplariness is a usual
                    locution of the chancellery, this phrase has a concrete meaning in Moses’ case.
                    Actually, not only the issue of this grant of arms but the whole project of the
                    Syriac publishing can be understood in light of the historical background,
                    namely the war against the Turks. The Ottoman threat and the siege of Vienna in
                    1529 fundamentally determined Ferdinand’s entire reign. Breicha-Vauthier has
                    already pointed out that the edition of the Syriac New Testament could serve
                    political goals<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. Breicha-Vauthier, “Le cadre historique de la
                            publication du manuscript” in <hi rend="italic">Le livre et le
                                Liban jusqu'a 1900. Exposition</hi>, ed. C. Aboussouan, (Paris:
                            Unesco–Agecoop, 1982), 125–126.</p>
                    </note> and Moses himself was aware of this aspect of their work. In a
                    manuscript he copied in Vienna in 1556, he inserted the following note in
                    cryptography: “May God Almighty grant to Ferdinand, King of the Romans, the
                    defeat of the Turks and a happy government of the peoples subject to him.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Kessel, “Moses of Mardin (d. 1592)” (Manuscript
                            Cultures 9 [2016]), 146–151; Borbone, Monsignore, 105–106. Borbone
                            described another mirror pair (<hi rend="italic">taw’amān</hi>) and
                            explored how Moses learned this special technique. Cf. Borbone,
                            Monsignore, 92–95. Apparently, the use of this encrypting method is a
                            characteristic of Moses’ early manuscripts, because there is a mirror
                            pair in his very first manuscript as well (London, British Library, Ms.
                            Harley 5512). On f. 176v-177r one can read: ”<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܫܡ ܐܒܐ ܘܒܪܐ
                                ܘܪܘܚܐ ܩܕܝܫܐ ܚܕ ܐܠܗܐ ܫܪܝܪܐ</foreign>. <hi rend="italic">In Nomine Patris
                                et Filii et Spiritus San(c)ti Amen Papa Pavlos III.</hi>” Neither
                            Wright in his catalogue, nor Leroy in his study referred to the presence
                            of this taw’amān in the manuscript, that is why it could remain
                            disregarded so long. Cf. W. Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                                Syriac manuscripts in the British Museum acquired since the year
                                1838</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vol. I.</hi> (London: Gilbert and
                            Rivington, 1870), 214–216; Leroy, Une copie syriaque.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The Ottoman expansion worried not only the country leaders at the European front
                    lines but also Christians of the Near East. Already in 1527, Maronite bishops
                    and the bishops of Syria appealed to Emperor Charles V asking for his help. They
                    requested 50,000 infantrymen, 100 cavalrymen, and a fleet of 400 sailing ships
                    to complement their 50,000 fighters who were ready to engage in battle against
                    the Turks “for His Majesty”. However, their request was left unanswered, or at
                    least no evidence of answer has been found until now.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> A. Rabbath, <hi rend="italic">Documents inédits
                                pour servir à l’histoire du christianisme en Orient (</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic smallcaps">xvi</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">ᵉ‒</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic smallcaps">xix</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">ᵉ siècles). Vol. II</hi>, (Paris–Leipzig: A. Picard et
                            Fils-Otto Harrassowitz, 1910), 616–623; R. Neck, “Diplomatische
                            Beziehungen zum Vorderen Orient unter Karl V” (Mitteilungen des
                            österreichischen Staatsarchivs 5 [1952]), 63–86, here 69 and 82–85.</p>
                    </note> Although looking for possible allies in the Near East in order to attack
                    the Ottomans in the rear coincided with the emperor’s interests, he looked for a
                    more powerful partner and sent envoys further in the East, as far as the Safavid
                    Empire in Iran. The Habsburg–Persian alliance started haltingly but generally
                    worked well until 1555, when the Shah Tahmasp and Sultan Suleiman the
                    Magnificent closed the Ottoman–Safavid war and signed the Peace of Amasya. Thus,
                    it was to be feared that Ferdinand would find himself in dire straits if
                    Suleiman could focus on the European seat of war.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Neck, Diplomatische Beziehungen, 75; B. von
                            Palombini, <hi rend="italic">Bündniswerben abendländischer Mächte um
                                Persien 1453-1600</hi>, Freiburger Islamstuditen I (Wiesbaden: Franz
                            Steiner Verlag, 1968), 84.</p>
                    </note> His brother, Charles having announced in 1555 his intention to retire,
                    already started to gradually abdicate parts of his empire. Ferdinand was to take
                    his seat on the throne of the Holy Roman Empire, so he had to face the loss of
                    their ally.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> It was this particular historical situation when he decided to send 300 copies
                    of the Syriac New Testament to the Maronite and the Syrian Orthodox patriarchs
                    and to grant Moses a coat of arms. Although no official instruction assigned to
                    Moses has been found, he might have played a diplomatic role. Charles V and
                    Ferdinand as well relied several times on the service of Eastern Christians in
                    their diplomatic relations with Oriental powers, like Petrus Maronita and Pietro
                    da Negro.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Palombini, Bündniswerben, 65–85.</p>
                    </note> Offering the books to the patriarchs as a friendly gift served to
                    express that the king and future emperor did not forget them, whereas Moses’
                    diploma was concrete evidence proving that the king rewards those who help him
                    somehow.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.5" xml:lang="en">
                <head>3. Moses’ family (<hi rend="italic">dispositio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The grant of arms accurately defines who is authorized to use the described coat
                    of arms: “You, aforementioned Moses of Mardin and Your brothers, Barṣawmo, which means son of
                        Lent,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The document calls Moses’ eldest brother Bartoma,
                            which is incorrect. Presumably, the scribe did not know the name Barṣawmo, that is why Moses
                            had to explain, that it means son of Lent in Syriac. Apparently, the
                            scribe tried to write down the name by hearing and he chose a similar
                            sounding name.</p>
                    </note> Simeon, and Joshua, sons of the priest Isaac in the village of Qaluq at
                    the Mount Qoros in the province of Savur,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33"
                        n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> On the topography of this region see A. Socin, “Zur
                            Geographie des Ṭūr ʿAbdīn”
                            (Zeitschrift der deutschen morgenlindischen Gesellschaft 34 [1881]),
                            237–269, here 265; A. Palmer, <hi rend="italic">Monk and Mason on the
                                Tigris Frontier: The Early History of Tur ͑Abdin</hi>, University of
                            Cambridge Oriental Publications 39 (Cambridge: Cambridge University
                            Press, 1990), XIX–XXII, 21–22.</p>
                    </note> your legitimate spouses and the children born from your legitimate
                    marriage and the ones to be born…” (f. 2v).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> A German inscription on the first page of the document resumes the content as:
                    “Grant of arms, Vienna, 15 March 1556. Meredineus Moses, Syrian priest and the
                    sons of his brothers Bartholomew and Isaac,” which is erroneous and might be the
                    result of a cursory reading.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> „Wappenbrief. Wien, 15. März 1556. Meredineus
                            Moses, syrischer Priester dann die Söhne seiner Brüder Bartholomäus und
                            Isaak” (2r). Karl Friedrich von Frank relayed this information without
                            verification. Cf. K. F. von Frank, Standeserhebungen und Gnadenakte für
                            das Deutsche Reich und die Österreichischen Erblande bis 1806 sowie
                            kaiserlich österreichische bis 1823 mit einigen Nachträgen zum
                            Alt-Österreichischen Adels-Lexikon 1823-1918. Vol. III, (Schloss
                            Senftenegg: Selbstverlag, 1967), 228.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Moses’ family members can be traced very easily because he regularly made
                    mention of them in his writings. In his first known manuscript, which is a Latin
                    Missal written with Syriac letters in 1549, there is a garshuni inscription made
                    by Moses, in which he invokes God for his family: “Remember, Oh Lord, Moses, the
                    sinner and his father, the priest Isaac, and his mother, Helene, and his
                    brother[s], the priest Barṣawmo,
                    Simeon, and Joshua<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35"
                        n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܼܟܪ ܐܘ̄ ܡܪܝܐ ܠܡܘܣܝ
                                ܐܠܟܐܛܝ ܘܠܐܒܘܗ ܩܣܝܣ ܐܝܣܚܩ ܘܐܡܗ ܗܝܠܐܢ. ܘܐܟܘܗ ܩܣܝܣ ܒܪܨܘܡܐ ܘܫܡܥܘܢ
                                ܘܝܫܘܥ.</foreign> London, British Library, Ms. Harley 5512, f. 166v.</p>
                    </note> A similar supplication enumerating his closest relatives can be found
                    also in the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps </hi>of the Syriac New Testament,
                    namely in the colophon of the Acts of the Apostles<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Liber Sacrosancti Evangelii, Acts of the Apostles,
                            f. 38r: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܰܠܲܘ ܥܰܠܼ
                                ܡܘܽܫܸܐ ܡܚܻܝܠܐ ܒܰܪ ܩܲܫܝܫܐ ܐܝܣܚܵܩ ܡܕܢܚܵܝܵܐ ܘܥܰܠ ܐܡܗ ܗܷܠܷܐܢܻܝ. ܘܥܰܠ
                                ܐܚܘ̈ܗܝ ܩܲܫܝܫܐ ܒܲܪܨܰܘܡܳܐ ܘܫܸܡܥܘܢ ܘܝܫܘܽܥ ܘܟܠ ܚܰܕ ܐܝܟ ܨܠܘܽܬܗ ܢܸܬܦܪܰܥ
                                ܐܡܝܢ݂</foreign> Cf. A. Müller, “Dissertationes duae de rebus itidem
                            Syriacis, et e reliquis Mardeni Epistolis maxime. De Mose Mardeno, una;
                            De Syriacis librorum sacrorum Versionibus… altera. Coloniae
                            Brandeburgicae” in<hi rend="italic"> Symbolae syriacae,</hi> ed. A.
                            Müller (Berolini, 1673), 1–46, here 5.</p>
                    </note> and in his Beth Gazo.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 106; Kessel, Moses of Mardin,
                            149.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> This detailed display of his family makes it possible to identify other members
                    of his family, too. There is a reader’s note in a copy of Bar Bahlūl’s Lexicon
                    preserved in Halle which was made by a certain <hi rend="italic">Ibrāhīm b. Qiss
                        Masꜥūd b. Qiss Barṣawma b. Qiss Isḥāq</hi> living in Qaluq in 1606.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> J. Assfalg, Verzeichniss der orientalischen
                            Handschriften in Deutschland. Vol. V. Syrische Handschriften,
                            (Wiesbaden: Franz Steiner Verlag, 1963), 115.</p>
                    </note> He is without doubt Moses’ great-nephew. He was not only a passionate
                    bookworm but also a prolific scribe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> He copied e.g. Barhebraeus’ <hi rend="italic">Book
                                of Rays</hi> (I. A. Barṣawm, <hi rend="italic">Sriṭ</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">oto d-Omid w-Merdo. Makhṭūṭ</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">āt Āmid wa-Mārdīn. Omid &amp; Mardin Manuscripts</hi>,
                            ed. Ignaṭiyus Zakkay I,
                            (Ma‘arrat Ṣaydnāyā: Dayro
                            d-Mor Afrem Suryoyo, 2008) 178–179), Eliya of Nisibis’ <hi rend="italic"
                                >Book of the Translator</hi> (A. McCollum, “Prolegomena to a New
                            Edition of Eliya of Nisibis's Kitāb al-turjumān fī taʿlīm luġat
                            al-suryān” (JSS 58 [2013]), 297–322, here 310) and Bar Bahlūl’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Lexicon</hi> (H. Hyvernat, “An Ancient Syriac
                            Lexicographer” (The Catholic University Bulletin 8 [1902]), 58–74, here
                            65.).</p>
                    </note> Whether he was aware of his right to use his great-uncle’s coat of arms,
                    we might not know, but at least there is one person who fulfilled Ferdinand’s
                    desire and followed Moses’ example, though not in printing but in copying
                    manuscripts.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.6" xml:lang="en">
                <head>4. Moses’ coat of arms (<hi rend="italic">dispositio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The draft of the grant of arms contains two heraldic descriptions, which is quite
                    odd. Having a closer look at them, however, one can see that they are similar,
                    the one being more detailed and elaborated than the other; actually, they
                    represent two different phases of the same coat of arms. Presumably, the scribe
                    showed a sketch to Moses before copying the text of the draft on the vellum, and
                    he must have asked for a few amendments. Thanks to Widmanstetter, Moses had
                    access to the offices of the Viennese administration, so he might have been
                    present at the moment of the composition of his grant of arms.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> His first letter was written at the chancellery
                                “<hi rend="italic">in uiena. in canzelleria di Reges Rome</hi>”.
                            Letter sent by Moses to Giovanni Rignalmo from Vienna, 23 November 1553:
                            Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 21r.</p>
                    </note> The scribe first tried to add the corrections in between the lines, then
                    continued on the margins, finally crossed out the whole description, and rewrote
                    it on another sheet of paper within his reach.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41"
                        n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Judging by the inscription at the back of the
                            paper, it was a draft of a letter addressed to Zacharia Delfino,
                            Apostolic Nuntio to Germany: “<hi rend="italic">Rdo Devoto syncere nobis
                                dilecto D. Zachariae Episcopo Pharensi S.mi D. N. Nuncio ad nos
                                deputato</hi>” (f. 3v).</p>
                    </note> That is why this middle folio differs from the others, and that is why
                    there is a seeming discrepancy in the foliation. Onto the fair copy of the
                    document, only the final, expanded version had been carried over.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The heraldic achievement is not depicted on either of these documents, and it is
                    not known whether it was displayed on the charter or not. The grant was valid
                    without the coloured heraldic arms, and, since the costs of the painting had to
                    be paid by the beneficiary, the charters sometimes remained without graphic
                        illustration.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Csízi, Kora újkori nemesi címerek, 165.</p>
                    </note> Nevertheless, on the grounds of the description, Moses’ coat of arms
                    could look like Figure 1.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The coat of arms follows the basic rules of tincture. As for the charges, both
                    the trimount and the church are conventional and often-used elements.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> R. Steimel, “Der Dreiberg. Zum Rechtssinnbild im
                            Wappen” (Germanien 13 [1941]), 58–65; O. Neubecker
                            <hi rend="st"> and W. </hi>
                            <hi rend="Emphasis">Rentzmann, </hi>
                            <hi rend="st">Wappenbilderlexikon, (München: Battenberg, </hi>
                            <hi rend="Emphasis">1974), </hi>319, 331, 332, 343.</p>
                    </note> It is an enigma, however, why Moses chose these figures. Would it be an
                    allusion to Widmanstetter’s coat of arms, which portrays an elephant standing on
                    a trimount and a two-towered building also appears in the crest?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Müller, Johann Albrecht von Widmanstetter, 114.</p>
                    </note> Or are they canting arms representing somehow the bearer’s name and
                    attributes, which were so popular in German civic heraldry?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Biewer and Henning, Wappen, 171.</p>
                    </note> If the latter, the trimount offers an obvious interpretation, since
                    Moses’ home region, Turabdin is a hilly region. The two towns, Mardin and Savur,
                    which are associated with him, are situated on the top of a hill. As for the
                    church, it also can be easily explained, since Moses was clerical. The concrete
                    form of the church, however, might raise a question, because this part of the
                    escutcheon is where Moses made the most amendments: he asked to add oblong
                    windows to the towers, two golden crosses on the top of them, an opening door,
                    and three round windows, which are in a triangular form, one beneath the roof
                    and two at the upper part of the door. Such a nuanced description is almost
                    unusual in heraldry, where the stylization of the charges is an important
                        principle<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>, 153.</p>
                    </note> and makes one think that Moses had a particular church in his head that
                    he described. However, a quest among the churches playing an important role in
                    Moses’ life did not bring evident result. There was no two-towered church in the
                    settlements of Qaluq, Savur, or Mardin, which are mentioned in the grant of arms
                    (f. 2v) and elsewhere as well, as Moses’ hometowns.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> T. A. Sinclair, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Turkey:
                                An Architectural &amp; Archaeological Survey. Vol. III</hi>,
                            (London: Pindar Press, 1989), 207–208, 321–322.</p>
                    </note> The seat of the Syrian Orthodox patriarch was at that time in a
                    monastery close to Mardin, called Dayr al-Zaꜥfarān. Being the centre of Moses’
                    church, it was a place of symbolic importance, and Moses undoubtedly visited
                        it,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> J. D. Mansi, <hi rend="italic">Stephani Baluzii
                                Tutelensis Miscellanea novo ordine digesta et non paucis ineditis
                                monumentis opportunisque animadversionibus aucta. Vol. III</hi>,
                            (Lucae: Apud Vincentium Junctinium, 1762), 199–206.</p>
                    </note> but its churches do not fit Moses’ description either.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Sinclair, Eastern Turkey, 214–218.</p>
                    </note> If the church was modelled on a Viennese church, the first choice should
                    be the one-time Carmelite Church (Kirche am Hof), because it was the closest to
                    the Moses’ residence, but this church belonged to a mendicant order, which had
                    to avoid building ostentatious edifices and had no towers, only a roof
                        turret.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> R. Perger and W. Brauneis, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Mittelalterlichen Kirchen und Klöster Wiens</hi>, Wiener
                            Geschichtsbücher 19, (Wien–Hamburg: Paul Zsolnay Verlag, 1977),
                            128–130.</p>
                    </note> Interestingly, Vienna’s iconic church, the St. Stephen’s Cathedral is
                    depicted with two towers on the <hi rend="italic">Albertinischer Plan</hi>,
                    which is the oldest map of Vienna (dated 1422). What is more, they have oblong
                    windows, a pointed roof, and huge crosses on the top (see Figure 2). Even three
                    round windows in triangular form can be noticed on the side, so the resemblance
                    is striking. The crux of the matter is that it is a free and stylized depiction
                    of the church. In reality, the building operations were stalled due to lack of
                    money, and the Northern Tower was only 12 meters high at the beginning of the
                        16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51"
                        n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>, 59–60.</p>
                    </note> Did Moses virtually complete the church? It is questionable, and the
                    absence of the barrel vault is another point of difference. Nevertheless, the
                    other oldest and most notable churches in Vienna (Peterskirche, Ruprechtskirche,
                    Maria am Gestade, Michaelskirche, Schottenkloster, Minoritenkirche) do not fit
                    the description, either.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Beyond the St. Stephen’s Cathedral there is another possible
                    identification, but there are as many reasons for it as against it. After his
                    return to the Near East, Moses lived in the monastery of Mār Ābay, where he
                    copied a manuscript in 1560/1561.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 107.</p>
                    </note> This monastery is not far from his birthplace, so it is not impossible
                    that he was among its monks before coming to Europe, too. The church was domed
                    and the monastery was surrounded by a wall with two towers, but they were robust
                    structures serving defensive purposes, not proper church towers.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Wießner, <hi rend="italic">Christliche
                                Kultbauten im </hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ṭūr ʿAbdīn. Teil I. Kultbauten mit traverserem Schiff
                                und Felsanlagen. Textband</hi>, Studien für spätantiken und
                            frühchristlichen Kunst 4 (Wiesbaden: Otto Harrassowitz, 1982),
                            58–60.</p>
                    </note> Thus, the identity of the church remains uncertain.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.7" xml:lang="en">
                <head>5. The crest and Moses’ dwelling place (<hi rend="italic"
                    >dispositio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">As for the other parts of the armorial achievement, the helmet is an open helmet,
                    the mantling is gules-silver and azure-or, which was popular in that period. In
                    the crest, there is an angel which probably needs further interpretation. It is
                    puzzling why Moses asked for a blond angel with red and green wings, and why the
                    strip, “what the clergymen call stole” should form an X on his chest. These
                    criteria are, again, additions appearing only in the second, more extensive
                    version of the description.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In Byzantine art, angels are sometimes represented in <hi rend="italic"
                        >orarion</hi>, i.e. eastern stole, which is the distinguishing mark of the
                    deacon in oriental rites. This portrayal had an impact on Western iconography as
                    well and some examples of this representation are attested in the West.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> M. B. McNamee, <hi rend="italic">Vested Angels:
                                Eucharistic Allusions in Early Netherlandish Paintings</hi>,
                            (Leuven: Peeters, 1998), 43–60.</p>
                    </note> It appeared even in heraldry, such an angel is depicted in the coat of
                    arms of Engelberg, for instance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> N<hi rend="Emphasis">
                                <seg rend="italic">eubecker</seg>
                            </hi>
                            <hi rend="st"> and W. </hi>
                            <hi rend="Emphasis">
                                <seg rend="italic">Rentzmann</seg>, </hi>
                            <hi rend="st">
                                <seg rend="italic">Wappenbilderlexikon</seg>
                            </hi>, 147.</p>
                    </note> Moses, however, did not need to go to Engelberg to see angels wearing
                        <hi rend="italic">orarion</hi>. He could observe them thoroughly in Vienna
                    when the homily was boring at the Carmelite Church (Kirche am Hof), which was
                    only at two steps from his supposed home.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Arriving in Vienna, Moses was probably hosted by Widmanstetter, as it was
                    already pointed out above, but later he moved to a student home, as it becomes
                    clear from an instruction he gave to Masius: “And if you, beloved Sir, write to
                    me, send the writing to the Alconlegio, since I live now with <hi rend="italic"
                        >studiosi</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 26
                            March 1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 16r <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܡܼܬܝ
                                ܕܟܿܬܒ ܠܝܼ ܚܘܼܒܟ. ܫܕܪ ܠܰܟܬܝܒܬܐ</foreign> Alconlegio <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܕܥܡ
                                </foreign>studiosi <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܡܿܪ ܐܢܐ
                                ܗܵܫܐ</foreign>.</p>
                    </note> This ‘<hi rend="italic">conlegio</hi>’ was most likely the Jesuit
                    college. Juan Alfonso de Polanco noted in his <hi rend="italic">Vita
                        Ignatii</hi> that the sons of the chancellor Jakob Jonas and other
                    high-ranking persons lived with the Jesuits in two small separate houses under
                    Jesuit discipline.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> “Et ab ipsa Nostrorum habitatione sejunctae duae
                            domus erant non magnae, ubi quidam Dni. Jonae Cancellarii et aliorum
                            primariorum filii, parentum rogatu, admissi fuerunt, ut suis ibi
                            expensis sub nostrorum disciplina viverent…” Polanco, Vita Ignatii
                            Loiolae, Vol. IV, 250.</p>
                    </note> Peter Canisius, one of the most famous Jesuits in Vienna and later
                    provincial wanted to establish a fraternity house for the “wealthiest young
                    noblemen” already in 1553, but the Dominican Monastery, where the Jesuits lived
                    at that time provisionally, was not suitable for this goal.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> In a letter sent on 12 October 1553 to Juan Alfonso
                            de Polanco, he wrote: “Scrisse al ultimo di una casa per nutrir et
                            instituir la Juuentu, con tal’ intentione, accio V. R. piu chiaramente
                            mi intenda, volessimo delli piu ricchi et nobilj Giouanj li quali
                            facilmente si troueranno, pigliare alcuno numero et metter li insieme in
                            vna casa vicina quanto fusse possibile, et nutrir li alli spesj loro, et
                            darli vn Rectore delli nostri, il quale li tenesse in buono gouerno del
                            anima et del cuorpo, et stesse con loro presente poi che non fusseno
                            occupati nelle classe.” O. Braunsberger, <hi rend="italic">Beati Petri
                                Canisii, Societatis Iesu, Epistulae et acta. Vol I </hi>(Friburgi
                            Brisgoviae: Herder, 1896), 437–438.</p>
                    </note> Having taken into possession the Carmelite Monastery in April-May 1554,
                    the Jesuits immediately set up the student residence, which opened its gates on
                    4 July 1554. Initially, six or seven young adolescents, among them the four sons
                    of Jacob Jonas, lived there under the supervision of Johannes Dirsius, but their
                    number increased rapidly, up to 120 in 1574.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                        n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> L. Maggio S.J., <hi rend="italic">Historia Collegii
                                Societatis Iesu Viennensis ab anno 1550 usque ad annum 1567</hi>,
                            Pannonhalmi Főapátság, Ms. 118.E.5, 20;
                                <hi rend="italic">Historia Collegii</hi>, ÖNB, Cod. 8367, 3r. On
                            Dirsius see L. Lukács, <hi rend="italic">Catalogi personarum et
                                officiorum Provinciae Austriae S.I. Vol I</hi>, Monumenta Historica
                            Societatis Iesu 117 (Romae: Institutum Historicum Societatis Iesu,
                            1978), 655. In 1555, King Ferdinand sent ten young German boys from
                            Augsburg to Vienna and tried to secure a place for them in this
                            convictorium. It shows the independence of the Jesuits, that only four
                            of them were accepted, the other six were dismissed with the king’s
                            consent. Cf. Polanco, Vita Ignatii Loiolae, Vol. IV, 234–235.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> That Widmanstetter was also among the “high-ranking persons” sending their
                    relatives to the Jesuits is not a groundless supposition. He and Jacob Jonas
                    were good friends and they both belonged to the biggest supporters and to the
                    inner circle of the Society of Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Friedrich Staphylus refferred to them in a letter
                            sent to Canisius with the following words: “Habes istius laboris tui
                            fideles socios, et adiutores, magnifi. D. D. Ionam et Lucretium (i.e.
                            Widmanstetter), uiros et excellenti doctrina, et uitae sanctimonia
                            admirabiles…” Braunsberger, Beati Petri Canisii Epistulae, 562–563.</p>
                    </note> Widmanstetter maintained especially good relations with the order and he
                    was linked to it with thousand threads: his younger brother studied also at the
                    Jesuits and entered the order in 1556,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Müller, Johann Albrecht von Widmanstetter, 65;
                            Lukács, Catalogi personarum, 2, 818.</p>
                    </note> he asked the Jesuits’ help to acquire Japenese and Indian alphabet for
                    the printing press,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Braunsberger, Beati Petri Canisii Epistulae, 450.
                            It is not clear, what ‘Indian’ is meant for. The Jesuit mission started
                            in India with the arrival of Francis Xavier (1506–1552) in 1542, so, on
                            one hand, it could mean effectively an Indian language. But on the
                            other, ‘Indian’ was also used for the Ethiopian language at that time.
                            Widmanstetter had a copy of the first edition of the Ethiopian New
                            Testament and the Jesuit mission to Ethiopia also stood on the
                            threshold, so this sense is more likely.</p>
                    </note> and he was member of the committee set up by Ferdinand I to find a new
                    building for the order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Braunsberger, Beati Petri Canisii Epistulae, 447,
                            n. 1; J. Wrba, “In der Nähe des Königs. Die Gründung des Jesuitenkollegs
                            in Wien” in <hi rend="italic">Ignatius von Loyola und die Gesellschaft
                                Jesu 1491‒1556</hi>, ed. A. Falkner and P. Imhof (Würzburg: Echter,
                            1990), 331‒357.</p>
                    </note> His fame reached even the founder, Ignatius of Loyola,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Jerome Nadal, who was visitator of the province in
                            1555, reported to Ignatius on the printing press set up by Widmanstetter
                            describing the chancellor as an „<hi rend="italic">huomo molto catolico
                                et dotto</hi>”. G. Nadal, <hi rend="italic">Epistolae P. Hieronymi
                                Nadal, Societatis Jesu ab anno 1546 ad 1577 nunc primum editae et
                                illustratae a patribus ejusdem societatis. Vol. I,</hi> Monumenta
                            Historica Societatis Iesu (Matriti: Typis Augustini Avrial, 1898),
                            309–310.</p>
                    </note> so he could easily have found a place for Moses. The ultimate reason for
                    this hypothesis is that Moses himself mentioned Canisius in one of his letters.
                    Apparently, the Jesuit superior instructed him how to dress: “Do not write in
                    your letters ‘padre’, because I am in priestly garb here, not in a monastic
                    dress. Formerly, I was in Vienna in laic dress, like in the first year, and
                    after many times Canisius spoke with me and dressed me as a priest<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi>”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 15 July
                            1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 22r: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܬܟܬܘܒ ܒܟܬܝܒܬܟ ܦܰܿܐܕܪܹܐ. ܡܛܠ
                                ܕܠܐ ܐܝܬܝ ܗܪܟܐ ܒܐܣܟܹܡܵܐ ܕܕܝܪܝܘܬܐ. ܐܠܐ ܒܐܣܟܻܡܐ ܕܩܫܝ̈ܫܐ ܘܡܢ ܩܕܡ ܙܒܢܐ
                                ܗܘܻܝܬ ܒܸܐܣܟܻܡܐ ܕܥܵܠ̈ܡܝܐ ܒܲܒܝܐܢܢܲܐ ܐܝܟ ܫܲܢܬܐ ܚܕܵܐ ܘܡܢ ܒܬܪ ܙܒܢ̈ܬܐ
                                ܣܓܝ̈ܐܬܐ ܐܡܼܪ ܠܝ ܟܲܐܢܝܻܙܻܝܵܐ ܘܠܒܫܲܢܝ ܐܝܟ ܩܫܝ̈ܫܐ.</foreign> In the Middle
                            Ages bishops and monks or mendicant friars were called “Father”,
                            diocesan priests not. The use of “Father” for all priests, is a recent
                            practice.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Moses, therefore, lived in the immediate vicinity of the Carmelite Church
                    (Kirche am Hof), the high altar of which was a huge, 10 meters wide polyptych,
                    the masterpiece of an unidentified master called Albrechtsmeister.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Perger and Brauneis, Die Mittelalterlichen Kirchen,
                            130.</p>
                    </note> On the external pair of wings, the master depicted 16 invocations of the
                    Virgin Mary representing the angels, mostly with blond hair, red-green wings and
                    in some cases with orarion, just like in Moses’ crest.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> See e.g. ‘Mary, Queen of Archangels’ on Figure 3.
                            On the history of the altar see F. Röhrig, <hi rend="italic">Der
                                Albrechtsaltar und sein Meister</hi> (Wien: Tusch, 1981). Out of the
                            32 original panels 28 survived and enrich today the collection of the
                            Stift Klosterneuburg. Some of them, including the one entitled ‘Mary,
                            Queen of Archangels’ are accessible online among ‘Gotische Tafenbilder’
                            under inventory number 12–32 on the following link: <ref
                                target="https://www.stift-klosterneuburg.at/online-collection"
                                >https://www.stift-klosterneuburg.at/online-collection</ref>.</p>
                    </note> These panels became the characteristic of the church, which is called
                    till today ‘Church to the Nine Choirs of Angels’ (Kirche zu den neun Chören der
                    Engel), so it is not astonishing that they served as a source of inspiration for
                    Moses, too.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> As for the other parts of the angel, the book of the Gospels in his hand is an
                    obvious allusion to Moses’ major Viennese accomplishment, the Syriac New
                    Testament. The standard in his right hand contains a motto in abbreviated form:
                    V.S.E.C. The expansion of the abbreviation is provided in the text, it means
                    “One Holy Catholic Church.” The elucidation of this motto is more problematic
                    since it is difficult to guess why Moses chose it.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.8" xml:lang="en">
                <head>6. Moses’ motto and his supposed conversion to Catholicism (<hi rend="italic"
                        >dispositio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">At first sight, this motto seems to be a commitment to the Catholic Church. As a
                    matter of fact, ‘One’, ‘Holy’ and ‘Catholic’ are the attributes of the Church
                    expressed in the Niceno-Constantinopolitan Creed, which is acknowledged by most
                    of the Christian denominations: Oriental Christians as well as Catholics and
                    Protestants equally. Moses’ religious affiliation is a controversial issue,
                    which has not been fully clarified yet. Originally, he was Syrian Orthodox, but
                    many signs indicate that he might have converted to Catholicism. His motto
                    provides an opportunity to take a closer look at this question.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The most concrete evidence for his possible conversion to Catholicism is his
                    Catholic profession of faith he made before the Pope and the cardinals during
                    his second stay in Rome in 1552.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The Syriac text of this profession of faith
                            perished, but Masius, who was the only competent person in Syriac at
                            that time in Rome, prepared a Latin translation and later published it.
                            A. Masius, <hi rend="italic">De paradiso commentarius; scriptus ante
                                annos prope septingentos à Mose Bar-Cepha Syro; Episcopo in
                                Beth-Raman &amp; Beth-Ceno; ac Curatore rerum sacrarum in Mozal, hoc
                                est Seleucia Parthorum</hi> (Antverpiae: Ex Officina Christophori
                            Plantini, 1569), 257–262.</p>
                    </note> There are, however, many uncertainties concerning this document and its
                    exact status is unclear.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> L. van Rompay, “Mushe of Mardin,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac
                                Heritage</hi>, eds. S. Brock et alii. (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias,
                            2011), 300–301. I will treat this issue in detail in another study.</p>
                    </note> There is, for instance, an inconsistency between this act and his
                    behaviour a few months later. In May 1553, Roman cardinals wanted to reordain
                    Moses in a proper, Catholic way, but he firmly resisted. He wrote to Masius in
                    an indignant tone calling the Roman prelates “lacking love and desiring vain
                        glory.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Müller, Epistolae duae, 6.</p>
                    </note> Admittedly it was a humiliating proposition from Moses’ point of view,
                    but many other non-Chalcedonians had to undergo this procedure; it was an
                    established custom in the Catholic Church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72"
                        n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> On this see S. Kennerley, “Ethiopian Christians in
                            Rome c.1400-1750,” in <hi rend="italic">Religious Minorities in Early
                                Modern Rome</hi>, ed. E. Michelson. Forthcoming.</p>
                    </note> One of Moses’ Roman friends, the Ethiopian Giovanni Battista Negro,
                    alias Yohạnnǝs, was reordained and later became
                    the second black bishop and the first black nuncio in the history of the Roman
                        Church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> M. Salvadore, “African Cosmopolitanism in the Early
                            Modern Mediterranean: The Diasporic Life of Yohannes, the Ethiopian
                            Pilgrim Who Became a Counter-Reformation Bishop” (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Journal of African History</hi>, 58:1 [2017]), 61–83.</p>
                    </note> If Moses really wanted to become Catholic, he only would have to allow
                    himself to be reordained and thus his dream would have come true. In sum,
                    despite his visible rapprochement to the Catholic Church, Moses left Rome as a
                    Syrian Orthodox.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In the light of this, it is surprising that he appears to be a Catholic priest
                    in Vienna according to the testimony of different documents. In the first
                    instance, he is referred to as a ‘Syrian Catholic priest’ in the text of the
                    grant of arms (f. 2r). The Syrian Catholic Church did not exist at that time, so
                    the word ‘Syrian’ should refer to his birthplace and ‘Catholic’ to his religion.
                    Moreover, Widmanstetter systematically called Moses a Catholic priest in the
                    edition of Syriac New Testament.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Moses is referred to as “Moses Meredinaeus ex
                            Mesopotamia Catholicus sacerdos” four times in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Liber Sacrosancti Evangelii</hi>.</p>
                    </note> And finally, the same appellation appears in a Latin note in a
                    manuscript, which was copied by Moses in Vienna in January 1556.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> “…descripsit Moyses Meredinaeus Syrus presbyter
                            catholicus, Viennae Austriacae, mense Ianuario, Anno M.D.LVI.” Cf.
                            Borbone, Monsignore, 105; Kessel, Moses of Mardin, 149.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> It is no wonder that reading Moses’ above-cited remark on how Canisius
                    instructed him how to dress, Müller was led to the conclusion that after all he
                    probably accepted the request to be reordained as a Catholic priest in
                        Vienna.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> “Attamen Catholicum non omnino frustra vocat
                            Widmanstadius. Siquidem tandem passus est sacerdotem se denuo a
                            Catholico creari. Liquet hoc ex verbis ejus, quae in dorso epistolae VI.
                            Masio scripserat, anno MDLV 15. Julii, post absolutum jam Evangeliorum
                            codicem: Ne scribas (inquit) in Epistolis Padre (hoc forte titulo Mosen,
                            Sacerdotem jam Pontificium, honorare voluit.) Neque enim huc usque
                            Schema Monasticum gero. Sed Sacerdotale. Et antehac habitum Laicum
                            gestavi Viennae circiter annum. Postea Canisius Sacerdotali me induit
                            habitu.” Müller, Dissertationes duae, 6–7.</p>
                    </note> Unfortunately, the ordination protocols of the diocese of Vienna, which
                    could clinch the matter, are preserved only from 1574, but other circumstances
                    do not confirm Müller’s supposition. There were hardly any seminarians at that
                    time in Vienna. In a 20 years period, only 20 young priests finished their
                    studies, i.e. one per year on average, and the majority of the students at the
                    Faculty of Theology were Jesuits.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> G. Heiss, “Die Wiener Jesuiten und das Studium der
                            Theologie und der Artes an der Universität und im Kolleg im ersten
                            Jahrzehnt nach ihrer Berufung (1551),” in <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Universität Wien im Konzert europäischer Bildungszentren 14.-16.
                                Jahrhundert</hi>, Veröffentlichungen des Instituts für
                            Österreichische Geschichtsforschung 56, ed. K. Mühlberger and M.
                            Niederkorn-Bruck (Wien–München: Oldenbourg–Böhlau, 2010), 245–268, here
                            247; Polanco, Vita Ignatii Loiolae, Vol. IV, 234–235.</p>
                    </note> If Jesuits gave the bulk of the seminarians and Moses lived among them,
                    it would be obvious that he was reordained with them. Fortunately, the most
                    important ecclesiastical events are soundly documented in Jesuit sources. While
                    these documents make mention of Erhardus Leodiensis’ ordination in 1554 and that
                    of Martinus Stevordiensis and Johannes Dirsius in 1555, Moses’ name does not
                    appear in any of them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Historia Collegii</hi>, ÖNB, Cod. 8367, 2r and 3v;
                            Polanco, Vita Ignatii Loiolae, Vol. IV, 256 and Vol. V, 227–228.</p>
                    </note> Another highly relevant source on this question is Moses’
                    correspondence. Interestingly Moses, unlike in the case of the failed attempt of
                    the Roman hierarchy, did not report about any change in his ecclesiastical
                    status to Masius during his Viennese period. He was so indignant when the
                    cardinals tried to convince him to accept their proposal that it is hard to
                    believe that he would have passed over a similar issue in silence.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> While there is no direct evidence for Moses’ Catholic reordination, there is
                    robust evidence on the contrary. His most current self-designations are
                    religiously neutral; he usually referred to himself as Moses the Oriental, Moses
                    of Mardin, or Moses of Savur,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Cf. Borbone, Monsignore, 100–106. See also München,
                            Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Cod. Syr. 6, f. 162r and Wien,
                            Österreichische Nationalbibliothek, Cod. 15162, f. 110v.</p>
                    </note> but there are some exceptions. The ‘Catholic’ adjective never appears in
                    his signatures, contrary to the Jacobite, i.e. Syrian Orthodox adjective, which
                    does occur in some places. In the Syriac colophon of the New Testament he
                    offered to Ferdinand I, he professed his belonging to the denomination of the
                    Jacobite Syrians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 101.</p>
                    </note> According to him, the edition of the Syriac New Testament was carried
                    out “for the Jacobite Syrians.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Cf. the Syriac colophon at the end of the Acts of
                            the Apostols of the <hi rend="italic">Liber Sacrosancti
                                Evangelii</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܗܼܘ ܝܰܗܒ
                                ܢܸܦ̈ܩܵܬܐ ܘܰܚܬܰܡ ܗܳܠܝܢ ܟܬ̈ܒܐ. ܠܣܘܪ̈ܝܵܝܐ ܝܲܥܩܘܒ̈ܝܐ.</foreign>.</p>
                    </note> His religious affiliation is even more evident from his letters. Every
                    time the Syrian Orthodox Church came up in his correspondence, he referred to it
                    as <hi rend="italic">his</hi> church. Writing about the books Ferdinand sent to
                    the Maronite and the Syrian Orthodox patriarchs, Moses called the latter “our
                        patriarch.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Venice, 1
                            August 1556: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 11r. See n.
                            20.</p>
                    </note> Writing about the <hi rend="italic">Beth Gazo</hi>, Moses explained to
                    Masius that it contains the prayers of <hi rend="italic">their</hi> church.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 15 July
                            1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 24v <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܒܝܬܓܰܙܵܐ. ܕܐܝܬ
                                ܒܗ ܨܠܵܘܬܐ ܕܥܕܬܐ ܕܝܠܢ</foreign>..</p>
                    </note> At another occasion, instructing Masius in liturgical matters Moses
                    wrote: “I would like you to know, oh my brother, that there is a custom in our
                    church, at the Jacobite Syrians, when we commemorate the saints and ask for
                    their intercession<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84"
                        n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 15 July
                            1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 24v <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܥ ܐܘ̄ ܐܵܚܝ ܕܐܝܬ
                                ܠܢ ܥܝܵܕܵܐ ܒܥܕܬܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܣܘܪ̈ܝܝܐ ܝܥܩ̈ܘܒܝܐ. ܕܢܬܕܟܪ ܠܩܕ̈ܝܫܐ ܘܢܒܵܥܐ
                                ܡܛܠܬܗܘܢ..</foreign>
                        </p>
                    </note> Further examples could be provided, but these instances aptly illustrate
                    that Moses considered himself as a Syrian Orthodox during his Viennese
                    years.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Assessing this evidence, we can state that in Latin texts, which were intended
                    for the general public, and especially in those cases where others talked about
                    Moses, he appeared to be Catholic, but in Syriac texts, which were practically
                    not accessible for the outside world, and in his private correspondence, Moses
                    confessed his Orthodoxy. The best example for this dichotomy is the Gospel he
                    copied for Ferdinand. In the Latin dedication, he expressed his hope, that the
                    Catholic faith will be reinforced in his home against the Nestorians and the
                    Muslims and that God will gather the Syrians “under the wings of the Roman
                    Church and Empire,” but in the Syriac colophon, he explicitly referred to
                    himself as a Jacobite Syrian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 102–103.</p>
                    </note> Why was this double play necessary?</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Answering this question, one must not forget the historical background: the
                    religious struggles of the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century. In Vienna,
                    Canisius was the front-line fighter of the Counter-Reformation. As a member of
                    the reform commission at the university, he stood for the dismissal of ‘heretic’
                    professors, while the others inclined to tolerate them as long as they did not
                    propagate their beliefs at lectures.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> K. Mühlberger, “Universität und Jesuitenkolleg in
                            Wien: Von der Berufung des Ordens bis zum Bau des Akademischen Kollegs,”
                            in <hi rend="italic">Die Jesuiten in Wien</hi>, ed. H. Karner and W.
                            Telesko (Wien: Austrian Academy of Sciences Press, 2003), 21–37, here
                            24–25.</p>
                    </note> Canisius’ religious zeal can be measured by his reaction to the
                    punishment of a professor at the Faculty of Arts, Nikolaus Polites, who had been
                    incarcerated and banished from the country. In a letter to the Jesuit Superior
                    General, Canisius regretted the punishment’s “leniency”, and he was of the
                    opinion it would encourage the “damned plague among professors and students,”
                    while the university was feeding “monsters and heretics.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Mühlberger, Universität und Jesuitenkolleg, 25.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Moses’ judgment as a Syrian Orthodox was different, but his Church was basically
                    also considered to be heretical. Although Oriental Christians were welcomed in
                    Rome and there was intensive contact with the representatives of most
                    denominations, the negotiations aimed at purging these churches of heterodox
                    tenets and embracing them in the Catholic Church. Similarly, there was at that
                    time an ambivalent attitude to the use and legitimacy of Oriental languages,
                    because on one hand, they could serve missionary purposes and supply new
                    arguments for the theological disputes with Protestants, but on the other,
                    scriptures written in these languages could also contain heretical teachings
                    which could be controlled at the expense of great difficulties. Several interest
                    groups contested with each other at the Roman Curia, and with the shift of power
                    relations, it also could change quickly whether Oriental studies and publishing
                    were supported or prohibited. Pope Paul III (1534–1549) and Cardinal Marcello
                    Cervini, later Pope Marcellus II (1555) patronized the edition of the Ethiopian
                    New Testament in 1548–1549,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> I. Guidi, “La prima stampa del Nuovo Testamento in
                            etiopico, fatta in Roma nel 1548-1549” (Archivio della R. Società Romana
                            di Storia Patria 9 [1886]), 273–278; B. Juel-Jensen, “Potken’s Psalter
                            and Tesfa Tsion’s New Testament, Modus baptizandi and Missal” (Bodleian
                            Library Record 15 [1996]), 480–496.</p>
                    </note> but a few years later, in 1553, the Talmud was burned in Rome by the
                    decree of the Roman Inquisition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> K. R. Stow, “The Burning of the Talmud in 1553, in
                            the Light of Sixteenth Century Catholic Attitudes Toward the Talmud”
                            (Bibliothèque d'Humanisme et Renaissance 34:3 [1972]), 435–459.</p>
                    </note> Although the decree was directed against blasphemous Jewish doctrines,
                    regrettably Syriac scriptures also fell victim to the subsequent raid on Hebrew
                        books.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Masius repined over the loss of his Syriac
                            manuscripts in a letter to his friend, Latinius (Lossen 1886: 185–186):
                            “Sed utinam codices saltem meos Syros Novi Testamenti expeditos habeam
                            (...) Sed illi pari cum aliis hebraeis calamitate premuntur.” M. Lossen,
                            Briefe von Andreas Masius und seinen Freunden 1538 bis 1573,
                            Publikationen der Gesellschaft für Rheinische Geschichtskunde 2
                            (Leipzig: Verlag von Alphons Dürr, 1886). See also Wilkinson, The
                            Kabbalistic Scholars, 46; François, Andreas Masius, 221–223.</p>
                    </note> In 1571, the Antwerp Polyglot Bible, which was the first Polyglot Bible
                    containing the Syriac text of the New Testament, almost failed to obtain the
                    Papal approbation, because the collaborators were suspected of being kabbalistic
                    or in favour of the Talmud and some of their works were on the Index.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> B. Rekers, <hi rend="italic">Benito Arias Montano
                                (1527–1598)</hi>, Studies of the Warburg Institute 33 (London:
                            Warburg Institute–University of London, 1971), 58–69. The Pope finally
                            decided to assign the matter to the Spanish Inquisition and it was the
                            Spanish Jesuit, Juan de Mariana, who saved the project with his assent.
                            Cf. Wilkinson, The Kabbalistic Scholars, 93–99.</p>
                    </note> In light of these events, it is not surprising that Moses preferred not
                    to publicize his Syrian Orthodox identity, in order not to plunge into danger
                    the whole Syriac printing project. In this situation, Moses’ motto seems to be a
                    perfect choice, since it was suitable for giving the semblance of being Catholic
                    and for staying true to the Syrian Orthodox beliefs at the same time. The
                    question arises, how conscious this decision was from Moses’ part: what did he
                    perceive from the contemporary political, ecclesiastical affairs?</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The initiative might have come from Widmanstetter, whose interest was to make
                    Moses appear as a Catholic in order not to jeopardize his long-cherished
                    publishing project. Moses’ appellation as a Catholic priest in the edition of
                    the New Testament and also in the text of the grant of arms might be attributed
                    to him. At the same time, he was certainly aware of the truth, since he was able
                    to read Syriac and understood Moses’ sincere colophons. What is more, he knew
                    the Syriac version of the Nicene Creed and he was familiar with the dogmatical
                        differences.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> This text is on the first folios of his Syriac
                            Missal (München, Bayerische Staatsbibliothek, Cod. Syr. 5, f. 1v–2r), to
                            which he added Latin notes on dogmatical differences. Cf. J. Aumer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Verzeichniß der orientalischen Handschriften der K.
                                Hof- und Staatsbibliothek in München: mit Ausschluß der
                                hebraeischen, arabischen und persischen; nebst Anhang zum
                                Verzeichnis der arabischen und persischen Handschriften</hi> 1875
                            (Reprinted Wiesbaden: Otto Harrassowitz, 1970), 114.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> On the other hand, Moses was also well-informed in political and ecclesiastical
                    questions. He followed the Roman political life with attention and he was fully
                    up to date in this field. After the election of Pope Paul IV (1555–1559), Moses
                    evaluated the situation with the following words: “As for the Pope Theatino, I,
                    myself, am not pleased with him. Even if Giovanni Battista Negro becomes more
                    important or less important, there is no hope for me to return to Rome, only if
                    the cardinal of England or Cardinal Morone becomes the Pope<hi rend="italic"
                        >.</hi>”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Vienna, 15 July
                            1555: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 24v. <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܦܲܐܦܰܐ ܬܝܐܬܝܢ ܠܐ ܨܿܒܝܐ ܒܗ
                                ܢܲܦܫܝ. ܘܐܢ ܢܗܘܐ ܓܘܐܢ ܒܐܬܝܣܬܰܐ ܢܝܺܓܿܪܐ ܪܰܒܿܐ ܐܰܘܿ ܙܥܘܪܐ. ܠܝܬ ܠܝ ܣܒܪܐ
                                ܕܸܐܗܦܘܟ ܠܪܗܘܡܝ. ܐܠܐ ܐܢ ܢܗܼܘܐ ܟܪܕܢܐܠ ܕܢܓܠ ܬܹܐܪܪܱܐ. ܐܘܿ ܟܪܕܢܐܠ ܡܵܘܪܵܘܢ
                                ܦܰܐܦܐ</foreign>. The Pope Theatino
                            is Cardinal Gian Pietro Carafa, who, as the head of the Roman
                            Inquisition, ordered copies of the Talmud to be burned and became Pope
                            Paul IV (1555–1559). The Ethiopian Giovanni Battista Negro was Moses’
                            friend and Carafa’s protégé. As such, he might have helped Moses. Moses,
                            however, was the protégé of the two mentioned <hi rend="italic"
                                >spirituali</hi> cardinals: Reginald Pole and Giovanni Morone. The
                            new pope, being the leader of the <hi rend="italic">zelanti</hi>, was
                            their sworn enemy. Moses, thus, had a more powerful adversary in the
                            person of the pontiff, than a well-wisher in the person of Giovanni
                            Battista. On the fray between <hi rend="italic">sprituali</hi> and <hi
                                rend="italic">zelanti</hi> see A. P. Robinson, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Career of Cardinal Giovanni Morone (1509-1580): Between Council and
                                Inquisition</hi> (Farnham: Ashgate, 2012), 60–109.</p>
                    </note> Moses knew these cardinals personally and he could correctly assess the
                    impact of the election on the Oriental studies and on his future. Apparently, he
                    was smart enough to choose such a clever and cunning motto on his own. His
                    circumspection is also attested by the occasion when he warned Masius not to
                    call him a monk because he is known as a priest in Vienna. At the same time, his
                    motto might also be a reflection of his desire for the unity of his church and
                    the Catholic church mentioned in the Latin dedication of the Syriac New
                    Testament.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.9" xml:lang="en">
                <head>7. Did Moses become a nobleman?</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Having examined the relevant passages of the grant of arms, there is one more
                    question to clarify, notably the aim and sense of this privilege. In public
                    knowledge, the use of coats of arms and nobility are closely related. No wonder,
                    since it was mainly the noblemen who were granted this royal favour.
                    Nevertheless, from the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>–14<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> centuries burghers also managed to obtain such a privilege,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> C. Kajatin, “Königliche Macht und bürgerlicher
                            Stolz. Wappen- und Adelsbriefe in Zürich,” in <hi rend="italic">Alter
                                Adel - neuer Adel? Zürcher Adel zwischen Spätmittelalter und Früher
                                Neuzeit</hi>, ed. P. Niederhäuser (Zürich: Chronos Verlag, 2003),
                            203–210; Biewer and Henning, Wappen, 248–249.</p>
                    </note> and later, in the 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>–17<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries it became attainable even for peasants
                    and lower-ranking servants of the royal court.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95"
                        n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> K. F. Bauer, Das Bürgerwappen. Das Buch von den
                            Wappen und Eigenmarken der deutschen Bürger und Bauern, (Frankfurt am
                            Main: Verlag der Hauserpresse, 1935).</p>
                    </note> It was an established custom of the sovereigns to elevate someone to the
                    peerage, donating coats of arms at the same time, but in these cases the
                    letters’ patent always explicitly referred to the act of ennoblement. In some
                    exceptional cases, however, patents of arms were officially recognised as
                    patents of nobility.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> E. Riedenauer, “Kaiserliche Standeserhebungen für
                            reichsstädtische Bürger 1519–1740. Ein statistischer Vorbericht zum
                            Thema “Kaiser und Patriziat”,” in <hi rend="italic">Deutsches Patriziat
                                1430–1740</hi>, ed. H. Rössler (Limburg a.d. Lahn: C. A. Starke
                            Verlag, 1968), 27–98, here 90, n. 35.</p>
                    </note> Moses’ charter does not contain any reference to the nobility, so he was
                    not raised to the noble rank, which is also confirmed by heraldic elements. In
                    the German heraldic tradition, the form of the helm denoted to the social rank
                    of the coat of arms holder: the so-called close helm (Stechhelm) was the
                    standard helm for burghers, while the open helm (Spangenhelm or Bügelhelm) was
                    reserved for the noblemen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> F. Gall, <hi rend="italic">Österreichische
                                Wappenkunde. Handbuch der Wappenwissenschaft</hi>,
                            (Wien–Köln–Weimar: Böhlau, 1996), 16; E. Gritzner, “Heraldik,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Grundriß der Geschichtswissenschaft</hi>, I/4. ed. A.
                            Meister (Lepzig–Berlin: B.G. Teubner, 1912), 59–97, here 78. The
                            Habsburg rulers tried to implement this practice in Hungary as well, and
                            the open helms were simply crossed out by the chancellery on the
                            request, if the petitioner was not entitled to it. Cf. Nyulásziné
                            Straub, É. <hi rend="italic">Magyarország címerkönyve. A heraldika
                                alapjai</hi>, (Budapest: Ceba, 2001), 132.</p>
                    </note> In the description of Moses’ heraldic achievement, the close helm (<hi
                        rend="italic">galea clausa</hi>) is mentioned, and other nobiliary elements,
                    like the crown of nobility and the supporters, are lacking,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Gall, Österreichische Wappenkunde, 17; Biewer and
                            Henning, Wappen, 137–138.</p>
                    </note> so it is in accordance with the rest of the document.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Beyond nobility, other privileges could also be donated with a coat of arms,
                    like exemption from personal rates and taxes (<hi rend="italic">exemptio ab
                        oneribus</hi>), admission in the service of the emperor (<hi rend="italic"
                        >familiaritas</hi>), the right to seal with red wax (<hi rend="italic">ius
                        cerae rubeae</hi>), etc., but Moses does not seem to have obtained any of
                    these. The only thing Moses was authorised in possession of this charter is the
                    use of the coat of arms described in the document. For the subjects of a
                    European monarchy, such a privilege had far-reaching consequences; it was the
                    symbol of social advancement, the antechamber of nobility.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Riedenauer, Kaiserliche Standeserhebungen, 35;
                            Biewer and Henning, Wappen, 47.</p>
                    </note> But for Moses, it was apparently not easy to assess the importance of
                    this favour.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.10" xml:lang="en">
                <head>8. On the use of the coat of arms (<hi rend="italic">dispositio</hi>)</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The document thoroughly describes the possible use of the coat of arms:</p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block">“in exercises, in serious or ludic campaigns, at games of
                    javelin tossing or in contests of infantry and cavalry spearmen, in battles,
                    duels, single contests, in any kind of close combats or fights with ranged
                    weapons, on shields, banners, standards, tents, tombs, seals, memorials, signet
                    rings, buildings, furnishings…” (f. 4r)</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It would be interesting to know whether and in which circumstances Moses used his
                    coat of arms. This question is difficult to answer, especially because the
                    number of documents related to Moses is very restricted, but some basic
                    considerations can be offered.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> After leaving Vienna, Moses travelled to Venice and embarked to sail for Syria.
                    On his way, he stopped on Cyprus, in Famagusta, where he sold a copy of the
                    Syriac New Testament to a certain Georges de Revelles on 18 October 1556. The
                    purchaser noted on the title page of the book that he bought it from “Moses of
                    Mardin from Mesopotamia, Catholic bishop.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100"
                        n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone, Monsignore, 84.</p>
                    </note> It is not known what the reason was for the misunderstanding, whether
                    Moses introduced himself as a Catholic prelate or not,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> The question of Moses’ bishophood has been treated
                            by several scholars. Kiraz proposed that he might had been consecrated
                            by Patriarch Niꜥamatallah. G. A.  Kiraz, “Introduction to the Gorgias
                            Reprint,” in <hi rend="italic">The Widmanstadt—Moses of Mardin Editio
                                princeps of the Syriac Gospels of 1555</hi> (Piscataway: Gorgias
                            Press, 2006), i–vi, here vi. Van Rompay suggested that it was only an
                            honorific title. Van Rompay, Mushe of Mardin, 301. Borbone conducted a
                            thorough investigation and concluded that Moses was never consecrated
                            bishop. He opined that “<hi rend="italic">Moses had a tendency, so to
                                say, to overstate his position</hi>”. Borbone, Monsignore,
                            83–85.</p>
                    </note> but his seal might have played a part in it. We are informed about his
                    seal from one of his letters: “As for what you said that ‘there is a cross on
                    your seal,’ [know] that the cross is not [only] for the metropolitans, but
                    [also] for every baptised people who are baptised in the name of the Holy
                        Trinity<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Letter sent by Moses to Masius from Venice, 15 July
                            1553: Berlin, Staatsbibliothek, Ms. or. fol. 13, f. 20v <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܕܐܡܼܪܬ ܕܐܝܬ
                                ܒܚܬܡܐ ܕܝܼܠܟ ܨܠܝܒܐ. ܠܐ ܐܝܬܘ̄ ܠܡܻܛܪܘܦ̈ܘܠܝܛܐ ܨܠܝܒܐ. ܐܠܐ ܠܟܠ ܥܡܝܕܐ
                                ܕܐܬܥܡܕ ܒܫܡܗܿ ܕܬܠܝܬܝܘܬܐ ܩܕܝܫ̄</foreign>.</p>
                    </note> Apparently, Moses felt compelled to give an answer to Masius who had
                    presumably objected the use of the cross in his heraldic bearings, which was the
                    privilege of bishops. The seals are no more visible on the letters, but Andreas
                    Müller still saw them in the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century and
                    prepared a sketch of it in his book (see Figure 4). This shows a shield divided
                    into four quarters, the first and fourth a cross crosslet, the second and the
                    third a cock. This latter is the symbol of audacity and combativeness, but in
                    Christian context, it is likely a reference to the story of St. Peter’s
                        denial.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Müller, Epistolae duae, 27.</p>
                    </note> The cross objected by Masius is the one appearing on the shield or
                    rather behind the shield, which in this form was indeed reserved for
                        bishops.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> B. B. Heim, Heraldry in the Catholic Church: Its
                            Origin, Customs, and Laws, (New Jersey: Humanities Press, 1978),74.</p>
                    </note> Moses acquired this seal in Rome before coming to Vienna,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> This becomes clear from the letter he sent on 8
                            June 1553 from Rome, in which he proudly described his probably new seal
                            to Masius: “<hi rend="italic">Here is my seal. Moses is written above
                                around the supreme cross.</hi>” <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܢܘ ܚܬܡܐ ܕܝܠܝ.
                                ܘܗܐ ܟܬܝܒ ܠܥܠ. ܡܘܣܝ. ܚܕܪܝ ܨܠܝܒܐ ܥܹܠܝܐ</foreign>.. Müller, Epistolae duae,
                            8. This inscription is not visible on the letter today, as it was
                            written in the wax, ‘<hi rend="italic">ad oram sigilli</hi>’, and
                            perished with the seal. In the light of this, it is not clear, why
                            Müller deciphered the letters on the seal as MWSW and not MWSY. He
                            wrote, that on both sides of the cross there are two-two Syriac letters
                            abbreviating Moses’ name: MŪsā SŪryō.</p>
                    </note> and he did not hasten to cut a new one with his new coat of arms, as he
                    apparently continued to use it after leaving the city.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> Although Moses was planning to return to Europe with Syriac manuscripts as soon
                    as possible, he stayed in the Near East for two decades and reappeared in Rome
                    only in 1578. He lived there until his death, probably 1592, and left his mark
                    on a number of manuscripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Manuscripts he copied or composed entirely or
                            partially: Roma, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Vat. ar. 902, Barb. or.
                            87, Barb. or. 29, Vat. syr. 229, Vat. ar. 945, Barb. or. 76, Vat. syr.
                            36, Vat. syr. 227, Vat. ar. 83, Vat. ar. 141, Vat. syr. 214, Vat. ar.
                            1482; Firenze, Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana, Or. 209, Or. 254.
                            Manuscripts containing his purchase note or reader’s note: Roma,
                            Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Vat. ar. 22, Vat. ar. 6, Vat. ar. 7,
                            Vat. ar. 114, Vat. ar. 81, Vat. ar. 328, Vat. syr. 6, Vat. syr. 18, Vat.
                            syr. 35, Vat. syr. 95, Vat. syr. 107, Vat. syr. 108, Vat. syr. 156, Vat.
                            syr. 158. Cf. Levi della Vida, Ricerche, 206–215, 415–423, 435; Borbone,
                            Monsignore, 99–113.</p>
                    </note> There is a codex in which he copied three texts and at the end of one of
                    them, there is a trace of a seal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> It is the response of Patriarch Michael III
                            (1170–1178) containing his profession of faith to the emperor Manuel I
                            Komnenos (1143–1180), Roma, Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, Vat. ar. 83,
                            ff. 52r–66v.</p>
                    </note> Unfortunately, the surface is blurred and the original figure is
                    invisible. However, the colophon helps to find out what kind of seal it could
                    be, as it reads: “With God’s help, the letter sent by Patriarch of the Syrians
                    to the king Manuel has been finished. Glory be to God. Amen. It was translated
                    from Syriac into Arabic by the miserable Moses, bishop only by name from the
                    denomination of the Syrians<hi rend="italic">.</hi>”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Vat. ar. 83, f. 66r: <foreign xml:lang="ar">بعون الله كملت
                                الرسالة الذي بعث بطريرك السريان للملك منولي. والحمد لله امين. ناقلها
                                من السرياني للعربي موسى الحقير بسم مطران من طايفة السريان.</foreign>
                            Another hand added here: <foreign xml:lang="ar">اليعاقبة
                                المشارقة</foreign>.</p>
                    </note> It was not the only occasion when Moses appeared as a bishop. In most of
                    his signatures during this last period of his life, he used this title.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text"> Borbone published nine such examples. Cf. Borbone,
                            Monsignore, 107–113. Two further instances in Vatican manuscripts: Roma,
                            Biblioteca ApostolicaVaticana, Vat. ar. 7, f. 1: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܫܬܪܝ ܗܕܐ ܐܠܟܬܐܒ
                                ܐܠܡܙܐܡܝܪ ܐܠܡܛܪܐܢ ܡܘܣܝ ܐܠܣܪܝܐܢܝ. ܡܢ ܐܠܫܡܐܣ ܝܘܣܦ ܐܒܢ ܓܒܪܝܐܠ ܘܘܐܠܕܬܗ
                                ܬܐܓ ܐܠܠܗ ܬܥܐܠܝ ܝܢܝܚ ܐܢܦܣܗܡ ܐܡܝܢ. ܘܐܟܝܗ ܐܒܢ ܝܐܡܝܢ. ܘܟܐܢ ܒܚܛܪܗ̈ ܐܠܫܡܐܣ
                                ܝܘܣܦ ܐܒܢ ܐܠܫܡ[ܐܣ...] ܐܠܚܡܨܝ. ܘܐܠܫܡܐܣ ܣܠܝܡܢ. ܐܠܠܗ ܝܪܚܡ ܐܡܘܐܬܗܡ ܘܐܡܘܐܬ
                                ܓܡܝܥ ܐܠܡܘܡܢܝܢ ܒܐܠܣܝܕ ܐܠܡܣܝܚ ܐܡܝܢ</foreign>; Vat. ar. 22, f. 127: <foreign xml:lang="ar">كملت رسالة
                                يعقوب والمجد لله دايماً ابدا امين على يد احقر عباد الله موسى بسم
                                مطران</foreign>.</p>
                    </note> Whether he was a consecrated bishop or he ascribed to himself this title
                    illicitly, he probably continued to use his old seal, since it was more suitable
                    to pretend that he was a bishop.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> In sum, until now not a single object has been found with Moses’ coat of arms.
                    In all likelihood, he did not cut it onto a seal. The other possibilities of use
                    were not really realistic in Moses’ case, so it might be the case that he never
                    used the coat of arms he was granted by Ferdinand on 15 March 1556.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.11" xml:lang="en">
                <head>References</head>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Primary sources</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Bayerische Staatsbibliothek</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <hi rend="italic">Liber Sacrosancti Evangelii de Iesv Christo Domino &amp;
                            Deo nostro. Reliqua hoc Codice comprehensa pagina proxima indicabit.
                            Div. Ferdinandi Rom. Imperatoris designati iussu &amp; liberalitate,
                            characteribus &amp; lingua Syra, Iesv Christo vernacula, Diuino ipsius
                            ore cõsecrata, et a Ioh. Euãgelista Hebraica dicta, Scriptorio Prelo
                            diligẽter Expressa</hi>. Johann Albrecht Widmanstetter and Moses of
                        Mardin (eds.) 1555. Viennae Austria: Michael Zymmerman = Widmannstetter,
                        Johann Albrecht. <hi rend="italic">Ketābā d-ewangelyōn qaddīšā de-māran
                            w-alāhan Yešuʿ mešihā</hi>. Rar. 155. Online access: <ref
                            target="http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/~db/0007/bsb00070810/images/"
                            >http://daten.digitale-sammlungen.de/~db/0007/bsb00070810/images/</ref>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cod. Syr. 5</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cod. Syr. 6</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Biblioteca ApostolicaVaticana</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. Vat. ar. 7</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. Vat. ar. 22</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. Vat. ar. 83</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Leiden University Library</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. Or. 26.756</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Unknown author, <hi rend="italic">Historia collegii Societatis Iesu
                            Viennensis pars I a. 1552-1638</hi>. Sammlung von Handschriften und
                        alten Drucken, Cod. 8367. Online access: <ref
                            target="http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/10006117">
                            <hi rend="color(808080)">http://data.onb.ac.at/rep/10006117</hi>
                        </ref>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cod. 15162</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. Syr. 1.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Österreichisches Staatsarchiv, Allgemeines Verwaltungsarchiv</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">‘Wappenbrief, Moses Meredineus, Wien, 15 March 1556.’Adelsakten,
                        Reichsadelsakten, box 272, no. 57.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Österreichisches Staatsarchiv, Haus-, Hof- und Staatsarchiv</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Reichskanzlei, Reichsregisterbücher, 7 Reichsregister Ferdinand I.
                        (1548–1558)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Pannonhalmi Főapátság</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Maggio, L. S.J. <hi rend="italic">Historia Collegii Societatis Iesu
                            Viennensis ab anno 1550 usque ad annum 1567</hi>. Ms. 118.E.5</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ms. or. fol. 13</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Secondary sources</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Assfalg, J. <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss der orientalischen Handschriften
                            in Deutschland</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vol. V. Syrische
                            Handschriften</hi>. Wiesbaden: Franz Steiner Verlag, 1963.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Aumer, J. <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniß der orientalischen Handschriften der
                            K. Hof- und Staatsbibliothek in München: mit Ausschluß der hebraeischen,
                            arabischen und persischen; nebst Anhang zum Verzeichnis der arabischen
                            und persischen Handschriften</hi> 1875, Reprinted Wiesbaden: Otto
                        Harrassowitz, 1970.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Barṣawm, I. A. <hi
                            rend="italic">Sriṭoto d-Omid w-Merdo. Makhṭūṭāt Āmid wa-Mārdīn. Omid &amp; Mardin Manuscripts</hi>. Ed.
                            Ignaṭiyus Zakkay I,
                        Ma‘arrat Ṣaydnāyā: Dayro d-Mor
                        Afrem Suryoyo, 2008.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Bauer, K. F.<hi rend="italic"> Das Bürgerwappen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Das
                            Buch von den Wappen und Eigenmarken der deutschen Bürger und
                        Bauern</hi>. Frankfurt am Main: Verlag der Hauserpresse, 1935.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Biewer, L. and E. Henning. <hi rend="italic">Wappen. Handbuch der
                            Heraldik</hi>. Köln–Weimar–Wien: Böhlau Verlag, 2017.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Borbone, P. G. “From Tur ‛Abdin to Rome: The Syro-Orthodox Presence in
                        Sixteenth-Century Rome.” In <hi rend="italic">Syriac in Its Multi-Cultural
                            Context: First International Syriac Studies Symposium, Mardin Artuklu
                            University, Institute of Living Languages, 20-22 April 2012,
                        Mardin</hi>, Eastern Christian Studies 23, eds. H.G.B. Teule, E.
                        Keser-Kayaalp, K. Akalin, N. Doru, M.S. Toprak. Leuven: Peeters, 2017,
                        277–288.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Borbone, P. G. ““Monsignore Vescovo di Soria”, also Known as Moses of Mardin,
                        Scribe and Book Collector.” <hi rend="italic">Khristianskii Vostok</hi> 8
                        (2017): 79–114.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Braunsberger, O. <hi rend="italic">Beati Petri Canisii, Societatis Iesu,
                            Epistulae et acta. Vol I.</hi> Friburgi Brisgoviae: Herder, 1896.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Breicha-Vauthier, A. “Le cadre historique de la publication du manuscript.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Le livre et le Liban jusqu'a 1900. Exposition</hi>, ed.
                        C. Aboussouan. Paris: Unesco–Agecoop, 1982, 125–126.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cardinali, G. “Ritratto di Marcello Cervini en orientaliste (con precisazioni
                        alle vicende di Petrus Damascenus, Mosè di Mārdīn ed Heliodorus Niger).” <hi
                            rend="italic">Bibliothèque d'Humanisme et Renaissance</hi> 80:1 (2018):
                        77–98 and 80:2 (2018): 325–343.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cecini, U. “Johann Albrecht Widmanstetter.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Christian-Muslim Relations: A Bibliographical History. Vol. VII.
                            1500-1600</hi>, eds. D. Thomas and J. Chesworth. Leiden–Boston: Brill,
                        2015, 235–239.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Csízi I. “Kora újkori nemesi címerek.” In <hi rend="italic">Heraldika</hi>.
                        ed. Kollega Tarsoly I. and Kovács E. Budapest: Tarsoly Kiadó, 2018,
                        155–208.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">François, W. “Andreas Masius (1514–1573): Humanist, Exegete and Syriac
                        Scholar.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi> 61:3
                        (2009): 199–244.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">von Frank, K. F. <hi rend="italic">Standeserhebungen und Gnadenakte für das
                            Deutsche Reich und die Österreichischen Erblande bis 1806 sowie
                            kaiserlich österreichische bis 1823 mit einigen Nachträgen zum
                            Alt-Österreichischen Adels-Lexikon 1823-1918</hi>. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Vol. III.</hi>, Schloss Senftenegg: Selbstverlag, 1967.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Gall, F. <hi rend="italic">Alma Mater Rudolphina, 1365–1965. Die Wiener
                            Universität und ihre Studenten</hi>. Wien: Verlag Austria Press,
                        1965.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Gall, F. <hi rend="italic">Österreichische Wappenkunde. Handbuch der
                            Wappenwissenschaft</hi>. Wien–Köln–Weimar: Böhlau, 1996.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">von Gévay, A. <hi rend="italic">Itinerar Kaiser Ferdinanďs I. 1521–1564</hi>.
                        Wien: Strauhssel. Witwe Und Sommer, 1843.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Gritzner, E. “Heraldik.” In <hi rend="italic">Grundriß der
                            Geschichtswissenschaft</hi>, I/4. ed. A. Meister. Lepzig – Berlin: B.G.
                        Teubner, 1912, 59–97.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Guidi, I. “La prima stampa del Nuovo Testamento in etiopico, fatta in Roma
                        nel 1548-1549.” <hi rend="italic">Archivio della R. Società Romana di Storia
                            Patria</hi> 9 (1886): 273–278.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Heim, B. B. <hi rend="italic">Heraldry in the Catholic Church: Its Origin,
                            Customs, and Laws</hi>. New Jersey: Humanities Press, 1978.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Heiss, G. “Die Wiener Jesuiten und das Studium der Theologie und der Artes an
                        der Universität und im Kolleg im ersten Jahrzehnt nach ihrer Berufung
                        (1551).” In <hi rend="italic">Die Universität Wien im Konzert europäischer
                            Bildungszentren 14.-16. Jahrhundert</hi>, Veröffentlichungen des
                        Instituts für Österreichische Geschichtsforschung 56, ed. K. Mühlberger and
                        M. Niederkorn-Bruck. Wien–München: Oldenbourg–Böhlau, 2010, 245–268.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Hyvernat, H. “An Ancient Syriac Lexicographer.” <hi rend="italic">The
                            Catholic University Bulletin</hi> 8 (1902): 58–74.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Juel-Jensen, B. “Potken’s Psalter and Tesfa Tsion’s New Testament, Modus
                        baptizandi and Missal.” <hi rend="italic">Bodleian Library Record</hi> 15
                        (1996): 480–496.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Kajatin, C. “Königliche Macht und bürgerlicher Stolz. Wappen- und Adelsbriefe
                        in Zürich.” In <hi rend="italic">Alter Adel - neuer Adel? Zürcher Adel
                            zwischen Spätmittelalter und Früher Neuzeit</hi>, ed. P. Niederhäuser.
                        Zürich: Chronos Verlag, 2003, 203–210.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Kennerley, S. “Ethiopian Christians in Rome c.1400-1750.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Religious Minorities in Early Modern Rome</hi>. ed. E.
                        Michelson. Forthcoming.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Kessel, G. “Moses of Mardin (d. 1592).” <hi rend="italic">Manuscript
                            Cultures</hi> 9 (2016): 146–151.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Kink, R. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der kaiserlichen Universität zu
                            Wien</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vol I.</hi> Wien: Carl Gerold &amp; Sohn,
                        1854.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Kiraz, G. A. “Introduction to the Gorgias Reprint.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            Widmanstadt—Moses of Mardin Editio princeps of the Syriac Gospels of
                            1555, </hi>Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2006, i–vi.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Leroy, J. “Une copie syriaque du Missale Romanum de Paul III et son
                        arrière-plan historique.” <hi rend="italic">Mélanges de l’Université Saint
                            Joseph</hi> 46 (1970–1971): 355–382.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Levi della Vida, G. <hi rend="italic">Ricerche sulla formazione del più
                            antico fondo dei manoscritti orientali della biblioteca vaticana</hi>.
                        Studi e testi 92. Città del Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana,
                        1939.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Lossen, M. <hi rend="italic">Briefe von Andreas Masius und seinen Freunden
                            1538 bis 1573.</hi> Publikationen der Gesellschaft für Rheinische
                        Geschichtskunde, II. Leipzig: Verlag von Alphons Dürr, 1886.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Lukács, L. <hi rend="italic">Catalogi personarum et officiorum Provinciae
                            Austriae S.I. Vol I.</hi> Monumenta Historica Societatis Iesu 117.
                        Romae: Institutum Historicum Societatis Iesu, 1978.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Maier, D. “Überlegungen zum Formular von Wappenbriefen der Reichskanzlei
                        (1338–1500)” <hi rend="italic">Mitteilungen des Instituts für
                            Österreichische Geschichtsforschung</hi> 126 (2018): 34–52.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Mansi, J. D. <hi rend="italic">Stephani Baluzii Tutelensis Miscellanea novo
                            ordine digesta et non paucis ineditis monumentis opportunisque
                            animadversionibus aucta</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vol. III</hi>. Lucae:
                        Apud Vincentium Junctinium, 1762.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Masius, A. <hi rend="italic">De paradiso commentarius; scriptus ante annos
                            prope septingentos à Mose Bar-Cepha Syro; Episcopo in Beth-Raman &amp;
                            Beth-Ceno; ac Curatore rerum sacrarum in Mozal, hoc est Seleucia
                            Parthorum</hi>. Antverpiae: Ex Officina Christophori Plantini, 1569.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">McCollum, A. “Prolegomena to a New Edition of Eliya of Nisibis's Kitāb
                        al-turjumān fī taʿlīm luġat al-suryān.” <hi rend="italic">JSS</hi> 58
                        (2013): 297–322.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">McNamee, M. B. <hi rend="italic">Vested Angels: Eucharistic Allusions in
                            Early Netherlandish Paintings</hi>. Leuven: Peeters, 1998.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Mühlberger, K. “Universität und Jesuitenkolleg in Wien: Von der Berufung des
                        Ordens bis zum Bau des Akademischen Kollegs.” In <hi rend="italic">Die
                            Jesuiten in Wien</hi>, ed. H. Karner and W. Telesko. Wien: Austrian
                        Academy of Sciences Press, 2003, 21–37.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Müller, A. “Epistolae duae Syriacae amoebaeae. Una Mosis Mardeni, Sacerdotis
                        Syri, altera Andreae Masii, JCti et Consil. Olim Cliviaci cum versione et
                        notis.” In: <hi rend="italic">Symbolae syriacae, </hi>ed. A. Müller.
                        Berolini, 1673, 1–36.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Müller, A. “Dissertationes duae de rebus itidem Syriacis, et e reliquis
                        Mardeni Epistolis maxime. De Mose Mardeno, una; De Syriacis librorum
                        sacrorum Versionibus… altera. Coloniae Brandeburgicae.” In<hi rend="italic">
                            Symbolae syriacae, </hi>ed. A. Müller. Berolini, 1673, 1–46.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Müller, M. <hi rend="italic">Johann Albrecht von Widmanstetter 1506-1557.
                            Sein Leben und Wirken</hi>. Bamberg: Verlag der Handels Druckerei,
                        1907.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Nadal, G. <hi rend="italic">Epistolae P. Hieronymi Nadal, Societatis Jesu ab
                            anno 1546 ad 1577 nunc primum editae et illustratae a patribus ejusdem
                            societatis. Vol. I.</hi> Monumenta Historica Societatis Iesu. Matriti:
                        Typis Augustini Avrial, 1898.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Neck, R. “Diplomatische Beziehungen zum Vorderen Orient unter Karl V.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Mitteilungen des österreichischen Staatsarchivs</hi> 5
                        (1952): 63–86.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Neubecker, O. and W. Rentzmann, 
                        <hi rend="italic">Wappenbilderlexikon. München: Battenberg </hi>1974.
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Nyulásziné Straub, É. <hi rend="italic">Magyarország címerkönyve. A heraldika
                            alapjai</hi>. Budapest: Ceba, 2001.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Palmer, A. <hi rend="italic">Monk and Mason on the Tigris Frontier: The Early
                            History of Tur ͑Abdin</hi>. University of Cambridge Oriental
                        Publications 39. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">von Palombini, B. <hi rend="italic">Bündniswerben abendländischer Mächte um
                            Persien 1453-1600</hi>. Freiburger Islamstuditen I. Wiesbaden: Franz
                        Steiner Verlag, 1968.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Perger, R. and Brauneis, W. <hi rend="italic">Die Mittelalterlichen Kirchen
                            und Klöster Wiens</hi>. Wiener Geschichtsbücher 19. Wien–Hamburg: Paul
                        Zsolnay Verlag, 1977.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">de Polanco, J. A. <hi rend="italic">Vita Ignatii Loiolae et Rerum Societatis
                            Jesu Historia. IV Vols</hi>. Matriti: Augustinus Avrial, 1894–1898.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Pfeifer, G. “Wappenbriefe (unter besonderer Berücksichtigung der Tiroler
                        Verhältnisse).” In <hi rend="italic">Quellenurkunde der Habsburgmonarchie
                            (16.-18. Jahrhundert). Ein exemplarisches Handbuch</hi>, ed. J. Pauser,
                        M. Scheutz and Th. Winkelbauer. Wien–München: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, 2004,
                        291–302.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Rabbath, A. <hi rend="italic">Documents inédits pour servir à l’histoire du
                            christianisme en Orient (</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic smallcaps">xvi</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">ᵉ‒</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic smallcaps">xix</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">ᵉ siècles). Vol. II</hi>. Paris–Leipzig: A. Picard et
                        Fils-Otto Harrassowitz, 1910.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Rekers, B. <hi rend="italic">Benito Arias Montano (1527–1598)</hi>. Studies
                        of the Warburg Institute 33. London: Warburg Institute, University of
                        London, 1971.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Riedenauer, E. “Kaiserliche Standeserhebungen für reichsstädtische Bürger
                        1519–1740. Ein statistischer Vorbericht zum Thema “Kaiser und Patriziat”.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Deutsches Patriziat 1430–1740</hi>, ed. H. Rössler.
                        Limburg a.d. Lahn: C. A. Starke Verlag, 1968, 27–98.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Robinson, A. P. <hi rend="italic">The Career of Cardinal Giovanni Morone
                            (1509-1580): Between Council and Inquisition.</hi> Farnham: Ashgate,
                        2012.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">van Roey, A. “Les études syriaques d'Andreas Masius.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Orientalia Lovaniensia Periodica</hi> 9 (1978): 141–158.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Röhrig, F. <hi rend="italic">Der Albrechtsaltar und sein Meister</hi>. Wien:
                        Tusch, 1981.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">van Rompay, L. “Mushe of Mardin.” In <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic
                            Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</hi>, ed. S. Brock et alii.
                        Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias, 2011, 300–301.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Salvadore, M. “African Cosmopolitanism in the Early Modern Mediterranean: The
                        Diasporic Life of Yohannes, the Ethiopian Pilgrim Who Became a
                        Counter-Reformation Bishop.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of African
                            History</hi>, 58:1 (2017): 61–83.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Sinclair, T. A. <hi rend="italic">Eastern Turkey: An Architectural &amp;
                            Archaeological Survey. Vol. III</hi>. London: Pindar Press, 1989.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Smelova, N. S. and Lipatov-Chicherin, N. A. “Georgii, arkhiepiskop Damasskii:
                        samozvancheskaia intriga v istorii otnoshenii Maronitskoi Tserkvi i Sviatogo
                        Prestola v seredine XVI v.” <hi rend="italic">Khristianskii Vostok</hi> 6
                        (2013): 244–311.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Socin, A. “Zur Geographie des Ṭūr ʿAbdīn.” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der deutschen
                            morgenlindischen Gesellschaft</hi> 34 (1881): 237–269.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Steimel, R. “Der Dreiberg. Zum Rechtssinnbild im Wappen.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Germanien </hi>13 (1941): 58–65.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Stow, K. R. “The Burning of the Talmud in 1553, in the Light of Sixteenth
                        Century Catholic Attitudes Toward the Talmud.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bibliothèque d'Humanisme et Renaissance</hi> 34:3 (1972): 435–459.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wesselius, J. W. “The Syriac Correspondance of Andreas Masius : A Preliminary
                        Report.” In <hi rend="italic">V. Symposium Syriacum, 1988: Katholieke
                            Universiteit, Leuven, 29‒31 août 1988</hi>, Orientalia Christiana
                        Analecta 236, ed. R. Lavenant. Roma: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum
                        Orientalium, 1990, 21–29.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wilkinson, R. J. <hi rend="italic">Orientalism, Aramaic and Kabbalah in the
                            Catholic Reformation. The First Printing of the Syriac New
                            Testament.</hi> Leiden‒Boston: Brill, 2007.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wilkinson, R. J. <hi rend="italic">The Kabbalistic Scholars of the Antwerp
                            Polyglot Bible.</hi> Leiden‒Boston: Brill, 2007.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wießner, G. <hi rend="italic">Christliche Kultbauten im </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Ṭūr ʿAbdīn. Teil I. Kultbauten mit traverserem Schiff und
                            Felsanlagen. Textband</hi>. Studien für spätantiken und frühchristlichen
                        Kunst 4. Wiesbaden: Otto Harrassowitz, 1982.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wrba, J. “In der Nähe des Königs. Die Gründung des Jesuitenkollegs in Wien.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Ignatius von Loyola und die Gesellschaft Jesu
                            1491‒1556</hi>, ed. A. Falkner and P. Imhof. Würzburg: Echter, 1990,
                        331‒357.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Wright, W. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac manuscripts in the British
                            Museum acquired since the year 1838</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Vol. I.</hi>
                        London: Gilbert and Rivington, 1870.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">
                        <pb/>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.12" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Annexe</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Below is the edition of the draft copy of Moses of Mardin’s grant of arms
                    (Österreichisches Staatsarchiv, Reichsadelsakten, box 272, no. 57.). This
                    version has been chosen, because it is more extent than the fair copy, i.e.
                    contains the entire text of the document and the description of the first sketch
                    of Moses’ coat of arms. As this latter was crossed out by the scribe, it is also
                        <hi rend="strikethrough">crossed out</hi> in this edition. Only the main
                    body of the text is published here, other inscriptions are discussed above in
                    the article. Abbreviations are expanded and the articulation of the text is
                    designed to ease the understanding.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">(2r) Ferdinandus etc honorabili, devoto, nobis dilecto Mosi Meredineo Sacerdoti
                    Syro Catholico gratiam nostram regiam et omne bonum. Existimamus Regiam
                    Maiestatem decere non solum subditos suos benemerentes liberalitate et
                    munificentia sua prosequi, verum etiam exteros et alienigenos, quos integritas
                    vitae et morum probitas scientiarumque exacta cognitio commendabiliores efficere
                    solent. Quam rem eo studiosius facimus, quod hinc existimamus Regiam
                    liberalitatem atque beneficientiam latius divulgari, atque in omnes provincias
                    sese extendere, eoque exemplo ceteros admonitos et incitatos ad virtutis
                    sectandae studia reddi propensiores. Quamobrem cum tu praefatus Moses Meredineus
                    Sacerdos Syrus ob egregias animi tui dotes, pietatem, religionem vitaeque
                    sanctimoniam, fidedigno luculentoque multorum testimonio abunde nobis sis
                    cognitus: intellexerimusque quam magna cum laude reipublicae Christianae
                    consulueris in excudendis Novo Testamento aliisque sanctissimis libris Syriaco
                    idiomate, et quantum denique operae et industriae ea in re collocaris, debemus
                    profecto ea omnia non clementi (2v) solum animo agnoscere, sed et peculiari
                    aliquo ornamento atque adeo munificentiae nostrae beneficio remunerare, ut ipse
                    bene actae vitae industriaeque tuae memoriam nostro testimonio auctoritateque
                    comprobatam ad posteros usque transmittere queas, tuoque exemplo alii ad bene
                    recteque vivendum inflammentur incitenturque.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Proinde ex certa nostra scientia animoque bene deliberato et de nostrae regiae
                    potestatis plenitudine tibi praefato Mosi Meredineo et fratribus tuis, Bartomae,
                    idest filio ieiunii, et Simeoni et Ieschua, filiis Isaaci sacerdotis in Caluq
                    villa ad montem Coros provinciae Zaur, legitime coniugati ac filiis vestrum
                    legitimo thoro natis, et deinceps nascituris in perpetuum infrascripta
                    insignia:</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <hi rend="strikethrough">clypeum scilicet caeruleum, in quo sint tres montes
                        aurei et super iis ecclesia biturrata argentea cum tecto semicirculari rubeo
                        et tectis duarum turrium itidem rubeis. Scuto ad[?]statur galea clausa,
                        cuius vertice surgat timidius angelus caeruleus praecinctus cum vexillo a
                        dextra candido et litteris V.S.E.C. rubeis significantibus Unam Sanctam
                        Ecclesiam Catholicam. Porro in manu sinistra teneat librum evangelicum
                        apertum. Ex galea utrinque defluant phalerae, quarum alterae sinistrae sint
                        coloris rubei et argentei, alterae vero dextrae caerulei et crocei aureive.
                        Angelus autem sit cinctus stola candida seu fascia candida,</hi>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">clypeum scilicet caeruleum, e cuius immo exurgant tres colliculi flavi aureive,
                    quorum medius altius paulo quam caeteri attollatur, sustineantque ecclesiam
                    biturritam albam cum tecto semicirculari rubeo, et tectis duarum turrium itidem
                    rubeis et fastigiatis, atque in cruces flavas aureasque desinentibus, quarum
                    utraque turris superne fenestra oblonga illustrari conspicitur, prout et in
                    pariete intermedio porta patens et tres fenestrae orbiculares forma triangulari,
                    sub tecto nimirum una et bine iuxta portae superius limen dispositae apparent.
                    (3r) Scuto imponatur galea clausa equestris phaleris seu laciniis et id genus
                    ornamentis ad laevam albis vel argenteis et rubeis ad dextram croceis seu aureis
                    et coelestinis molliter defluentibus et circumfusis ornata e cuius vertice.
                    Pubetenus emineat imago angeli veste lauzurea fluxa praecinctus, humeros vero
                    fascia (quam stolam Ecclesiastici appellant) candida ita redimitus ut in pectore
                    decussim faciat, alis expansis et rubeo albicante ac viridi coloribus
                    conspicuis, coma flava, et utroque lacerto ad cubitum usque nudato atque
                    extenso, tenens sinistra manu librum evangelicum apertum, dextra vexillum album
                    in cunei modu, formatu hastili flavo aureove et mucronis loco cruce aurea
                    superne ornato, in quo vexillo quatuor litterae rubreae V.S.E.C. Unam Sanctam
                    Ecclesiam Catholicam denotantes descriptae seu depictae cernuntur,</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">(2v) uti haec omnia pictoris ars et ingenium in medio huiusce nostri diplomatis
                    regii melius representavit, clementer concessimus, donavimus et elargiti sumus,
                    (4r) pro ut harum litterarum nostrarum vigore donamus, concedimus et elargimur,
                    expresse statuentes ac decernentes, quod tu, Moses fratresque tui praedicti,
                    filiique, nepotes, heredes et descendentes legitimi utriusque sexus in omnem
                    posteritatem iam descripta armorum insignia ex hoc tempore deinceps in perpetuum
                    in omnibus et singulis honestis ac decentibus actibus, exercitiis et
                    expeditionibus tam serio, quam ioco, in hastilibus ludis seu hastatorum
                    dimicationibus pedestribus vel equestribus, in bellis, duellis singularibusque
                    certaminibus et quibuscumque pugnis eminus, cominus, in scutis, banneriis,
                    vexillis, tentoriis, sepulchris, sigillis, monumentis, annulis, aedificiis,
                    suppellectilibus, tam in rebus spiritualibus, quam temporalibus et mixtis, in
                    locis omnibus, prout vobis libitum fuerit, aut necessitas vestra postulaverit,
                    habere, gestare et deferre, ac simul quibuslibet privilegiis, immunitatibus,
                    libertatibus et iuribus uti, frui ac gaudere possitis, quibus alii quoque
                    armigeri seu huiuscemodi armorum vel insignium ornamentis decorati utuntur,
                    fruuntur et gaudent iure vel consuetudine. Quapropter omnibus et singulis
                    ecclesiasticis et secularibus, electoribus, principibus, archiepiscopis,
                    episcopis, ducibus, marchionibus, comitibus, baronibus, militibus, nobilibus,
                    clientibus, capitaneis, vicedominis, advocatis, praefectis, procuratoribus,
                    officialibus, quaestoribus, civium magistris, iudicibus, consulibus, regum
                    heraldis et caduceatoribus et denique omnibus nostris et Sacri Romani Imperii ac
                    quorumcumque regnorum, et avitorum nostrorum (4v) dominiorum, et provinciarum
                    nostrarum haereditariarum subditis et fidelibus dilectis cuiuscumque status,
                    gradus, ordinis, conditionis et praeminentiae fuerint, seu quacumque perfulgeant
                    dignitate, firmiter mandamus et praecipimus, ut te praefatum Mosen Meredineum,
                    praedictosque tuos fratres ac liberos, nepotes, heredes et posteros ex vobis
                    legitimo connubio prognatos ac in perpetuum descensuros praescriptis armorum
                    insignibus ac omnibus et singulis honoribus, privilegiis, immunitatibus et
                    iuribus, quibus alii nostri et Sacri Romani Imperii armigeri seu armorum
                    insignibus decorati utuntur, fruuntur, potiuntur et gaudent, libere, pacifice et
                    sine molestia aut impedimento uti, frui, potiri et gaudere sinant, et ab aliis
                    etiam permitti curent.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Quatenus gravissimam indignationem nostram et mulctam XXV. marcharum auri puri
                    fisco nostro regio et parti laesae ex aequo, omni spe veniae sublata, solvendam
                    evitare voluerint, quam poenam his, qui hoc diploma et rescriptum nostrum
                    observare neglexerint aut spreverint, quotiescumque scilicet temere illi
                    adversati fuerint irrogandam decernimus et statuimus.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In cuius rei ampliorem fidem atque testimonium hisce litteris nostris manu nostra
                    propria subscriptis sigillum nostrum regium appendi voluimus.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Datum Viennae, 15 mensibus Martii Anno Domini 1556</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <pb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv22n2mercz.13" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Figures</head>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <p rend="bold">Figure 1: Moses’ coat of arms. Copyright by Rita Várfalvi.</p>
                    <p>
                        <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV22N2Mercz_image1.jpg" rend="center"/>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="bold">Figure 2: St. Stephen’s Cathedral, detail of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Albertinischer Plan</hi>, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>
                        half of the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century (the original is dated
                        to 1421/1422), Copyright by Wien Museum.</p>
                    <p>
                        <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV22N2Mercz_image2.jpg" rend="center"/>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="bold">Figure 3: Mary, Queen of Archangels. Albrechtsmeister:
                        Albrechtsaltar. Copyright by Stift Klosterneuburg.</p>
                    <p>
                        <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV22N2Mercz_image3.jpg" rend="center"/>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="bold">Figure 4: Moses’ seal. Copyright by Rita Várfalvi.</p>
                    <p>
                        <graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV22N2Mercz_image4.jpg" rend="center"/>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
