<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2018</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                        <surname>Brock</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Grigory</forename>
                        <surname>Kessel</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences and University of Manchester</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sergey</forename>
                        <surname>Minov</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2019</date>
                <idno>Volume 22.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv22n1bib-recent</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Sebastian P. Brock</author>
                        <author>Grigory Kessel</author>
                        <author>Sergey Minov</author>
                        <title level="a">Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2018</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol22/HV22N1Bib-Recent.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2019</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="235" to="293">235–293</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="6"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>

            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2019-03-08">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="bibliography">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <head>Recent Publications on Syriac Topics: 2018∗</head>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p xml:lang="en">∗ The list of publications
                        is based on the online <hi rend="italic">Comprehensive Bibliography on
                            Syriac Christianity</hi>, supported by the Center for the Study of
                        Christianity at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem (<ref
                            target="http://www.csc.org.il/db/db.aspx?db=SB"
                            >http://www.csc.org.il/db/db.aspx?db=SB</ref>). Suggested additions and
                        corrections can be sent to: csc@mail.huji.ac.il</p></note>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Books</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Acharya, F., <hi rend="italic">Psalmic Odes from Apostolic Times: An
                            Indian Monk’s Meditation</hi> (Bengaluru: ATC Publishers, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Adelman, S., <hi rend="italic">After Saturday Comes Sunday</hi>
                        (Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Alobaidi, T., and Dweik, B., <hi rend="italic">Language Contact and the
                            Syriac Language of the Assyrians in Iraq</hi> (Saarbrücken, Germany:
                        Lambert Academic Publishing, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Andrade, N.J., <hi rend="italic">The Journey of Christianity to India in
                            Late Antiquity: Networks and the Movement of Culture</hi> (Cambridge:
                        Cambridge University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Aravackal, R., <hi rend="italic">The Mystery of the Triple Gradated
                            Church: A Theological Analysis of the Kāḇā d-Massqāṯā (Book of Steps)
                            with Particular Reference to the Writing of Aphrahat and John the
                            Solitary</hi> (Oriental Institute of Religious Studies India
                        Publications 437; Kottayam, India: Oriental Institute of Religious Studies,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Aydin, G. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Syriac Hymnal According to the Rite of
                            the Syriac Orthodox Church of Antioch</hi> (Teaneck, New Jersey: Beth
                        Antioch Press / Syriac Music Institute, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bacall, J., <hi rend="italic">Chaldean Iraqi American Association of
                            Michigan</hi> (Charleston, South Carolina: Arcadia Publishing,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barry, S.C., <hi rend="italic">Syriac Medicine and Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq’s
                            Arabic Translation of the Hippocratic Aphorisms</hi> (Journal of Semitic
                        Studies Supplement 39; Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Belinitzky, B., and Rotman, Y. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Cave of
                            Treasures: Syriac Anthology from Late Antiquity in Hebrew
                            Translation</hi> (Tel Aviv: Tel Aviv University Press, 2018) [in
                        Hebrew].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bcheiry, I., <hi rend="italic">Hagiography, History, and Manuscript
                            Culture: Studies in Syriac Christianity</hi> (Patrimoine Syriaque 9;
                        Kaslik, Liban: Parole de l’Orient, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bhayro, S., Ford, J.N., Levene, D., and Saar, O.-P., <hi rend="italic"
                            >Aramaic Magic Bowls in the Vorderasiatisches Museum in Berlin:
                            Descriptive List and Edition of Selected Texts</hi> (Magical and
                        Religious Literature of Late Antiquity 7; Leiden: Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bruns, P., and Kremer, T. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca:
                            Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi>
                        (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz
                        Verlag, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Buda, L., <hi rend="italic">Mar Ephrem and the Early Syriac Ascetic
                            Tradition</hi> (Mōrān ’Eth’ō 43; Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical
                        Research Institute, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carlson, T.A., <hi rend="italic">Christianity in Fifteenth-Century
                            Iraq</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coakley, J.F., <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts in
                            Cambridge University Library and College Libraries Acquired since
                            1901</hi> (Ely, Cambridgeshire: Jericho Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Deeg, M., <hi rend="italic">Die Strahlende Lehre: Die Stele von Xi’an</hi>
                        (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 12; Wien: LIT, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>den Biesen, K., <hi rend="italic">Hemels Brood en Geestelijke Drank: Orde
                            van de viering van de goddelijke Qurobo volgens de traditie van de
                            Syrisch Orthodoxe Kerk van Antiochië</hi> (Losser, The Netherlands: Bar
                        Ebroyo Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ebeid, B., <hi rend="italic">La Tunica di al-Masīḥ: la Cristologia delle
                            grandi confessioni cristiane dell’Oriente nel X e XI secolo</hi> (Roma:
                        Edizioni Orientalia Christiana, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Falcetta, A., <hi rend="italic">The Daily Discoveries of a Bible Scholar
                            and Manuscript Hunter: A Biography of James Rendel Harris
                            (1852-1941)</hi> (London: T&amp;T Clark, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Farina, M. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur
                            langue</hi> (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Farrokh, K., Maksymiuk, K., and Sánchez Gracia, J., <hi rend="italic">The
                            Siege of Amida (359 CE)</hi> (Siedlce: Siedlce University of Natural
                        Sciences and Humanities, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Feldtkeller, A., and Zeuge-Buberl, U., <hi rend="italic">Networks of
                            Knowledge: Epistemic Entanglement Initiated by American Protestant
                            Missionary Presence in Nineteenth-Century Syria</hi>
                        (Missionsgeschichtliches Archiv 28; Stuttgart: Franz Steiner, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Forness, Ph.M., <hi rend="italic">Preaching Christology in the Roman Near
                            East: A Study of Jacob of Serugh</hi> (Oxford Early Christian Studies;
                        Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gianazza, G., <hi rend="italic">‘Abdisho bar Berīkā (Ebedjesu) (1250ca –
                            m. 1318). I fondamenti della religione (Kitāb uṣūl al-dīn):
                            Introduzione, testo critico arabo e traduzione italiana</hi> (Patrimonio
                        culturale arabo cristiano 14; Bologna: CreateSpace, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>——— (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Ṣalībā Ibn Yūḥannā al-Mawṣilī (XIVe s.).
                            Asfār al-asrār I</hi> (Patrimoine Arabe Chrétien 33; Beirut: Centre de
                        documentation et de recherches arabes chrétiennes, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Testi teologici di Ebedjesu</hi> (Patrimonio
                        culturale arabo cristiano 15; Bologna: CreateSpace, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Girling, K., <hi rend="italic">The Chaldean Catholic Church: Modern
                            History, Ecclesiology and Church-State Relations</hi> (Culture and
                        Civilization in the Middle East; London: Routledge, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Godwin, R.T., <hi rend="italic">Persian Christians at the Chinese Court:
                            The Xi’an Stele and the Early Medieval Church of the East</hi> (London:
                        I.B. Tauris, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Grainger, J.D., <hi rend="italic">Syrian Influences in the Roman Empire to
                            AD 300</hi> (London: Routledge, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gutman, A., <hi rend="italic">Attributive Constructions in North-Eastern
                            Neo-Aramaic</hi> (Studies in Diversity Linguistics 15; Berlin: Language
                        Science Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gzella, H. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Dictionary</hi> (Theological
                        Dictionary of the Old Testament 16; Grand Rapids, Michigan: William B.
                        Eerdmans, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Haile, G., <hi rend="italic">The Ethiopian Orthodox Church’s Tradition on
                            the Holy Cross</hi> (Texts and Studies in Eastern Christianity 10;
                        Leiden: Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harrak, A., <hi rend="italic">Le Monastère de Mar-Behnam à la période
                            atabeg – XIII</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">e</hi><hi rend="italic">
                            s. L’art au service de la foi</hi> (Cahiers d’études syriaques 5; Paris:
                        Geuthner, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. (ed. and tr.), <hi rend="italic">Mar Narsai: Homily 33 on the
                            Sanctification of the Church</hi> (Texts from Christian Late Antiquity
                        54; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hassanabadi, M., Jahani, R., and Jahani, C., <hi rend="italic">A Unified
                            Gospel in Persian: An Old Variant of the Gospels along with Exegetical
                            Comments by Yahyā Ibn Ayvaz-e Tabrīzī-ye Armanī</hi> (Studia Iranica
                        Upsaliensia 33; Uppsala: Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hilkens, A., <hi rend="italic">The Anonymous Syriac Chronicle of 1234 and
                            its Sources</hi> (Bibliothèque de Byzantion 18; Leuven: Peeters,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hollerweger, H., <hi rend="italic">Baum des Lebens: Darstellung und
                            Verehrung des Kreuzes im Orient</hi> (Linz, Austria: Initiative
                        Christlicher Orient und Freunde des Turabdin, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Intagliata, E.E., <hi rend="italic">Palmyra after Zenobia, 273–750: An
                            Archaeological and Historical Reappraisal</hi> (Oxford: Oxbow Books,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jarjour, T., <hi rend="italic">Sense and Sadness: Syriac Chant in
                            Aleppo</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kahl, O., <hi rend="italic">‘Ubaidallāh Ibn Buḫtīšū‘ on Apparent Death:
                            The Kitāb Taḥrīm dafn al-aḥyā’, Arabic Edition and English
                            Translation</hi> (Islamic Philosophy, Theology and Science 105; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kalinin, M.G. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Joseph Ḥazzāyā. Book of the
                            Chapters on Knowledge: Newly Discovered Fragments</hi> (Opera Mystica
                        Syriaca 1; Mount Athos: Interpress, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kavvadas, N., <hi rend="italic">Ephraem der Syrer und Basilios der Große,
                            Justinian und Edessa: Die Begegnung griechischer und syrischer
                            Traditionsautorität in der Ephraemvita und der
                            miaphysitisch-chalkedonische Konflikt</hi> (Supplements to Vigiliae
                        Christianae 146; Leiden: Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Knudsen, E.E., and Wardini, E., <hi rend="italic">Neologisms in Modern
                            Literary Syriac</hi> (Perspectives on Linguistics and Ancient Languages
                        10; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Koonammakkal, T., <hi rend="italic">The Church in the Churches: A Syriac
                            Ecclesiology</hi> (Kuravilangad, Kerala, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kuruvilla, A., <hi rend="italic">Eastern and Reformed: A Theological
                            Enquiry into the Doctrine of Atonement and the Holy Spirit of the Mar
                            Thoma Syrian Church</hi> (Eugene, Oregon: Wipf and Stock Publishers,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loosley Leeming, E., <hi rend="italic">Architecture and Asceticism:
                            Cultural Interaction between Syria and Georgia in Late Antiquity</hi>
                        (Texts and Studies in Eastern Christianity 13; Leiden: Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lorrain, A., <hi rend="italic">Le Commentaire de Théodoret de Cyr sur
                            l’Épître aux Romains: études philologiques et historiques</hi> (Texte
                        und Untersuchungen zur Geschichte der altchristlichen Literatur 179; Berlin:
                        Walter de Gruyter, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Manteghi, H., <hi rend="italic">Alexander the Great in the Persian
                            Tradition: History, Myth and Legend in Medieval Iran</hi> (London: I.B.
                        Tauris, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mathews, E.G., Jr. (ed. and tr.), <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s
                            Additional Homilies on Good Friday</hi> (Texts from Christian Late
                        Antiquity 51, The Metrical Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug; Piscataway, New
                        Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. (tr.), <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homilies on the Six Days of
                            Creation: The Fourth Day</hi> (Texts from Christian Late Antiquity 52,
                        The Metrical Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                        Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Muraoka, T. (ed. and tr.), <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Serugh’s
                            Hexaemeron</hi> (Ancient Near Eastern Studies Supplement Series 52;
                        Leuven: Peeters, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nedungatt, G., <hi rend="italic">Covenant Life, Law and Ministry according
                            to Aphrahat</hi> (Kanonika 26; Roma: Edizioni Orientalia Christiana
                        &amp; Valore Italiano, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Neroth van Vogelpoel, A.C.J., <hi rend="italic">The Commentary of Gabriel
                            of Qatar on the East Syriac Morning Service on Ordinary Days: Text,
                            Translation, and Discussion</hi> (Texts from Christian Late Antiquity
                        53; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Önder, J. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Die Feier der Krankensalbung nach dem
                            Ritus der Syrisch-Orthodoxen Kirche von Antiochien</hi> (Glane / Losser:
                        Bar Hebraeus Verlag, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ondrey, H.T., <hi rend="italic">The Minor Prophets as Christian Scripture
                            in the Commentaries of Theodore of Mopsuestia and Cyril of
                            Alexandria</hi> (Oxford Early Christian Studies; Oxford: Oxford
                        University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Petrovich, R., <hi rend="italic">Living the Life of Light: A Drama of
                            Ascension. A Translation of the Odes of Solomon from Syriac and
                            Commentary</hi> (Reno, Nevada: Jamilian University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Philip, A.T., and Alexander, G., <hi rend="italic">Western Rites of
                            Syriac-Malankara Orthodox Churches: The Mission Untold</hi> (Kerala,
                        India: OCP Publications, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rajan, M., <hi rend="italic">Martyrs, Saints and Prelates of the Syriac
                            Orthodox Church. Volume 6</hi> (Puthencruz, India: Travancore Syriac
                        Orthodox Publishers, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reeves, J.C., and Reed, A.Y., <hi rend="italic">Enoch from Antiquity to
                            the Middle Ages. Volume 1: Sources from Judaism, Christianity, and
                            Islam</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Riba, B., <hi rend="italic">Le village de Kafr ‘Aqāb: Étude monographique
                            d’un site du ğebel Waṣṭāni (Massif calcaire de la Syrie du Nord).
                            Topographie et architecture</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’Antiquité Tardive
                        38; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ross, K.R., Tadros, M., and Johnson, T.M. (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Christianity in North Africa and West Asia</hi> (Edinburgh Companions
                        to Global Christianity; Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ruani, F. (tr.), <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe. Hymnes contre les
                            hérésies</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’Orient chrétien 4; Paris: Les Belles
                        Lettres, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rudolf, S., <hi rend="italic">Syrische Astrologie und das Syrische
                            Medizinbuch</hi> (Science, Technology, and Medicine in Ancient Cultures
                        7; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sahner, Ch.C., <hi rend="italic">Christian Martyrs under Islam: Religious
                            Violence and the Making of the Muslim World</hi> (Princeton, New Jersey:
                        Princeton University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Saint-Laurent, J.-N., and Smith, K.R. (ed. and tr.), <hi rend="italic">The
                            History of Mar Behnam and Sarah: Martyrdom and Monasticism in Medieval
                            Iraq</hi> (Persian Martyr Acts in Syriac: Text and Translation 7;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stewart, A.C. (tr.), <hi rend="italic">The Testament of the Lord: Worship
                            &amp; Discipline in the Early Church</hi> (Popular Patristics Series 58;
                        Yonkers, New York: St Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Talay, Sh., and Barthoma, S.O. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An
                            Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the
                            First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway,
                        New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tannous, J., <hi rend="italic">The Making of the Medieval Middle East:
                            Religion, Society, and Simple Believers</hi> (Princeton, New Jersey:
                        Princeton University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Teule, H.G.B., and Brüning, A. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handboek oosters
                            christendom</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Theotokis, G., <hi rend="italic">Byzantine Military Tactics in Syria and
                            Mesopotamia in the 10th Century: A Comparative Study</hi> (Edinburgh:
                        Edinburgh University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomas, S., <hi rend="italic">Privileged Minorities: Syrian Christianity,
                            Gender, and Minority Rights in Postcolonial India</hi> (Global South
                        Asia; Seattle, Washington: University of Washington Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomaskutty, J., <hi rend="italic">Saint Thomas the Apostle: New
                            Testament, Apocrypha, and Historical Traditions</hi> (T&amp;T Clark
                        Jewish and Christian Texts 25; London: Bloomsbury T&amp;T Clark,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Travis, H. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and
                            Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ubierna, P., and Francisco, H.R., <hi rend="italic">Apuntes de Siríaco:
                            Breve introducción a la lengua y literatura siríacas</hi> (Byzantina
                        &amp; Orientalia, Adnotationes linguarum 1; Buenos Aires: Instituto
                        Multidisciplinario de Historia y Ciencias Humanas, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vesa, V., <hi rend="italic">Knowledge and Experience in the Writings of
                            St. Isaac of Nineveh</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 51;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Weitz, L.E., <hi rend="italic">Between Christ and Caliph: Law, Marriage,
                            and Christian Community in Early Islam</hi> (Divinations: Rereading Late
                        Ancient Religion; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania: University of Pennsylvania
                        Press, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Weltecke, D. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte
                            und Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Witkamp, N., <hi rend="italic">Tradition and Innovation: Baptismal Rite
                            and Mystagogy in Theodore of Mopsuestia and Narsai of Nisibis</hi>
                        (Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae 149; Leiden: Brill, 2018).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Theses</head>
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl>Barczok, R., <hi rend="italic">Die Vita des Josef Busnaya als Quelle zur
                            Geschichte des 10. Jahrhundert des heutigen Nordirak</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; Universität Konstanz, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brelaud, S., <hi rend="italic">Présences chrétiennes en Mésopotamie durant
                            l’époque sassanide (III</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">e</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">–VII</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">e</hi><hi
                            rend="italic"> siècles): géographie et société</hi> (Thèse de doctorat;
                        Sorbonne Université, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Han, J.H., <hi rend="italic">Rethinking Prophecy in Late Antique
                            Syria</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; University of Pennsylvania,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jakob, J., <hi rend="italic">Syrisches Christentum und früher Islam:
                            Theologische Reaktionen in syrisch-sprachigen Texten vom 7. bis 9.
                            Jahrhundert</hi> (Dissertation zur Erlangung des akademischen Grades
                        Doktor der Theologie; Universität Salzburg, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kessel, G., <hi rend="italic">Life and Works of Šem‘ōn d-Ṭaibūtēh (7th
                            Century): A Tentative Reconstruction</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Radboud
                        Universiteit Nijmegen, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kunu, V., <hi rend="italic">Renunciant Stories across Traditions: A Novel
                            Approach to the Acts of Thomas and the Buddhist Jātakas</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; Temple University, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lollar, J.A., <hi rend="italic">A Sanctifying Myth: The Syriac History of
                            John in Its Social, Literary, and Theological Context</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; The Florida State University, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mazzola, M., <hi rend="italic">Bar ‘Ebroyo’s Ecclesiastical History:
                            Church History Writing in the 13th Century Middle East</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; Universiteit Gent / École Pratique des Hautes Études,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mutter, J.S., <hi rend="italic">By the Book: Conversion and Religious
                            Identity in Early Islamic Bilād Al-Shām and Al-Jazīra</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; University of Chicago, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sun, J., <hi rend="italic">Re-Dating the Seven Early Chinese Christian
                            Manuscripts: Christians in Dunhuang before 1200</hi> (Ph.D.
                        dissertation; Universiteit Leiden, 2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ugolnik, Z., <hi rend="italic">The Mirror of Glory: Sense and Subjectivity
                            in Near Eastern Mysticism</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; Columbia University,
                        2018).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wright, J., <hi rend="italic">After Antiquity: Joseph and Aseneth in
                            Manuscript Transmission. A Case Study for Engaging with What Came after
                            the Original Version of Jewish Pseudepigrapha</hi> (D.Phil.
                        dissertation; University of Oxford, 2018).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Articles</head>
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl>Abdalla, M., “The Term <hi rend="italic">Seyfo</hi> in Historical
                        Perspective,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide:
                            Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern
                        History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 92-105.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Abou Sekeh, F., “Syrische Eremiten und ihre Eremitagen als Pilgerziele,”
                        in: D. Ariantzi and I. Eichner (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Für Seelenheil und
                            Lebensglück: Das byzantinische Pilgerwesen und seine Wurzeln</hi>
                        (Byzanz zwischen Orient und Okzident 10; Mainz: Verlag des
                        Römisch-Germanischen Zentralmuseums, 2018), 273-290.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Abousamra, G., and Lemaire, A., “Une plaque syriaque d’un métropolite,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 131:3-4 (2018), 381-389.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Afif, N., Bhayro, S., Kessel, G., Pormann, P.E., Sellers, W.I., and
                        Smelova, N., “The Syriac Galen Palimpsest: A Tale of Two Texts,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018), 110-154.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Afif, N., Bhayro, S., Pormann, P.E., Sellers, W.I., and Smelova, N.,
                        “Analyzing Images, Editing Texts: The Manchester Project,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018), 155-185.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Akdemir, B., “Zur Rolle syrisch-aramäischer Ärzte in Antike und
                        Mittelalter,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia
                            Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt
                            2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 1-12.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Akhrass, R.-Y., “La figure de l’apôtre Pierre dans les écrits de Sévère
                        d’Antioche,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal Journal</hi> 56
                        (2018), 91-127.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Number of Ecumenical Councils: An Oriental Orthodox Point of
                        View,” <hi rend="italic">Proche-Orient Chrétien</hi> 68 (2018),
                        106-114.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Alibertis, D., “East Meets East in the Chaldean Furnace: A Comparative
                        Analysis of Romanos’s Hymns and Jacob of Serugh’s Homily on the Three
                        Children,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac
                            Studies</hi> 18 (2018), 24-41.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Alpi, F.N., “Sévère d’Antioche,” <hi rend="italic">Connaissance des Pères
                            de l’Église</hi> 151 (2018), 27-38.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Amsler, F., “La construction de l’homme ennemi ou l’anti-paulinisme dans
                        le corpus pseudo-clémentin,” in: J. Schröter, S. Butticaz and A. Dettwiler
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Receptions of Paul in Early Christianity: The
                            Person of Paul and His Writings Through the Eyes of His Early
                            Interpreters</hi> (Beihefte zur Zeitschrift für die neutestamentliche
                        Wissenschaft 234; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018), 729-748.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Annus, A., “Asceticism in Ancient Mesopotamia and Syria: A Study of Autism
                        in Antiquity,” in: S. Fink and R. Rollinger (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Conceptualizing Past, Present and Future: Proceedings of the Ninth
                            Symposium of the Melammu Project Held in Helsinki/Tartu, May 18-24,
                            2015</hi> (Melammu Symposia 9; Münster: Ugarit-Verlag, 2018),
                        521-539.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Aravackal, R., “The Spirituality of <hi rend="italic">Qyāmā</hi>: An Ideal
                        for Modern Monasticism,” <hi rend="italic">Christian Orient</hi> 39:3
                        (2018), 164-186.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Arlen, J.S., “Gišeroy kc‘urdk‘ (Hymns of the Night): Seven Madrāše of
                        Ephrem the Syrian Preserved in Armenian,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal
                            of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:2 (2018), 267-318.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Arnzen, R., Arzhanov, Y.N., Bamballi, N., Čéplö, S., and Kessel, G.,
                        “Coding and Encoding: Towards a New Approach to the Study of Syriac and
                        Arabic Translations of Greek Scientific and Philosophical Texts,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Comparative Oriental Manuscript Studies Bulletin</hi> 4:2
                        (2018), 205-213.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Asade, D., “La literatura farmacéutica en lengua siríaca, griega y árabe:
                        el caso de la <hi rend="italic">Hierá de Archigénes</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Circe de clásicos y modernos</hi> 22:1 (2018), 11-28.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Atman, S., “Assyrian Genocide from a Gender Perspective,” in: Sh. Talay
                        and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of
                            Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World
                            War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                        Gorgias Press, 2018), 215-232.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ayali-Darshan, N., “The Sequence of Sir 4:26–27 in Light of Akkadian and
                        Aramaic Texts from the Levant and Later Writings,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeitschrift für die alttestamentliche Wissenschaft</hi> 130:3 (2018),
                        436-449.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baarda, T.C., “The Poems of Ghattas Maqdisi Elyas and the Remembrance of
                        Turabdin,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo
                            1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans
                            during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 347-364.</bibl>
                    <bibl>BarAbraham, A., “German Perceptions of the Sayfo: How Much Did Germany
                        Know?,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo
                            1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans
                            during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 71-88.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Safeguarding the Cross: Emergence of Christian Militias in Iraq and
                        Syria,” in: A. Schmoller (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Middle Eastern Christians
                            and Europe: Historical Legacies and Present Challenges</hi> (Orientalia
                        ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 13; Wien: LIT, 2018), 217-238.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baroudi, F., and Akhrass, R.-Y., “Le patriarche Sévère d’Antioche dans la
                        liturgie maronite,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal
                            Journal</hi> 56 (2018), 1-12 [in Arabic].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barry, S.C., “Was Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq the Author of the Arabic Translation of
                        Paul of Aegina’s <hi rend="italic">Pragmateia</hi>? Evidence from the Arabic
                        Translations of the Hippocratic <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms </hi>and the
                        Syriac Lexicons of Bar Bahlul and Bar ‘Ali,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                            Semitic Studies</hi> 63:2 (2018), 457-465.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barsky, E., Furman, Y., and Loesov, S., “Two-Hundred-Word Swadesh List for
                        a Modern Aramaic Variety (Turoyo),” <hi rend="italic">Aula Orientalis</hi>
                        36 (2018), 77-112.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barsky, E., Kalinin, M.G., and Loesov, S., “The Basic Lexicon of Mlaḥsô: A
                        Comparative Study,” <hi rend="italic">Aula Orientalis</hi> 36 (2018),
                        209-234.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Be Djallo, B., “Die Änderung des türkischen Familiennamens zurück zum
                        traditionellen aramäischen Familiennamen,” in: D. Weltecke (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und Gegenwart</hi>
                        (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018), 251-260.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beaumont, M., “‘Ammār al-Baṣrī: Ninth Century Christian Theology and
                        Qur’anic Presuppositions,” in: M. Beaumont (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Arab
                            Christians and the Qur’an from the Origins of Islam to the Medieval
                            Period</hi> (History of Christian-Muslim Relations 35; Leiden: Brill,
                        2018), 83-105.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bednarowicz, S., “Before and After Linguicide: A Linguistic Aspect of the
                        Sayfo,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo
                            1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans
                            during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 365-384.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Neues Alphabet, neue Sprache, neue Kultur: Was kann die Adaptation
                        der lateinischen Schrift für das Turoyo implizieren?,” in: D. Weltecke
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und
                            Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018),
                        203-214.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beggiani, S.J., “The Incarnational Theology and Spirituality of John the
                        Solitary of Apamea,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac
                            Studies</hi> 21:2 (2018), 391-421.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Benjamen, A., “Assyrians between the State and the Iraqi Opposition:
                        Minoritization and Pluralism in the Second Half of the Twentieth Century,”
                            <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Middle East Studies</hi> 50:4
                        (2018), 781-785.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bergjan, S.-P., “Diodor von Tarsos,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der
                        Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe
                        Verlag, 2018), vol. 2, 1597-1605.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bergjan, S.-P., and Wyrwa, D., “Theodor von Mopsuestia,” in: C. Riedweg,
                        C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit
                            und der Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3;
                        Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol. 2, 1605-1614.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Theodoret von Kyrrhos,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        2, 1620-1633.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bernabò, M., and Pavan, M., “Addenda al catalogo dei manoscritti siriaci
                        del Tur ‘Abdin nel Fondo Grünwald,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                            Periodica</hi> 84:2 (2018), 407-420.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berti, V., “Fuoco nel cuore, polvere in bocca: la scrittura della <hi
                            rend="italic">trance </hi>estatica nella mistica cristiana siriaca
                        (secoli VII-VIII),” in: L. Canetti and A. Piras (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Esperienze e tecniche dell’estasi tra Oriente e Occidente</hi>
                        (Quaderni di Studi e Materiali di Storia delle religioni 21; Brescia:
                        Morcelliana, 2018), 44-71.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beth Yuhanon, B., “The Methods of Killing Used in the Assyrian Genocide,”
                        in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An
                            Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the
                            First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway,
                        New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 177-214.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bettiolo, P., “Écriture et “nature” dans les écoles syro-orientales,” in:
                        M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi>
                        (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 111-136.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bhayro, S., and Rudolf, S., “Budge’s <hi rend="italic">Syriac Book of
                            Medicines</hi> after One Hundred Years: Problems and Prospects,” in:
                        S.V. Panayotov and L. Vacín (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Mesopotamian Medicine
                            and Magic: Studies in Honor of Markham J. Geller</hi> (Ancient Magic and
                        Divination 14; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 116-130.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bilgic, Z., “Aramäisch des Tur Abdin schreiben und lesen: Überlegungen,
                        warum die Sprechergemeinschaft des Tur Abdin das Neu-Aramäische nicht als
                        Schriftsprache anerkennt,” in: D. Weltecke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue
                            Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1;
                        Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018), 215-250.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Birol, S., “Forgotten Witnesses: Remembering and Interpreting the ‘Sayfo’
                        in the Manuscripts of Tur ‘Abdin,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of
                            Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        327-346.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Some Approaches to Jacob of Sarug’s Remarks on Pagan Cults,” in: P.
                        Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des
                            IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter
                        Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        13-24.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Blumenthal, C., “<hi rend="italic">Mu‘tazila</hi> in der arabischen
                        Bibelübersetzung des Bišr b. al-Sirrī,” <hi rend="italic">Arabica</hi> 65:3
                        (2018), 314-330.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bodor, A., “The Use of the Peshitta of Isaiah in Rendering Isaiah
                        Quotations in the Old Syriac and Peshitta Gospels,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Aramaic Studies</hi> 16:1 (2018), 20-41.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bohas, G., “La morphophonologie dans la <hi rend="italic">Grande
                            grammaire</hi> de Barhebraeus, à travers l’étude des verbes défectueux,”
                        in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur
                            langue</hi> (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 89-206.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F., “La langue du Paradis, la langue comme patrie,” in:
                        M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi>
                        (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 9-25.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S.P., “A Sixth-Century Syriac Document of Agreement from
                        Alexandria,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 100 (2017 [2018]),
                        1-12.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Dated Syriac Manuscripts Copied at Deir al-Surian,” in: Ž. Paša
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in
                            Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth
                            Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio
                        Istituto Orientale, 2018), 355-371.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “An Ecumenical Role Played by Monastic Literature: The Case of St
                        Isaac the Syrian,” <hi rend="italic">Japan Mission Journal</hi> 72:1 (2018),
                        29-38.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “An Episcopal Adventus in Syriac,” in: E. Ene D-Vasilescu (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">A Journey along the Christian Way: Festschrift for the
                            Right Rev. Kallistos Ware on His 85th Anniversary</hi> (Beau Bassin,
                        Mauritius: Scholars’ Press, 2018), 52-61.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “George, Bishop of the Arab Tribes, <hi rend="italic">Mimro </hi>on
                        the Myron (British Library, Add. 12,165),” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox
                            Patriarchal Journal</hi> 56 (2018), 1-28.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “In Memoriam: Robert P. R. Murray, S.J.,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye:
                            Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:2 (2018), 255-261.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “A Lead Syriac Protective Talisman,” in: L. Nehmé and A. Al-Jallad
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">To the Madbar and Back Again: Studies in the
                            Languages, Archaeology, and Cultures of Arabia Dedicated to Michael C.A.
                            Macdonald</hi> (Studies in Semitic Languages and Linguistics 92; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2018), 309-326.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mary as a ‘Letter’ and Some Other Letter Imagery in Syriac
                        Liturgical Texts,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi>
                        21:1 (2018), 3-20.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “<hi rend="italic">The Small/Young Daniel</hi> Re-Edited,” in: L.
                        DiTommaso, M. Henze and W. Adler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered
                            Bible: Studies in Biblical Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of
                            Michael E. Stone</hi> (Studia in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26;
                        Leiden: Brill, 2018), 250-284.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Some Problems in Editing Liturgical Poetry,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 18 (2018),
                        3-14.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, S.P., Kessel, G., and Minov, S., “Recent Publications on Syriac
                        Topics: 2017,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1
                        (2018), 143-195.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brown, P., “[Review of:] M. Debié, <hi rend="italic">L’écriture de
                            l’histoire en syriaque: transmissions interculturelles et constructions
                            identitaires entre hellénisme et islam</hi> (Late Antique History and
                        Religion 12; Leuven: Peeters, 2015),” <hi rend="italic">Al-‘Uṣūr
                            al-Wusṭā</hi> 26 (2018), 225-231.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bruns, P., “Der Arme an der Tür ein Sinnbild für den Erlöser? Zur Deutung
                        der Lazarusperikope in der syrischen Literatur,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen
                            Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum
                        Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 25-44.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Eine Erwiderung an die Araber – Dionysius bar Salîbî († 2.XI.1171)
                        und der Islam,” <hi rend="italic">Forum Katholische Theologie</hi> 34:1
                        (2018), 1-15.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bumazhnov, D.F., “Isaak von Ninive (7. Jh.): Neue Herausforderungen durch
                        einen alten Heiligen,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile
                            gelebter Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 75-88.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Transformationen der Paradiesbäume. Gnostische, manichäische und
                        syrisch-christliche Parallelen zum Baum <hi rend="italic">Zaqqūm</hi>, Koran
                        37,62–64 u.a.,” in: H. Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and F. Feder (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Ägypten und der Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 47-58.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Zwischen Schule und Schweigen: Der hl. Isaak von Ninive und die
                        ostsyrischen “Schulphilosophen”,” in: P. Gemeinhardt and I. Tanaseanu-Döbler
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">“Das Paradies ist ein Hörsaal für die Seelen”:
                            Institutionen religiöser Bildung in historischer Perspektive</hi>
                        (Studies in Education and Religion in Ancient and Pre-Modern History in the
                        Mediterranean and Its Environs 1; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018),
                        201-220.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bush, K., Penn, M.P., Crouser, R.J., Howe, N.R., and Wu, S., “Challenging
                        the Estrangela / Serto Divide: Why the Standard Model of Syriac Scripts Just
                        Doesn’t Work,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1
                        (2018), 43-80.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Büttner, W., “Einige Aspekte aus dem syrischen Schrifttum zum
                        psychophysischen Problem,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages
                            in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 45-52.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Butts, A.M., “The Greco-Roman Context of the Syriac Language,” in: M.
                        Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi>
                        (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 137-165.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Calà, I., Daccache, J., and Hawley, R., “The Textual Interest of the
                        Syriac Versions of Galen’s <hi rend="italic">Simples</hi>,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018), 186-207.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Camplani, A., “John the Baptist according to Marcion’s Gospel and Early
                        Syriac Texts,” in: J.H. Ellens, I.W. Oliver, J. von Ehrenkrook, J. Waddell
                        and J.M. Zurawski (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Wisdom Poured Out Like Water:
                            Studies on Jewish and Christian Antiquity in Honor of Gabriele
                            Boccaccini</hi> (Deuterocanonical and Cognate Literature Studies 38;
                        Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018), 556-574.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Carlson, T.A., “The Long Shadow of Sasanian Christianity: The Limits of
                        Iraqi Islamization in the Abbasid Period,” <hi rend="italic">Mizan: Journal
                            for the Study of Muslim Societies and Civilizations</hi> 3:1 (2018),
                        on-line:
                        http://www.mizanproject.org/journal-post/the-long-shadow-of-sasanian-christianity/.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Çetinoğlu, S., “Genocide/<hi rend="italic">Seyfo </hi>and How Resistance
                        Became a Way of Life,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian
                            Genocide: Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in
                        Modern History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 178-190.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chialà, S., “The Monastery of Mor Yaqub d-Qarno and the Cave of Jacob of
                        Nisibis: A Possible Identification,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                            Periodica</hi> 84:2 (2018), 357-369.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Childers, J.W., “Divining Gospel: Classifying Manuscripts of John Used in
                        Sortilege,” in: L.I. Lied and M. Maniaci (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Bible as
                            Notepad: Tracing Annotations and Annotation Practices in Late Antique
                            and Medieval Biblical Manuscripts</hi> (Manuscripta Biblica 3; Berlin:
                        Walter de Gruyter, 2018), 66-84.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clines, R.J., “Wayward Leadership and the Breakdown of Reform on the
                        Failed Jesuit Mission to the Maronites, 1577-1579,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Early Modern History</hi> 22:4 (2018), 215-237.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coghill, E., “The Gleaner Woman: A Text in the Neo-Aramaic Dialect of
                        Peshabur,” in: G.J. Brooke, A.H.W. Curtis, M. al-Hamad and G.R. Smith
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern and Arabian Essays: Studies in Honour
                            of John F. Healey</hi> (Journal of Semitic Studies Supplement 41;
                        Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018), 71-87.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Information Structure in the Neo-Aramaic Dialect of Telkepe,” in: E.
                        Adamou, K. Haude and M. Vanhove (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Information
                            Structure in Lesser-described Languages: Studies in Prosody and
                            Syntax</hi> (Studies in Language Companion Series 199; Amsterdam: John
                        Benjamins, 2018), 297-328.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Neo-Aramaic Dialect of Telkepe,” in: N. Vidro, R. Vollandt,
                        E.-M. Wagner and J. Olszowy-Schlanger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                            Semitic Linguistics and Manuscripts: A Liber Discipulorum in Honour of
                            Professor Geoffrey Khan</hi> (Studia Semitica Upsaliensia 30; Uppsala:
                        Uppsala Universitet, 2018), 234-271.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Contini, R., “Remarques conclusives,” in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études
                        syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 237-241.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Côté, D., “Le vrai Prophète et ses incarnations dans les <hi rend="italic"
                            >Homélies </hi>pseudo-clémentines,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias Chaves
                        and S. Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines:
                            Mélanges en l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme
                        ancien et origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018),
                        309-337.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Sacrifices et théurgie dans les <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pseudo-Clémentines</hi>,” in: S.C. Mimouni and L. Painchaud (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">La question de la “sacerdotalisation” dans le judaïsme
                            synagogal, le christianisme et le rabbinisme</hi> (Judaïsme ancien et
                        origines du christianisme 9; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018), 391-409.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dalyan, M.G., “I. Dünya Savaşı’nda Nasturi Patriği Mar Şamun Benyamin ve
                        Faaliyetleri,” in: <hi rend="italic">Savaşan Devletlerİn Tarİhçİlerİnİn
                            Gözüyle: 100. Yilinda Bİrİncİ Dünya Savaşi / “Through the Eyes of the
                            Warring Countries Historians”: The First World War Centenary
                            International Symposium, 12-15 Kasım 2014</hi>. 2 vols. (Antalya:
                        Akdeniz Üniversitesi Yayınları, 2018), vol. 2, 982-1001.</bibl>
                    <bibl>de Ghantuz Cubbe, M., “Le XIV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle
                        maronite,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 84:2
                        (2018), 421-467.</bibl>
                    <bibl>de Wet, C.L., “The Curse of Ham (Gen. 9:18–27): Slavery, Sin, and
                        Punishment in John Chrysostom, Augustine, and the <hi rend="italic">Cave of
                            Treasures</hi>,” in: Idem, <hi rend="italic">The Unbound God: Slavery
                            and the Formation of Early Christian Thought</hi> (Routledge Studies in
                        the Early Christian World; London: Routledge, 2018), 104-145.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Debié, M., “Guerres et religions en Mésopotamie du Nord dans l’Antiquité
                        tardive: un <hi rend="italic">mimro </hi>inédit de Jacques de Saroug sur
                        l’église Saint-Étienne que les Perses ont transformée en temple du feu à
                        Amid (Diyarbakιr) en 503 è.c.,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox
                            Patriarchal Journal</hi> 56 (2018), 29-89.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “In Memoriam: Ephrem-Isa Yousif,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal
                            of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:2 (2018), 263-265.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Delaini, P., “Conoscenza medica dei meccanismi della percezione, del sogno
                        e dei fenomeni dispercettivi nel mondo iranico di età tardoantica,” in: L.
                        Canetti and A. Piras (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Esperienze e tecniche
                            dell’estasi tra Oriente e Occidente</hi> (Quaderni di Studi e Materiali
                        di Storia delle religioni 21; Brescia: Morcelliana, 2018), 72-98.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Demir, S., “The Atrocities against the Assyrians in 1915: A Legal
                        Perspective,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide:
                            Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern
                        History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 106-136.</bibl>
                    <bibl>den Biesen, K., “Auf der Suche nach Ephräm dem Syrer: Für eine neue
                        wissenschaftliche Interpretationsmethode seiner theologischen Werke,” in: D.
                        Weltecke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und
                            Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018),
                        111-134.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Irresistible Love of God: Two Syrian Church Fathers on Universal
                        Salvation in Christ,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross
                            and the Crescent: Studies in Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the
                            Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta
                        304; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2018), 437-448.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Deschler, J.-P., “Aus dem Mimro IX Jakobs von Serug über die Taufe:
                        Übertragung in deutsche Zwölfsilber,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in Honor of Samir Khalil
                            Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday</hi> (Orientalia
                        Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2018),
                        485-498.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dickens, M., “Syriac Inscriptions near Urgut, Uzbekistan,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Studia Iranica</hi> 46:2 (2017 [2018]), 205-260.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Huns, Turks and Tatars in Syriac Liminal Spaces,” in: G.J. Brooke,
                        A.H.W. Curtis, M. al-Hamad and G.R. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near
                            Eastern and Arabian Essays: Studies in Honour of John F. Healey</hi>
                        (Journal of Semitic Studies Supplement 41; Oxford: Oxford University Press,
                        2018), 119-132.</bibl>
                    <bibl>DiTommaso, L., “The Apocryphal Daniel Apocalypses: Works, Manuscripts, and
                        Overview,” <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides Theologicae Lovanienses</hi> 94:2
                        (2018), 275-316.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Doerfler, M.E., “Glimpses from the Margins: Re-telling Late Ancient
                        History at the Edges of the Law,” in: A.J. Berkovitz and M. Letteney (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Rethinking ‘Authority’ in Late Antiquity: Authorship,
                            Law, and Transmission in Jewish and Christian Tradition</hi> (Routledge
                        Monographs in Classical Studies; London: Routledge, 2018), 107-122.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Donef, R., “The Assyrian Delegation in the Paris Peace Conference,” in: H.
                        Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and
                            Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 217-238.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Donner, F.M., “Talking about Islam’s Origins,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin
                            of the School of Oriental and African Studies</hi> 81:1 (2018),
                        1-23.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Drijvers, J.W., “Jovian between History and Myth,” in: D.W.P. Burgersdijk
                        and A.J. Ross (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Imagining Emperors in the Later
                            Roman Empire</hi> (Cultural Interactions in the Mediterranean 1; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2018), 234-256.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dryden, R., “Workshop: Linked Data and Syriac Sources, Vrije Universität,
                        Amsterdam,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1
                        (2018), 197-204.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dubovick, Y.M., ““Oil, Which Shall Not Quit My Head”: Jewish-Christian
                        Interaction in Eleventh-Century Baghdad,” <hi rend="italic">Entangled
                            Religions</hi> 6 (2018), 96-123.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dusenbury, D.L., “Judaic Authority in Nemesius of Emesa’s <hi
                            rend="italic">De natura hominis </hi>(390 CE),” in: G. Roskam and J.
                        Verheyden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Light on Creation: Ancient Commentators
                            in Dialogue and Debate on the Origin of the World</hi> (Studien und
                        Texte zu Antike und Christentum 104; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018),
                        127-156.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Easton, R.L., Knox, K.T., Christens-Barry, W.A., and Boydston, K.,
                        “Spectral Imaging Methods Applied to the Syriac Galen Palimpsest,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018), 69-82.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ebeid, B., “La Chiesa giacobita tra politica imperiale e preservazione
                        dottrinale: la formazione di una identità “nazionale”,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in Honor
                            of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth
                            Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio
                        Istituto Orientale, 2018), 527-546.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Trinitarian Doctrine of Ibn aṭ-Ṭayyib: An Interpretation of
                        Babai the Great’s Metaphysical System in the World of Islam,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018), 93-131.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ebied, R.Y., “An Arabic Version of a Miracle by St. George in the City of
                        Baghdad,” <hi rend="italic">Collectanea Christiana Orientalia</hi> 15
                        (2018), 21-30.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “An Arabic Version of a Miracle by St. George in the City of
                        Baghdad,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018),
                        133-143.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Eco Conti, S., “Les sources grecques des textes grammaticaux syriaques,”
                        in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur
                            langue</hi> (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 27-54.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Eilo, A., “Fatwās: The Syrian Uprising and the Sectarian Fragmentation,”
                        in: D. Weltecke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte
                            und Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang,
                        2018), 297-322.</bibl>
                    <bibl>el Gemayel, R., “<hi rend="italic">Sinaï arabe</hi> 308 (366<hi
                            rend="superscript">r</hi>–382<hi rend="superscript">v</hi>): traités
                        polémiques de christologie antimiaphysite et d’ecclésiologie antilatine,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018), 237-300.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Elkhoury, A., “Fisher- and Net-Imageries of the Church and Her Missionary
                        Role in the Poetry of Jacob of Sarug,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen
                            Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum
                        Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 53-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Emery, D., “The Galen Palimpsest and the Modest Ambitions of the Digital
                        Data Set,” <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018),
                        83-109.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Er, S., “Preparation of the Eucharistic Gifts: Bread and Wine in the
                        Syriac Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox Patriarchal
                            Journal</hi> 56 (2018), 129-142.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Eskhult, M., “Stenij’s Edition of the Epistle to the Hebrews from Codex
                        Tischendorf, Dated to 892 AD – with Special Reference to the Use of
                        Particles,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018),
                        145-158.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Farina, M., “La linguistique syriaque selon Jacques d’Édesse,” in: M.
                        Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi>
                        (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 167-187.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Manuscrits de grammaires et lexiques syriaques,” in: M. Farina
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études
                        syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 243-254.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “New Autograph by ‘Abdīšō‘ Marūn: Renaissance Rome and the Syriac
                        Churches,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi>
                        70:3-4 (2018), 241-256.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fathi, J., “Les notices d’Ibn Ḫallikān sur l’<hi rend="italic">Épitomé des
                            Dynasties</hi> de Barhebraeus,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
                            l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018), 159-199.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Féghali, P., “Un des premiers textes des évangiles conservé par ‘Alī
                        al-Ṭabarī,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018),
                        201-220.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fiori, E., “[Review of:] N. Kavvadas, <hi rend="italic">Joseph Hazzaya. On
                            Providence: Text, Translation and Introduction</hi> (Texts and Studies
                        in Eastern Christianity 8; Leiden: Brill, 2016),” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeitschrift für Antikes Christentum / Journal of Ancient
                            Christianity</hi> 22:2 (2018), 371-382.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fomicheva, S.V., “Educational Background of Mar Narsai: Between the
                        “Tradition of the School” and Theodore of Mopsuestia’s Exegesis,” in: P.
                        Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des
                            IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter
                        Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        61-70.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ford, J.N., and Abudraham, O., “Syriac and Mandaic Incantation Bowls,” in:
                        D. Regev and H. Hizmi (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Finds Gone Astray: ADCA
                            Confiscated Items</hi> (ADCA Reports 1; Jerusalem: Antiquities
                        Department of the Civil Administration, 2018), 75-111.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Forness, Ph.M., “Cultural Exchange and Scholarship on Eastern
                        Christianity: An Early Modern Debate over Jacob of Serugh’s Christology,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi> 70:3-4
                        (2018), 257-284.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fox, S.E., “Three Generations of Jilu Speakers,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic
                            Studies</hi> 16:2 (2018), 206-214.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fuchs, G., “Die Gerechten des Alten Bundes im Liber Graduum (<hi
                            rend="italic">ktābā d-masqātā</hi>),” in: H. Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and
                        F. Feder (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Ägypten und der Christliche Orient: Peter
                            Nagel zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 85-113.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Galadari, A., “The Camel Passing through the Eye of the Needle: A Qur’anic
                        Interpretation of the Gospels,” <hi rend="italic">Ancient Near Eastern
                            Studies</hi> 55 (2018), 77-89.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gaunt, D., “Two Documents on the 1895 Massacres of Syriacs in the Province
                        of Diyarbekir: A Discussion,” <hi rend="italic">Études arméniennes
                            contemporaines</hi> 10 (2018), 187-201.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Géhin, P., and Brock, S.P., “Vestiges of a Syrian Orthodox Liturgical
                        Collection,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 131:3-4 (2018),
                        337-379.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gemayel, M.-N., “Copistes Maronites et manuscrits,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in Honor of
                            Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday</hi>
                        (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale,
                        2018), 373-382.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Georgia, A.T., “The Monster at the End of His Book: Monstrosity as
                        Theological Strategy and Cultural Critique in Tatian’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Against the Greeks</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian
                            Studies</hi> 26:2 (2018), 191-219.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Girling, K., “Dominican Contributions to Christian Life in
                        Mesopotamia-Iraq (c. 1750–2017),” <hi rend="italic">The Downside Review</hi>
                        136:2 (2018), 85-98.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Godwin, R.T., “Sacred Sovereigns across the Silk Road: The Church of the
                        East’s Gift of Buddhist-Christian Icons to the Chinese Emperor in 781, and
                        Its Relevance to Buddhist-Christian Studies,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Buddhist-Christian Studies</hi> 38 (2018), 203-216.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gourinat, J.-B., “Diels’ Whodunit: The Reliability of the Three Mentions
                        of Aëtius in Theodoret,” in: J. Mansfeld and D.T. Runia (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Aëtiana IV: Papers of the Melbourne Colloquium on Ancient
                            Doxography</hi> (Philosophia Antiqua 148; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        17-52.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Greenberg, G., “Jeremiah in the Peshitta,” in: J.R. Lundbom, C.A. Evans
                        and B.A. Anderson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Book of Jeremiah:
                            Composition, Reception, and Interpretation</hi> (Supplements to Vetus
                        Testamentum 178; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 340-358.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Griffith, S.H., “The Bible in the Qur’an; the Qur’an in the Bible:
                        Scriptural Intertextuality in the Language of Islam,” in: K.E. Shuve (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Books and Readers in the Premodern World: Essays in
                            Honor of Harry Gamble</hi> (Writings from the Greco-Roman World
                        Supplement 12; Atlanta, Georgia: SBL Press, 2018), 137-170.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Christianity’s Historic Roots in the Middle East: Christians at Home
                        in the ‘World of Islam’,” in: K.C. Ellis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Secular
                            Nationalism and Citizenship in Muslim Countries: Arab Christians in the
                            Levant</hi> (Minorities in West Asia and North Africa; Cham,
                        Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan, 2018), 29-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Qur’an in Christian Arabic Literature: A Cursory Overview,” in:
                        M. Beaumont (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Arab Christians and the Qur’an from the
                            Origins of Islam to the Medieval Period</hi> (History of
                        Christian-Muslim Relations 35; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 1-19.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gross, S.M., “A Persian Anti-Martyr Act: The Death of Rabba bar Naḥmani in
                        Light of the Syriac Persian Martyr Acts,” in: G. Herman and J.L. Rubenstein
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Aggada of the Bavli and Its Cultural
                            World</hi> (Brown Judaic Studies 362; Providence, Rhode Island: Brown
                        Judaic Studies, 2018), 211-242.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gschwandtner, C.M., “Performing Anatheism: Dialogic Hospitality in Syriac
                        Liturgical Poetry,” in: R. Kearney and M. Clemente (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Art of Anatheism</hi> (Reframing Continental Philosophy of
                        Religion; London: Rowman &amp; Littlefield International, 2018),
                        175-196.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gucha, V.P., “The Assyrian Orphanage of the German Orient Mission in
                        Urmia: From Its Foundation to Its End,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen
                            Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum
                        Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 71-88.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Guinot, J.-N., “Théodoret de Cyr et le monachisme syrien,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Connaissance des Pères de l’Église</hi> 151 (2018),
                        39-51.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gurry, P.J., “The Harklean Syriac and the Development of the Byzantine
                        Text: A Historical Test for the Coherence-Based Genealogical Method (CBGM),”
                            <hi rend="italic">Novum Testamentum</hi> 60:2 (2018), 183-200.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gutas, D., “A New “Edition” of Ḥunayn’s <hi rend="italic">Risāla</hi>,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Arabic Sciences and Philosophy</hi> 28:2 (2018),
                        279-284.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hainthaler, T., “Christological Research and Oriental Churches,” in: <hi
                            rend="italic">Orientalia Patristica: Papers of the International
                            Patristic Symposium, May 1–4, 2017</hi> (Drobeta-Turnu Severin: Didahia
                        Severin Publishing, 2018), 97-108.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Severus von Antiochien (gest. 538): Kirchenvater der
                        Anti-Chalcedonier,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile gelebter
                            Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80. Geburtstag</hi>
                        (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz
                        Verlag, 2018), 51-64.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Halbertsma, T., and Dickens, M., “Inner Mongolian Syro-Turcica I:
                        Contextualizing the Syro-Turkic Gravestones from Inner Mongolia,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Monumenta Serica</hi> 66:2 (2018), 279-302.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Halo, T., “The Targeting of Assyrians during the Christian Holocaust in
                        Ottoman Turkey,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of
                            Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        41-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hämeen-Anttila, J., “The Christian Context of the Qur’ān,” in: D.R. Thomas
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Routledge Handbook on Christian-Muslim
                            Relations</hi> (Routledge Handbooks; London: Routledge, 2018),
                        23-32.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hansbury, M.T., “<hi rend="italic">Theosis</hi> in Isaac III,” <hi
                            rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 31 (2016 [2018]), 291-304.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harrower, S., “Visual Exegesis at ‘The World’s Oldest Church’: A Case
                        Study for Historiography,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Antikes
                            Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity</hi> 22:3 (2018),
                        456-479.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hartung, B.A., “The Authorship and Dating of the Syriac Corpus attributed
                        to Ephrem of Nisibis: A Reassessment,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                            Antikes Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity</hi> 22:2 (2018),
                        296-321.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The <hi rend="italic">Mêmrâ on the Signs Moses Performed in
                            Egypt</hi>: An Exegetical Homily of the “School” of Ephrem,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:2 (2018),
                        319-356.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hattar, R.H., “Sacred Oriental Music: Preserving the Identity of Middle
                        Eastern Christians,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018),
                        301-310.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Heal, K.S., and Manis, J.R., “New Sources for the Armenian Commentary on
                        Genesis Attributed to Ephrem,” in: L. DiTommaso, M. Henze and W. Adler
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered Bible: Studies in Biblical
                            Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of Michael E. Stone</hi> (Studia
                        in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        522-532.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Heimgartner, M., “The Letters of the East Syrian Patriarch Timothy I:
                        Scriptural Exegesis between Judaism, Christianity and Islam,” in: G. Tamer,
                        R. Grundmann, A.E. Kattan and K. Pinggéra (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Exegetical Crossroads: Understanding Scripture in Judaism, Christianity
                            and Islam in the Pre-Modern Orient</hi> (Judaism, Christianity, and
                        Islam – Tension, Transmission, Transformation 8; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter,
                        2018), 47-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hellot-Bellier, F., “The Increasing Violence and the Resistance of
                        Assyrians in Urmia and Hakkari (1900–1915),” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide
                            of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        107-134.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Henze, M., “Seeing the End: The Vocabulary of the End Time in <hi
                            rend="italic">Syriac Apocalypse of Daniel</hi> 13,” in: L. DiTommaso, M.
                        Henze and W. Adler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered Bible: Studies
                            in Biblical Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of Michael E.
                            Stone</hi> (Studia in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2018), 554-568.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Heyberger, B., “Migration of the Middle Eastern Christians and European
                        Protection: A Long History,” in: A. Schmoller (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Middle Eastern Christians and Europe: Historical Legacies and Present
                            Challenges</hi> (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 13; Wien: LIT,
                        2018), 23-42.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hill, K.R., “On the Brink of Extinction: Christians in Iraq and Syria,”
                        in: D. Philpott and T.S. Shah (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Under Caesar’s
                            Sword: How Christians Respond to Persecution</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge
                        University Press, 2018), 30-69.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hjälm, M.L., “Scriptures beyond Words: “Islamic” Vocabulary in Early
                        Christian Arabic Bible Translations,” <hi rend="italic">Collectanea
                            Christiana Orientalia</hi> 15 (2018), 49-69.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hofmann, T., “The Ottoman Genocide of 1914–1918 against Aramaic-Speaking
                        Christians in Comparative Perspective,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide
                            of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        21-40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horn, C.B., “Children in Oriental Christian and Greek Hagiography from the
                        Early Byzantine World (ca. 400–800 CE),” in: R. Aasgaard, C.B. Horn and O.M.
                        Cojocaru (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Childhood in History: Perceptions of
                            Children in the Ancient and Medieval Worlds</hi> (London: Routledge,
                        2018), 174-192.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Jesus, the Wondrous Infant, at the Exegetical Crossroads of
                        Christian Late Antiquity and Early Islam,” in: G. Tamer, R. Grundmann, A.E.
                        Kattan and K. Pinggéra (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Exegetical Crossroads:
                            Understanding Scripture in Judaism, Christianity and Islam in the
                            Pre-Modern Orient</hi> (Judaism, Christianity, and Islam – Tension,
                        Transmission, Transformation 8; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018),
                        27-46.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hoskin, M., “The Close Proximity of Christ to Sixth-Century Mesopotamian
                        Monks in John of Ephesus’ <hi rend="italic">Lives of Eastern Saints</hi>,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Ecclesiastical History</hi> 69:2 (2018),
                        262-277.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hugonnard-Roche, H., “Die Schule von Keneschre,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn
                        and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der
                            Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel:
                        Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol. 3, 2469-2474.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “E Dio disse: “La terra produca germogli” (Gen. 1, 11). Sulla
                        tradizione botanica siriaca,” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 8
                        (2018), 85-103.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “La tradition du <hi rend="italic">Peri hermeneias</hi> d’Aristote en
                        syriaque, entre logique et grammaire,” in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études
                        syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 55-93.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Paul der Perser,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        3, 2462-2465.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Probus,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        3, 2465-2469.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Qenneshre et la tradition des lettres gréco-syriaques,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Connaissance des Pères de l’Église</hi> 151 (2018),
                        52-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Severos von Antiochien,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der
                        Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe
                        Verlag, 2018), vol. 3, 2236-2245.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Traductions en contexte: logique et noétique du grec au syriaque,”
                        in: M. Zonta and P. Grezzi (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Terminologia filosofica
                            tra Oriente e Occidente</hi> (Lessico intellettuale europeo 126;
                        Firenze: Leo S. Olschki, 2018), 67-92.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Überblick,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        3, 2447-2452.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunter, D.G., “<hi rend="italic">Acts of Thomas</hi>,” in: Idem, <hi
                            rend="italic">Marriage and Sexuality in Early Christianity</hi>
                        (Minneapolis, Minnesota: Fortress Press, 2018), 81-90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hunter, E.C.D., “Perspectives on Syriac Christianity in Southern
                        Mesopotamia and the Gulf,” in: G.J. Brooke, A.H.W. Curtis, M. al-Hamad and
                        G.R. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern and Arabian Essays:
                            Studies in Honour of John F. Healey</hi> (Journal of Semitic Studies
                        Supplement 41; Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018), 169-180.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “A Victim of the Sayfo: Addaï Scher and His Contribution to
                        Scholarship,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of
                            Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        163-176.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hutter, M., “Rivalität und Konflikte zwischen Christen und Zoroastriern,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Schweizerische Zeitschrift für Religions- und
                            Kulturgeschichte</hi> 112 (2018), 91-104.</bibl>
                    <bibl>İçöz, A., “Defining a Christian Virtue in the Islamic Context: The Concept
                        of Gratitude in Elias of Nisibis’ <hi rend="italic">Kitāb Daf‘
                        al-Hamm</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Ilahiyat Studies</hi> 9:2 (2018),
                        165-182.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Illert, M., “Die Erfahrung des Heiligen Geistes bei Pseudo-Makarios und in
                        den frühen syrischen Liturgien,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages
                            in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 89-94.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Pseudo-Makarios (4. Jh.): “Erleuchtet von der Schönheit seines
                        unaussprechlichen Lichtes”,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile
                            gelebter Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 13-18.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Impagliazzo, M., “De la guerre au génocide: les causes du “seyfo” des
                        chrétiens syriaques,” <hi rend="italic">Revue d’histoire ecclésiastique</hi>
                        113:3-4 (2018), 690-708.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Isaac, E., ““I Will Stay with Jesus and Will Never Betray Him!”: Sayfo in
                        Mansuriye,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo
                            1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans
                            during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 147-162.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ishaq, A., “Some Remarks on Jacob of Edessa &amp; Basil of Caesarea’s
                        Hexaemeron,” in: <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Patristica: Papers of the
                            International Patristic Symposium, May 1–4, 2017</hi> (Drobeta-Turnu
                        Severin: Didahia Severin Publishing, 2018), 203-231.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jacobs, B., “Preliminary Considerations on Dionysius Bar Ṣalībī’s Islamic
                        Sources,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:2
                        (2018), 357-389.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Unveiling Christ in the Islamicate World: Fakhr al-Dīn al-Rāzī’s
                        Prophetology as a Model for Christian Apologetics in Gregory Bar ‘Ebrōyō’s
                        Treatise on the Incarnation,” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of the
                            Islamicate World</hi> 6:1-2 (2018), 187-216.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Johnson, S.F., “The Languages of Christianity on the Silk Roads and the
                        Transmission of Mediterranean Culture into Central Asia,” in: N. Di Cosmo
                        and M. Maas (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Empires and Exchanges in Eurasian Late
                            Antiquity: Rome, China, Iran, and the Steppe, ca. 250–750</hi>
                        (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2018), 206-219.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Journée, G., “Aétius et le problème des sources de Théodoret: à propos de
                            <hi rend="italic">GAC </hi>4.12,” in: J. Mansfeld and D.T. Runia (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Aëtiana IV: Papers of the Melbourne Colloquium on
                            Ancient Doxography</hi> (Philosophia Antiqua 148; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        196-224.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Juhás, P., “Zum paronomastischen Infinitiv in der syrischen
                        Baruch-Apokalypse (samt einigen Beobachtungen zur Partikel <hi rend="italic"
                            >dalmā</hi>),” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 131:3-4 (2018),
                        313-335.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jullien, Ch., “La piété du Perse “barbare”: modélisations chrétiennes en
                        milieu sassanide,” in: F. Jullien (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Guerre et paix en
                            monde iranien: revisiter les lieux de rencontre</hi> (Cahiers de Studia
                        Iranica 62; Leuven: Peeters, 2018), 67-90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jullien, F., “L’enfant au monastère: les pratiques d’accueil en milieu
                        monastique syriaque (V<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>–VIII<hi
                            rend="superscript">e</hi> s.),” <hi rend="italic">Oriens
                            Christianus</hi> 100 (2017 [2018]), 13-31.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Des chrétiens engagés pour la paix entre la Perse et Byzance:
                        l’ambassade du catholicos Īšō‘yahb de Gdala,” in: F. Jullien (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Guerre et paix en monde iranien: revisiter les lieux de
                            rencontre</hi> (Cahiers de Studia Iranica 62; Leuven: Peeters, 2018),
                        199-222.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jurasz, I., “Le Nom et le Lieu de Dieu. Étude d’un témoignage inconnu de
                        la cosmologie bardesanite,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                            Periodica</hi> 84:2 (2018), 297-337.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Lettre de Mara bar Sérapion et la <hi rend="italic">paideia
                        </hi>hellénistique,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de l’Académie Belge pour
                            l’Etude des Langues Anciennes et Orientales</hi> 7 (2018),
                        81-135.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Karimullah, K.I., “Translating Greek into Arabic and Syriac: Remarks on a
                        New Contribution to the Field,” <hi rend="italic">Intellectual History of
                            the Islamicate World</hi> 6:3 (2018), 389-405.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kaufhold, H., “Christliche Motive auf Briefmarken nahöstlicher Staaten,”
                        in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca:
                            Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi>
                        (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz
                        Verlag, 2018), 95-126.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kavvadas, N., “The Lance of the Cherub before the Tree of Life: A
                        Difficult Typology and the Words behind It,” <hi rend="italic">Δελτίο
                            Βιβλικών Μελετών</hi> 33:A-B (2018), 42-49.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Keser-Kayaalp, E., “The Great Mosque of Diyarbakır in Light of Discussions
                        on <hi rend="italic">Spolia </hi>and Classicism,” in: I. Jevtić and S.
                        Yalman (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Spolia Reincarnated: Afterlives of Objects,
                            Materials, and Spaces in Anatolia from Antiquity to the Ottoman Era</hi>
                        (Istanbul: Koç University Research Center for Anatolian Civilizations,
                        2018), 125-147.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kessel, G., and Smelova, N., “Sinai Syriac Manuscripts in Exile,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Sinaiticus: The Bulletin of the Saint Catherine
                            Foundation</hi> (2018), 13-15.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kessel, G., and Bamballi, N., “Field Notes on Syriac Manuscripts II: A
                        Philosophical Manuscript <hi rend="italic">Olim </hi>Mosul 35 Rediscovered,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1 (2018),
                        21-42.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kessel, G., and Seleznyov, N.N., “Bibliography of Syriac and Christian
                        Arabic Studies in Russian, 2017,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of
                            Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1 (2018), 127-141.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Khalifé-Hachem, É., “La lecture de l’Écriture Sainte dans le monachisme
                        syriaque,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the
                            Crescent: Studies in Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion
                            of His Eightieth Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304;
                        Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2018), 471-484.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Khan, G., “Remarks on the Historical Development and Syntax of the Copula
                        in North-Eastern Neo-Aramaic Dialects,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic
                            Studies</hi> 16:2 (2018), 234-269.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Sound Symbolism in Neo-Aramaic,” in: G.J. Brooke, A.H.W. Curtis, M.
                        al-Hamad and G.R. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern and Arabian
                            Essays: Studies in Honour of John F. Healey</hi> (Journal of Semitic
                        Studies Supplement 41; Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018),
                        197-214.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Khosroeva, A., “The Ottoman Genocide of the Assyrians in Persia,” in: H.
                        Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and
                            Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 106-136.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Significance of the Assyrian Genocide after a Century,” in: Sh.
                        Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology
                            of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World
                            War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                        Gorgias Press, 2018), 61-70.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kim, S., “A Note on the Syriac Pseudo-Chrysostomic Sermon <hi
                            rend="italic">In peccatricem</hi>, CPG 5140.10v,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi> 70:3-4 (2018),
                        223-225.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kindt, B., Haelewyck, J.-C., Schmidt, A.B., and Atas, N., “La concordance
                        bilingue grecque-syriaque des <hi rend="italic">Discours </hi>de Grégoire de
                        Nazianze,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin de l’Académie Belge pour l’Etude des
                            Langues Anciennes et Orientales</hi> 7 (2018), 51-80.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kiraz, G.A., “Towards a Lexicon of Syriac Loanwords in Christian Arabic,”
                        in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent:
                            Studies in Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His
                            Eightieth Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma:
                        Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2018), 383-394.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kitchen, R.A., “Timothy I of Baghdad: A Stranger in His Own Land,” in:
                        J.M. Houston and J. Zimmermann (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sources of the
                            Christian Self: A Cultural History of Christian Identity</hi> (Grand
                        Rapids, Michigan: William B. Eerdmans, 2018), 257-274.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Which One Is He? Narsai of Nisibis on Moses and the Divine Name and
                        Essence and a Few Plagues,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian
                            Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 18 (2018), 15-23.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Klein, K.M., “Mourning for the Dead and the Beginning of Idolatry in the
                            <hi rend="italic">Kitāb al-Aṣnām</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Spelunca
                            Thesaurorum</hi> – an Unknown Parallel to <hi rend="italic">Sūrat
                            at-Takāṯ</hi><hi rend="italic">ur</hi> (Q102)?,” in: L. Nehmé and A.
                        Al-Jallad (eds.), <hi rend="italic">To the Madbar and Back Again: Studies in
                            the Languages, Archaeology, and Cultures of Arabia Dedicated to Michael
                            C.A. Macdonald</hi> (Studies in Semitic Languages and Linguistics 92;
                        Leiden: Brill, 2018), 551-566.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Koch, K., and Mar Meelis Zaia, “Déclaration commune sur la vie
                        sacramentelle: comité mixte pour le dialogue théologique entre l’Église
                        catholique et l’Église assyrienne de l’Orient,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Proche-Orient Chrétien</hi> 68:1-2 (2018), 84-105.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kofsky, A., and Ruzer, S., “The Gospel according to Tolstoy: Between
                        Nineteenth-Century Lives of Jesus, Tatian and Marcion,” in: M.B. Blidstein,
                        S. Ruzer and D. Stökl Ben Ezra (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Scriptures, Sacred
                            Traditions, and Strategies of Religious Subversion: Studies in Discourse
                            with the Work of Guy G. Stroumsa</hi> (Studien und Texte zu Antike und
                        Christentum 112; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018), 229-250.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Koshy, L., “The Reconciliatory Nature of the Rite of Incensing: A
                        Liturgico-Theological Analysis in the Syro-Malankara <hi rend="italic"
                            >Qurbono </hi>and Syro-Malabar <hi rend="italic">Qurbana</hi>,” in: A.
                        Lossky, G. Sekulovski and T. Pott (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Liturgie et
                            religiosité: 64</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">e</hi><hi
                            rend="italic"> Semaine d’études liturgiques, Paris, Institut
                            Saint-Serge, 26–29 juin 2017</hi> (Semaines d’Études Liturgiques
                        Saint-Serge 64; Münster: Aschendorff, 2018), 209-222.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kraft, A., “Miracles and Pseudo-Miracles in Byzantine Apocalypses,” in: M.
                        Gerolemou (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Recognizing Miracles in Antiquity and
                            Beyond</hi> (Trends in Classics, Supplementary Volumes 53; Berlin:
                        Walter de Gruyter, 2018), 111-130.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Кръстев, К.С., “Арабски и сирийски извори за управлението на хановете Крум
                        (след 796 – 814) и Омуртаг (814 – около 831),” in: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Българско царство: Сборник в чест на 60-годишнината на доц. д-р Георги
                            Н. Николов</hi> (София: Университетско издателство “Св. Климент
                        Охридски”, 2018), 276-303.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kuhn, M., “Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s Trinitarian Formulation in the Islamic Milieu,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Islam and Christian-Muslim Relations </hi>29:2 (2018),
                        123-143.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Third Treatise of Shaykh Abū al-Faraj ‘Abd Allāh Ibn al-Ṭayyib
                        on Unity and Trinity,” <hi rend="italic">Islam and Christian-Muslim
                            Relations </hi>29:3 (2018), 269-287.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kujumdzieva, S., “The Syriac Tropologion,” in: Eadem, <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Hymnographic Book of Tropologion: Sources, Liturgy and Chant
                            Repertory</hi> (London: Routledge, 2018), 54-73.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lafli, E., “Roman Funerary Steles and Byzantine Inscriptions in the Museum
                        of Şanlıurfa,” <hi rend="italic">Philia: International Journal of Ancient
                            Mediterranean Studies</hi> 4 (2018), 74-95.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lahdo, A., “‘Iwardo: A Struggle for Existence,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O.
                        Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the
                            Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias
                        Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        135-146.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lalik, K., “Ethnic and Religious Factors of Chaldo-Assyrian Identity in an
                        Interface with the Kurds in Iraqi Kurdistan,” in: J. Bocheńska (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Rediscovering Kurdistan’s Cultures and Identities: The
                            Call of the Cricket</hi> (Palgrave Studies in Cultural Heritage and
                        Conflict; Cham, Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan, 2018), 213-257.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lamassu, N., “Epilogue: Tombstones and Inverted Crosses,” in: H. Travis
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and Political
                            Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 307-310.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lau, M., “The Dream Come True? Matthew of Edessa and the Return of the
                        Roman Emperor,” in: B. Neil and E. Anagnostou-Laoutides (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Dreams, Memory and Imagination in Byzantium</hi>
                        (Byzantina Australiensia 24; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 160-179.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Leezenberg, M., “Transformations in Minority Religious Leadership: The
                        Yezidis, Shabak, and Assyrians in Northern Iraq,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Sociology of Islam</hi> 6:2 (2018), 233-260.</bibl>
                    <bibl>LeMasters, P., “Peaceable Responses to Persecution: The Experience of
                        Eastern Christian Communities in the Middle East,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            of Ecumenical Studies</hi> 53:3 (2018), 386-406.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lied, L.I., and Monger, M.P., “Look to the East: New and Forgotten Sources
                        of <hi rend="italic">4 Ezra</hi>,” in: L. DiTommaso, M. Henze and W. Adler
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered Bible: Studies in Biblical
                            Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of Michael E. Stone</hi> (Studia
                        in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        639-652.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loosley, E., “Cultural Imperialism at the Borders of Empire: The Case of
                        the ‘Villa of the Amazons’ in Edessa,” in: G.J. Brooke, A.H.W. Curtis, M.
                        al-Hamad and G.R. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern and Arabian
                            Essays: Studies in Honour of John F. Healey</hi> (Journal of Semitic
                        Studies Supplement 41; Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018),
                        215-230.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lorenz, P.E., “The Lukan Genealogy (Luke 3:23–38) as a Living Text: The
                        Genealogy of Jesus in the Traditions of Codex Bezae and Aphrahat,” in:
                        H.A.G. Houghton (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Liturgy and the Living Text of the
                            New Testament: Papers from the Tenth Birmingham Colloquium on the
                            Textual Criticism of the New Testament</hi> (Texts and Studies 16;
                        Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 71-120.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lourié, B., “Rewritten Bible in the “Museum” Slavonic Translation of the
                        Song of Songs,” <hi rend="italic">Scrinium</hi> 14 (2018), 257-272.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “[Review of:] A.Tefera, <hi rend="italic">The Ethiopian Homily on the
                            Ark of the Covenant: Critical Edition and Annotated Translation of
                        </hi>Dǝrsanä Ṣǝyon (Texts and Studies in Eastern Christianity 5; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2015),” <hi rend="italic">Восток / Oriens</hi> 1 (2018),
                        233-237.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ma, X., and Wang, C., “On the Xiapu Ritual Manual <hi rend="italic">Mani
                            the Buddha of Light</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Religions</hi> 9:7 (2018),
                        1-40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Makko, A., “The Assyrian “Concept of Unity” after <hi rend="italic"
                            >Seyfo</hi>,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian
                            Genocide: Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in
                        Modern History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 239-253.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Maksymiuk, K., “Mass Deportations in Syria and Northern Mesopotamia under
                        the Rule of Xusrō I Anōšīrvān (540–542),” in: F. Puell de la Villa and D.
                        García Hernán (eds.), <hi rend="italic">War and Population Displacement:
                            Lessons of History</hi> (Cañada Blanch/Sussex Academic Studies on
                        Contemporary Spain; Eastbourne: Sussex Academic Press, 2018), 46-53.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Strategic Aims of Šāpur II during the Campaign in Northern
                        Mesopotamia (359–360),” <hi rend="italic">Historia i Świat</hi> 7 (2018),
                        87-97.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mandolino, G., “La testimonianza del patriarca nestoriano Israel di Kaškar
                        (m. 872) sulla pseudo-<hi rend="italic">Teologia di Aristotele</hi>,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 8 (2018), 153-166.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mansfeld, J., “Theodoret as a Source for the Aëtian <hi rend="italic"
                            >Placita</hi>,” in: J. Mansfeld and D.T. Runia (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Aëtiana IV: Papers of the Melbourne Colloquium on Ancient
                            Doxography</hi> (Philosophia Antiqua 148; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        174-195.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marcocci, G., “Rites and Inquisition: Ethnographies of Error in Portuguese
                        India (1560–1625),” in: I.G. Županov and P.A. Fabre (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">The Rites Controversies in the Early Modern World</hi>
                        (Studies in Christian Mission 53; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 145-164.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Marcus, J., “The Gospel of Peter as a Jewish Christian Document,” <hi
                            rend="italic">New Testament Studies</hi> 64:4 (2018), 473-494.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matitashvili, S., “The Monasteries Founded by the Thirteen Syrian Fathers
                        in Iberia: The Rise of Monasticism in Sixth-Century Georgia,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Studies in Late Antiquity</hi> 2:1 (2018), 4-39.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Matsui, D., and Wang, P., “The Syro-Uighur Christian Inscription of Yulin
                        Cave 16,” <hi rend="italic">Dunhuang Research</hi> 2 (2018), 34-39 [in
                        Chinese].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mazzola, M., “The Textual Tradition of Bar ‘Ebroyo’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Chronicle</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 131:1-2 (2018),
                        73-100.</bibl>
                    <bibl>McLaughlin, A.E.T., and Berkes, L., “A Syriac Letter Reused for a Greek
                        Tax Receipt from the Early Islamic Period,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of
                            the American Society of Papyrologists</hi> 55 (2018), 59-69.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mengozzi, A., “Simon Magus and Simon Peter in Rome: The Sureth Version of
                        a Late East-Syriac Hymn for the Commemoration of St Peter and Paul,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Kervan: International Journal of Afro-Asiatic Studies</hi>
                        22 (2018), 65-90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mengozzi, A., and Miola, E., “Paronomastic Infinitives in North-Eastern
                        Neo-Aramaic: A Typological Approach,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi>
                        16:2 (2018), 270-299.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Minov, S., “Bar Sarōšway on Melchizedek: Reception of Extra-Biblical
                        Material in the East-Syrian Tradition of Scriptural Exegesis,” in: L.
                        DiTommaso, M. Henze and W. Adler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered
                            Bible: Studies in Biblical Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of
                            Michael E. Stone</hi> (Studia in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26;
                        Leiden: Brill, 2018), 718-735.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The <hi rend="italic">Exhortation of the Apostle Peter</hi>: A
                        Syriac Pseudepigraphon and Its Monastic Context,” in: M.B. Blidstein, S.
                        Ruzer and D. Stökl Ben Ezra (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Scriptures, Sacred
                            Traditions, and Strategies of Religious Subversion: Studies in Discourse
                            with the Work of Guy G. Stroumsa</hi> (Studien und Texte zu Antike und
                        Christentum 112; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018), 167-181.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Monferrer-Sala, J.P., “The Lyre of Exegesis: Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s Analytical
                        Patterns of the Account of the Destruction of Sodom,” in: G. Tamer, R.
                        Grundmann, A.E. Kattan and K. Pinggéra (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Exegetical
                            Crossroads: Understanding Scripture in Judaism, Christianity and Islam
                            in the Pre-Modern Orient</hi> (Judaism, Christianity, and Islam –
                        Tension, Transmission, Transformation 8; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018),
                        119-144.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Nine Post-Hexaplaric Readings in the Arabic Translation of the Book
                        of Numbers by al-Ḥārith b. Sinān b. Sunbāṭ (10th c. CE),” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Zeitschrift für die alttestamentliche Wissenschaft</hi> 130:4 (2018),
                        602-615.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “A Summary in Michael the Syrian’s ‘Chronography’ and its Companions
                        in Greek, Syriac and Arabic, With an Incursion in Ethiopic,” in: G. Mandalà
                        and I. Pérez Martín (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Multilingual and Multigraphic
                            Documents and Manuscripts of East and West</hi> (Perspectives on
                        Linguistics and Ancient Languages 5; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press,
                        2018), 463-484.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The <hi rend="italic">Testament of Adam</hi> in Arabic Dress: Two
                        Coptic-Arabic Witnesses of the Narrative Type ‘b’,” in: L. DiTommaso, M.
                        Henze and W. Adler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Embroidered Bible: Studies
                            in Biblical Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha in Honour of Michael E.
                            Stone</hi> (Studia in Veteris Testamenti Pseudepigrapha 26; Leiden:
                        Brill, 2018), 736-757.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Monnickendam, Y., “Late Antique Christian Law in the Eastern Roman Empire:
                        Toward a New Paradigm,” <hi rend="italic">Studies in Late Antiquity</hi> 2:1
                        (2018), 40-83.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moriggi, M., “A Syriac Cross from Hatra,” in: G.J. Brooke, A.H.W. Curtis,
                        M. al-Hamad and G.R. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Near Eastern and
                            Arabian Essays: Studies in Honour of John F. Healey</hi> (Journal of
                        Semitic Studies Supplement 41; Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2018),
                        241-247.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moubarakah, M., “Contribution du Patriarche maronite Étienne Douaïhy à une
                        controverse française entre catholiques et calvinistes (1673),” in: Ž. Paša
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in
                            Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth
                            Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio
                        Istituto Orientale, 2018), 547-561.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Müller, H., “Assyrian Christians in Iraq, the League of Nations and
                        Transnational Christian Advocacy (1920s–1940s),” in: Sh. Talay and S.O.
                        Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the
                            Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias
                        Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        253-304.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Murray, A.V., “Franks and Eastern Christians in the Principality of
                        Antioch, 1099-1187: Ethnicity and Identity,” in: K.N. Ciggaar and V. van
                        Aalst (eds.), <hi rend="italic">East and West in the Medieval Eastern
                            Mediterranean III: Antioch from the Byzantine Reconquest until the End
                            of the Crusader Principality. Acta of the Congress held at Hernen Castle
                            (the Netherlands) in May 2009</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 269;
                        Leuven: Peeters, 2018), 113-126.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L., “De Syrisch-orthodoxe Kerk,” in: H.G.B. Teule
                        and A. Brüning (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handboek oosters christendom</hi>
                        (Leuven: Peeters, 2018), 158-171.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Writing Assyrian History: The Military, the Patriarch and the
                        British in Yaqu bar Malek Ismael’s <hi rend="italic">Assyrians in Two World
                            Wars</hi> (Tehran 1964),” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of
                            Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern
                        Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        235-252.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L., and Teule, H.G.B., “De Westerse Kerken in het
                        Midden-Oosten,” in: H.G.B. Teule and A. Brüning (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Handboek oosters christendom</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2018),
                        493-503.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mutzafi, H., “Akkadian Substrate Words and Meanings Surfacing in
                        Neo-Aramaic,” <hi rend="italic">Brill’s Journal of Afroasiatic Languages and
                            Linguistics</hi> 10:1 (2018), 24-51.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Folk Etymology in the North-Eastern Neo-Aramaic Dialects,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 16:2 (2018), 215-233.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Naby, E., “Abduction, Rape and Genocide: Urmia’s Assyrian Girls and
                        Women,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide:
                            Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern
                        History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 158-177.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Napiorkowska, L., “Patterns of Diffusion of Phonological Change in the
                        North-Eastern Neo-Aramaic Dialect of Azran,” in: N. Vidro, R. Vollandt,
                        E.-M. Wagner and J. Olszowy-Schlanger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                            Semitic Linguistics and Manuscripts: A Liber Discipulorum in Honour of
                            Professor Geoffrey Khan</hi> (Studia Semitica Upsaliensia 30; Uppsala:
                        Uppsala Universitet, 2018), 217-233.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nassif, A., “Symbolisme et théologie biblique dans les Bō‘wōtō de St.
                        Jacques de Sarough,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for
                            Syriac Studies</hi> 18 (2018), 58-66.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Naumescu, V., “Syriac as a <hi rend="italic">Lingua Sacra</hi>: Speaking
                        the Language of Christ in India,” in: S. Luehrmann (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Praying with the Senses: Contemporary Orthodox Christian Spirituality
                            in Practice</hi> (Bloomington, Indiana: Indiana University Press, 2018),
                        103-119.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nawotka, K., “Syriac and Persian Versions of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Alexander Romance</hi>,” in: K.R. Moore (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Brill’s Companion to the Reception of Alexander the Great</hi> (Brill’s
                        Companions to Classical Reception 14; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 525-542.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Neely, B., “The Patriarch and the Insider Movement: Debating Timothy I,
                        Muhammad, and the Qur’an,” in: A.S. Ibrahim and A. Greenham (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Muslim Conversions to Christ: A Critique of Insider
                            Movements in Islamic Contexts</hi> (New York: Peter Lang, 2018),
                        3-78.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Neuhäuser, D.L., Neuhäuser, R., and Harrak, A., “Reports and Drawings of
                        Celestial Observations in the 8th Century Syriac <hi rend="italic">Chronicle
                            of Zuqnīn</hi> (Auroral and Meteoric Phenomena),” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 18 (2018),
                        67-90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Noel, W., and Rosen, R.M., “The Syriac Galen Palimpsest Project: An
                        Introduction,” <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018),
                        1-8.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Parmentier, M.F.G., “Fragments of Gregory of Nyssa’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Contra Eunomium</hi> in Syriac Translation,” in: M. Brugarolas (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Gregory of Nyssa: Contra Eunomium I. An English
                            Translation with Supporting Studies</hi> (Supplements to Vigiliae
                        Christianae 148; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 593-604.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paulsen Galal, L., ““If I Want to Travel, I Just Travel”: Travels and
                        Dwellings among Assyrians and Copts in Denmark,” in: A. Schmoller (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Middle Eastern Christians and Europe: Historical Legacies
                            and Present Challenges</hi> (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 13;
                        Wien: LIT, 2018), 217-238.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Paša, Ž., “Īšū‘yāb I al-Arzunī and Confession of the Faith: Critical
                        Edition and Translation,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44
                        (2018), 359-385.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Martyrdom of Babowai the Catholicos and Patriarch, and the
                        Confession of the Faith of Barṣawma of Nisibis: Critical Edition and
                        Translation,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the
                            Crescent: Studies in Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion
                            of His Eightieth Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304;
                        Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale, 2018), 499-525.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pedersen, N.A., “The Legendary Addai and the <hi rend="italic">First
                            Apocalypse of James</hi>,” in: H. Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and F. Feder
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Ägypten und der Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel
                            zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 187-211.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Peers, G., “Isaac of Antioch’s Organ and the Media of Musical Subjects,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 26:1 (2018),
                        75-109.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perczel, I., “Accommodationist Strategies on the Malabar Coast:
                        Competition or Complementarity?,” in: I.G. Županov and P.A. Fabre (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">The Rites Controversies in the Early Modern World</hi>
                        (Studies in Christian Mission 53; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 191-232.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “‘The Oldest Monument Extant of the Study of Indian Languages by
                        Europeans’?: A 17th-Century Malayalam Encyclopaedia Discovered in the
                        Mannanam Library,” in: J.C. Chennattuserry and I. Payyappilly (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Revisiting a Treasure Trove: Perspectives on the
                            Collection at St Kuriakose Elias Chavara Archives and Research
                            Centre</hi> (Bengaluru: Centre for Publications CHRIST, 2018),
                        94-104.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Some Early Documents about the Interactions of the Saint Thomas
                        Christians and the European Missionaries,” in: M. Kooria and M.N. Pearson
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Malabar in the Indian Ocean: Cosmopolitanism in a
                            Maritime Historical Region</hi> (New Delhi: Oxford University Press,
                        2018), 76-120.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perczel, I., and Kurukkoor, G., “A Malayalam Church History from the
                        Eighteenth Century, Based on Original Documents,” in: J.C. Chennattuserry
                        and I. Payyappilly (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Revisiting a Treasure Trove:
                            Perspectives on the Collection at St Kuriakose Elias Chavara Archives
                            and Research Centre</hi> (Bengaluru: Centre for Publications CHRIST,
                        2018), 111-131.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Perkams, M., “Der <hi rend="italic">Brief des Mārā bar Serapiyōn</hi>:
                        Stoische Indifferenz und biblische Weisheit in der Welt des Aion,” in: P.
                        Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des
                            IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter
                        Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        127-138.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pettipiece, T., “Biblical and Manichaean Citations in Titus of Bostra’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Contra Manichaeos</hi>,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias
                        Chaves and S. Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines:
                            Mélanges en l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme
                        ancien et origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018),
                        393-402.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pieper, L., “Paulos Mar Gregorios (1922–1996): Indische Orthodoxie im
                        “Zeitalter der Ökumene”,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile
                            gelebter Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 219-232.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Paulos Mar Gregorios: (Dis-)Kontinuität syrischer Tradition im
                        indischen Kontext,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt
                            2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 139-146.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pietruschka, U., “Eine Karšūnī-Handschrift und ihr historischer und
                        religiöser Kontext,” in: H. Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and F. Feder (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Ägypten und der Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 213-225.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Präsentation und Umformung biblischen Materials in den <hi
                            rend="italic">‘Uyūn al-aḫbār</hi> des Ibn Qutayba (828-889 AD),” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi> 70:1-2 (2018),
                        105-122.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pittappillil, F., “Baptismal Memrā’ of Anonymous Author of the Ninth
                        Century,” <hi rend="italic">Liturgia Sacra</hi> 24:1 [51] (2018),
                        71-91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Polański, T., “Word Translating Image: In Search of Modern-Language
                        Equivalents for Syriac and Coptic Terminology,” <hi rend="italic">Folia
                            Orientalia</hi> 55 (2018), 255-267.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Popa, C.-S., “Griechisches Dogma in syrischer Gestalt. Die Christologie
                        des Briefes: Des Sophronius von Jerusalem an Arkadius von Zypern,” in: P.
                        Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des
                            IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter
                        Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        147-154.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Syrians and the Appeal to Abraham in the Early Islamic Times,” in:
                        L. Bormann (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Abraham’s Family: A Network of Meaning
                            in Judaism, Christianity, and Islam</hi> (Wissenschaftliche
                        Untersuchungen zum Neuen Testament 415; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018),
                        465-476.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Possekel, U., “Bardaisan’s Influence on Late Antique Christianity,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 21:1 (2018),
                        81-125.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Potoczny, M., “An Accommodation of the Syriac Holy Week Celebrations in
                        the Cultural Context of the Syro-Malankara Church: Notes Based on the
                        Practice of Some Parishes of the Archidiocese of Thiruvalla,” in: A. Lossky,
                        G. Sekulovski and T. Pott (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Liturgie et religiosité:
                            64</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">e</hi><hi rend="italic"> Semaine
                            d’études liturgiques, Paris, Institut Saint-Serge, 26–29 juin 2017</hi>
                        (Semaines d’Études Liturgiques Saint-Serge 64; Münster: Aschendorff, 2018),
                        177-191.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Ordination to the Presbyterate in the Syriac Churches: History and
                        Structure of the Rite,” <hi rend="italic">Roczniki Teologiczne</hi> 65:8
                        (2018), 125-140 [in Polish].</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pritula, A., “‘Abdīšō‘ of Gazarta, the First Literate of the Chaldean
                        Church: Poems Dedicated to the Popes of Rome,” <hi rend="italic">Вестник
                            СПбГУ, Востоковедение и африканистика</hi> 10:3 (2018), 374-391.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prostko-Prostyński, J., “Who Wrote the Syriac Chronicle of
                        Pseudo-Zachariah Rhetor?,” in: R. Koliński, J. Prostko-Prostyński and W.
                        Tyborowski (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Awīlum ša la mašê – Man Who Cannot Be
                            Forgotten: Studies in Honor of Prof. Stefan Zawadzki Presented on the
                            Occasion of his 70th Birthday</hi> (Alter Orient und Altes Testament
                        463; Münster: Ugarit-Verlag, 2018), 179-188.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Quandt, A.B., and Wolcott, R.C., “The Codicology and Conservation of the
                        Syriac Galen Palimpsest,” <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1
                        (2018), 33-68.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rammelt, C., “Ibas von Edessa: Ein Bischof zwischen den Fronten im
                        christologischen Diskurs,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile
                            gelebter Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80.
                            Geburtstag</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55;
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 33-50.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reed, A.Y., “Rethinking Sacrifice in the Pseudo-Clementines <hi
                            rend="italic">Homilies</hi>,” in: S.C. Mimouni and L. Painchaud (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">La question de la “sacerdotalisation” dans le judaïsme
                            synagogal, le christianisme et le rabbinisme</hi> (Judaïsme ancien et
                        origines du christianisme 9; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018), 411-432.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Renger, A.-B., and Stellmacher, A., “The Making of the Stylite in the
                        Interplay of Text, Image and Performance: On the Exercise of Saint Simeon,”
                        in: R. Alciati (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Norm and Exercise: Christian
                            Asceticism between Late Antiquity and Early Middle Ages</hi> (Potsdamer
                        Altertumswissenschaftliche Beiträge 65; Stuttgart: Franz Steiner, 2018),
                        165-186.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ri, A.S.-M., “La <hi rend="italic">Caverne des trésors</hi> et les
                        recherches sur Mar Éphrem,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias Chaves and S.
                        Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines: Mélanges en
                            l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme ancien et
                        origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018), 417-428.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ritter, A.M., “Nemesios von Emesa,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der
                        Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe
                        Verlag, 2018), vol. 2, 1579-1586.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roggema, B.H., “Salvaging the Saintly Sergius: Hagiographical Aspects of
                        the Syriac Legend of Sergius Baḥīrā,” in: N. Jaspert and A. Cuffel (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Entangled Hagiographies of the Religious Other</hi>
                        (Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2018), 55-83.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rosenberg, M., “Struck by Wood, Struck by God: Virginity Beyond/Despite
                        Anatomy,” in: Idem, <hi rend="italic">Signs of Virginity: Testing Virgins
                            and Making Men in Late Antiquity</hi> (New York: Oxford University
                        Press, 2018), 90-116.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rosenblatt, A., “Maronite Music Today: The Local and Global Models,” <hi
                            rend="italic">International Journal of Arts &amp; Sciences</hi> 11:1
                        (2018), 203-211.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rouwhorst, G.A.M., “The Descent of Christ into the Underworld in Early
                        Christian Liturgy,” in: M. Sarot and A.L.H.M. van Wieringen (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">The Apostles’ Creed: ‘He Descended into Hell’</hi>
                        (Studies in Theology and Religion 24; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 54-78.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Ritual Interactions between Jews and Christians East of Antioch,”
                        in: P. Lanfranchi and J. Verheyden (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Jews and
                            Christians in Antiquity: A Regional Perspective</hi> (Interdisciplinary
                        Studies in Ancient Culture and Religion 18; Leuven: Peeters, 2018),
                        163-181.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Ruani, F., “<hi rend="italic">Cave canem</hi>! Notes sur le rejet du salut
                        des animaux chez quelques auteurs syriaques,” in: M. Cutino, I. Iribarren
                        and F. Vinel (eds.), <hi rend="italic">La restauration de la création:
                            Quelle place pour les animaux? Actes du colloque de l’ERCAM tenu à
                            Strasbourg du 12 au 14 mars 2015</hi> (Supplements to Vigiliae
                        Christianae 145; Leiden: Brill, 2018), 183-212.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mystery Cults and Syriac Heresiology: A Fruitful Polemical
                        Association?,” <hi rend="italic">Religion in the Roman Empire</hi> 4:3
                        (2018), 331-352.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rubenstein, J.L., “Martyrdom in the Persian Martyr Acts and in the
                        Babylonian Talmud,” in: G. Herman and J.L. Rubenstein (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">The Aggada of the Bavli and Its Cultural World</hi> (Brown
                        Judaic Studies 362; Providence, Rhode Island: Brown Judaic Studies, 2018),
                        175-210.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Saadi, A.-M., “Interdependence of Classical Syriac and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Suryoyo of Tur Abdin</hi> (STA): Orthography for the STA,” in: D.
                        Weltecke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und
                            Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018),
                        169-192.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Salvesen, A., ““Christ Has Subjected Us to the Harsh Yoke of the Arabs”:
                        The Syriac Exegesis of Jacob of Edessa in the New World Order,” in: G.
                        Tamer, R. Grundmann, A.E. Kattan and K. Pinggéra (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Exegetical Crossroads: Understanding Scripture in Judaism, Christianity
                            and Islam in the Pre-Modern Orient</hi> (Judaism, Christianity, and
                        Islam – Tension, Transmission, Transformation 8; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter,
                        2018), 145-161.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Samir, S.Kh., “La doctrine de l’Incarnation de Yaḥyā ibn ‘Adī à la lumière
                        du <hi rend="italic">Traité </hi>17 Sbath,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
                            graeco-arabica</hi> 8 (2018), 189-193.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sato, N., “The Memory of Sayfo and Its Relation to the Identity of
                        Contemporary Assyrian/Aramean Christians in Syria,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O.
                        Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays on the
                            Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi> (Gorgias
                        Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018),
                        305-326.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schilling, A.M., “Ein Koran-Florilegium in syrischer Überlieferung:
                        Alphonse Mingana und der “Disput gegen die Nation der Araber” des Dionysios
                        bar Ṣalībī,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia
                            Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt
                            2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 155-180.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schmoller, A., “Of Safe Havens and Sinking Ships: The Church in Oral
                        Histories of Middle Eastern Christians in Austria,” in: A. Schmoller (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Middle Eastern Christians and Europe: Historical
                            Legacies and Present Challenges</hi> (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒
                        Oecumenica 13; Wien: LIT, 2018), 147-198.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scully, J., “Free Will and Ascetical Labor: How Babai the Great Fixes the
                        Platonic Conception of the Soul,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Eastern
                            Christian Studies</hi> 193-222 (2018), 70:3-4.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Redemption for the Serpent: The Reception History of Serpent
                        Material from the <hi rend="italic">Physiologus </hi>in the Greek, Latin,
                        and Syriac Traditions,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Antikes
                            Christentum / Journal of Ancient Christianity</hi> 22:3 (2018),
                        422-455.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Seleznyov, N.N., “Seven Sessions or Just a Letter? Observations on the
                        Structure of the Disputations between Elias, Metropolitan of Nisibis, and
                        the Vizier Abū l-Qāsim al-Maghribī,” <hi rend="italic">Scrinium</hi> 14
                        (2018), 434-445.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sepmeijer, F., and Ciggaar, K.N., “The <hi rend="italic">Lament on
                            Tripoli</hi> by Solomon of Ašluḥ (Sulayman al-Ašlūḥī): Its Historical
                        and Cultural Character,” in: K.N. Ciggaar and V. van Aalst (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">East and West in the Medieval Eastern Mediterranean III:
                            Antioch from the Byzantine Reconquest until the End of the Crusader
                            Principality. Acta of the Congress held at Hernen Castle (the
                            Netherlands) in May 2009</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 269;
                        Leuven: Peeters, 2018), 9-36.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shareef, D.M., Qyrio, M.I., and Ali, C.N., “An Investigation of Refusal
                        Strategies as Used by Bahdini Kurdish and Syriac Aramaic Speakers,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Advances in Language and Literary Studies</hi> 9:1 (2018),
                        89-101.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shemunkasho, A., “Die Gedenkfeier des heiligen Gabriel als eine lebendige
                        Quelle für die Pilgernden,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 100
                        (2017 [2018]), 32-42.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mor Philoxenos Yuhanna Dolabani (1885–1969): Ein Vater
                        syrisch-orthodoxer Spiritualität im 20. Jahrhundert,” in: M. Tamcke (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Profile gelebter Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison
                            Griffith zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe:
                        Syriaca 55; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 205-218.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shepardson, Ch.C., “Give It Up for God: Wealth, Suffering, and the
                        Rhetoric of Religious Persecution in John of Ephesus’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Church History</hi>,” in: W. Mayer and C.L. de Wet (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Reconceiving Religious Conflict: New Views from the
                            Formative Centuries of Christianity</hi> (Routledge Studies in the Early
                        Christian World; London: Routledge, 2018), 86-109.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sims-Williams, N., “A Newly Identified Sogdian Fragment from the Legend of
                        Saint George,” <hi rend="italic">DABIR: The Digital Archive of Brief Notes
                            &amp; Iran Review</hi> 6 (2018), 110-115.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sivan, H., “Subversive Pilgrimages: Barsauma in Jerusalem,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 26:1 (2018),
                        53-74.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Song, G., “The Many Faces of Our Lady: Chinese Encounters with the Virgin
                        Mary between 7th and 17th Centuries,” <hi rend="italic">Monumenta
                            Serica</hi> 66:2 (2018), 303-356.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sparre, S.L., and Galal, L.P., “Incense and Holy Bread: The Sense of
                        Belonging through Ritual among Middle Eastern Christians in Denmark,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Ethnic and Migration Studies</hi> 44:16 (2018),
                        2649-2666.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Starr, P.J., “Isḥāq ibn Ḥunayn’s Version of Περὶ φύσεως ἀνθρώπου: A
                        ‘Balance of Alternatives’ in Translating ἑαυτοῦ,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in Honor of
                            Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday</hi>
                        (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale,
                        2018), 659-667.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stavridis, S., “Lady Surma: Pillar of the Assyrian Nation, 1883–1975,” in:
                        H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and
                            Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 191-216.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Stewart, C., “Giving Voice to Ancient Texts: Manuscript Scholarship in the
                        Digital Era,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Middle East
                            Studies</hi> 50:1 (2018), 119-123.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Strohmaier, G., “Syrer am Kalifenhof in Bagdad,” in: D. Weltecke (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und Gegenwart</hi>
                        (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018), 83-110.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Suermann, H., “Anton Baumstark (1872–1948): Anfänge der Wissenschaft vom
                        Christlichen Orient in Bonn,” in: H. Meyer, C. Schirrmacher and U. Vollmer
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Die Bonner Orient- und Asienwissenschaften: Eine
                            Geschichte in 22 Porträts</hi> (Gossenberg: OSTASIEN Verlag, 2018),
                        65-84.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Die Entstehung des Islam und seine Expansion aus Sicht der Aramäer,”
                        in: D. Weltecke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte
                            und Gegenwart</hi> (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang,
                        2018), 47-82.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Die Lage der Christen im Nahen / Mittleren Osten zwischen Exodus und
                        Rückkehr,” in: M. Bonacker and G. Geiger (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Grenzen –
                            der demokratische Rechtsstaat und die Herausforderung der Migration</hi>
                        (Paderborn: Ferdinand Schöningh, 2018), 75-90.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Suh, M.K.W., “Τὸ πνεῦµα in 1 Corinthians 5:5: A Reconsideration of
                        Patristic Exegesis,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 72:2
                        (2018), 121-141.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Sun, J., “The Earliest Statements of Christian Faith in China? A Critique
                        of the Conventional Chronology of <hi rend="italic">The Messiah Sutra</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">On One God</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Sungkyun Journal
                            of East Asian Studies</hi> 18:2 (2018), 133-152.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Syryany, I., “‘The Ten Plagues Brought on Egypt by Moses’ in the Exegesis
                        of Jacob of Serugh,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for
                            Syriac Studies</hi> 18 (2018), 42-57.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Szymczak, T., “Efrem o wolności: Hymny o Kościele 2, 3, 6, 13, 19,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Lignum Vitae</hi> 19 (2018), 33-61.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Talay, Sh., “The Beginning of the End of Syriac Christianity in the Middle
                        East,” in: Sh. Talay and S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915:
                            An Anthology of Essays on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the
                            First World War</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway,
                        New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2018), 1-18.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tamcke, M., “Ephraem und die Lutheraner,” in: Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in Honor of
                            Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth Birthday</hi>
                        (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio Istituto Orientale,
                        2018), 419-436.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Letters on the Sayfo from Assyrian Eyewitnesses,” in: Sh. Talay and
                        S.O. Barthoma (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Sayfo 1915: An Anthology of Essays
                            on the Genocide of Assyrians/Arameans during the First World War</hi>
                        (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 50; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                        Press, 2018), 89-104.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mardin, die Bagdadbahn und die Deutsche Orientmission,” in: H.
                        Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and F. Feder (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Ägypten und
                            der Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und
                        Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        305-311.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. ““Reform der Kirche des Ostens von innen?”: Programm und Lebenswerk
                        des Yuhannon Pera,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen Syrologentages in Eichstätt
                            2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018), 181-192.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Reformation in einer orientalischen Kirche des 19. Jahrhunderts?
                        Beobachtungen anhand des “Vaters” der “lutherischen Nestorianer” Yuhannon
                        Pera (1850–1924),” in: M. Tamcke (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Profile gelebter
                            Theologie im Orient: Sidney Harrison Griffith zum 80. Geburtstag</hi>
                        (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 55; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz
                        Verlag, 2018), 181-194.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Was Macht einen Mönch zum Mönch? Kontroversen um das Mönchsideal in
                        der Ostsyrischen Literatur an der Wende des 6. zum 7. Jahrhundert,” in: <hi
                            rend="italic">Orientalia Patristica: Papers of the International
                            Patristic Symposium, May 1–4, 2017</hi> (Drobeta-Turnu Severin: Didahia
                        Severin Publishing, 2018), 25-34.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tannous, J., “Romanness in the Syriac East,” in: W. Pohl, C. Gantner, C.
                        Grifoni and M. Pollheimer-Mohaupt (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Transformations
                            of Romanness: Early Medieval Regions and Identities</hi>
                        (Millennium-Studien / Millennium Studies 71; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter,
                        2018), 457-480.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tardieu, M., “Le Barberousse jacobite de Ḥāḥ,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias
                        Chaves and S. Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines:
                            Mélanges en l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme
                        ancien et origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018),
                        429-436.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tavolieri, C., “Body and Soul: The Dangers of Music and Song in Syriac
                        Christianity,” in: A. Garcia-Ventura, C. Tavolieri and L. Verderame (eds.),
                            <hi rend="italic">The Study of Musical Performance in Antiquity:
                            Archaeology and Written Sources</hi> (Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge
                        Scholars Publishing, 2018), 247-260.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Teule, H.G.B., “Christians in Iraq: The Transition from Religious to
                        Secular Identity,” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Asian
                            Christianity</hi> 1 (2018), 11-24.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “De (Assyrische) Kerk van het Oosten,” in: H.G.B. Teule and A.
                        Brüning (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handboek oosters christendom</hi> (Leuven:
                        Peeters, 2018), 172-186.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “De Maronitische Kerk,” in: H.G.B. Teule and A. Brüning (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Handboek oosters christendom</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2018),
                        187-196.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Syrisch christendom van India: de Thomaschristenen,” in: H.G.B.
                        Teule and A. Brüning (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handboek oosters
                            christendom</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2018), 268-281.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Syrische spiritualiteit en kloosterleven,” in: H.G.B. Teule and A.
                        Brüning (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handboek oosters christendom</hi> (Leuven:
                        Peeters, 2018), 749-764.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomas, D.A., “Making Sense of the Bible in Early <hi rend="italic"
                            >kalām</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Eastern Christian
                            Studies</hi> 70:1-2 (2018), 85-103.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomas, D.R., “With the Qur’an in Mind,” in: M. Beaumont (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Arab Christians and the Qur’an from the Origins of Islam
                            to the Medieval Period</hi> (History of Christian-Muslim Relations 35;
                        Leiden: Brill, 2018), 131-149.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomassen, E., “Bardesanes (Bardaisan) von Edessa,” in: C. Riedweg, C.
                        Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und
                            der Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel:
                        Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol. 1, 874-877.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Saving Letter, Saving Book: The <hi rend="italic">Hymn of the
                            Pearl</hi>, the 23rd <hi rend="italic">Ode of Solomon</hi> and the <hi
                            rend="italic">Gospel of Truth</hi>,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias Chaves
                        and S. Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines:
                            Mélanges en l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme
                        ancien et origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018),
                        437-452.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tillier, M., “The Evolution of Judicial Procedures in East-Syrian Canon
                        Law after the Islamic Conquests: The Judicial Oath,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</hi> 70:3-4 (2018),
                        227-240.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Timuş, M., “Polémique mazdéenne anti-christologique: mécanismes de
                        déconstruction (ŠGW 15),” <hi rend="italic">Schweizerische Zeitschrift für
                            Religions- und Kulturgeschichte</hi> 112 (2018), 105-122.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tissot, Y., “Sur les textes courts des deux premiers <hi rend="italic"
                            >Actes de Thomas</hi>,” in: E. Crégheur, J.C. Dias Chaves and S.
                        Johnston (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christianisme des origines: Mélanges en
                            l’honneur du Professeur Paul-Hubert Poirier</hi> (Judaïsme ancien et
                        origines du christianisme 11; Turnhout: Brepols, 2018), 453-473.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toma, W., “The Presence of Images in the Church of the East,” in: Ž. Paša
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies in
                            Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth
                            Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio
                        Istituto Orientale, 2018), 449-470.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Toth, M.B., “Pulling It All Together: Managing the Syriac Galen Palimpsest
                        Project,” <hi rend="italic">Manuscript Studies</hi> 3:1 (2018), 9-32.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tozman, M.K., “Türkiye Türklerendir (Die Türkei den Türken): Die Aramäer
                        in Südostanatolien und der Kurdenkonflikt,” in: D. Weltecke (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Neue Aramäische Studien: Geschichte und Gegenwart</hi>
                        (Schola Nisibina 1; Frankfurt am Main: Peter Lang, 2018), 261-296.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Travis, H., “The Assyrian Genocide across History: Collective Memory,
                        Legal Theory, and Power Politics,” in: H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge
                        Studies in Modern History 29; London: Routledge, 2018), 1-91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Exile or Extinction: The Assyrian Genocide from 1915 to 2015,” in:
                        H. Travis (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Genocide: Cultural and
                            Political Legacies</hi> (Routledge Studies in Modern History 29; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 254-306.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Treiger, A., “Mutual Influences and Borrowings,” in: D.R. Thomas (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Routledge Handbook on Christian-Muslim Relations</hi>
                        (Routledge Handbooks; London: Routledge, 2018), 194-206.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tubach, J., “Die Personennamen der Doctrina Addai,” in: P. Bruns and T.
                        Kremer (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen
                            Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum
                        Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        193-212.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Die Personennamen des Liber Legum Regionum,” in: H. Behlmer, U.
                        Pietruschka and F. Feder (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Ägypten und der
                            Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Texte und
                        Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        313-320.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vagelpohl, U., “The User-Friendly Galen: Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq and the
                        Adaptation of Greek Medicine for a New Audience,” in: P. Bouras-Vallianatos
                        and S. Xenophontos (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Greek Medical Literature and
                            Its Readers: From Hippocrates to Islam and Byzantium</hi> (Publications
                        of the Centre for Hellenic Studies, King’s College London; London:
                        Routledge, 2018), 113-130.</bibl>
                    <bibl>van Reeth, J.M.F., “Le dualisme de Bardésane et de Mani: une lutte
                        mythique ou symbolique?,” in: M.-A. Persoons, C. Cannuyer and D. De Smet
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Les combats dans les mythes et les littératures de
                            l’Orient &amp; Miscellanea orientalia et iranica belgo-polonica:
                            Wojciech Skalmowski in memoriam</hi> (Acta Orientalia Belgica 31;
                        Bruxelles: Société royale belge d’études orientales, 2018), 283-292.</bibl>
                    <bibl>van Rompay, L., “Eusèbe: l’évêque presque oublié de la ville de Homs et la
                        diffusion de ses écrits,” <hi rend="italic">Connaissance des Pères de
                            l’Église</hi> 151 (2018), 10-26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vergani, E., “La Miscellanea Assemani della Biblioteca Ambrosiana: due <hi
                            rend="italic">mêmrê Sulla fede</hi> (il primo intestato a Efrem),” in:
                        Ž. Paša (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Between the Cross and the Crescent: Studies
                            in Honor of Samir Khalil Samir, S.J. on the Occasion of His Eightieth
                            Birthday</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 304; Roma: Pontificio
                        Istituto Orientale, 2018), 395-418.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vesa, V., “The Anaphoras of Mar Theodore of Mopsuestia in the East Syriac
                        Rite and of St. John Chrysostom in the Byzantine Church – Structure and
                        Theology: Comparative Study,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Universitatis
                            Babeş-Bolyai, Theologia Orthodoxa</hi> 63:1 (2018), 99-110.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vileno, A.M., and Wilkinson, R.J., “Die <hi rend="italic">Peshitta
                        </hi>von 1684 im Kontext des Werkes von Christian Knorr von Rosenroth als
                        Beitrag zu einem “kabbalistischen Christentum”,” in: E. Rohmer (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Ringen um den rechten Glauben: Orthodoxie, Konfession und
                            Toleranz 150 Jahre nach der Reformation. Akten der 27. Tagung der
                            Christian Knorr von Rosenroth-Gesellschaft</hi> (Morgen-Glantz:
                        Zeitschrift der Christian Knorr von Rosentoth-Geselschaft 28; Bern: Peter
                        Lang, 2018), 201-230.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Villey, É., “Quadrivium dans la tradition syriaque,” in: H. Touati (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie de l’humanisme méditerranéen</hi> (2018),
                        on-line: <ref
                            target="http://www.encyclopedie-humanisme.com/?Quadrivium-dans-la-tradition-syriaque"
                            >http://www.encyclopedie-humanisme.com/?Quadrivium-dans-la-tradition-syriaque</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Weiss, T., “The Creation of the World from Twenty-Two Letters and the
                        Syriac Context of <hi rend="italic">Sefer Yeṣirah</hi>,” in: Idem, <hi
                            rend="italic">Sefer Yeṣirah and Its Contexts: Other Jewish Voices</hi>
                        (Divinations: Rereading Late Ancient Religion; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania:
                        University of Pennsylvania Press, 2018), 55-75.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Waltisberg, M., “Philologisches zu den <hi rend="italic">Oden
                        Salomos</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen
                            Gesellschaft</hi> 168:1 (2018), 67-91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wang Yuanyuan, and Lin Wushu. “Discovery of an Incantation of St. George
                        in Ritual Manuscripts of a Chinese Folk Society,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Monumenta Serica</hi> 66:1 (2018), 115-130.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Watt, J.W., “The Commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Rhetoric </hi>by Bar
                        Hebraeus,” in: F. Woerther (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Commenting on
                            Aristotle’s Rhetoric, from Antiquity to the Present / Commenter la
                            Rhétorique d’Aristote, de l’Antiquité à la période contemporaine</hi>
                        (International Studies in the History of Rhetoric 11; Leiden: Brill, 2018),
                        116-131.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Jakob von Edessa,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        3, 2474-2479.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Rhetorical Education and Florilegia in Syriac,” in: M. Farina (ed.),
                            <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études
                        syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 95-110.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Sergios (Sargīs) von Reš‘aynā,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der
                        Spätantike</hi>. 3 vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe
                        Verlag, 2018), vol. 3, 2452-2462.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Syriac,” in: S. McGill and E.J. Watts (eds.), <hi rend="italic">A
                            Companion to Late Antique Literature</hi> (Blackwell Companions to the
                        Ancient World; Hoboken, New Jersey: Wiley Blackwell, 2018), 47-60.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Westerhoff, M., “Afrems trinitarische Skizzen,” in: P. Bruns and T. Kremer
                        (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Beiträge des IX. Deutschen
                            Syrologentages in Eichstätt 2016</hi> (Eichstätter Beiträge zum
                        Christlichen Orient 6; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        213-229.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Osterlachen – das Motiv des betrogenen Todes bei Ephraem, einem
                        koptischmanichäischen Psalm und im koptischen “Buch der Auferstehung”,” in:
                        H. Behlmer, U. Pietruschka and F. Feder (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Ägypten
                            und der Christliche Orient: Peter Nagel zum 80. Geburtstag</hi> (Texte
                        und Studien zur Koptischen Bibel 1; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2018),
                        321-333.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wickes, J.T., “Between Liturgy and School: Reassessing the Performative
                        Context of Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Madrāšê</hi>,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 26:1 (2018), 25-51.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wilkinson, R.J., “Working towards a Definition of Syriac in the Sixteenth
                        and Seventeenth Centuries,” in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les
                            auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études syriaques 15; Paris:
                        Geuthner, 2018), 207-236.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Witkamp, N., “‘In the Posture of One Who Prays’: The <hi rend="italic"
                            >Orans</hi> Position in Theodore of Mopsuestia’s Baptismal Rite,” in: H.
                        van Loon, G. de Nie, M. Op de Coul and P. van Egmond (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Prayer and the Transformation of the Self in Early
                            Christian Mystagogy</hi> (Late Antique History and Religion 18; Leuven:
                        Peeters, 2018), 191-208.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wood, Ph., “Christians in Umayyad Iraq: Decentralisation and Expansion
                        (600–750),” in: A. George and A. Marsham (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Power,
                            Patronage, and Memory in Early Islam: Perspectives on Umayyad
                            Elites</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2018), 255-274.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Woods, D., “Heraclius’ Alleged Farewell Salute to Syria,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Byzantion</hi> 88 (2018), 423-433</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wyrwa, D., “Tatian,” in: C. Riedweg, C. Horn and D. Wyrwa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Philosophie der Kaiserzeit und der Spätantike</hi>. 3
                        vols. (Die Philosophie der Antike 5.1-3; Basel: Schwabe Verlag, 2018), vol.
                        1, 817-825.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Yorulmaz, Ş., “Maronites in Mersin through Its Process of Becoming an
                        Important Port City: The Nineteenth and the Twentieth Century,” in: F.
                        Yenişehirlioğlu, E. Özveren and T. Selvi Ünlü (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Eastern Mediterranean Port Cities: A Study of Mersin, Turkey – From
                            Antiquity to Modernity</hi> (The Urban Book Series; Cham, Switzerland:
                        Springer, 2018), 93-109.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Youssef, J., “Ibn al-Ṭayyib’s <hi rend="italic">Paradise of
                            Christianity</hi>: Introductory Observations on an 11th Century Biblical
                        Commentary in Arabic,” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018),
                        403-424.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Youssef, Y.N., “Between Gregory the Theologian and Severus of Antioch,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 44 (2018), 425-438.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zachhuber, J., “Personhood in Miaphysitism: Severus of Antioch and John
                        Philoponus,” in: A. Torrance and S. Paschalidis (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Personhood in the Byzantine Christian Tradition: Early, Medieval, and
                            Modern Perspectives</hi> (London: Routledge, 2018), 29-43.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zambon, M., ““Apprendere qualcosa di sicuro” (ps. Clem. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Hom</hi>. I 3, 1): verità filosofica e verità profetica nella I omelia
                        pseudoclementina,” <hi rend="italic">Studia graeco-arabica</hi> 8 (2018),
                        13-48.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zawadzki, K.F., “‘Keiner soll die Lektüre der Schrift
                        durcheinanderbringen!’: Ein neues griechisches Fragment aus dem
                        Johanneskommentar des Cyrill von Alexandrien,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Biblica</hi> 99:3 (2018), 393-413.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zographos, A.-A., “A Monk’s Repose: The Icon of <hi rend="italic">The
                            Dormition of Saint Ephrem the Syrian</hi> and Contemporary Orthodox
                        Monasticism,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Association of Western Art
                            History</hi> 48:2 (2018), 53-81.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zurawski, J.M., “Rethinking the Divide between 4 Ezra and 2 Baruch:
                        Getting to the (Evil) Heart of the Matter,” in: J.H. Ellens, I.W. Oliver, J.
                        von Ehrenkrook, J. Waddell and J.M. Zurawski (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wisdom Poured Out Like Water: Studies on Jewish and Christian Antiquity
                            in Honor of Gabriele Boccaccini</hi> (Deuterocanonical and Cognate
                        Literature Studies 38; Berlin: Walter de Gruyter, 2018), 177-192.</bibl>
                    <bibl> Zweck, J., “Messengers, Materiality, and Transmission in the Old English
                        Apollonius of Tyre, Letter of Abgar, and Life of St Mary of Egypt,” in:
                        Idem, <hi rend="italic">Epistolary Acts: Anglo-Saxon Letters and Early
                            English Media</hi> (Toronto Anglo-Saxon Series; Toronto: University of
                        Toronto Press, 2018), 106-145.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
