<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Judith M. Lieu, <hi rend="italic">Marcion and the Making of a
                    Heretic: God and Scripture in the Second Century</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Blake</forename>
                        <surname>Hartung</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Saint Louis University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2019</date>
                <idno>Volume 22.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv22n1prhartung</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Blake Harting</author>
                        <title level="a">Judith M. Lieu, Marcion and the Making of a
                            Heretic: God and Scripture in the Second Century</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol22/HV22N1PRHartung.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="309" to="312">309–312</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="9"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-03-08">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">Judith M. Lieu, <hi rend="italic">Marcion and the Making of a
                    Heretic: God and Scripture in the Second Century</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge
                University Press, 2015). xvi + 502 pp; paperback; $37.99.</ab>
                <ab type="review-author">Blake Hartung, Saint Louis University</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
            <p xml:lang="en">The second-century teacher Marcion of Pontus (and the “Marcionite” Christians who
                followed him) looms large in early Syriac Christianity. In the fourth century,
                Ephrem regularly and vehemently attacked the Marcionite movement, attesting to its
                enduring strength in Syria and Mesopotamia. Decades later, well after the triumph of
                Nicene orthodoxy, Rabbula and Theodoret were apparently still struggling against
                Marcionites in the countryside.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"
                            ><p xml:lang="en"> See Theodoret, <hi rend="italic">Ep. </hi>81; <hi
                            rend="italic">Life of
                        Rabbula</hi> 41.</p></note>
                The Marcionite presence in the region was old and enduring. In fact, debate still
                swirls over Walter Bauer’s argument that Marcionite “heretics” were the first
                Christians in Edessa.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"
                        ><p xml:lang="en"> W. Bauer, <hi rend="italic">Rechtgläubigkeit und Ketzerei im ältesten Christentum </hi>(Tübingen: Mohr, 1934), 20–33. </p></note>
            </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> In light of the significance of Marcion and his movement for Syria and Mesopotamia
                in Late Antiquity, Judith Lieu’s <hi rend="italic">Marcion and the Making of a
                    Heretic</hi> is of special interest for the Syriac studies community. Lieu’s
                monograph is one of several important new studies on Marcion published in the past
                few years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"
                            ><p xml:lang="en"> See S. Moll, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Arch-Heretic
                            Marcion</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2010); M. Vinzent, <hi
                            rend="italic">Marcion and the Dating of the
                            Synoptic
                            Gospels</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2014); M. Klinghardt, <hi
                            rend="italic">Das älteste Evangelium und die
                            Enstehung der kanonischen
                            Evangelien</hi>, 2 vols. (Tübingen: Francke, 2015); D. Roth, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Text of Marcion’s
                        Gospel</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2015).</p></note>
                In this array of recent scholarship, <hi rend="italic">Marcion and the Making of a
                    Heretic</hi> stands out for both its scope and attention to detail. This review
                will offer general considerations of the book, but with a particular focus on its
                relevance for Syriac scholarship. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Lieu’s key claim, one which frames the entire structure of the book, is that
                scholars meet Marcion only second hand. “Marcion,” she writes, “is glimpsed only
                through the lens of the words of others, who are for the most part engaged in an
                ever more heated and vigorous polemic against him. It is his shadow as much as his
                presence that determines the future.” (p. 7) As such, the “real Marcion,” the
                Marcion of the second century, remains a mystery. Lieu recognizes that any attempt
                to reconstruct that Marcion must critically engage with the (adversarial) sources
                that purport to describe his character, works, and thought. Her task in the first of
                the book’s three parts, therefore, is to offer a thorough and systematic analysis of
                the early Christian anti-Marcionite polemical tradition from Justin to Irenaeus,
                Tertullian, and the Syriac tradition. This approach has its strengths, allowing the
                reader to examine each author’s presentation of Marcion on its own terms. It also
                bolsters Lieu’s attempted reconstruction of Marcion in the second and third sections
                of the book. One drawback of this approach is that, unlike with a more synthetic or
                topical approach to anti-Marcionite polemic, the reader can struggle to keep track
                of the shifting polemical portrayals of Marcion. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Lieu’s careful treatment of the early Syriac tradition and the many questions still
                debated in Syriac scholarship (in chapter 7) is consistent with her rigorous
                approach elsewhere in the book. The Syriac anti-Marcionite polemical material has
                not been subjected to such rigorous study in some time (notable exceptions include
                important articles by H.J.W. Drijvers and David Bundy).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en"> See D. Bundy, “Marcion and the Marcionites in Early Syriac Apologetics,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon </hi>101 (1988), 21–32; H. J. W. Drijvers, “Marcionism in Syria: Principles, Problems, Polemics,” <hi rend="italic">The Second Century </hi>6 (1987), 153–172; idem, “Marcion’s Reading of Gal. 4,8: Philosophical Background and Influence on Manichaeism,” in W. Sundermann, J. Duchesne-Guillemin, and F. Vahman, eds., 
                        <hi rend="italic">A Green Leaf: Papers in Honor of Professor J. P. Asmussen </hi>(Leiden: Peeters, 1988), 339–348; idem, “Christ As Warrior and Merchant: Aspects of Marcion’s Christology,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica </hi>21 (1989), 73–85.</p></note> Reading Lieu’s
                analysis of the Syriac material in concert with her treatment of the Greek and Latin
                sources can highlight the close and often surprising parallels among the
                polemicists. These parallels allow us to better understand the broad trajectory of
                early Christian polemical discourse to which the Syriac anti-Marcionites belong. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> The second and third sections of the book move from analysis of the mediating
                sources for Marcion’s life and teaching toward an attempted reconstruction of
                Marcion in his second-century context. In this effort, Lieu is appropriately careful
                and measured in her treatment of the sources. Her thorough knowledge of the contours
                of the anti-Marcionite polemical tradition and the intellectual currents of the
                second-century Greco-Roman world renders persuasive her effort to draw out the “real
                Marcion”. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Lieu’s reconstruction of Marcion places his rejection of the Creator (or demiurge)
                at the center of his thought. In this respect, more than any other, she argues,
                Marcion diverged from both the biblical tradition and the Platonism of his day,
                though he was steeped in both (p. 337). Lieu is confident that unlike “gnostic”
                Christians, Marcion did not have a detailed cosmogony of the sort attacked by Ephrem
                and Eznik of Kolb (p. 435–36). Lieu thus challenges the radical rethinking of
                Marcion championed by H.J.W. Drijvers. Drawing primarily upon Syriac and Armenian
                sources, Drijvers argued that Marcion held to a “mythic” account of the origins of
                the universe and matter (<hi rend="italic">hylē</hi>).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn5" n="5"
                        ><p xml:lang="en"> Drijvers, “Marcion’s Reading of Gal. 4,8,” 348.</p></note>
                Lieu finds no evidence for this portrait of Marcion in other sources, arguing that
                it reflects later Marcionite developments, rather than Marcion himself. That being
                said, Lieu rejects the simple dichotomies that have historically characterized
                scholarship on Marcion—that he was either “biblical” or “philosophical” in
                orientation; either a true “Paulinist,” or a “heretic” who operated far beyond the
                bounds of acceptable Christian belief. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Lieu’s portrait of Marcion should caution us against attri-buting the beliefs of
                “Marcionites”—as refracted through the arguments of their opponents (such as
                Ephrem)—to Marcion himself. We should be careful not to assume that the “Marcion” of
                Ephrem and Eznik was the Marcion of second-century Rome. It should also remind us
                that the Marcionite Christians represented a dynamic theological and exegetical
                tradition in Late Antique Syria and Mesopotamia, now almost entirely lost to
                history, which also claimed the name “Christian.” </p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> One minor weakness of this very strong work is the use of the old non-vocalized form
                of transliteration for Semitic languages (though this may have been the publisher’s
                decision). In addition, a deeper engagement with other Syriac or Armenian sources
                beyond Ephrem (like the anti-Marcionite <hi rend="italic">Pseudo-Ephrem A</hi>,
                which Lieu mentions but does not discuss), would have enriched her portrait. That
                being said, Lieu’s work is remarkably thorough in its treatment of the sources and
                the scholarship, and will be a standard resource for the study of Marcion for years
                to come. For Syriac scholars, it represents another fine step toward the full
                integration of Syriac evidence into the mainstream of early Christian studies. </p></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
