<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">J.F. Coakley, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Holy
                    Mar Pappos and Twenty-four Thousand who Were Martyred with Him</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Jeff W.</forename>
                        <surname>Childers</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Abilene Christian University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2019</date>
                <idno>Volume 22.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv22n1prchilders</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Jeff W. Childers</author>
                        <title level="a">J.F. Coakley, ed., The Story of the Holy
                            Mar Pappos and Twenty-four Thousand who Were Martyred with Him</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/><!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol22/HV22N1PRChilders.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2018</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="22">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="307" to="308">307–308</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="8"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
                
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2018-03-08">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title">
                <ab type="review-title">J.F. Coakley, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Holy
                        Mar Pappos and Twenty-four Thousand who Were Martyred with Him</hi> (Ely:
                    Jericho Press, 2017). Pp. iii + 38; $46.</ab>
                <ab type="review-author">Jeff W. Childers, Abilene Christian University</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body">
                <p xml:lang="en">J.F. Coakley has produced a fine little volume that students of Syriac will find
                    useful, especially those who have an interest in hagiographical texts. The
                    Syriac text of <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Holy Mar Pappos</hi> derives
                    from the fifteenth-century Cambridge ms. Or. 1137. The inaccessibility of the
                    earlier Damascus Patriarchate 12/18 (that may in fact have been the exemplar for
                    the Cambridge text) accounts for Coakley’s sole reliance on the later source.
                    The volume consists of a brief introduction, unvocalized Estrangela Syriac text,
                    and a good English translation, divided into 40 short paragraphs.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The<hi rend="italic"> Story </hi>ostensibly narrates the
                    martyrdoms of the Roman general Pappos and his twenty-four thousand Christian
                    soldiers near Antioch in 309. The introduction explains the reasons for seeing
                    the tale as purely legendary. Apart from the fact that the Roman general Pappos,
                    his military campaign in Nisibis, and an event involving twenty-four thousand
                    soldiers are otherwise unknown in Roman sources, large parts of the text have
                    been adapted, with fairly light revision, from the tales of the celebrated
                    Edessene martyrs Shmona, Guria, and Habbib.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The town around which the critical action occurs, Kapra d’Magdla near Antioch,
                    is also otherwise unknown. However, the story shows great interest in locations
                    and in the date of the martyrdom (15 November, the same as the martyrdoms of
                    Shmona and Guria, albeit six years later; §30), suggesting that the
                    hagiographers were seeking to establish or reinforce a martyrs’ cult for their
                    own region, based on the existing Edessene tale. After Mar Pappos and his
                    soldiers are beheaded on a great slaughtering stone (§26), their corpses are
                    dragged and thrown into a pit one mile north of town. The blood-drenched stone,
                    however, heaves itself upright and rolls along the bloody path under its own
                    power, in pursuit of the crowned heroes, until it reaches the edge of the pit
                    into which their bodies were hurled and stands guard over them (§§31, 35). After
                    the triumph of Constantine, the site of the stone overlooking the pit comes to
                    be consecrated by the bishop of Antioch, who builds a shrine that serves as a
                    pilgrimage destination and place of miracles. The concern with dates, locations,
                    the inauguration of a shrine by recognized ecclesial authority, and the witness
                    of miracles all function to illustrate typical hagiographical motifs.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The Syriac text is straightforward and easy to read, with rather limited
                    vocabulary. Intermediate Syriac students will have no trouble working through
                    the text at an encouraging pace, aided by Coakley’s occasional notes and
                    emendations, as well as by his plain English translation. The text allows for
                    good practice in intermediate grammar and intermediate syntax. It also offers
                    opportunities to engage questions about hagiography, including literary
                    development and interdepen-dence, the function of hagiography in local settings,
                    and its continuing significance beyond its original context.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> The Jericho Press, Coakley’s private academic press, has printed an attractive
                    book, using the Estrangela type that originally belonged to the Cambridge
                    University Press. The layout is clean and very legible, with numbered Syriac and
                    English paragraphs occupying the upper and lower portions of the pages,
                    respectively, in a fashion that aids quick comparison of the two. Rubrication
                    adorns the title page and opening page of text. In addition to an <hi
                        rend="italic">errata</hi> slip included with the volume that corrects three
                    typographical errors in the Syriac, and a misprint already corrected on page 19,
                    we notice irregularities in the text justification on pages 36, 38, and an error
                    on page 8, note 3, line 1: for “nam eof” read “name of.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
