<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">An Armenian Invocational Prayer of a Lost Memra of Jacob of
					Serugh on Good Friday and the Destruction of Sheol</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>Andy</forename>
						<surname>Hilkens</surname>
					</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2hilkens</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Andy Hilkens</author>
						<title level="a">An Armenian Invocational Prayer of a Lost Memra of Jacob of
							Serugh on Good Friday and the Destruction of Sheol</title>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2Hilkens.pdf</idno>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23>">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="263" to="277">263-277</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="2"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:lang="en">
					<term>Memro</term>
					<term>Armenian</term>
					<term>Invocational prayer</term>
					<term>Jacob of Serugh</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
			<change when="2020-09-05">File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="article">
		<front>
			<div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
				<head>ABSTRACT <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p xml:lang="en"> This article
							grew out of research that began during the first two years of a
							three-year postdoctoral fellowship at the Department of History at Ghent
							University (2016-2018), funded by the Research Foundation of Flanders
							(Fonds Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek Vlaanderen, FWO), and continued at the
							Center for the Study of Christianity at the Hebrew University of
							Jerusalem, where I took up a one-year postdoctoral research fellowship
							in 2018-2019. I am thankful to Edward G. Mathews Jr. for offering his
							advice and corrections to the edition and translation. Thanks are also
							in order for the reviewers for their generous feedback and suggestions
							for improvement, especially of the translation. As always, any remaining
							errors are entirely my own. </p></note>
				</head>
				<p> This article offers the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> and translation
					of the Armenian translation of an invocational prayer of a now lost memra of
					Jacob of Serugh on Good Friday and the destruction of Sheol. This text is
					different from the Armenian homily on Good Friday which was recently edited and
					translated by <pb n="264"/> Edward G. Mathews, Jr. On the basis of comparisons
					with extant homilies of Jacob, it is argued that the prayer is genuine. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2hilkens.1">
				<head>I. INTRODUCTION</head>
				<p> It was not only Syriac Orthodox Christians who recognized the eloquence of Jacob
					of Serugh (d. 29 November 520 or 521), one of the most prolific authors of
					homilies of Late Antiquity; other Christian communities did as well. In
					particular, Armenian Christians seem to have appreciated his works. As many as
					twenty-five of his homilies may have been translated into Armenian, as well as
					his Lives of Daniel of Aghlosh and Hannina. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2"
						n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> On the homilies, see A. Hilkens, “The manuscripts of
							the Armenian homilies of Jacob of Serugh: preliminary observations and
							checklist” <hi rend="italic">Manuscripta</hi> (forthcoming); id., “The
							Armenian reception of the homilies of Jacob of Serugh: new findings.” in
								<hi rend="italic">Caught in Translation: Studies on Versions of
								Late-Antique Christian Literature</hi>, Texts and Studies in Eastern
							Christianity 17, ed. M. Toca and D. Batovici. Leiden: Brill, 2019,
							64–84. For an earlier introduction, which was the inspiration for my
							research, see Edward G. Mathews, Jr., “Jacob of Serugh, Homily on Good
							Friday and other Armenian treasures: first glances,” in <hi
								rend="italic">Jacob of Serugh and his times</hi>, ed. G. Kiraz
							(Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2010), 133–161. The Armenian version of
							the Life of Hannina remains unedited but one manuscript witness of the
							Life of Daniel was published in L. Ter-Petrosyan, “Jacob of Serugh’s
							‘Life of Mar Daniel of Galash,’” <hi rend="italic">Ējmiadzin</hi> 36
							(1979): 22–40. </p></note> Research on the manuscript tradition is still
					in its infancy, but has already revealed an interesting characteristic: a small
					number of manuscripts only preserve the invocational prayers with which Jacob
					began his metrical homilies. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
							xml:lang="en"> A. Hilkens, “The manuscripts of the Armenian homilies”
							(forthcoming); id., “‘Beautiful little gems in their own right’:
							seventeenth-century Armenian collections of invocational prayers from
							Jacob of Serugh’s memre” (to be published in a Festschrift for Sebastian
							Brock, edited by M. Hjälm, B. Bitton-Ashkelony and R. Kitchen).
						</p></note> Occasionally, these manuscripts contain the only remnants of an
					Armenian translation of a homily of Jacob, which is still extant in Syriac,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en"> A. Hilkens, “The
							Armenian version of Jacob of Serugh’s Memra on the Five Talents,” <hi
								rend="italic">Le Muséon </hi>(forthcoming 2020). </p></note> as is
					the case for instance with <pb n="265"/> his memra on the Five Talents, but two
					invocational prayers of homilies of which the Syriac original appears to be lost
					have also survived, one on Jonah and the Ninevites <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"> Id., “An Armenian invocational prayer
							of a lost homily on Jonah and the Ninevites by Jacob of Serugh” (in
							preparation). </p></note> and another on Good Friday and the Destruction
					of Sheol. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p xml:lang="en"> This text is
							different from (1) the Armenian translation of Jacob’s now lost homily
							on the topic of Good Friday and (2) Jacob’s last homily on Mary and
							Golgotha, both recently edited and translated in E.G. Mathews, Jr., <hi
								rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Additional Homilies on Good
								Friday</hi> (Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2018), as well as (3-4)
							from the two homilies edited in P. Bedjan,<hi rend="italic"> Homiliae
								selectae Mar-Jacobi Sarugensis</hi> (Paris: Harrassowitz, 1910)
							[repr. P. Bedjan and S.P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">Homilies of Mar Jacob
								of Sarug / Homiliae Selectae Mar-Jacobi Sarugensis</hi> (Piscataway
							NJ: Gorgias Press, 2006)], vol. 2, 522–554 and 554–579, and (3) the <hi
								rend="italic">turgama</hi> on this topic edited and translated by F.
							Rilliet, <hi rend="italic">Jacques de Sarough, Six Homélies Festales en
								Prose</hi>, PO 43.4 (Paris: Firmin-Didot, 1986), 610–628.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> This brief article presents the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>,
					translation, and commentary on the latter text. Currently, only three manuscript
					witnesses are known. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p xml:lang="en">
							Some 6500 manuscripts in the Matenadaran await to be catalogued in
							detail so it is possible that more witnesses will turn up in the future.
						</p></note> The first is New Julfa (Isfahan), Church of the All-Saviour (=
					NOJ) 295, fols. 64v-65v, a homiliary (<foreign xml:lang="hy"
					>քարոզգիրք</foreign>, k‛arozgirk‛) that was copied in 1659 in the Shenher
					convent in Julfa (a city, currently in the Azerbaijani exclave of Nakhchivan).
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p xml:lang="en"> S. Ter-Avetissian,
								<hi rend="italic">Katalog der armenischen Handschriften in der
								Bibliothek des Klosters in Neu-Djoulfa. Band I</hi> (Vienna:
							Mekhitarist Press, 1970), 729 (cat. nr. 464). Unfortunately, this
							manuscript has remained inaccessible to me until the time of publication
							of this article, but the makeup of the collection and the title of the
							text as described in the catalogue makes it likely that this is the same
							text. </p></note> The second was copied six years later in Kayseri
					(Central Anatolia): Yerevan, Matenadaran - Mesrop Mashtots Institute of Ancient
					Manuscripts (= M) 2291, fols. 119rv, a miscellany (with a section of texts
					clearly drawn from a similar homiliary as the previous manuscript). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en"> G. Ter-Vardanyan, <hi
								rend="italic">General catalogue of Armenian manuscripts of the
								Mashtots Matenadaran. Volume VII</hi> (Yerevan: Nairi, 2012),
							813–820. </p></note> The third is Jerusalem, Armenian Patriarchate (= J)
					1499, a manuscript of uncertain <pb n="266"/> origin to which several different
					scribes contributed in the late sixteenth and seventeenth centuries. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p xml:lang="en"> N. Bogharyan, <hi
								rend="italic">General Catalogue of the Manuscripts in St. James’
								monastery. Volume 5 </hi>(Jerusalem: St. James’ Press, 1971),
							235–236. </p></note> This explains why it contains two different
					collections of invocational prayers from Jacob’s homilies and prologues of other
					homilies by and attributed to other authors (most notably Ephrem and the
					Armenian homilist Arak‛el of Baghesh/Bitlis <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
						n="11"><p xml:lang="en"> For a brief English introduction to Arak’el
							vardapet and a translation of his Lament on the Fall of Constantinople
							in 1453, see A.J. Hacikyan, <hi rend="italic">The Heritage of Armenian
								Literature. Volume II: From the Sixth to the Eighteenth Century</hi>
							(Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 2000), 668–681. For an
							introduction into his corpus of writings (in Armenian), see A. Ghazinyan
							and P.M. Khachatryan, <hi rend="italic">Arakʿel of Baghesh (15th
								century). Study, critical texts, notes</hi>, Medieval Armenian Hymns
							8 (Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1971), H.A. Anasyan, <hi
								rend="italic">Armenian Bibliography 5th-18th cc. Volume 1
							</hi>(Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1959), col. 1106–1143 and
							id., <hi rend="italic">Armenian Bibliography 5th-18th cc. Volume 2</hi>
							(Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1976), col. 89–151. </p></note>
					(1380-1454)), both of which include a version of the invocational prayer from
					this lost homily on Good Friday (p. 53 and pp. 142-143). <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> Bogharyan’s description of this
							manuscript is incomplete: he only mentions the existence of the first
							collection and the names of a few authors without identifying any of the
							texts. Of the second collection he only identifies three texts, on the
							Star (p. 131), on the Ninevites (p. 133) and on Antioch (p. 148) - which
							makes it seem as though these texts may be the complete homilies, but in
							fact these are only the invocational prayers, surrounded by many other
							prologues of homilies that Bogharyan has not mentioned. A complete
							description of the contents of these two (and the other) collections
							will be provided in Hilkens, “‘Beautiful little gems in their own
							right’” (forthcoming). Unfortunately I did not find out about the
							presence of the invocational prayer on Good Friday in this manuscript
							until after submitting this article to Hugoye for review. During the
							limited time that I was able to consult the extensive collection of
							Armenian manuscripts in Jerusalem, I only had time to catalogue and
							identify the texts in this manuscript but not to copy any of them (aside
							from the ones on the Five Talents) nor to compare the version of this
							prayer with the one in M 2291. Subsequently I did order images of the
							manuscript in question, but unfortunately, due to various factors
							including the Covid-19 crisis, these images did not reach me in time
							before the <pb n="267"/> publication of this article. That having been
							said, judging from my study of the Armenian translation of the
							invocational prayer of Jacob’s homily on the Five Talents, which is a
							similar case, also being present in M 2291 and twice in J 1499, I would
							suggest that the versions of the invocational prayer on Good Friday in J
							1499 will probably not vary a great deal, neither from one another nor
							from the version in M 2291. </p></note>
				</p>
				<pb n="267"/>
				<p> It is worth noting that this text is never explicitly attributed to Jacob of
					Serugh. In M 2291 and in the first collection in J 1499 the text remains
					anonymous, but in the second collection in J 1499 as well as in NOJ 295, it is
					attributed to “the same Jacob” <foreign xml:lang="hy">(Նորին Յակոբայ)</foreign>.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p xml:lang="en"> For the titles,
							see above and footnotes 16, 17, and 21 below. </p></note> This label
					refers back to Jacob of Serugh <foreign xml:lang="hy">(Յակոբայ Սրճոյ, յակոբայ
						սրճեցոյ)</foreign> who is identified as the author of earlier texts in both
					collections: a text “on the Mystery of Sunday” <foreign xml:lang="hy">(ի
						խորհուրդ կիւրակէի)</foreign> in the case of NOJ 295 (fols. 40v-41r) and one
					on the Raising of Lazarus and another text that was intended to be read on Holy
					Monday in the second collection in J 1499 (pp. 136-137 and 138-140
					respectively). I have not been able to see this text on the Mystery of Sunday in
					NOJ 295, but a text with the same title, which is always attributed to “Jacob of
					Serugh” and whose language suggests that it is indeed a translation of one of
					Jacob’s invocational prayers, is extant in other manuscripts: M 2291, fols.
					116v-117r, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p xml:lang="en"> Title:
								<foreign xml:lang="hy">Նորին սրբոյն Յակոբայ Սրճեցոյ ասացեալ ի
								խորհուրդ կիրակէի,</foreign> “Said by the same holy Jacob of Serugh
							about the Mystery of Sunday.” </p></note> M 2103, fols. 14rv, <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p xml:lang="en"> On this manuscript, see
							Ter-Vardanyan, <hi rend="italic">General catalogue</hi>, col. 17–20.
						</p></note> and J 1499, p. 19 <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
							xml:lang="en"> Title:<foreign xml:lang="hy"> նորին սրբոյն յակոբայ
								սրճեցոյ ասացեալ ի խորհուրդ կիւրակէի,</foreign> “Spoken by the same
							holy Jacob of Serugh on the Mystery of Sunday.” </p></note> and pp.
					144-145. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en"> Title:
								<foreign xml:lang="hy">նորին սրբոյն յակոբայ ասացեալ ի խորհուրդ
								կիւրակէի,</foreign> Spoken by the same holy Jacob on the Mystery of
							Sunday.” Neither of these texts in this manuscript is mentioned in the
							catalogue. I am preparing an edition of this text based on the
							accessible witnesses (M 2103, M 2291 and J 1499). </p></note> In
					contrast to this text <pb n="268"/> and what is likely to be the invocational
					prayer of Jacob’s metrical homily on the Raising of Lazarus in J 1499, the text
					for Great Monday is actually not a translation of one of Jacob’s writings, but
					the prologue of a homily of the fifteenth-century Armenian author Arak‛el of
					Baghesh. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p xml:lang="en"> On this
							text, see Anasyan, <hi rend="italic">Armenian Bibliography 5th-18th cc.
								Volume 1</hi>, col. 1141-1142 (nr. 10) who mentions the following
							witnesses in addition to M 2291: M 2121, f. 378v-9r, M 745, f.
							112v-113r, M 597, f. 53v-54r and M 3457, f. 211v-212r. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The attribution to Jacob of the prayer on Good Friday and the Destruction of
					Sheol appears to be correct. The Armenian text seems to be a translation of a
					now lost Syriac original, genuinely written by Jacob. The language is very
					similar to Jacob’s and some of the imagery that is used in this invocational
					prayer is also attested in other homilies by Jacob. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> Links with characteristics of other
							writings by Jacob are explained in the footnotes. </p></note>
					Furthermore, the way in which the invocational prayer is built up is also
					typical for his work. The four constituent components of preaching that Jacob
					tends to include in his introductory prayers are all represented: the Lord, the
					speaker, the memra, and the hearers. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
							xml:lang="en"> S. Ashbrook Harvey, “Th Poet’s Prayer: Invocational
							Prayers in the Mêmrê of Jacob of Sarug,” in <hi rend="italic">Papers
								presented at the Seventeenth International Conference on Patristic
								Studies held in Oxford 2015</hi>, StPatr 78, ed. M. Vinzent, J.
							Wickes and K.S. Heal (Turnhout: Brepols, 2017), 51–60, at 53.
						</p></note> The first two verses connect the Lord and the speaker (i.e.
					Jacob): Jacob beseeches “Christ, the one who gives light to the universe” to
					also illuminate Jacob’s “obscured mind to preach about” him. The reference to
					preaching already links these two components to the memra itself. In the last
					two verses of the prayer, the homily is described as “the words of the
					bridegroom” and “my homily”, which allow Jacob to not only link the memra to the
					Lord (“the bridegroom”), but also both to the other two components: the speaker
					(“my homily”) and his audience (“sons of the bride of the church” and “daughters
					of Sion”). </p>
				<pb n="269"/>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="hy" xml:id="hv23n2hilkens.2">
				<head xml:lang="en">II. EDITION AND TRANSLATION</head>
				<p xml:lang="hy">
					<l rend="underline">Ի Մեծի ուրբաթին եւ ի կործանումն դժոխոց</l>
					<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> As mentioned above,
							the title in NOJ 295 and the second collection in J 1499 is preceded by
							the words <foreign xml:lang="hy">Նորին Յակոբայ ասացեալ</foreign>,
							“Spoken/dictated by the same Jacob”, but because my edition is based on
							M 2291, I have not added those words to the text. </p></note>
					<l>Լուսատու տիեզերաց ք[րիստո]ս </l>
					<l>լուսաւորեա զմթացեալ միտս իմ քարոզել զքէն. </l>
					<l>շնորհ[եա]յ ինձ յողորմութէ քումմէ. </l>
					<l>զի ողորմութեամբ քո ճանաչեցից զմարդասիրութիւն քո. </l>
					<l>տուր ինձ շնորհս քարոզել զքէն. </l>
					<l>զի ամ[ենայ]քն ոյք լսիցեն զղջանալով դարձցին ի չար գ[ո]րծ[ո]ց իւր[եան]ց. </l>
					<l>սիրով բարերարութ[են]է քո մերձեցիր առ իս. </l>
					<l rend="indent">ք[ա]ր[ո]զել մարդկան զփառս քո.</l>
					<l>զի որք լսիցեն խնդրեսցեն ի քէն ներել յանցանաց.</l>
					<l>զպահպանիչ հոգիդ ս[ուր]բ առաքեա առ իս.</l>
					<l>զի ես նովաւ զօրանամ խօսել վ[ա]ս[ն] անյաղթ զօրութ[են]է քում</l>
					<l>որպէս կործանեցեր ի ձայնէ եղջերփողոյն զպարիսպն երիքովի.</l>
					<l>և այժմ շնորհեայ ձայնի քարոզութե[ան]ս իմոյ կործանել զամրութի[ւն] թշնամոյն. </l>
					<l>որ սրսկմամբ արեան քո զկահս խորանին սրբեցեր.</l>
					<l>և այժմ ցօղեա առ իս զողորմութի[ւն] քո. </l>
					<pb n="270"/>
					<l>մատամբ քո լուսաւորութի[ւն] շնորհեցեր մեծին մովսէսի. </l>
					<l>ք[ա]ր[ո]զել զա[ստուա]ծութի[ւն] քո.</l>
					<l>և այժմ լուսաւորեա զիս ծագմամբ լուսավ քո.</l>
					<l>զի ես լուսովն քո լուսաւորեցից զորդիս եկեղեցոյ քում.</l>
					<l>որդիք հարսին եկեղեցւոյ. ընկալարուք զբանս փեսային.</l>
					<l>և դստերք սիոնի լուարուք զքարոզս:</l>
				</p>
				<lb/>
				<lg xml:lang="en">
					<l real="underline">On Great Friday and the Destruction of Sheol <note
							place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en"> The link between
								the crucifixion and the destruction of Sheol also appears in Jacob’s
								last and unfinished homily, on Mary and Golgotha: “when the one
								slain cries out in a [loud] voice and the walls of Sheol have
								fallen” (Mathews, <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Additional
									Homilies</hi>, 78, ll. 33–34). See also T. Kollamparampil, <hi
									rend="italic">Salvation in Christ according to Jacob of Serugh:
									An exegetico-theological study on the homilies of Jacob of
									Serugh on the Feasts of Our Lord</hi>, Gorgias Dissertations in
								Early Christian Studies 49 (Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2010),
								210–211. </p></note>
					</l>
					<l>O Christ, the one who gives light to the universe,</l>
					<l>illuminate my obscured mind to preach about you. <note place="foot"
							xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> See also in the Armenian homily
								on Good Friday: “the mind that has seen You is illumined by You to
								speak of what it has received from You” (Mathews, <hi rend="italic"
									>Jacob of Sarug’s Additional Homilies</hi>, 33, ll. 12–13) and
								“O day-star, great sun, spread forth Your rays into my dark heart,
								that I may be illumined to speak of You in a worthy manner”
								(Mathews, <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Additional
									Homilies</hi>, 33, ll. 18–20). For Jacob’s use of the imagery of
								light and darkness, see Kollamparampil, <hi rend="italic">Salvation
									in Christ</hi>, 345–347. </p></note>
					</l>
					<l>Grant me from your mercy, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
								xml:lang="en"> In this text, the term<foreign xml:lang="hy">
									ողորմութիւն </foreign>is consistently used to render the idea of
								mercy. In the case of the Armenian version of Jacob’s homily on the
								Five Talents, or at least the Armenian equivalent of its
								invocational prayer, <foreign xml:lang="hy">ողորմութիւն
								</foreign>appears as the counterpart to two Syriac words that can be
								rendered as “mercy”,<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܚܢܢܐ
									</foreign>and<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܪ̈ܚܡܐ,</foreign> see
								Hilkens, “The Armenian version” (forthcoming). On<foreign
									xml:lang="syr"> ܚܢܢܐ, </foreign>divine mercy, in Jacob’s oeuvre,
								see Kollamparampil, <hi rend="italic">Salvation in Christ</hi>,
								206–207. </p></note>
					</l>
					<pb n="271"/>
					<l>so that through your mercy I may comprehend your love of humanity.</l>
					<l>Grant me grace to preach about you,</l>
					<l>so that all who listen may turn away in penance from their evil deeds.</l>
					<l>Touch me through love from your beneficence to proclaim <note place="foot"
							xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en"> The verb that is used here
									is<foreign xml:lang="hy"> քարոզել</foreign>, k’arozel, from the
									Syriac<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܟܪܙ.</foreign> The same word is
								used in line 5, where I have translated it as “to preach”.
							</p></note> your glory to humanity,</l>
					<l>so that those who listen may entreat you to forgive trespasses.</l>
					<l>Send to me the protector, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
								xml:lang="en"> The word <foreign xml:lang="hy">պահպանիչ
								</foreign>also means “blessing”, but the translation “guardian,
								protector” makes more sense in this context. I am thankful to the
								anonymous reviewer for this and several other suggestions for
								improvement of the translation. </p></note> your Holy Spirit,</l>
					<l>so that through It I may be strengthened <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
							n="27"><p xml:lang="en"> Because I have only inspected the text in M
								2291, I am hesitant to correct the indicative present <foreign
									xml:lang="hy">զօրանամ </foreign>(zōranam), but I would suggest
								that the translation may have originally contained the
									subjunctive<foreign xml:lang="hy"> զօրասցի </foreign>(zōrasc’i),
								hence my translation “so that through It I may be strengthened”
								rather than “for through It I am strengthened”. Having said that,
								this error may also be present in the other witnesses. In the case
								of the Armenian version of the invocational prayer of Jacob’s homily
								on the Five Talents, for instance, all four witnesses that I have
								seen contain the same error in the equivalent of verse 18: <foreign
									xml:lang="hy">առաքինութիւն </foreign>(aṙak’inut’iwn) instead
									of<foreign xml:lang="hy"> առաքելութիւն</foreign>
								(aṙak’elut’iwn), the latter of which is the equivalent of<foreign
									xml:lang="syr"> ܫܠܝܚܘܬܐ,</foreign> “mission”, which is in the
								Syriac text, see Hilkens, “The Armenian version” (forthcoming).
							</p></note> to speak about your invincible force.</l>
					<l>As you destroyed the walls of Jericho by the sound of the horn, <note
							place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p xml:lang="en"> Josh 6:1–27. Jacob
								also evokes the fall of Jericho in his homily on the veil of Moses,
								where he compares it to Christ’s overthrowing of Sheol, see
								Kollamparampil, <hi rend="italic">Salvation in Christ</hi>, 196 n
								138 and 332. </p></note>
					</l>
					<l>so also now give grace to the sound of my preaching to destroy the stronghold
						of the enemy. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en"> For
								Jacob’s use of military language, see e.g. A. McCollum, <hi
									rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homilies on Jesus’
									Temptation</hi>, Texts from Christian Late Antiquity 38, The
								Metrical Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug 33 (Piscataway NJ: Gorgias
									<pb n="272"/> Press, 2014) and A. Hilkens, “Rhetoric in Jacob of
								Serugh’s Mimro on St. George the Martyr,” in <hi rend="italic"
									>Rhetoric and historiography</hi>, ed. L. Van Hoof and M.
								Conterno, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (forthcoming). In
								the homily on St. George, for instance, Jacob urges his hearers to
								build strongholds <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܚܣ̈ܢܐ)</foreign>:
								“Blessed are you who make fortified strongholds that cannot be
								captured, in which those who flee from Satan take refuge” (Bedjan
								and Brock, <hi rend="italic">Homilies / Homiliae</hi>, vol. 5, 770,
								l. 4). </p></note>
					</l>
					<l>(You) who by the sprinkling <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
								xml:lang="en"> Here, the idea of sprinkling is rendered in Armenian
								with the noun<foreign xml:lang="hy"> սրսկումն </foreign>(srskumn,
								‛sprinkling’). In the next verse an entirely different root is used,
								which suggests perhaps that Jacob himself also used two different
								Syriac roots. </p></note> of your blood sanctified the furnishings
						of the tabernacle, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en"
								> Presumably this is the “tabernacle of mysteries”, the “house for
								the holy things”, the “house for the mysteries” that was built by
								Melchizedek, like the altar that was built by Abraham and Isaac on
								Golgotha, the site of the crucifixion, at least according to Jacob.
								Here it is not a metaphor for Christ himself, but for the Church,
								which was sanctified by the blood that flowed out of Christ’s side,
								see A.B. Elkhoury, <hi rend="italic">Types and Symbols of the Church
									in the Writings of Jacob of Serugh</hi>, PhD Dissertation,
								Katholische Universität Eichstätt-Ingolstadt 2017, 56 and 69–71.
								There may also be links with the unstudied homily on the Mystery of
								the Tabernacle of which the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi>
								appeared recently, R. Akhrass and I. Syryany, <hi rend="italic">160
									Unpublished Homilies of Jacob of Serugh</hi>, 2 vols. (Damascus:
								Department of Syriac Studies, Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate, 2017),
								vol. 2, 174–191. A study of this homily could also be useful on
								another level, as it was also translated into Armenian. The
								diplomatic edition of the Armenian text, based on an unknown
								manuscript, was published in <hi rend="italic">Spiritual writings
									and homilies </hi>(Constantinople, 1722), 388–410. Only three
								Armenian manuscripts are known, two manuscripts in the Armenian
								Patriarchate in Jerusalem (154c, pp. 1552–1561, copied in 1737, and
								1365, fols. 52v-83v of unknown date) as well as a late copy in the
								Matenadaran, M 2786, fols. 129v-135r (19th c.). </p></note>
					</l>
					<l>so also now sprinkle your mercy on me. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
							n="32"><p xml:lang="en"> Jacob also uses the image of the sprinkling of
								mercy in his homily on the Ascension: “He walked on the earth and
								sprinkled mercy and filled it with hope” (Kollamparampil, Salvation
								in Christ, 207). For the edition and translation of this homily, see
								P. Bedjan, S. Martyrii, qui et Sahdona, quae supersunt omnia,
								Paris-Leipzig: Harrassowitz, 1902, 808–832 (at 812, l. 17; repr. in
								P. Bedjan, <hi rend="italic">Cantus seu Homiliae Mar Jacobi in Jesum
									et Mariam</hi>, Paris-Leipzig: Harrassowitz, 1902, 169–220 and
								Bedjan and Brock,<hi rend="italic"> Homiliae / Homilies</hi>, vol.
								6, 196–220). A vocalized version of this <pb n="273"/> edition,
								furnished with an English translation, can be found in T.
								Kollamparampil, <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homily on the
									Ascension of Our Lord</hi>, Texts from Late Antiquity 24, The
								Metrical Homilies of Jacob of Sarug 21 (Piscataway NJ: Gorgias
								Press, 2010). In the Armenian translation of the homily on the
								Ascension the verb <foreign xml:lang="hy">ցօղեմ,</foreign> derived
								from the noun<foreign xml:lang="hy"> ցօղ</foreign>, “dew,” is used
								to render the verb <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܰܣ, </foreign>“to
								sprinkle,” see<foreign xml:lang="hy" rend="italic"> Գիրք եւ ճառ
									հոգեշահ </foreign><hi rend="italic">[Spiritual writings and
									homilies]</hi>, 345–369 (at 350) as well as the draft edition of
								Paris, Bibliothèque nationale de France, ms. arm. 116, fols.
								319r-322v (AD 1307), prepared by Alin Suciu and available on his
								Academia.edu page:<foreign xml:lang="hy"> շրջեցաւ յերկրի
								</foreign>(P 116: <foreign xml:lang="hy">յաշխարհի), և ցօղեաց ի նա
									զգութ իւր, և ելից զնա յուսով, </foreign>“He went around the
								earth, he sprinkled his mercy on it, and he filled it with hope.”
								That the translator of the invocational prayer from the homily on
								Good Friday and the Destruction of Sheol used <foreign xml:lang="hy"
									>ցօղեա</foreign>, the imperative form of this verb, in this
								verse suggests that the verb<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܪܰܣ
								</foreign>may have appeared in the Syriac Vorlage. However, note
								also how in the Armenian version of the homily on the
									Ascension,<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܚܢܢܐ </foreign>(“mercy”) is
								rendered as<foreign xml:lang="hy"> գութ </foreign>rather than
									<foreign xml:lang="hy">ողորմութիւն,</foreign> which could
								suggest the involvement of a different translator. </p></note>
					</l>
					<pb n="273"/>
					<l>By your finger <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p xml:lang="en">
								Perhaps alluding to Lev 4:5–6, which describes how during the
								sacrifice at the tabernacle, the priest dips his finger in the blood
								and sprinkles the blood seven times before the veil. </p></note> you
						granted illumination to the great Moses to proclaim your divinity,</l>
					<l>so also now illuminate me by the dawning <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
							n="34"><p xml:lang="en"> Presumably<foreign xml:lang="hy"> ծագմամբ
								</foreign>is the equivalent of<foreign xml:lang="syr">
									ܒܕܢܚܐ.</foreign> In the Armenian version of Jacob’s Memra on the
								Star that appeared to the Magi and on the Slaughter of
									Infants<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܒܕܢܚܐ,</foreign> the very first
								word, was rendered as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ծագումն.</foreign> For
								the Syriac text of this homily, see Bedjan, Homiliae selectae,
								vol.1, 84–153 (first word of line 1), translated into English by N.
								Macabasag, “Jacob of Serugh’s Memra on the Star that appeared to the
								Magi and on the Slaughter of Infants (vat. syr. 118)”, <hi
									rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017): 237–302. The
								Armenian text is unedited. So far, I have only identified six
								manuscripts of the Armenian translation, the oldest manuscript being
								ms. 1, fols. 20v-37v, in the collection of the Mekhitarist fathers
								in Vienna. In this manuscript, the text is incorrectly ascribed to
								Jacob of Nisibis. This misattribution also occurs in the most recent
								witness, ms. 1286, fols. 5r-10v (dated 1820), in the collection of
								the Mekhitarist fathers in Venice. </p></note> of your light, <note
							place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en"> For the idea of the
								dawning of the sun on the mind, see e.g. Jacob’s second homily on
								Elissaeus and on the King of Moab (Bedjan, <hi rend="italic"
									>Homiliae selectae</hi>, vol. 4, 282, l. 6–7; Kollamparampil,
									<hi rend="italic">Salvation in Christ</hi>, 387). </p></note>
					</l>
					<pb n="274"/>
					<l>so that by your light I may illuminate <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36"
							n="36"><p xml:lang="en"> On illumination, see above. </p></note> the
						sons <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p xml:lang="en"> The <hi
									rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> of <foreign xml:lang="hy"
									>որդիք,</foreign> “sons”, is most likely <foreign xml:lang="syr"
									>ܒܢ̈ܝ,</foreign> which literally means “sons”, but can be
								translated more generally as “children (of your church).”
							</p></note> of your church.</l>
					<l>Sons <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p xml:lang="en"> Here the
								translation as “sons” is fairly certain, given that it acts as a
								counterpart to the “daughters of Sion”. </p></note> of the bride of
						the church, receive the words of the bridegroom <note place="foot"
							xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p xml:lang="en"> On Jacob’s use of this popular
								and much older theme of the Church as the bride of Christ who is the
								bridegroom (Mk 2:19–20; Jn 3:29; Eph 5:25–27; 2 Cor 11:2), see e.g.
								Elkhoury, <hi rend="italic">Types and Symbols</hi>, 221. The theme
								is also used in the Armenian homily on Good Friday, Mathews, <hi
									rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Additional Homilies</hi>, 82.
							</p></note>
					</l>
					<l>and daughters of Zion, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
								xml:lang="en"> Cf. Zech 9:9; Jn 12:15; Mt 21:5. Jacob uses this term
								in the singular to refer to Israel, see Kollamparampil <hi
									rend="italic">Salvation</hi>, 156–157, 254, 256 and Elkhoury,
									<hi rend="italic">Types and Symbols</hi>, 292, 294. </p></note>
						listen to my homily <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
								xml:lang="en"> The Armenian word <foreign xml:lang="hy">քարոզ
								</foreign>k‛aroz is used for a homily here. In the translation of
								the invocational prayer of the homily on the Five Talents, memra is
								consistently translated as<foreign xml:lang="hy"> ճառ</foreign>, a
								word commonly used to refer to homilies, but which has the basic
								meaning of “discourse”. This may suggest that the word <foreign
									xml:lang="hy">քարոզ</foreign> k‛aroz here, was used by the
								compiler of the invocational prayers, who appears to have made
								alterations to the last verses of several other invocational prayers
								as well, see Hilkens, “The Armenian version” (forthcoming).
							</p></note> .</l>
				</lg>
			</div>
			<div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
				<listBibl>
					<head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
					<bibl>Akhrass R. and I. Syryany. <hi rend="italic">160 Unpublished Homilies of
							Jacob of Serugh</hi>, 2 vols. Damascus: Department of Syriac Studies,
						Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate, 2017.</bibl>
				
				<bibl>Anasyan, H.A. <hi rend="italic">Armenian Bibliography 5th-18th cc. Volume
						1</hi>. Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1959.</bibl>
				<bibl>Anasyan, H.A. <hi rend="italic">Armenian Bibliography 5th-18th cc. Volume
						2</hi>. Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1976.</bibl>
				<pb n="275"/>
				<bibl>Ashbrook Harvey, S. “The Poet’s Prayer: Invocational Prayers in the Mêmrê of
					Jacob of Sarug.” In <hi rend="italic">Papers presented at the Seventeenth
						International Conference on Patristic Studies held in Oxford 2015</hi>,
					StPatr 78, ed. M. Vinzent, J. Wickes and K.S. Heal. Turnhout: Brepols,
					2017.</bibl>
				<bibl>Bedjan, P. <hi rend="italic">Cantus seu Homiliae Mar Jacobi in Jesum et
						Mariam</hi>, Paris-Leipzig: Harrassowitz, 1902.</bibl>
				<bibl>Bedjan, P. <hi rend="italic">Homiliae selectae Mar-Jacobi Sarugensis</hi>. 5
					vols. Paris: Harrassowitz, 1910 [repr. Bedjan P. and Brock, S.P. <hi
						rend="italic">Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug / Homiliae Selectae Mar-Jacobi
						Sarugensis</hi>, 6 vols. Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2006.</bibl>
				<bibl>Bogharyan, N., <hi rend="italic">General Catalogue of the Manuscripts in St.
						James’ monastery. Volume 5</hi>. Jerusalem: St. James’ Press, 1971. </bibl>
				<bibl>Elkhoury, A.B. <hi rend="italic">Types and Symbols of the Church in the
						Writings of Jacob of Serugh</hi>. PhD Dissertation, Katholische Universität
					Eichstätt-Ingolstadt, 2017.</bibl>
				<bibl>Ghazinyan, A. and P.M. Khachatryan, <hi rend="italic">Arak’el of Baghesh (15th
						century). Study, critical texts, notes</hi>, Medieval Armenian Hymns 8,
					Yerevan: Armenian Academy of Sciences, 1971.</bibl>
				<bibl>Hacikyan, A.J. <hi rend="italic">The Heritage of Armenian Literature. Volume
						II: From the Sixth to the Eighteenth Century</hi>. Detroit: Wayne State
					University Press, 2000.</bibl>
				<bibl>Hilkens, A. “The Armenian reception of the homilies of Jacob of Serugh: new
					findings.” In <hi rend="italic">Caught in Translation: Studies on Versions of
						Late-Antique Christian Literature</hi>, Texts and Studies in Eastern
					Christianity 17, ed. M. Toca and D. Batovici. Leiden: Brill, 2019.</bibl>
				<bibl>Hilkens, A. “Rhetoric in Jacob of Serugh’s Mimro on St. George the Martyr.” In
						<hi rend="italic">Rhetoric and historiography</hi>, ed. L. Van Hoof and M.
					Conterno. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (forthcoming).</bibl>
				<pb n="276"/>
				<bibl>Hilkens, A. “The manuscripts of the Armenian homilies of Jacob of Serugh:
					preliminary observations and checklist” <hi rend="italic">Manuscripta</hi>
					(forthcoming 2020).</bibl>
				<bibl>Hilkens, A. “‘Beautiful little gems in their own right’: seventeenth-century
					Armenian collections of invocational prayers from Jacob of Serugh’s memre”
					(forthcoming in a Festschrift for Sebastian Brock, edited by M. Hjälm, B.
					Bitton-Ashkelony and R. Kitchen).</bibl>
				<bibl>Hilkens, A. “The Armenian version of Jacob of Serugh’s Memra on the Five
					Talents,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> (forthcoming 2020).</bibl>
				<bibl>Kollamparampil, T. <hi rend="italic">Salvation in Christ according to Jacob of
						Serugh: An exegetico-theological study on the homilies of Jacob of Serugh on
						the Feasts of Our Lord</hi>, Gorgias Dissertations in Early Christian
					Studies 49. Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2010.</bibl>
				<bibl>Kollamparampil, T. <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homily on the Ascension
						of Our Lord</hi>, Texts from Late Antiquity 24. The Metrical homilies of
					Jacob of Sarug 21. Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2010.</bibl>
				<bibl>Macabasag, N. “Jacob of Serugh’s Memra on the Star that appeared to the Magi
					and on the Slaughter of Infants (vat. syr. 118).” <hi rend="italic">Parole de
						l’Orient</hi> 43 (2017): 237–302.</bibl>
				<bibl>Mathews, Jr., E.G. “Jacob of Serugh, Homily on Good Friday and other Armenian
					treasures: first glances.” In <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Serugh and his
						times</hi>, ed. G. Kiraz, Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2010.</bibl>
				<bibl>Mathews, Jr., E.G. <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Additional Homilies on
						Good Friday</hi>. Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press: 2018.</bibl>
				<bibl>McCollum, A. <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homilies on Jesus’
						Temptation</hi>, Texts from Christian Late Antiquity 38. The Metrical
					Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug 33. Piscataway NJ: Gorgias Press, 2014.</bibl>
				<pb n="277"/>
				<bibl>Rilliet, F. <hi rend="italic">Jacques de Sarough, Six Homélies Festales en
						Prose</hi>, PO 43.4. Paris: Firmin-Didot, 1986.</bibl>
				<bibl>Ter-Avetissian, S. <hi rend="italic">Katalog der armenischen Handschriften in
						der Bibliothek des Klosters in Neu-Djoulfa. Band I</hi>. Vienna: Mekhitarist
					Press, 1970.</bibl>
				<bibl>Ter-Petrosyan, L. “Jacob of Serugh’s ‘Life of Mar Daniel of Galash’”, <hi
						rend="italic">Ējmiadzin</hi> 36 (1979): 22–40.</bibl>
				<bibl>Ter-Vardanyan, G.<hi rend="italic"> General catalogue of Armenian manuscripts
						of the Mashtots Matenadaran. Volume VII</hi>. Yerevan: Nairi, 2012.</bibl>
				<bibl><hi rend="italic">Spiritual writings and homilies</hi>. Constantinople,
					1722.</bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
