<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Mary in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> and the Early Syriac
					Fathers</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>Roger-Youssef</forename>
						<surname>Akhrass</surname>
					</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2akhrass</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Roger-Youssef Akhrass</author>
						<title level="a">Mary in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> and the Early
							Syriac Fathers</title>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2Akhrass.pdf</idno>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23>">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="323" to="354">279-321</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="4"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:lang="en">
					<term>Mary</term>
					<term>Šḥimo</term>
					<term>Ephrem</term>
					<term>Jacob of Serugh</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
			<change when="2020-09-04">File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="article">
		<front>
			<div type="abstract">
				<head>Abstract</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In this article, I examine the Old Testament roots and the
					patristic background of the Marian typology as it figures in the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, the service book for regular weekday prayers in
					the West Syriac tradition. The focus is placed on two early Syriac Fathers:
					Ephrem (+373) and Jacob of Serugh (+521). The comparison reveals, first, that
					the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> shares in common with Ephrem several Marian
					symbols: Eve, the Burning bush, the Ark of Covenant, the Staff of Aaron, the
					Fleece, the King’s daughter, the Thirsty earth, the Veil enclosing water, and
					the Chariot of Ezekiel.; Secondly, that Jacob of Serugh introduced new types
					which were echoed in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>: the Tent of Abraham, the
					Tree bearing the lamb, the Veil of Moses, the new Well, the Sling of David, the
					new Pitcher of Elisha, the swift Cloud, the closed Door etc.; and, Thirdly, that
					the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> has original Marian symbols unfound in Ephrem
					and Jacob of Serugh, like the Ladder of Jacob, the Tablets of the Law, the Jar
					of Manna, the Rock in the desert, the Candelabrum, the Locked garden, and sealed
					fountain. I also show, finally, how the condensed thought of Ephrem, was
					expanded and simplified with both Jacob of Serug and the <hi rend="italic"
						>Šḥimo</hi>, within the context of Marian typology. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.intro">
				<pb n="324"/>
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In the West Syriac tradition, the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>
					<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p xml:lang="en"> We are using in the
							current article the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> edition of the <hi
								rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܫܚܺܝܡܳܐ܆ ܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܳܐ ܕܫܰܒܬܳܐ ܫܚܺܝܡܬܳܐ ܠܦܽܘܬ
								ܛܶܟܣܳܐ ܕܥܺܕܬܳܐ ܣܽܘܪܝܳܝܬܐ ܕܰܐܢܛܝܽܘܟ ܬܪܺܝܨܰܬ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ</foreign>), ed.
							Aphram Barsoum, Jounieh, 1981<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>. The English
							translation is borrowed, when available, from Bede Griffiths, <hi
								rend="italic">The Book of Common Prayer of the Syrian Church, Awsār
								Slāwōt’ō</hi> 1. Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research
							Institute, 2017. </p></note> is the service book for regular weekday
					prayers which was compiled most likely at the end of the seventh century by
					Jacob of Edessa. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> The
							manuscript tradition (British Library Add 14704; Paris syr. 150) attests
							that the services of the canonical hours of the ferial days were
							arranged by Jacob of Edessa (cf. William Wright, <hi rend="italic">A
								Short History of Syriac Literature</hi>. London: A. and C. Black,
							1894, p. 145-146; Ignatius Aphram I Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">The
								Scattered Pearls. A History of Syriac Literature and Sciences</hi>,
							tr. Matti Moosa, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2003<hi rend="superscript"
								>2</hi>, p. 59-60). The latest theological study on the <hi
								rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> by Menzer Habil accepts this assumption
							(‘‘La théologie du salut selon le cycle hebdomadaire syro-antiochien.
							Étude historique et théologique’’, Villeneuve d’Ascq : Atelier national
							de reproduction des thèses, 2013, p. 27-34). </p></note> In this book,
					the Mother of God is commemorated in numerous verse hymns and metrical texts,
					mostly anonymous, apart from a few verses explicitly ascribed to Ephrem, Jacob
					of Serugh, Balaï, and Simon the Potter. But when considering exclusively the
					works recognized by the scholars as authentically written by Ephrem the Syrian,
					one may be surprised to notice that the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> in use
					today in the Syriac Orthodox Church contains only one stanza dedicated for Mary
					that derives from the authentic Ephrem (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܳܢܰܘ
						ܝܰܪܚܳܐ</foreign>ܐ <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 5, <pb n="325"/> 1). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p xml:lang="en"> Here are the other Marian
							hymns of the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> attributed to Ephrem in
							Assemani and Lamy, and which are actually parts of anonymous <hi
								rend="italic">madroshe</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܺܝܟ ܗ̱ܽܘ
								ܚܰܝܠܳܐ</foreign> (<hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 15, <foreign
								xml:lang="syr">ܡܰܕܪܳܫܳܐ ܕܗܳܢܰܘ ܝܰܪܚܳܐ</foreign>, Lamy II, col.
								519),<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܐܰܒܳܐ ܟܬܰܒ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ </foreign>(<hi
								rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 72, Lamy III, col. 969);<foreign
								xml:lang="syr"> ܐ̱ܪ̈ܳܙܰܝܟܝ ܒܰܪ̱ܬ ܕܰܘܺܝܕ</foreign> (<hi rend="italic"
								>Šḥimo</hi> p. 103,<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܡܰܕܪܳܫܳܐ
								ܕܦܰܪܕܰܝܣܳܐ,</foreign> Lamy II, col. 535),<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܐ
								ܪܓܺܝܫܺܝܢ ܟܪ̈ܽܘܒܶܐ </foreign>(<hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 158,
							Assemani VI, p. 479-480). The verse hymns entitled<foreign
								xml:lang="syr"> ܒܳܥܽܘܬܐ ܕܡܳܪܝ ܐܰܦܪܶܝܡ </foreign>(Supplication of St.
							Ephrem) are definitely not of him. </p></note> The parts ascribed to
					Jacob of Serugh, on the other hand, seem to be more significant. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en"> Over the seven<foreign
								xml:lang="syr"> ܒܳܥܽܘܬܐ ܕܡܳܪܝ ܝܰܥܩܽܘܒ </foreign>dedicated to Mary in
							the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, three are extracted from the same
							homily 196 of Jacob of Serugh (<hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 16,
							73-74, 90 = B VI, hom. 196, p. 3-4, 13, 14, 6-7 [615-616; 625-626;
							618-619]). The remaining supplications are unfound in the published
							homilies of Jacob (see Appendix 3). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Faithful in general to the tradition of the Syriac Fathers, these texts make
					great use of typology. In this paper, I suggest to study three texts of the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> containing different Old Testament prefigurations
					of Mary. This will lead us to demonstrate how the Syriac Liturgy, like Jacob of
					Serugh and Simon the Potter, has expanded and simplified Ephrem’s condensed
					thought. The comparison of the Marian typology in the <hi rend="italic"
						>Šḥimo</hi> with Ephrem and Jacob of Serugh will hopefully show, at least in
					part, how this compiled service book has embraced the earlier tradition and
					developed it. Results are summarized in three appendices: 1- Table of the Old
					Testament Marian symbols, used in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> with their
					parallel references in the Bible, Ephrem and Jacob of Serugh; 2- Table of
					particular Marian titles and epithets used in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>
					with their parallel occurrences in Ephrem and Jacob of Serugh; 3- Marian verses
					attributed to Jacob of Serugh in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> lacking
					parallels in his published homilies. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.1">
				<head>1. THE TENT OF ABRAHAM, THE TREE BEARING THE LAMB AND THE NEW WELL</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In a short paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> (p. 114), three symbols
					from the book of Genesis prefiguring Mary are mentioned: </p>
				<pb n="326"/>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “The glorious Tent of Abraham in which God entered and
							dwelt, as well as the tree bearing the lamb offered instead of Isaac,
							and the new well in the desert, depicted your figure.” <note
								place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"><foreign
										xml:lang="syr"> ܡܰܫܟܢܳܐ ܫܒܺܝܚܳܐ ܕܰܐܒܪܳܗܳܡ. ܕܰܐܠܳܗܳܐ ܥܰܠ
										ܘܰܫܪܳܐ ܒܶܗ. ܐܳܦ ܐܺܝܠܳܢܳܐ ܛܥܺܝܢ ܐܶܡܪܳܐ. ܕܰܚܠܳܦ ܐܺܝܣܚܳܩ
										ܐܶܬܩܰܪܰܒ. ܘܒܺܝܪܳܐ ܚܕܰܬܐ ܕܰܒܕܰܒܪܳܐ. ܛܽܘܦܣܳܐ ܕܺܝܠܶܟܝ̱ ܪܳܫܡܺܝܢ
										ܗ̱ܘܰܘ. </foreign>The current editions of the <hi
										rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> give<foreign xml:lang="syr">
										ܒܺܝܪܬܳܐ (</foreign>palace) instead of<foreign xml:lang="syr"
										> ܒܺܝܪܳܐ </foreign>(well). This is an error to be corrected,
									for there is absolutely no biblical or patristic reference to a
									“new palace in the desert”. Moreover, the same paragraph in the
										<hi rend="italic">Fenqiṯo </hi>(4<hi rend="superscript"
										>th</hi> General Sunday, 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>
									<hi rend="italic">Qawmo d-lilyo</hi>) changes the last sentence
									from “depicted your figure” <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܛܽܘܦܣܳܐ
										ܕܺܝܠܶܟܝ ܪܳܫܡܺܝܢ ܗ̱ܘܰܘ)</foreign> into “gives life to the
										mortals”<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܝܳܗܒܳܐ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܠܡܳܝܽܘ̈ܬܶܐ)
									</foreign>which corresponds better to a well than a palace.
								</p></note>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The three depictions of Mary found in the above mentioned stanza are all alien
					to Ephrem. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">a)</hi> Although the most famous Syrian poet states that: “God
					dwelt in the tent of Abraham” (<hi rend="italic">On Genesis</hi> 7, 4, CSCO 152,
					p. 65), he doesn’t go further in comparing that tent with Mary. Jacob of Serugh,
					however, makes the step. He affirms that if somebody asks boldly how the womb of
					Mary was able to contain God, the answer is that it is easy for Him to dwell in
					the smallness, as He dwelt in the bush on Mount Sinai and in the tent of Abraham
					(cf. B III, hom. 94, p. 588). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
							xml:lang="en">
							<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܘܰܐܝܟܰܢܳܐ ܠܰܡ ܟܰܪܣܳܐ ܥܪܳܬܶܗ ܘܰܗܘܳܐ ܥܽܘܠܐ܆
								ܘܛܰܥ̈ܢܳܝܗ̱ܝ ܒܽܘܪ̈ܟܶܐ ܘܺܝܢܶܩ ܚܰܠܒܳܐ ܐܶܢ ܐܰܠܳܗܰܐ ܗ̱ܘ. ܐܳܘ ܠܳܟ ܕܳܐܡܰܪ
								ܗܶܢܶܝܢ ܗܳܠܶܝܢ ܡܰܪܳܚܳܐܺܝܬ܆ ܐܰܝܟܰܘ ܬܶܗܪܳܟ ܐܰܘ ܕܽܘܡܳܪܐ ܠܡܰܢ ܩܳܪܶܐ ܐܰܢܬ.
								ܟܰܪܣܳܐ ܙܥܽܘܪܝܳܐ ܘܪܰܒ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ ܡܶܢ ܒܶܪ̈ܝܳܬܳܐ܆ ܘܠܐ ܝܺܕܰܥܬܳܝܗ̱ܝ ܕܰܦܫܺܝܩ
								ܢܶܫܪܶܐ ܒܰܙܥܽܘܪܽܘܬܳܐ. ܐܳܦܠܳܐ ܒܣܰܢܝܳܐ ܫܪܳܐ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ ܡܳܕܶܝܢ ܥܰܠ ܛܽܘܪ
								ܣܺܝܢܰܝ܆ ܐܳܦܠܳܐ ܠܡܰܫܟܢܳܐ ܨܶܝܕ ܐܰܒܪܳܗܳܡ ܥܰܠ ܐܰܝܟ ܕܰܟܬܺܝܒ. </foreign>
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">b)</hi> The second image is the tree bearing the ram (Gn 22,
					13) which is a symbol of Mary giving birth to Christ. Another stanza of the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> refers to the same image in greater detail (p. 89).
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p xml:lang="en">
							<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܬܳܐ ܐܰܒܪܳܗܳܡ. ܒܰܕܶܩ ܠܰܢ ܥܰܠ ܐܺܝܠܳܢܳܐ ܘܡܶܛܽܠ
								ܐܶܡܪܳܐ. ܥܰܠ ܐܺܝܠܳܢܳܐ ܡܰܢ ܢܰܨܒܶܗ ܘܡܶܛܽܠ ܐܶܡܪܳܐ ܡܰܢܽܘ ܝܰܠܕܶܗ. ܠܰܘ
								ܒܰܪܢܳܫܳܐ ܢܰܨܒܶܗ ܠܺܐܝܠܳܢܳܐ ܘܠܐ ܡܶܢ ܢܶܩܝܳܐ ܐܶܬܺܝܠܶܕ ܐܶܡܪܳܐ. ܘܠܰܘ ܡܶܢ
								ܙܰܪܥܳܐ ܒܛܶܢܬܶܗ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܠܰܡܫܺܝܚܳܐ. ܗܽܘ ܨܒܳܐ ܒܳܗ̇ ܘܐܰܓܶܢ ܒܳܗ̇. ܘܰܕܢܰܚ
								ܡܶܢܳܗ̇ ܘܰܚܬܺܝܡܳܐ. ܬܰܘ ܢܶܙܡܰܪ ܠܶܗ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܒܕܽܘܟܪܳܢ ܝܳܠܶܕܬܶܗ ܗ̄
								ܨܠܽܘܬܳܗ̇ ܥܰܡܰܢ. </foreign>
						</p></note> But according to Ephrem, the tree bearing the lamb <pb n="327"/>
					is a symbol of the Cross only. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
							xml:lang="en">
							<hi rend="italic">On Genesis</hi> 20, 3 (CSCO 152, p. 84); <hi
								rend="italic">Sermones in Hebdomadem Sanctum</hi> II, 449-452 (CSCO
							412, p. 16); <hi rend="italic">Sogyata</hi> 3, 10 (CSCO 186, p. 204).
							This is against what S.P. Brock wrote: “Some of the ‘types’, however,
							are distinctive to the Syriac tradition: thus Mary as a ‘tree’ is based
							ultimately on Ephrem’s Commentary on Gen. 22:13, where the ram ‘held’ in
							the tree (bush) is seen as a type of Christ, the Lamb, held in Mary’s
							womb.” (Sebastian P. Brock, “Mary,” in<hi rend="italic"> Gorgias
								Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage: Electronic
								Edition</hi>, edited by Sebastian P. Brock, Aaron M. Butts, George
							A. Kiraz and Lucas Van Rompay,<ref
								target="https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mary">
								https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mary</ref>). </p></note> The Marian
					typology here is apparently absent from his writings. Jacob of Serugh, on the
					other hand, expands the image and sees in the landscape of the Moriah, not only
					the death of Christ but also his miraculous birth: the ram born from the thicket
					without marriage is the image of Jesus’ birth from the Virgin Mary; the offering
					of the ram represents the sacrifice of the Cross and the preservation of Isaac’s
					life from death’s corruption prefigures the resurrection of Christ (cf. B III,
					hom. 80, p. 311-312; <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en">
							Konat suggests that Hom. 80 entitled “On the Mysteries, Types and
							Figures of Christ” is a compilation of verses from different homilies of
							Jacob, made probably by a redactor and not by the author himself, though
							the latter assumption cannot be omitted (see Johns Abraham Konat, ‘‘A
							Metrical Homily of Jacob of Serugh on the Mysteries, Types and Figures
							of Christ: Authentic or Compilation?’’, <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi>
							118:1-2 (2005), p. 72-73). </p></note> B IV, hom. 109, p. 102-103). In
					his third homily on Nativity, Jacob asserts: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “That tree which provided the ram on the mountain of
							Isaac is the young girl who conceived the fruit in her womb without
							marital union. The Well that came out in the wilderness for the world
							and it [world] drank is the infant in whom the thirst of the peoples has
							been quenched.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
									xml:lang="en"> ET in <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homilies
										on the Nativity</hi>, tr. Thomas Kollamparampil, New Jersey:
									Gorgias Press, 2010, <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> III, lines
									119-122, p. 200 (see also <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> I, line
									643, p. 82 = B VI, hom. 201, p. 138 [750]). </p></note>
							<pb n="328"/> (B VI, hom. 203, 184 [796]) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">c)</hi> This strophe brings us to the third image of the well
					in the desert, which refers to Num. 21:16-18. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
						n="11"><p xml:lang="en"> A well<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܒܺܪܳܐ)
							</foreign>was there, the well of which the Lord said to Moses: Gather
							the people to me and I will give them water. At that time Israel sang
							this song, ‘Come up, O well, sing to it. The well that the leaders dug,
							and the chiefs of the people excavated and searched it with their
							staffs.’ From the wilderness it was given at Mattanah. (The Antioch
							Bible) </p></note> The well the nobles of the people dug with their rods
					and staffs, while the people were gathered and watching refers to the rock of
					the previous chapter Num. 20:8-11, which Moses struck with his staff. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> Take you a rod and
							gather the assembly, you and Aaron your brother. Speak unto the
								rock<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܟܺܐܦܳܐ) </foreign>in their sight, so
							that it will give its water; bring our water from the rock and let the
							assembly and their beasts drink it. Moses took a staff from before the
							Lord as he commanded him. Moses and Aaron gathered all the assembly to
							the rock, and said to them: Hear now, you complainers! From this rock we
							shall bring out water for you. Moses raised his hand and hit the rock
							with his rod two times, and much water came out, and all the people
							drank, and their beasts. (The Antioch Bible). </p></note> In the Pauline
					imagery, the rock is the Christ (1 Cor. 10:4). In the Pauline lineage, Jacob of
					Serugh identifies the rock hit by Moses’s rod with Christ’s side opened with the
					soldier’s lance on the Cross (Jo 19:34). It is the well dug upon Golgotha from
					which the Living Waters flowed out (B I, hom. 18, p. 445; B II, hom. 48, p.
					336). He calls it a “new well”<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܒܺܪܳܐ ܚܕܰܬܳܐ)”
					</foreign>and makes the connection with the above mentioned chapters of the book
					of Numbers (B II, hom. 53, p. 588-589; B III, hom. 95, p. 647-648). </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> But surprisingly, in a single couplet, Mary is assigned the title of “new well”: </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> “Mary is the new well, whence flowed the Living Waters; though unpierced, she
					gave birth to abundant streams for the thirsty.” <pb n="329"/> (B VI, hom. 199,
					p. 91 [703]) <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p xml:lang="en"> ET from
							S.P. Brock, “The Mysteries Hidden in the Side of Christ”, <hi
								rend="italic">Sobornost </hi>7 (1978), p. 470. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The discussion of the authenticity of the homily in question is beyond the
					limits of this paper. But it is worth noting the problem created by this
					imagery: in the case of Mary the well is unpierced, unlike the rock or the well
					of Moses and the Lord’s side which are comparable by the mere fact that they
					were both pierced. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p xml:lang="en">
							Peppard notes that the Bible reports encounters of women at wells.
							Jacob, Isaac, and Moses found their wives at wells. When Jesus met the
							Samaritan woman at a well (John 4), marriage was a topic of discussion.
							Thus, whenever in the Bible a man and a woman meet at a water source, a
							bride may be found, be she real or spiritual only (Michael Peppard, <hi
								rend="italic">The World’s Oldest Church: Bible, Art and Ritual at
								Dura-Europos, Syria</hi>, New Haven, Conn: Yale University Press,
							2016, p. 191). Following this biblical tradition, Syriac iconography
							represents the Virgin Mary receiving the announcement about her
							pregnancy at a wellspring. The Annunciation scenes in many Syriac
							manuscripts include a well with water or a vessel containing water, such
							as a pitcher beside the Virgin who receives the Holy Spirit in the form
							of water. In the Rabbula Gospels, Mary listens to the angel’s words,
							while water flows from a fountain or well into the vessel beside her. In
							the 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century icons, the well is placed
							between Mary and the angel Gabriel (cf. Lamia Doumato, “Book Review of
							Peppard, <hi rend="italic">The World’s Oldest Church…”, Syriac Orthodox
								Patriarchal Journal</hi> 55, 2017, p. 86-87). </p></note> Yet,
					another stanza in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> tries to maintain that Mary
					is the rock of the desert, although Christ is actually the true Rock: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “The rock which brought forth streams in the desert was
							clearly a figure of you, holy virgin from whom came forth in the
							creation the Son of God, Who is the true rock, as Paul said.” (<hi
								rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 165, ET p. 929) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Murray has showed that Ephrem is acquainted with the Jewish legend of the twelve
					streams giving drink to the twelve tribes, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
						n="15"><p xml:lang="en"> Robert Murray,<hi rend="italic"> Symbols of Church
								and Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac Tradition,</hi> London / New
							York: Cambridge University Press, 1975, p. 209-210. Murray explains that
							this tradition was attached to the Rock already <pb n="330"/> by the
							second century BC, but in its developed form seems to combine Elim (Ex.
							15: 27) with the well of Be’er (Num. 21:16-18), and finally makes all
							one with the miraculous travelling well of Miriam. </p></note> echoed
					also in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> (p. 105). <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p xml:lang="en"> “… there are twelve springs which
							flowed in the desert…” </p></note> But in all his <pb n="330"/>
					writings, this rock of Exodus – Numbers is always a type of Christ, and never of
					Mary. In <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 2,10, it is applied to Christ sending the
					Apostles: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“O Source untasted by Adam, </l>
							<l>which gave forth twelve speaking springs</l>
							<l>and Life filled the world! </l>
							<l>Jesus, who was called ‘Rock’</l>
							<l>was represented as a type in the midst of the rock,</l>
							<l>[to show] that through the twelve Apostles</l>
							<l>he gives the ‘Medicine of Life’ to the whole world to drink.”</l>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In summary, neither Ephrem nor Jacob of Serugh applies to Mary the image of the
					rock. The latter states clearly: “The rock that gave birth to rivers for the
					great people is Christ who supplied life to the dead world.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en"> B VI, Hom. 203, p. 183 [795], ET in
								<hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homilies on the Nativity</hi>,
							op. cit.,<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> III, lines 111-112, p. 198. See
							also Hom. 80, p. 307. </p></note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass">
				<head>2. THE BUSH, THE ARK, THE FLEECE AND THE LADDER</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The Saturday Vespers in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> gives a concise stanza
					which contains four Marian symbols: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “Moses likened you to the bush and David, your father,
							to the ark, Gideon figured you by the fleece and Jacob the just by the
							ladder, by which the race of man has been raised up to heaven.” (Šḥimo
							p. 150, ET p. 859) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">a)</hi> The typological application of the burning bush (Ex
					3,2) to Mary’s womb, abundantly attested in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> (p.
					5, 28, 54, 83, 88, 150, 176, 180-181, 183, 189), is found in some <pb n="331"/>
					works not certainly attributed to Ephrem. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18"
						n="18"><p xml:lang="en"> Cf. <hi rend="italic">Commentary on the
								Diatessaron</hi> I, 25; Sermo II, 13-16 (CSCO 363, p.39) ET by S.P.
							Brock “Homily on the Nativity” in, <hi rend="italic">The Harp of the
								Spirit, Poems of Saint Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, Cambridge: The
							Institute for Orthodox Christian Studies, 2013<hi rend="superscript"
								>3</hi>, p. 91. </p></note> But in the V<hi rend="superscript"
						>th</hi>-VI<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, the image became familiar
					to Jacob of Serugh who explained it extensively in his great <hi rend="italic"
						>Homily on Faith</hi> (cf. B III, hom. 94, p. 588-589). </p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">b) </hi>The Ark of the Covenant with its contents resembles
					Mary. In the ark were the jar of Manna and the tables of the Law; in Mary were
					the bread of life and the Word of God (<hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 65, 69,
					89, 180). Also, the jar of the Manna and the tables themselves are symbols of
					Mary because they embrace symbols of Christ: the Manna (bread) and the word of
					God (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>). Furthermore, the staff of Aaron which budded
					within the holy of holies is taken as a figure of the Virgin Mary who brought
					forth Christ without intercourse with man (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, and p.
					183). </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Ephrem compares Mary to the Ark only in regard to the Word of God dwelling in
					her (cf. <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 4, 113; 16, 16). He calls her “a pure
					tablet” <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܠܽܘܚܳܐ ܕܟܺܝܬܳܐ)</foreign> in comparison to the
					stony tablets of the Law (<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 16, 17). He refers also to
					the staff of Aaron: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“The staff of Aaron sprouted, and the dry wood brought forth;</l>
							<l>his symbol has been explained today-it is the virgin womb that gave
								birth.” </l> (<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 1, 17) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Ephrem doesn’t seem to use the jar of Manna as a Marian symbol. This is also the
					case for Jacob of Serugh, who compares David leaping and dancing before the ark
					(2 Sam. 6: 14-16) with John leaping in the womb of his mother Elizabeth in front
					of Mary (B VI, hom. 198, p. 58-59 [670-671] cf. also B VI, hom. 197, p. 37
					[649]). This comparison explains why the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> stanza
					quoted above says about Mary: “David your father likened you to the ark”.
					Moreover, Jacob <pb n="332"/> states that Aaron’s staff which sprouted leaves
					without watering pictured the womb which carried the fruit without marriage (B
					III, hom. 80, p. 314, Hom 93, p. 565, B VI, hom. 201, p. 138 [750]). According
					to Jacob, the two tablets are figures of the two testaments (B I, hom. 25, p.
					593-594). No Marian typology is evoked in this regard. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">c)</hi> In the writings of Ephrem, there is at least one
					certain reference to the fleece of Gideon (Jud. 6:36-40) as a symbol of the
					Virgin Mary <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> The
							fleece of Gideon symbolizes also the teaching of the Christ (<hi
								rend="italic">Virg.</hi> 8, 17) and the baptism (<hi rend="italic"
								>Epiph.</hi> 7, 14). </p></note> : “One depicted His descent by the
					rain descending gently, and represented Mary by the magnificent and pure
					fleece.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p xml:lang="en"><foreign
								xml:lang="syr"> ܚܰܕ ܨܳܐܰܪ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ ܡܰܚܰܬܬܶܗ܆ ܒܡܶܛܪܳܐ ܕܰܢܚܶܬ ܢܺܝܚܳܐܺܝܬ܆
								ܘܰܠܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܬܽܘܒ ܪܳܫܶܡ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ܆ ܒܓܶܙܬܳܐ ܓܐܺܝܬܳܐ
							ܘܰܕܟܺܝܬܳܐ.</foreign>Sermo II, 3, 304-307(CSCO 311, p. 62). One may also
							mention Sog. I, 16:<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܓܶܙܬܳܐ ܗ̱ܝ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܕܰܢܚܶܬ
								ܠܳܗ̇܆ ܡܶܢ ܐܰܒܳܐ ܡܶܛܪܳܐ ܕܒܽܘܪܟܬܳܐ. </foreign>
						</p></note> When speaking about the fleece, Jacob combines the symbolism of
					Mary and the baptism found separately in Ephrem (B III, hom. 80, p. 312-313,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> ET by Konat, “A
							Metrical Homily”, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, p. 79-80. </p></note>
					see also B VI, hom. 203, 183 [795]). </p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">d) </hi>The ladder of Jacob (Gen. 28:12) is a Christological
					symbol present in the background of Joh 1: 51. In the <hi rend="italic"
						>Šḥimo</hi>, it represents, on one hand, the Church (p. 116), and on the
					other hand, the Virgin May by whom the humans were raised up to heaven (p. 150,
					176, 180). For Ephrem, Christ revealed himself to Jacob through the ladder (Sog.
					III, 8). For Jacob of Serugh, the ladder is an image of the Cross (B III, hom.
					74, p. 196-197; B V, hom. 166, p. 475) and the crucified himself (B V, hom. 179,
					p. 710). The Marian typology is absent in both writers’ works. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.3">
				<head>3. THE VEIL</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> a) In a particular image of the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, Mary is called
					“veil of the godhead<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ ܕܰܐܠܳܗܽܘܬܳܐ)
					</foreign>whose mystery was represented by Moses” (p. 64-65, ET p. 465). Both
					Mary and the veil covering the shining face of Moses (Exod. 34:33-35) <pb
						n="333"/> concealed something from the Godhead. This comparison, unknown to
					Ephrem, is marvelously developed by Jacob of Serugh, in his <hi rend="italic"
						>Homily on the veil of Moses</hi>: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>That hidden child who did not loose the seals of virginity at his
								birth</l>
							<l>loosened the veil of prophecy at his crucifixion.</l>
							<l>Joy of heart did he provide to both prophecy and virginity,</l>
							<l>for at his birth and at his crucifixion the two of them shone
								out:</l>
							<l>for virginity he preserved intact, that she might not be laid
								bare,</l>
							<l>while prophecy’s face he uncovered, that she might not be veiled.</l>
							<l>Since his birth did not tear that veil of virginity,</l>
							<l>on his cross he tore off that covering from prophecy.</l>
							<l>He preserved youth in the ranks of virginity,</l>
							<l>while he lightened the burden that old age was carrying.</l>
							<l>The young Mary continued on in her virginity,</l>
							<l>while the aged Moses cast off the covering that proved heavy.</l>
							<l>The virgin rejoiced that he had preserved her virginity,</l>
							<l>the prophet too rejoiced that he had removed from him the veil.</l>
							<l>He left virginity’s beauty preserved untouched,</l>
							<l>He revealed prophecy’s beauty that had been covered up.</l>
							<l>Moses leaps with Joy for he has revealed his beauty that had been
								veiled;</l>
							<l>Mary exults for her virginity has not been harmed.</l>
							<l>The girl and the aged man both have gained their true beauty</l>
							<l>through the Son of God who himself is the beauty of all beautiful
								things.</l>
							<pb n="334"/>
							<l>The great prophet bore him on his face beneath the veil,</l>
							<l>Mary bore him within the gates of her virginity.</l>
							<l>At his birth he left the seals unbroken,</l>
							<l>at his crucifixion he removed the veils from the prophets.</l>
							<l>He revealed their words, and the earth was illumined at their
								revelation;</l>
							<l>their symbols shone out and all now possess their explanation.</l>
							<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en"> ET by
									Sebastian P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Sarug’s Homily on
										the Veil on Moses’ Face</hi>. Texts from Christian Late
									Antiquity 20, Homilies of Mar Jacob of Sarug 1. Piscataway, NJ:
									Gorgias Press, 2009, p. 50-52. </p></note> (B III, hom. 79, p.
							300-301) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">b)</hi> But another couplet attributed in the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> to Jacob of Serugh describes Mary as a veil, in a
					different sense: </p>
				<cit><quote><p xml:lang="en"> “May that veil <foreign xml:lang="syr"
					>(ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign>, which poured life on the pathway of the world, make
					intercession and offer our prayers before God.” (p. 104, ET p. 379) </p></quote></cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The couplet is not found in the so far published homilies of the bishop of
					Serugh. But it has resonances in his writings, rooted in the Bible, specifically
					in Prov. 30: 4: </p>
				<cit><quote><p xml:lang="en"> “Who has gone up to heaven and come down? Who has gathered
					up the wind in the palms of his hands? Who has bound the waters in a veil
						<foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܡܰܢ ܨܰܪ ܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ ܒܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign>?...” </p></quote></cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The veil referred to here is the clouds, as confirmed by a parallel verse Job
					26:8 “He has bound the waters in His clouds <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܨܰܪ ܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ
						ܒܰܥܢ̈ܳܢܰܘܗ̱ܝ)</foreign>”. Ephrem comments on the question of Salomon and
					applies it to both the Eucharist and Mary, making reference also to the veil
					that covers the offerings and the altar, and the tradition of taking the
					Eucharist in veiled hands: </p>
				<pb n="335"/>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“[14] ‘Who has ever grasped the wind in his hands?’</l>
							<l>Come and see, Solomon, what your father’s Lord (Ps 110:1) has
								done!</l>
							<l>Fire and Spirit, against their nature,</l>
							<l>he has mingled and poured into his disciples’ hands.</l>
							<l>[15] Who has ever bound the waters in a veil?”<foreign xml:lang="syr"
									> (ܡܰܢܽܘ ܨܰܪ ܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ ܒܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign> he asked.</l>
							<l>See, a font in a veil — the lap of Mary <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܗܐ
									ܒܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ ܡܰܒܽܘܥܳܐ ܟܶܢܦܳܗ̇ ܕܡܰܪܝܰܡ)! </foreign></l>
							<l>Your handmaids receive in a veil<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܒܓܰܘ
									ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign></l>
							<l>From the Cup of Life, a drop of life<foreign xml:lang="syr"> (ܢܽܘܛܦܰܬ
									ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ) </foreign></l>
							<l>[16] See, Power concealed in the veil of the sanctuary,</l>
							<l>a power which no mind has ever conceived.</l>
							<l>His love bent down, descended, and hovered</l>
							<l>over the veil on the altar of reconciliation.” (Fid. 10,14-16)</l>
							<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> ET by Robert
									Murray, “A Hymn of St. Ephrem to Christ on the Incarnation, the
									Holy Spirit, and the Sacraments”, <hi rend="italic">Eastern
										Churches Review</hi> 3, 1970, p. 144. [translation modified]
								</p></note>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The Fire and Spirit are in the lap of Mary and in the Bread and the Cup (<hi
						rend="italic">Fid.</hi> 10,17). The veil is Mary’s lap which is compared to
					a cloud containing a font - Christ, and distilling life to the world. The veil
					also covers the altar, the Cup of Life, and the hands of the women receiving the
					communion. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> This constellation of symbols is repeated more plainly by Jacob of Serugh on
					different occasions. Like Ephrem, Jacob rephrases the question of Prov. 30:4:
					“Who has ever seen the Spirit hold in the palms, or a veil in which waters are
					bound?” This happened, answered Jacob, in the incarnation which was completely
					unexpected because nobody has ever hoped to see and touch God who is Spirit: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“The ear heard and the eye saw and the hands held</l>
							<l>the Spirit in the palms and the Living Waters in the veil.</l>
							<l>The Fire is placed on the fingers of humans,</l>
							<l><pb n="336"/></l>
							<l>And they turn it over without being burned by the flame.</l>
							<l>Behold, the Living Waters are in the holy Veil – Mary</l>
							<l>who was bound up and sealed in virginity.</l>
							<l>The Holy Spirit dwelt in the bread and it became Body,</l>
							<l>And behold, the humans are holding the Glorious (Spirit) in the
								palms.</l>
							<l>The Fire and the Spirit are being eaten and drunk.</l>
							<l>This is something new that no one has ever imagined.”</l>
							<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p xml:lang="syr">
									<l>ܡܰܢܽܘ ܚܙܶܐ ܠܶܗ ܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܒܚܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ ܟܰܕ ܡܶܬܠܰܒܟܳܐ܆ ܐܰܘ ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ
										ܕܰܨܪܺܝܪܺܝܢ ܒܳܗ̇ ܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ ܡܶܡܬܽܘܡ [...]</l>
									<l>ܘܫܶܡܥܰܬ ܐܶܕܢܳܐ ܘܰܚܙܳܬ ܥܰܝܢܳܐ ܘܰܠܒܰܟ ܐܺܝ̈ܕܶܐ܆ ܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܒܚܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ
										ܘܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܒܓܰܘ ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ.</l>
									<l>ܢܽܘܪܳܐ ܕܣܺܝܡܳܐ ܥܰܠ ܨܶܒ̈ܥܳܬܳܐ ܕܰܒܢܰܝ̈ܢܳܫܳܐ܆ ܘܰܡܗܰܦܟܺܝܢ ܠܳܗ̇
										ܘܠܐ ܝܳܩܕܺܝܢ ܒܳܗ̇ ܒܫܰܠܗܶܒܺܝܬܳܐ.</l>
									<l>ܗܳܐ ܒܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ ܕܩܽܘܕܫܳܐ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܡܰܝ̈ܳܐ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ܆ ܘܰܨܪܺܝܪܳܐ ܗ̱ܘܳܬ
										ܘܰܚܬܺܝܡܳܐ ܗ̱ܘܳܬ ܒܰܒܬܽܘܠܽܘܬܳܐ.</l>
									<l>ܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܕܩܽܘܕܫܳܐ ܫܪܳܬ ܠܳܗ̇ ܒܠܰܚܡܳܐ ܘܰܗܘܳܐ ܦܰܓܪܳܐ܆ ܘܗܳܐ
										ܠܒܺܝܟܺܝܢ ܠܳܗ̇ ܐ̱ܢܳܫܳܐ ܒܚܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ ܠܰܡܫܰܒܰܚܬܳܐ.</l>
									<l>ܘܢܽܘܪܳܐ ܘܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܗܐ ܡܶܬܰܐܟܠܳܐ ܐܳܦ ܡܶܫܬܰܬܝܳܐ܆ ܥܒܳܕܳܐ ܚܰܕܬܳܐ ܕܠܐ
										ܣܠܶܩ ܡܶܡܬܽܘܡ ܥܰܠ ܪܶܥܝܳܢܳܐ܀</l>
								</p></note> (B IV, hom. 133, p. 743-745) <note place="foot"
								xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en">
									<l>“Who is the one who grasped the wind/Spirit in his cupped
										hands unless here,</l>
									<l>for Fire and Spirit are grasped in the palms of hands and in
										swaddling clothes?</l>
									<l>Who has tied up water in a veil <foreign xml:lang="syr"
											>(ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign>, unless Mary</l>
									<l>who in her virginity, conceived the child who is wholly a
										marvel?</l>
									<l>The young virgin carried the Living Water in the womb,</l>
									<l>and it became a wonder that had never happened in the world,
										apart from it.</l>
									<l>O King Solomon, come, see that your parable has been
										explained by Him,</l>
									<l>and sing praise to the Lord of your father, if you can.</l>
									<l>The wind has been grasped in the palms and in the fingers</l>
									<l>and without violence the waters were bound up within the veil
											<foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ)</foreign>.”</l>
									<l>(<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> III, lines 153-162, p. 204 = B
										VI, hom. 203, p. 185-187 [797-798])</l>
									<l>“That- “who bound the water in the veil”- why it was
										said,</l>
									<l>but because of the bosom of Mary which multiplied life.</l>
									<l>If you look, who held the wind/Spirit in His hand,</l>
									<l>behold, inside the palms (there is) fire and Spirit, for he
										who takes Him.”</l>
									<pb n="337"/> (B III, hom. 80, p. 314, ET Konat, “A Metrical
									Homily”, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, p. 81 ; see also B II,
									Hom. 43, p. 236) </p></note>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<pb n="337"/>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The detailed interpretation given by Jacob of Serugh, inspired by some condensed
					words of <hi rend="italic">Hymn 10 on Faith</hi> of Ephrem, reveals a rhetorical
					difference between the two Syrian poets. It is about writing intensely or
					extensively. The power of Ephrem’s poetry is in its concise phrasing joined to a
					highly suggestive imagery, whereas the style of Jacob reflects his prolixity
					dictated by his concern to instruct and entertain, through a clear discourse,
					the audience sitting and listening to him for long hours. The prayers of the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> follow Jacob’s strategy and simplify the condensed
					ephremian thought, making it more accessible to the simple worshippers. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.4">
				<head>4. THE SIMPLIFICATION OF EPHREM’S THOUGHT IN THE <hi rend="italic"
					>ŠḤIMO</hi></head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Even though only one single stanza in the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> derives
					from the genuine Ephrem (cf. introduction), the book is imbued with ephremian
					thought. The following examples will hopefully show how Liturgy tries to make
					the ephremian legacy more accessible, by elucidating its allusive style. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">a)</hi> Towards the disputants who pretend to know everything
					about God, His son and His deeds, Ephrem expresses his basic embarrassment to
					find an appropriate name for Jesus (Nat. 6, 1-2). The same applies for Jesus’
					mother: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“Our Lord, no one knows how to address Your mother.</l>
							<l>[If] one calls her “virgin,” her child stands up,</l>
							<l>and “married”- no one knew her [sexually].</l>
							<l>But if Your mother is incomprehensible, who is capable of
								[comprehending] You?” (<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 11, 1)</l>
							<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="syr"> ܠܶܐܡܳܟ
									ܡܳܪܰܢ܆ ܠܳܐ ܐ̱ܢܳܫ ܝܳܕܰܥ܆ ܐܰܝܟܰܢ܆ ܢܶܩܪܶܝܗ̇ ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܢܶܩܪܶܝܗ̇܆
									ܝܰܠܕܳܗ̇ ܩܳܐܶܡ ܘܰܡܙܰܘܰܓܬܳܐ܆ ܠܳܐ ܐ̱ܢܳܫ ܚܰܟܡܳܗ̇܆ ܘܶܐܢ ܗܽܘ ܕܶܐܡܳܟ܆
									ܠܳܐ ܡܶܬܕܰܪܟܳܐ܆ ܠܳܟ ܡܰܢ ܣܳܦܶܩ. </p></note>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<pb n="338"/>
				<p xml:lang="en"> This idea expressed by Ephrem in 23 words is reformulated twice in the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, once in the meter of<foreign xml:lang="syr">
						ܩܽܘܩܳܝܐ </foreign>(attributed to Simon the Potter) with 42 words (p. 15),
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p xml:lang="syr"> ܡܽܘܢ ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱
							ܐܳܘ ܒܪ̱ܬ ܕܘܺܝܕ ܠܳܐ ܝܳܕܰܥ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ. ܘܰܐܝܢܳܐ ܫܡܳܐ ܠܶܟܝ̱ ܐܶܟܰܢܶܐ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܠܳܐ
							ܪܓܺܝܫ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ. ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱: ܒܪܳܐ ܝܺܢܶܩ ܡܶܢܶܟܝ̱. ܐܶܡܳܐ ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱:
							ܒܬܽܘ̈ܠܰܝܟܝ̱ ܩܰܝܳܡܺܝܢ. ܡܶܟܺܝܠ ܝܳܠܕܰܬ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ ܩܳܪܶܐ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ ܠܶܟܝ̱. ܘܢܶܒܗܰܬ
							ܣܳܦܪܳܐ ܕܳܪܽܘܫܳܐ ܕܒܳܨܶܐ ܠܶܗ ܠܝܰܠܕܶܟܝ̱ ܗ̄ ܚܪܶܡ ܗ̱ܽܘ ܕܒܳܨܶܐ ܠܶܗ.
						</p></note> and again in the meter of<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܙܳܕܶܩ ܕܢܶܗܘܶܐ
					</foreign>with 48 words (p. 89). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
							xml:lang="syr"> ܐܰܝܟܰܢ ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱. ܒܰܪ̱ܬ ܕܰܘܺܝܕ ܠܳܐ ܝܳܕܰܥ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ ܕܬܰܗܺܝܪ
							ܐ̱ܢܳܐ ܠܺܝ. ܘܰܐܚܕܰܢܝ̱ ܬܶܗܪܳܐ. ܘܕܽܘܡܳܪܳܐ ܘܠܳܐ ܣܳܦܶܩ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ ܐܶܒܨܶܐ ܝܰܠܕܶܟܝ̱.
							ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱ ܐܶܡܳܐ ܒܬܽܘ̈ܠܰܝܟܝ̱ ܩܰܝܳܡܺܝܢ. ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱ ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܚܰܠܒܳܐ ܥܰܠ
							ܚܰܕܝܶܟܝ̱. ܡܶܟܺܝܠ ܐܶܩܪܶܝܟܝ̱. ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܝܳܠܕܰܬ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ. ܕܰܐܢ̱ܬܝ̱ ܗܘܰܝܬܝ̱
							ܠܶܗ ܒܬܶܕܡܽܘܪܬܐ. ܐܶܡܳܐ ܠܡܳܪܳܐ ܕܡܰܠܰܐܟ̈ܶܐ. ܬܰܘ ܢܶܙܡܰܪ ܠܶܗ. ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ
							ܒܕܽܘܟܪܳܢ ܝܳܠܶܕܬܶܗ ܗ̄ ܨܠܽܘܬܳܗ̇ ܥܰܡܰܢ. </p></note> Both reformulations
					lack the last and most important contrast in Ephrem’s stanza (if Your mother is
					incomprehensible, who is capable of [comprehending] You?). Here is the
					translation of the first text: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “How to call you, I know not, daughter of David; and
							what name to give you, Mary, I cannot tell. If I call you virgin, I see
							a son who sucks at your breast; if I call you mother, your virginity
							remains; therefore I will call you mother of God, that the learned may
							be put to shame and the disputant who would question your child <foreign
								xml:lang="syr">(ܝܰܠܕܶܟܝ)</foreign>, halleluia, cursed be he who
							would investigate Him.” (ET, p. 231) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en">
					<hi rend="italic">b)</hi> In another example, Ephrem compares two miraculous
					births: Eve born from Adam and Jesus from Mary. He says: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“The man (Adam) who never gives birth, bore Eve the mother:</l>
							<l>how much more should Eve’s daughter (Mary) be believed to have borne
								a child without [the aid of] a man!”</l>
							<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="syr"> ܠܚܰܘܳܐ
									ܝܳܠܽܘܕܬܳܐ ܝܰܠܕܳܗ̇܆ ܓܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܡܶܡܬܽܘܡ ܠܳܐ ܝܳܠܶܕ܆ ܟܡܳܐ ܬܶܬܗܰܝܡܰܢ
									ܒܰܪܬ ܚܰܘܳܐ܆ ܕܠܳܐ ܓܰܒܪܳܐ ܝܰܠܕܳܐ ܝܶܠܕܰܬ. </p></note> (<hi
								rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 1, 15) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<pb n="339"/>
				<p xml:lang="en"> It is striking that two modern translations of this paragraph missed the meaning
					of <foreign xml:lang="syr">“ܓܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܡܶܡܬܽܘܡ ܠܳܐ ܝܳܠܶܕ”</foreign>, and translated
					it: “the man who never was born” (McVey) <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30"
						n="30"><p xml:lang="en"> “He gave birth to the Mother, Eve-he, the man who
							never was born; how worthy of faith is the daughter of Eve, who without
							a man bore a child!” (Kathleen Elizabeth McVey, <hi rend="italic">Ephrem
								the Syrian. Hymns on the Nativity, Hymns Against Julian, Hymns on
								Virginity and on the Symbols of the Lord.</hi> The Classics of
							Western Spirituality. New York / Mahwah: Paulist Press, 1989, p. 65)
						</p></note> , “A man (Adam) who himself knew no birth” (Brock). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en"> “A man (Adam) who
							himself knew no birth, bore Eve the mother: how much more should Eve’s
							daughter (Mary) be believed to have given birth without the aid of a
							man!” (Sebastian P. Brock, ‘‘Mary in Syriac Tradition’’, in <hi
								rend="italic">Mary’s Place in Christian Dialogue: Occasional Papers
								of the Ecumenical Society of the Blessed Virgin Mary,
							1970–1980</hi>. Edited by Stacpoole, Alberic. Slough: St. Paul’s
							Publications, 1982, p. 187). </p></note> This is quite understandable
					because Ephrem’s elusive style makes often his ideas difficult to grasp at first
					glance – and sometimes after multiple readings. Therefore, Jacob of Serugh
					elucidates as usual the condensed thought of Ephrem and puts it in a developed
					paragraph, of which I quote only a few couplets: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">
							<l>“You admit that a man gave birth to a woman and you have no
								difficulty,</l>
							<l>and you do not believe that Mary, in a virginal way, gave birth…</l>
							<l>Adam, a man gave birth to a woman and there is no doubt,</l>
							<l>and Mary, a woman, since she gave birth to child, there is
								controversy…</l>
							<l>If you are an unbeliever, take the two (away) from your teaching, and
								admit to me that neither Adam nor Mary gave birth.</l>
							<l>It is unjust that you believe the begetting through man,</l>
							<l>and you falsely accuse the woman that she is corrupted as a result of
								her birthing.</l>
							<pb n="340"/>
							<l>The way of her having a child is abandoned but not that of a man
								(Adam);</l>
							<l>grant to her that generation of man in her virginity.</l>
							<l>When Eve came forth, there was no breach in the integral nature, and
								how here, in the coming forth of the child are there many
								breaches?”</l> (B VI, hom. 199, 92- 93 [704-705]) <note place="foot"
								xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en"> ET by James Puthuparambil,
										<hi rend="italic">Mariological Thought of Mar Jacob of
										Serugh, Moran ‘Eth’o</hi> 25, SEERI, Kottayam, 2005, p.
									xviii. </p></note>
						</p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The same idea is found in a hymn of the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> composed in
					the meter of<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܳܟ ܡܳܪܝܐ ܩܳܪܶܝܢܰܢ:</foreign>
					<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p xml:lang="syr"> ܕܝܰܠܕܳܗ̇ ܓܰܒܪܳܐ
							ܠܰܐܢ̱ܬܬܳܐ ܡܰܘܕܶܐ ܥܰܡܳܐ. ܘܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܝܶܠܕܰܬ ܠܰܡܫܺܝܚܳܐ ܟܳܦܪܺܝܢ ܛܳܠܽܘܡ̈ܶܐ.
							ܚܰܘܳܐ ܐܳܕܳܡ ܝܰܠܕܳܗ̇ ܘܰܚܬܺܝܡ ܣܶܛܪܶܗ. ܘܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܝܶܠܕܰܬ ܠܰܡܫܺܝܚܳܐ ܘܰܢܛܺܝܪܺܝܢ
							ܒܬܽܘܠܶܝ̈ܗ̇. ܐܶܢ ܓܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܠܳܐ ܝܳܠܶܕ ܝܺܠܶܕ: ܟܡܳܐ ܫܰܪܺܝܪ ܒܰܛܢܳܗ̇ ܕܰܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ.
							ܕܺܝܠܶܕܬܶܗ ܠܥܰܡܰܢܽܘܐܶܝܠ ܒܬܶܗܪܳܐ ܘܕܽܘܡܳܪܳܐ. </p></note>
				</p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en"> “The [Jewish] people admit that the man (Adam) gave
							birth to the woman (Eve). But the unbelieving deny that Mary gave birth
							to Christ. Adam gave birth to Eve while his side remained sealed, and
							Mary gave birth to Christ while her virginity was preserved. If the man
							who does not give birth, did give birth, how much more true is the
							conception of the Virgin who gave birth to Emmanuel, miraculously and
							marvelously.” (<hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> p. 47) </p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> One can see again how the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> is explaining in 33 words
					what Ephrem had expressed in 15 words only, and Jacob of Serug in a long
					paragraph of 273 words. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In his long letter to Rabban Yeshu’, a Syrian monk fascinated by the Greek
					rituals, who criticized the simplicity of the Syriac prayers, Bar Salibi reveals
					that the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi> service book was prepared to be chanted by
					the simple worshippers and nuns. Therefore its compilers chose simple verses
					which would immediately be assimilated by the mind and would stimulate the heart
					to repentance: </p>
				<pb n="341"/>
				<p rend="H Block Quote"> “What harm is there in the simple service <foreign
						xml:lang="syr">(ܬܶܫܡܶܫܬܳܐ ܫܚܺܝܡܬܳܐ)</foreign>, that you are despising? It
					contains “multum in parvo,” <foreign xml:lang="syr">(ܒܰܙܥܽܘܪ̈ܝܳܬܳܐ ܚܶܡܠܰܬ
						ܠܣܰܓܺܝ̈ܐܶܐ)</foreign> and has been arranged for the weak<foreign
						xml:lang="syr"> (ܡܚܺܝ̈ܠܶܐ)</foreign>, and at one time, for the nuns. Now
					that it has been established everywhere, you see that it carries significance
					and substance about all the essential topics: the Mother of God, the Apostles,
					the Fathers, the Prophets, the Martyrs, repentance, and the dead.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p xml:lang="en"> Alphonse Mingana, <hi
								rend="italic">Woodbrooke Studies</hi>, 1 (1927), p. 34 [Text p. 74]
							– translation modified. </p></note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.conclusion">
				<head>CONCLUSION</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Concerning the Old Testament typology, Ephrem was likely the first Syrian poet
					to point out the following Marian symbols: Eve, the Burning bush, the Ark of
					Covenant, the Staff of Aaron, the Fleece, the King’s daughter, the Thirsty
					earth, the Veil enclosing water, and the Chariot of Ezekiel. To this list, Jacob
					of Serugh added the Tent of Abraham, the Tree bearing the lamb, the Veil of
					Moses, the new Well, the Sling of David, the new Pitcher of Elisha, the swift
					Cloud, the closed Door, and titles with biblical resonances like City, Ship and
					Dove. With the <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, more original images and titles
					were adduced: the Ladder of Jacob, the Tablets of the Law, the Jar of Manna, the
					Rock in the desert, the Candelabrum, the Locked garden, and sealed fountain etc.
					(see Appendices 1-2). The study of this evolution must be complemented by a
					comparison with the <hi rend="italic">Hymni de Maria</hi> published by Lamy (II,
					col. 517–642). Nevertheless, it is interesting to note how some images applied
					initially by Ephrem to the Cross (tree bearing the lamb, ladder of Jacob), or to
					the Christ (dove, light, rock), became later with Jacob of Serugh and the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, Marian symbols, particularly in the<foreign
						xml:lang="syr"> ܡܰܘܪ̈ܒܶܐ</foreign> (Cantus ad Magnificat), most of which are
					translated from Greek <pb n="342"/> antiphons. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35"
						n="35"><p xml:lang="en"> Dom Jules Jeannin, <hi rend="italic">Mélodies
								liturgiques Syriennes et Chaldéennes</hi>, vol. 2, Paris : Leroux,
							1928, p. 23. </p></note> Unfortunately, in these hymns, the Virgin
					receives some Christological titles such as “Light of those sitting in the
					darkness” (p. 186), “Wonder” (p. 181) and “the Ladder of Jacob” (p. 176, 180). </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Anyway, this study has shown that the theological style of Jacob’s metrical
					homilies and especially of Ephrem’s didactic hymns<foreign xml:lang="syr">
						(ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ) </foreign>didn’t lend itself to liturgical use. Liturgy had to
					adapt the legacy of the early great theologians and poets by two means: first,
					by adding devotional material (praise, intercession etc.) and second, by
					simplifying Ephrem’s condensed poetry, in spite of the loss that such attempt
					might cause. It seems that in various fields, the Syrians liked to keep two
					parallel tracks: just like they had a common and simple version of the Bible
						(<hi rend="italic">Pšitto</hi>), along with the Syro-hexaplar version
					reserved to scholars, they sought also to have a simple and light collection of
					Hymns for common prayer <hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, besides the literary and
					weighty corpus of Ephrem’s didactic hymns <foreign xml:lang="syr"
						>(ܡܕܪ̈ܫܐ)</foreign>. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.abbreviations">
				<table rend="ruls">
					<head>ABBREVIATIONS</head>
					<row>
						<cell>A I-II</cell>
						<cell> = Akhrass, Roger-Youssef and Syryany, Imad, eds. <hi rend="italic"
								>160 Unpublished Homilies of Jacob of Serugh</hi>. Damascus: Syriac
							Orthodox Patriarchate, 2017.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Assemani VI</cell>
						<cell>= Stefanus Evodius Assemani, ed. <hi rend="italic">Sancti patris
								nostri Ephraem Syri opera omnia quæ exstant, Græce, Syriace,
								Latine</hi>. Tomus tertius: Syriace et latine, Roma: Typographia
							Pontificia Vaticana, 1743.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>B I–VI </cell>
						<cell>= Paulus Bedjan, ed. <hi rend="italic">Homiliae Selectae Mar Jacobi
								Sarugensis</hi>, Paris – Lipsiae, t. I, 1905 (hom. 1– <pb n="343"/>
							33); t. II, 1906 (hom. 33–70); t. III, 1907 (hom. 71–107); t. IV, 1908
							(hom. 108–146); t. V, 1910 (hom. 147–195), Piscataway NJ, t. VI, 2006
							(hom. 196–211).</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>c.</cell>
						<cell>=couplet</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>CSCO</cell>
						<cell>= <hi rend="italic">Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum
							Orientalium</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell rend="italic">Fid. </cell>
						<cell>= de Fide (Hymns on Faith, CSCO 154).</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell rend="italic">Epiph. </cell>
						<cell>= de Epiphania (on Epiphany, CSCO 186)</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>hom.</cell>
						<cell>homily</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Lamy I-IV</cell>
						<cell> = T. J. Lamy,<hi rend="italic"> Sancti Ephraem Syri hymni et
								sermones</hi>, 4 vol., Malines 1882–1902.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell rend="italic">Nat. </cell>
						<cell> = de Nativitate (On the Nativity, CSCO 186)</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>PO</cell>
						<cell>= <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi></cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Sog.</cell>
						<cell>= Sogyata (CSCO 186)</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell rend="italic">Virg.</cell>
						<cell>= de Virginitate (On Virginity, CSCO 223)</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
			</div>
			<pb n="344"/>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.appendix.1">
				<head>APPENDIX 1</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Table of the Old Testament Marian symbols, used in the <hi rend="italic"
						>Šḥimo</hi> with their parallel references in the Bible, Ephrem and Jacob of
					Serugh. </p>
				<table>
					<row rend="bold">
						<cell rend="italic">Šḥimo</cell>
						<cell>Bible</cell>
						<cell>Ephrem</cell>
						<cell>Jacob of Serugh</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell> Eve<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܚܘܐ</foreign> (p. 48) </cell>
						<cell>Cf. Gen. 3:20; 4:1; 2Co 11:3; 1 Tim. 2:13</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 2,7 ; 4, 111-112 ; 17,4 ; 22,31 ; <hi
								rend="italic">Virg.</hi> 37, 1 ; <hi rend="italic">Ecc.</hi> 35 ;
							46, 11-13 ; 47, 1; 49, 7 ; <hi rend="italic">Diat.</hi> 2, 2 etc.</cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 196, p. 4, 15-23 [616, 627-635]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Tent of Abraham <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܡܫܟܢܐ ܕܐܒܪܗܡ</foreign> (p.
							114) </cell>
						<cell>Gen. 18:1-10</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 94, p. 588</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Tree bearing the lamb<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܐܝܠܢܐ ܛܥܝܢ
								ܐܡܪܐ</foreign> (p. 89; 114) </cell>
						<cell>Gen. 22:13</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 80, p. 311-312; B IV, hom. 109, p. 102-103; B VI, hom.
							201, p. 138 [750] and hom. 203, 184 [796]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Ladder of Jacob<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܣܒܠܬܐ</foreign> (p. 150; 176;
							180) </cell>
						<cell>Gn 28:12</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Bush<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܣܢܝܐ</foreign> (p. 5; 54; 83; 88; 150;
							176; 180; 181; 183; 189) </cell>
						<cell>Exod. 3:2</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Diat.</hi> I, 25; Sermo II, 13-16 (CSCO 363, p.39).
							(authenticity?) </cell>
						<cell>B III. hom. 94, p. 588-589</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Jar of Manna<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܩܣܛܐ ܕܡܢܢܐ</foreign> (p. 65; 69;
							180) Exod. 16: 33; Heb. 9:4 </cell>
						<cell>Exod. 16: 33; Heb. 9:4</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<pb n="345"/>
					<row>
						<cell>Rock in the desert<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܟܐܦܐ ܒܕܒܪܐ</foreign> (p.
							165) </cell>
						<cell>Exod. 17:1-6</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Tablets of the Law<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܘ̈ܚܐ ܕܢܡܘܣܐ</foreign> (p.
							88-89; 180) </cell>
						<cell>Exod. 25:16</cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܚܐ ܕܟܝܬܐ </foreign>“Pure tablet”<hi
								rend="italic"> Nat.</hi> 16, 17 </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell> Candelabrum <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܡܢܪܬܐ</foreign> (p. 180<hi
								rend="superscript">2</hi> in Mawrbo) </cell>
						<cell> Ex 25:31-40; 37: 17-29; Num. 8:1-4 </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>- › love of God (B I, hom. 26, p. 621); › Cross in the Church (B V,
							hom. 173, p. 600) </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Veil of the Godhead <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܫܦܐ ܕܐܠܗܘܬܐ
							</foreign>(p. 64-65) </cell>
						<cell>Ex 34:33-35</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 79, p. 300-301</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Staff of Aaron <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܛܗ ܕܐܗܪܘܢ</foreign> (p. 65;
							69; 180; 183) </cell>
						<cell>Num. 17</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 1, 17</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 80, p. 314, Hom 93, p. 565, B VI, hom. 201, p. 138
							[750]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>New well <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܻܪܐ ܚܕܬܐ</foreign> (p. 114) </cell>
						<cell>Num. 20:8-11; 21:16-18</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>Christic title except in B VI, hom. 199, p. 91 [703]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Fleece <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܙܬܐ</foreign> (p. 69; 180; 181) </cell>
						<cell>Jud. 6:36-40; Ps. 72:6</cell>
						<cell>Sermo II, 3, 304-307 (CSCO 311, p. 62); Sog. I, 16</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 80, p. 312-313; B VI, hom. 203, 183 [795]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Sling of David <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܠܥܐ</foreign> (p. 147) </cell>
						<cell>1 Sam. 17:40</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B II, hom. 34, p. 64</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Ark <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܒܘܬܐ</foreign> (p. 65, 69, 89, 180) </cell>
						<cell>2 Sam. 6:14-16</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 4, 113; 12, 2; 16, 16</cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 197, p. 37 [649]; hom. 198, p. 58-59 [670-671] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>New Pitcher of Elisha <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܘܩܬܐ ܕܐܠܝܫܥ</foreign>
							(p. 69, 181) </cell>
						<cell>2 Kings 2:19-22</cell>
						<cell>Cf. <hi rend="italic">Epiph.</hi> 8:22</cell>
						<cell>B IV, hom. 116, p. 263-264; hom. 144, p. 903; B VI, hom. 203, p. 183
							[795]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>King’s daughter <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܬ ܡܠܟܐ</foreign> (p. 67, 86) </cell>
						<cell>Ps. 45:9-16; cf. Exod. 2:5-10</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 5, 21 › Church (Sermo II, 3, CSCO 311, p.
							63, 75, 77) </cell>
						<cell>A II, hom. 73, c. 188-190 › Church (B I, hom. 22, p. 538; B II, hom.
							34, p. 45; B III, hom. 74, p. 203; A II, hom. 74, c. 347-348) </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Thirsty earth <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܪܥܐ ܨܗܝܬܐ</foreign> (p. 47) </cell>
						<cell>Ps. 63:1; 72:6; Isa. 53:2</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 1, 11; 4, 84; 9, 4; 18, 13; 26, 6; Sermo
							II, 3, 304-307 (CSCO 311, p. 62); (cf.<hi rend="italic"> Fid.</hi> 12,
							10)</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>City <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܝܢܬܐ</foreign> (p. 73) </cell>
						<cell> Ps 72:16 (cf. Ps 60:9; 108:10) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>Cf. B V, hom. 163, p. 399;<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܡܕܝܢܬ ܬܘܩܦܐ
							</foreign>B VI, hom. 201, p. 135 [747] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Veil <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܫܦܐ</foreign> (p. 104) </cell>
						<cell>Prov. 30:4</cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic"> Fid.</hi> 10:14-15</cell>
						<cell>B II, hom. 43, p. 236; B III, hom. 80, p. 314; B IV, <pb n="347"/>
							hom. 133, p. 743-745; B VI, hom. 203, p. 185-187 [797-798]; A I, 9, c.
							154; 13, c. 114-115;</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Ship <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܦܐ</foreign> (p. 5, 16, 47, 84, 96,
							123) </cell>
						<cell>Cf. Prov. 31:14</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 196, p. 4 [616];<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܐܠܦܐ ܢܛܝܪܬܐ
							</foreign>hom. 201, p. 135 [747]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Dove <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܢܐ</foreign> (p. 48) </cell>
						<cell>Cf. Cant 6:9</cell>
						<cell>- › Christ (<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 26, 8) </cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 201, p. 116, 130, 135, 147 [728, 742, 747, 759]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Locked garden and sealed fountain <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܢܬܐ ܐܚܝܕܬܐ
								ܘܡܥܝܢܐ ܛܒܝܥܬܐ</foreign> (p. 73) </cell>
						<cell>Cant 4:12</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Swift Cloud <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܢܐ ܩܠܝܠܬܐ</foreign> (p. 54, 64,
							69, 180) </cell>
						<cell>Isa. 19:1</cell>
						<cell>- ›<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܥܢܢܐ ܢܗܝܪܬܐ</foreign> Sog. II, 4; cf. Fid.
							41,1; 81, 4 </cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 201, p. 130 [742]; hom. 203, p. 183 [795]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Chariot <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܟܒܬܐ</foreign> (p. 15, 38, 40, 65,
							73, 142, 158, 183) </cell>
						<cell>Ezek. 1:4-28</cell>
						<cell>Sog. I, 44; III, 4 Cf. <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 18, 5 </cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 196, p. 4 [616]; hom. 197, p. 43 [655]; hom. 198, p. 52, 65
							[664, 677]; hom. 199, p. 82 [694]; hom. <pb n="348"/> 201, p. 109-110,
							128, 132, 154 [721-722, 740, 744, 766], hom. 203, p. 181, 190 [793, 802]
							etc.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Closed Door <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܪܥܐ ܕܐܚܝܕ</foreign> (p. 73, 111,
							177, 181, 190) </cell>
						<cell>Ezek. 44: 1-2</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom. 80, p. 314; hom. 94, p. 584; B V, hom. 164, p. 436; B VI,
							hom. 196, p. 4 [616]; hom. 199, p. 83, 89 [695, 701]; hom. 203, p. 183
							[795]; <hi rend="italic">Against Jews</hi>, 6 (PO 38/1, p. 168).</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
			</div>
			<pb n="349"/>
			<div xml:lang="en" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.appendix.2">
				<head>APPENDIX 2</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Table of particular Marian titles and epithets used in the <hi rend="italic"
						>Šḥimo</hi> with their parallel occurrences in Ephrem and Jacob of Serugh </p>
				<table>
					<row rend="bold">
						<cell>Titles, epithets</cell>
						<cell>Ephrem</cell>
						<cell>Jacob of Serugh</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Daughter of the poor <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܬ ܡܣ̈ܟܢܐ</foreign> (p.
							48) </cell>
						<cell> Sog. II, 2</cell>
						<cell>B I, Hom. 6, p. 128; B VI, hom. 196, p. 4, 14 [616, 626]; hom. 198, p.
							55 [667]; hom. 199, p. 81 [693]; hom. 201, 110 [722]; A I, 1, c.
							25</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Prophetess <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܒܝܬܐ </foreign> (p. 48) </cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Diat.</hi> 2, 6</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Light <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܘܗܪܐ</foreign> (p. 186) <foreign
								xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܗ ܕܢܘܗܪܐ</foreign> (p. 178) </cell>
						<cell>Christic title; Mary is the eye or the earth which receives the
							light.</cell>
						<cell>Christic title; Mary is the Mother of the Light <foreign
								xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܐ ܕܢܘܗܪܐ</foreign> B VI, hom. 197, p. 37 [649];
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>East <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܢܚܐ</foreign> (p. 48) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>B III, hom 93, p. 566; B VI, hom. 198, p. 56-57 [668-669]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Second heaven <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܡܝܐ ܕܬܪܬܝܢ</foreign> (p. 16,
							64, 68, 87, 130, 158) </cell>
						<cell>Cf. <hi rend="italic">Fid.</hi> 81,4; <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi>
							23,11; Sog. II, 10-11</cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 196, p. 3 [615]; hom. 198, p. 51-54 [663-666];<foreign
								xml:lang="syr"> ܫܡܝܐ ܚܕܬܐ </foreign>hom. 201, p. 132 [744]</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Palace <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܪܬܐ</foreign> (p. 83-84) <foreign
								xml:lang="syr">ܒܺܝܪܰܬ ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ</foreign> (p. 68) </cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܺܝܪܰܬ ܡܠܟܐ܆ ܩܕܘܫ ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ </foreign><hi
								rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 17, 5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܝܟܠ
								ܡܠܟܐ</foreign>
							<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 12, 2 </cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 201, p. 130 [742];<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܒܺܝܪܬܐ ܕܒܣܪܐ
							</foreign>hom. 201, p. 131 [743];<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܒܺܝܪܬܐ ܦܐܝܬܐ
							</foreign>B VI, hom. 196, p. 4 [616];<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܒܺܝܪܬܐ
								ܕܟܝܬܐ </foreign>hom. 201, p. 139 [751]; <foreign xml:lang="syr"
								>ܒܺܝܪܰܬ ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ </foreign>hom. 197, p. 29 [641] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Dwelling of the Most High <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܟܝܢܬܐ
								ܕܡܪܝܡܐ</foreign> (p. 150) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܟܝܢܬܐ ܕܐܠܗܘܬܐ </foreign>B VI, hom. 197, p. 37
							[649]; <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܗܐ ܒܟܝ ܫܪܝܐ ܫܟܝܢܬܐ ܕܪܡܐ</foreign> hom.
							201, p. 132 [744] </cell>
					</row>
					<pb n="350"/>
					<row>
						<cell>Glorious throne <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܪܘܢܘܣ ܓܐܝܐ</foreign> (p. 183) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܒܥܟܝ ܕܟܝܐ ܬܪܘܢܘܣ ܓܐܝܐ </foreign>B VI, hom.
							201, p. 132 [744] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Shrine of the Godhead <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܘܣܐ ܕܐܠܗܘܬܐ</foreign>
							(p. 183),<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܢܘܣܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ ܩܕܝܫܐ </foreign>(p. 158) </cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܬ ܡܥܡܪܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ </foreign><hi rend="italic"
								>Diat.</hi> 2, 6 </cell>
						<cell><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܘܣܐ ܕܟܝܐ</foreign> B VI, hom. 196, p. 9, 26
							[621, 638]; hom. 201, p. 126-127 [738-739] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Holy Storehouse <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘܨܪ ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ</foreign> (p. 180) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܠܝܬ ܩܘ̈ܕܫܐ</foreign> hom. 197, p. 43 [655]
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Dwelling in which the mysteries were preserved <foreign xml:lang="syr"
								>ܕܝܪܐ ܕܐܪ̈ܙܐ ܢܛܝܪܝܢ ܨܝܕܝܗ̇</foreign> (p. 47) </cell>
						<cell>- › Christ is<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܓܙܐ ܕܐܪ̈ܙܐ </foreign>(<hi
								rend="italic">Fid.</hi> 9,12) </cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܩܒܘܬܐ ܕܡܠܝܐ ܐܪ̈ܙܐ܆ ܐܪܘܢܐ ܕܡܠܐ ܐܪ̈ܙܐ</foreign> B
							VI, hom. 197, p. 37 [649]; hom. 198, p. 59 [671] <foreign xml:lang="syr"
								>ܠܡܐܢܐ ܕܐܪ̈ܙܐ</foreign> hom. 197, p. 29 [641]; </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Mystery of purity <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܟܦܬܐ ܕܐܪ̈ܙܐ</foreign> (p.
							16) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܠܝܬ ܐܪ̈ܙܐ</foreign> hom. 199, p. 82 [694]
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Full of beauty <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܠܝܬ ܫܘܦܪ̈ܐ</foreign> (p. 16,
							47, 48, 74, 165, 178) </cell>
						<cell>- Cf. <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 11, 2 </cell>
						<cell>B VI, hom. 196, p. 4-5 [616-617]; hom. 197, p. 29 [641] etc.</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Veil which is spread over the creation <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܘܐܠܐ
								ܕܦܪܝܣ ܥܠ ܒܪ̈ܝܬܐ</foreign> (p. 47) See Veil above </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Pearl <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܓܢܝܬܐ</foreign> (p. 30, 69) </cell>
						<cell>Her virginity: <hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 12, 7</cell>
						<cell>Her virginity: B VI, hom. 201, p. 135-136 [747-748]</cell>
					</row>
					<pb n="351"/>
					<row>
						<cell>Harbour and place of rest for the World <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܡܐܢܐ
								[ܘܢܘܚܐ ܕܥܠܡܐ]</foreign> (p. 48) </cell>
						<cell><hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 9, 4; Christic title (<hi rend="italic"
								>Nat.</hi> 19, 18) </cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܡܐܢܐ ܕܐܪ̈ܙܐ</foreign> B VI, hom. 197, p. 29
							[641] ›<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܡܐܢܐ ܘܢܘܚܐ </foreign>is the altar (B I,
							hom. 22, p. 539) </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Letter containing our prayers <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܓܪܬܐ</foreign>
							(p. 168) </cell>
						<cell>-</cell>
						<cell>- › Sealed letter<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܐܓܪܬܐ ܚܬܝܡܬܐ </foreign>(cf.
							Is 29:11) B VI, hom. 196, p. 24 [636] </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell>Vine <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܦܬܐ</foreign> (p. 167) </cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܬܐ ܨܗܝܬܐ</foreign>
							<hi rend="italic">Nat.</hi> 8, 8 </cell>
						<cell>
							<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܬܐ ܒܬܘܠܬܐ</foreign> B VI, hom. 198, p. 55
							[667]; hom. 201, p. 119 [731]; hom. 203, p. 192 [804] </cell>
					</row>
				</table>
			</div>
			<pb n="352"/>
			<div xml:lang="syr" xml:id="hv23n2akhrass.appendix.3">
				<head xml:lang="en">APPENDIX 3</head>
				<p xml:lang="en">Marian verses attributed to Jacob of Serugh in the <hi
						rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, without parallels in his published homilies</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 16</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܨܠܽܘܬܶܟܝ̱ ܥܰܡܰܢ ܐܳܘ ܡܒܰܪܰܟܬܳܐ ܨܠܽܘܬܶܟܝ̱ ܥܰܡܰܢ: ܠܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܶܟܝ̱ ܢܶܫܡܰܥ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ
					ܘܰܢܚܰܣܶܐ ܠܰܢ܀ ܡܰܠܝܰܬ ܪܰܚܡܶܐ ܐܰܦܺܝܣܝ̱ ܘܰܒܥܳܝ ܠܰܡܠܶܐ ܪܰܚܡܶܐ: ܕܢܶܥܒܶܕ ܪܰܚܡܶܐ ܥܰܠ
					ܢܰܦܫܳܬܳܐ ܕܫܳܐܠܳܢ ܪܰܚܡܶܐ܀ ܒܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܳܗ̇ ܕܗܳܝ ܕܰܛܥܶܢܬܳܟ ܝܰܪ̈ܚܶܐ ܬܶܫܥܳܐ܆ ܒܰܪ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ
					ܐܰܥܒܰܪ ܡܶܢܰܢ ܫܰܒ̈ܛܶܐ ܕܪܽܘܓܙܳܐ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi> ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܰܐܒܳܐ
					ܕܰܓܒܳܐ ܠܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܕܡܶܣܟܺܢ̱ܬܳܐ ܗ̱ܘܳܬ: ܘܣܶܓܕܬܳܐ ܠܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܡܶܣܟܺܢܳܐܺܝܬ ܢܚܶܬ ܘܰܫܪܳܐ ܒܳܗ̇.
					ܬܰܘܕܺܝ ܠܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܕܰܒܡܶܣ̈ܟܺܢܶܐ ܦܫܺܝܩ ܠܶܗ ܕܢܶܥܡܰܪ: ܚܰܕ ܗ̱ܽܘ ܟܝܳܢܳܐ ܕܰܬܠܳܬܰܝ̈ܗܽܘܢ ܠܶܗ
					ܬܶܫܒܽܘܚܬܳܐ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 74</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܰܐܒܳܐ ܕܫܰܕܰܪ ܥܺܝܪܳܐ ܘܣܰܒܪܳܗ̇ ܠܡܰܪܝܰܡ: ܘܣܶܓܕܬܳܐ ܠܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܥܰܡ ܒܰܪ̱ܬ ܩܳܠܶܗ
					ܢܚܶܬ ܘܰܫܪܳܐ ܒܳܗ̇. ܬܰܘܕܺܝ ܠܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܕܕܰܟܝܳܗ̇ ܘܡܰܪܩܳܗ̇ ܘܟܶܢ ܐܰܓܶܢ ܒܳܗ̇: ܘܰܥܠܰܝܢ
					ܪ̈ܰܚܡܶܐ ܒܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܳܗ̇ ܒܟܽܠܥܶܕܳܢܺܝ̈ܢ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 90</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܰܐܒܳܐ ܕܰܓܒܳܐ ܠܡܰܪܝܰܡ: ܕܡܰܟܺܝܟܳܐ ܗ̱ܘܳܬ: ܘܣܶܓܕܬܳܐ ܠܰܒܪܳܐ ܕܡܰܟܺܝܟܳܐܺܝܬ
					ܢܚܶܬ ܘܰܫܪܳܐ ܒܳܗ̇. ܬܰܘܕܺܝ ܠܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܕܰܒܡܰܟܺܝ̈ܟܶܐ ܦܫܺܝܩ ܠܶܗ ܕܢܶܥܡܰܪ: ܚܰܕ ܗ̱ܽܘ ܟܝܳܢܳܐ
					ܕܰܬܠܳܬܰܝܗܽܘܢ ܠܶܗ ܬܶܫܒܽܘܚܬܳܐ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 47-48</p>
				<pb n="535"/>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܐܶܠܦܳܐ ܛܥܺܝܢܰܬ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܚܰܕ̈ܬܶܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܒܺܝܪܬܳܐ ܕܡܰܠܟܳܐ ܢܚ̣ܶܬ
					ܘܰܫܪܳܐ ܒܳܗ̇. ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܓܰܢܬܳܐ ܕܺܐܝܬ ܒܳܗ̇ ܫܰܒܛܳܐ ܦܫܺܝܛܳܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱
					ܕܰܝܪܳܐ ܕܐ̱ܪ̈ܳܙܶܐ ܢܛܺܝܪܺܝܢ ܨܶܐܕܶܝܗ̇܀ ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܗܕܺܝܪܬܳܐ ܒܢܶܫ̈ܶܐ ܘܡܰܠܝܰܬ
					ܫܽܘܦܪ̈ܶܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܘܺܝܠܳܐ ܕܰܦܪܺܝܣ ܥܰܠ ܒܶܪ̈ܝܳܬܳܐ. ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܙܰܕܝܩܽܘܬܳܐ
					ܕܠܳܐ ܐܶܬܢܰܟܝܰܬ. ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܚܰܘܳܐ ܕܝܶܠܕܰܬ ܠܥܰܡܰܢܽܘܐܶܝܠ܀ ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܛܠܺܝܬܳܐ
					ܦܐܺܝܬܳܐ ܘܡܰܠܝܰܬ ܫܽܘܦܪ̈ܶܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܝܰܘܢܳܐ ܕܪܰܒܝܰܬ ܠܢܶܫܪܳܐ ܡܰܠܟܳܐ. ܬܳܝ
					ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܟܰܠܬܳܐ ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܘܠܳܐ ܡܙܰܘܰܓܬܳܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܠܡܺܐܢܳܐ ܘܢܰܘܚܳܐ ܕܟܽܠܶܗ
					ܥܳܠܡܳܐ܀ ܬܳܝ ܒܰܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܡܰܕܢܚܳܐ ܕܝܶܠܕܰܬ ܠܡܳܪܶܐ ܢܽܘܗܪ̈ܶܐ: ܫܠܳܡܳܐ ܥܰܡܶܟܝ̱ ܢܒܺܝܬܐ
					ܕܛܶܥܢܰܬ ܠܡܳܪܶܐ ܢܒܺܝ̈ܶܐ. ܠܶܗ ܬܶܫܒܽܘܚܬܳܐ ܘܠܶܟܝ̱ ܐܺܝܩܳܪܳܐ ܘܠܶܗ ܪܽܘܡܪܳܡܳܐ: ܘܰܥܠܰܝܢ
					ܪ̈ܰܚܡܶܐ ܒܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܶܟܝ̱ ܒܟܽܠ ܥܶܕ̈ܳܢܺܝܢ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 104</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܡܰܢ ܗ̱ܺܝ ܗܳܕܶܐ ܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ ܕܩܳܝܡܳܐ ܒܕܳܪ̈ܰܝ ܥܳܠܡ̈ܶܐ: ܘܠܳܐ ܝܳܗܒܳܐ ܠܶܗ ܠܚܶܫܟܐ ܕܢܰܡܠܶܟ
					ܥܰܠ ܒܶܪ̈ܝܳܬܐ. ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܐܺܝܬܶܝܗ̇ ܕܰܒܦܰܪܨܽܘܦܳܗ̇ ܨܺܝܪ ܐܺܝܡܳܡܳܐ: ܘܡܳܐ ܕܰܡܡܰܠܠܳܐ ܫܶܡܫܳܐ
					ܕܳܢܰܚ ܡܶܢ ܣܶܦ̈ܘܳܬܳܗ̇܀ ܡܰܠܶܠܝ̱ ܡܰܠܶܠܝ̱ ܡܰܠܶܠܝ̱ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܕܫܰܦܺܝܪ ܗ̱ܽܘ ܠܶܟܝ̱: ܕܳܡܶܐ
					ܠܺܝ ܓܶܝܪ ܡܰܡܠ̱ܠܳܐ ܕܦܽܘܡܶܟܝ̱ ܠܰܕܓܰܒܪܺܐܶܝܠ. ܐܳܡܪܳܐ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܕܠܺܝ ܛܽܘܒܰܝ ܠܺܝ ܕܡܰܠܟܳܐ
					ܝܶܠܕܶܬ: ܘܰܥܒܺܝܕܳܐ ܐ̱ܢܳܐ ܡܪܰܒܝܳܢܺܝܬܳܐ ܠܰܡܠܶܟ ܡܰܠܟ̈ܶܐ܀ ܗܳܝ ܫܽܘܫܶܦܳܐ ܕܪܶܣܡܰܬ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ
					ܒܽܐܘܪܚܶܗ ܕܥܳܠܡܳܐ: ܬܦܺܝܣ ܘܰܬܫܰܕܰܪ ܠܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܰܢ ܨܶܝܕ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ. <pb n="354"/> ܗܺܝ
					ܐܳܡܪܳܐ ܠܶܗ ܠܡܳܪܳܗ̇ ܘܰܒܪܳܗ̇ ܐܳܦ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܗ̇: ܕܚܽܘܣ ܥܰܠ ܥܳܠܡܳܐ ܕܡܶܛܽܠܳܬܶܗ ܚܰܫܳܐ
					ܣܰܝܒܰܪܬ܀ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܟ ܬܶܩܥܶܐ ܗܳܝ ܠܶܓܝܽܘܢܳܐ ܕܒܶܝܬ ܓܰܒܪܺܐܶܝܠ: ܘܝܰܬܺܝܪ ܡܶܢܗܽܘܢ ܐܶܬܚܰܙܝܰܬ
					ܠܰܢ ܗܺܝ ܒܰܪ̱ܬ ܕܘܺܝܕ. ܢܫܰܒܚܽܘܢ ܥܺܝܪ̈ܶܐ ܘܰܒܢܰܝ̈ܢܳܫܳܐ ܕܺܐܝܬ ܥܰܠ ܐܰܪܥܳܐ: ܠܗܰܘ ܕܰܕܢܰܚ
					ܠܰܢ ܡܶܢ ܕܰܟܝܽܘܬܳܗ̇ ܨܠܽܘܬܳܗ̇ ܥܰܡܰܢ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 130-131</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱ ܡܰܪܝܰܡ ܘܛܽܘܒܳܐ ܠܢܰܦܫܶܟܝ̱ ܛܽܘܒܳܢܺܝܬܳܐ: ܕܪܰܒ ܗ̱ܽܘ ܛܽܘܒܶܟܝ̱ ܐܳܦ ܡܶܢ ܛܽܘܒܐ
					ܕܟܽܠ ܛܽܘܒܳܢ̈ܶܐ. ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱ ܕܰܛܥܶܢܬܝ̱ ܥܰܦܶܩܬܝ̱ ܚܰܒܶܒܬܝ̱ ܐܰܝܟ ܕܰܠܫܰܒܪܳܐ: ܠܓܰܢ̱ܒܳܪ
					ܥܳܠܡ̈ܶܐ ܕܰܛܥܺܝ̣ܢ ܠܰܐܪܥܳܐ ܒܪܶܡܙܶܗ ܟܰܣܝܳܐ܀ ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱ ܕܡܶܢܶܟܝ̱ ܕܢܰܚ ܦܳܪܽܘܩܳܐ ܥܰܠ
					ܓܳܠܽܘܬܳܐ: ܘܰܠܫܰܒܳܝܳܗ̇ ܦܟܰܪ ܒܰܛܢܳܢܶܗ ܘܫܰܝܶܢ ܐܰܪܥܳܐ. ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱ ܕܶܐܬܬܣܺܝܡ ܦܽܘܡܶܟܝ̱
					ܕܰܟܝܳܐ ܥܰܠ ܣܶܦܘ̈ܳܬܶܗ: ܕܗܰܘ ܕܰܣܪ̈ܳܦܶܐ ܕܢܽܘܪܳܐ ܟܳܘܙܺܝܢ ܡܶܢ ܓܰܘܙܰܠܬܶܗ܀ ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱
					ܕܪܰܒܺܝܬܝ̱ ܒܚܰܠܒܶܟܝ̱ ܢܰܩܕܳܐ ܐܰܝܟ ܕܰܠܫܰܒܪܳܐ: ܠܰܬܕܳܐ ܕܝܳܢܩܺܝܢ ܥܳܠܡ̈ܶܐ ܡܶܢܶܗ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ
					ܘܢܽܘܗܪܳܐ. ܛܽܘܒܰܝܟܝ̱ ܕܪܳܥܶܡ ܝܽܘܡ ܕܽܘܟܪܳܢܶܟܝ̱ ܒܰܐܪܒܰܥ ܦܶܢ̈ܝܳܢ: ܘܰܡܙܰܝܚܺܝܢ ܠܶܗ
					ܥܺܝܪ̈ܶܐ ܘܐ̱ܢܳܫ̈ܳܐ ܩܰܕܺܝܫܳܐܺܝܬ܀ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܪܳܡܳܐ ܕܰܫܒܰܩ ܠܪ̈ܳܡܶܐ ܘܟܽܠ ܓܰܐܝ̈ܳܬܳܐ:
					ܘܰܒܡܽܘܟܳܟܶܗ ܫܪܳܐ ܒܡܶܣܟܺܢ̱ܬܳܐ ܒܰܪ̱ܬ ܚܳܕܽܘܪ̈ܶܐ. ܛܳܒܳܐ ܕܰܐܘܪܶܒ ܕܽܘܟܪܳܢ ܐܶܡܶܗ ܚܰܣܳܐ
					ܒܪ̈ܰܚܡܰܝܟ: ܠܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܘܡܺܝ̈ܬܶܐ ܕܝܰܩܰܪܘ̱ ܥܺܐܕܳܗ̇ ܨܠܽܘܬܳܗ̇ ܥܰܡܰܢ܀ <hi rend="centered"
						>***</hi>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="italic">Šḥimo</hi>, p. 158-159</p>
				<p xml:lang="syr"> ܬܰܘ ܦܳܪ̈ܽܘܫܶܐ ܒܚܽܘܒܳܐ ܪܰܒܳܐ ܘܗܰܝܡܳܢܽܘܬܳܐ: ܢܝܰܩܰܪ ܘܢܰܘܪܶܒ ܝܽܘܡ ܥܰܕܥܺܐܕܳܗ̇
					ܕܛܽܘܒܳܢܺܝܬܳܐ. <pb/> ܒܫܰܗܪ̈ܶܐ ܡܬܺܝ̈ܚܶܐ ܘܩܰܘܡ̈ܶܐ ܐܰܡܺܝ̈ܢܶܐ ܘܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܳܐ: ܕܝܳܗܒܳܐ
					ܒܰܐܥ̈ܦܶܐ ܐܰܓܪܳܐ ܠܰܐܝܢܳܐ ܕܰܡܝܰܩܰܪ ܠܳܗ̇܀ ܬܳܝ ܩܰܕܺܝܫܬܳܐ ܘܦܰܠܶܓܝ̱ ܕܳܫ̈ܢܶܐ ܒܝܽܘܡ
					ܥܰܕܥܺܐܕܶܟܝ̱: ܠܟܶܢܫܰܢ ܕܰܨܗܶܐ ܠܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܶܟܝ̱ ܘܰܠܒܳܥ̈ܘܳܬܶܟܝ̱. ܢܶܗܘܶܐ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܫܽܘܪܳܐ
					ܠܟܶܢܫܳܐ ܕܰܡܝܰܩܰܪ ܠܶܟܝ̱: ܘܢܶܙܓܽܘܪ ܡܶܢܰܢ ܟܽܠ ܡܰܚ̈ܘܳܬܳܐ ܘܫܰܒ̈ܛܶܐ ܕܪܽܘܓܙܳܐ܀ ܚܰܝܠܳܐ
					ܕܚܰܝܠܶܟܝ̱ ܢܚܰܝܶܠ ܠܟܶܢܫܰܢ ܥܰܠ ܩܽܘܠܳܣܰܝ̈ܟܝ̱: ܘܰܢܙܰܡܶܢ ܠܰܢ ܠܰܓܢܽܘܢ ܢܽܘܗܪܳܐ
					ܒܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܶܟܝ̱. ܒܓܽܘ̈ܕܶܐ ܕܥܺܝ̣ܪ̈ܶܐ ܢܶܡܢܶܐ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܠܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܘܡܺܝ̈ܬܶܐ: ܕܙܰܝܰܚܘ̱
					ܥܺܐܕܶܟܝ̱ ܘܶܐܚܰܕܘ̱ ܓܰܘܣܳܐ ܒܰܨܠܰܘ̈ܳܬܶܟܝ̱܀ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܫܰܦܝܳܐ ܒܩܺܝܢܬܳܐ ܚܠܺܝܬܳܐ ܥܰܡ
					ܗܽܘ̈ܠܳܠܶܐ: ܬܶܣܰܩ ܠܳܟ ܡܳܪܝ̱ ܡܶܢ ܡܰܪܥܺܝܬܳܟ ܒܕܽܘܟܪܳܢ ܐܶܡܳܟ. ܚܬܽܘܡ ܒܰܨܠܺܝܒܳܟ
					ܬܰܪ̈ܥܶܝܗ̇ ܪ̈ܳܡܶܐ ܡܶܢ ܢܶܟܝ̈ܳܢܶܐ: ܕܬܰܣܶܩ ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܳܟ ܡܳܪܝ̱ ܘܠܰܐܒܽܘܟ ܘܰܠܪܽܘܚ
					ܩܽܘܕܫܳܐ܀ <hi rend="centered">***</hi>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
