<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Griechische Philosophie und Wissenschaft bei den Ostsyrern: Zum
					Gedenken an Mār Addai Scher (1867-1915)</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>Yury</forename>
						<surname>Arzhanov</surname>
					</name>
					<affiliation>
						<orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
					</affiliation>
				</author>
				<sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
				<editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
				<editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2prarzhanov</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Yury Arzhanov</author>
						<title level="a">Griechische Philosophie und Wissenschaft bei den Ostsyrern:
							Zum Gedenken an Mār Addai Scher (1867-1915)</title>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2PRArzhanov.pdf</idno>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="422" to="425">422-425</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="7"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
			<change when="2020-08-30">File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="review">
		<body>
			<div type="title" xml:lang="en">
				<ab type="review-title">M. Perkams and A. M. Schilling, eds., <hi rend="italic">
						Griechische Philosophie und Wissenschaft bei den Ostsyrern: Zum Gedenken an
						Mār Addai Scher (1867–1915)</hi>(Berlin: de Gruyter, 2020). Pp. ix + 214;
					€79.95.</ab>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p> This volume, edited by M. Perkams and A. M. Schilling, goes back to a colloquium
					held at the University of Jena (Germany) on the occasion of the 100th
					anniversary of the tragic death of Mar Addai Scher, who fell victim to the
					Armenian and Assyrian genocide in 1915. The book principally consists of the
					papers presented at the colloquium and is supplemented by three other essays.
					The volume aims to present an up-to-date overview of research on the reception
					of Greek philosophy in the East Syriac (hereafter: ES) schools in the late
					antique and early medieval periods. This goal is met, even though the word <hi
						rend="italic">Wissenschaft</hi> in the title of the book is misleading since
					the volume contains no contribution to the history of natural sciences in the ES
					schools, a desideratum which Perkams notes in his introduction. However, the
					German word <hi rend="italic">Wissenschaft</hi> can refer not only to science
					but also to knowledge or learning in general, and it is probably this meaning
					that justifies its place in the title, for in his introduction Perkams speaks of
					“christ-liche Wissenstradition.” </p>
				<p> Various contributions focus on one of two areas which traditionally have
					constituted main points of scholarly interest: forms of education in the ES
					schools (primarily the famous school of Nisibis) and the reception of Greek
					philosophy (with special focus on Aristotelian logic). The book gives attention
					also to the figure and legacy of Addai Scher, the Chaldean bishop of Siirt. </p>
				<p> In the introduction, Perkams outlines several characteristics of the ES
					tradition of philosophy, upon which he further elaborates in his article
					“Ostsyrische Philosophie: Die Rezeption und Ausarbeitung griechischen Denkens in
					der Schule von Nisibis bis Barḥaḏbšabbā.” Thus, Perkams approaches ES philosophy
					primarily in terms of the reception of the Greek <pb n="423"/> literary heritage
					and in the context of education; this constitutes also the approach taken by
					most other contributors. </p>
				<p> M. Heimgartner, in his article on the knowledge of Greek philosophy by the ES
					catholicos Timothy I, states that in the time of Timothy the term “Greek
					philosophy” was constituted from two elements: Aristotle’s logic and patristic
					literature. Heimgartner stresses that cultural and political factors stimulated
					Timothy’s interest in Aristotelian works: the language of logic was applicable
					both to polemics against other Christian groups and to dialogue with the Muslim
					elite. </p>
				<p> N. Kavvadas’ essay elaborates on the latter aspect, i.e., the<hi rend="italic">
						Sitz im Leben</hi> of Aristotelian logic in the ES schools, and presents a
					number of notable cases of what the author calls “Jargon der Logik.” In the
					examples given, Kavvadas discovers similar patterns in the use of Greek logical
					terminology, which turns out to be an instrument of power (“Sprache der Macht”).
					This pattern most likely goes back to the philosophical and rhetorical training
					of the Christian elite. This training included Aristotelian logic for polemical
					purposes and aimed at providing students with a powerful instrument for
					confronting both Christian and non-Christian opponents. </p>
				<p> Such an approach towards Greek philosophy brings the ES educated elite close to
					their WS counterpart. This observation is supported by several essays that
					present a number of case studies, the results of which generally point in the
					same direction, namely, to the idea of an interdependence of ES and WS
					traditions. J. O. Schmitt revisits the question of Barhebraeus’ use of ES
					sources and concludes that the WS maphrian was generally “open-minded towards
					the Church of the East.” A. M. Schilling offers a detailed analysis of the
					so-called “Koran-Florilegium,” preserved by the twelfth-century WS author
					Dionysius bar Ṣalībī, which turns out to be dependent upon an eighth-century
					work of the ES catholicos Timothy I. M. Perkams demonstrates that the <hi
						rend="italic">Cause of the Foundation of the Schools</hi>, written in the
					early seventh century by Barḥadbšabbā, to a large extent depends upon the <hi
						rend="italic">Commentary on the Categories Addressed to Theodore</hi>,
					composed in the early sixth century by <pb n="424"/> Sergius of Rēšʿaynā. E.
					Fiori’s evaluation of the references to Dionysius the Areopagite by ES authors
					shows that their knowledge of the <hi rend="italic">Corpus Dionysiacum</hi> was
					second-hand and derived most likely from monastic florilegia. Fiori’s article
					points at the need for a more detailed analysis of the forms of transmission of
					Greek philosophical works, not only in ES but also in WS sources. </p>
				<p> All contributions mentioned thus far present the ES philosophical tradition not
					as an isolated phenomenon, but as part of a broader process of a Syriac
					reception of the Greek philosophical heritage. This process was to a large
					extent shaped by new forms of Christian education at both the ES and WS schools.
					Two articles published in the volume deal specifically with the ES educational
					system. A. Becker sums up the main points of his monograph, which appeared in
					2006. Thus, speaking about the ES schools, he stresses their relation to the
					Babylonian rabbinic educational system and highlights their general rejection of
					classical rhetorical education in favor of monastic ascetic practice.
					Additionally, Becker describes in his essay the role Addai Scher played in the
					modern “recovery of East Syrian scholastic culture.” Both Scher’s catalogues of
					Syriac manuscripts preserved in the monastic libraries, and his editions of
					historical sources, such as the works of Barḥadbšabbā and Theodore Bar Kōnī,
					greatly contributed to our knowledge of the intellectual life of the Church of
					the East. At the same time, Becker asks how the educational background of Scher
					himself might have shaped his understanding of the history of the Church, and
					thus also our understanding of it. U. Possekel’s article on the School of
					Nisibis re-examines the extant sources on this most famous ES educational
					establishment. Based mainly on the <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>, the article
					outlines the school’s history, structure, and educational profile, and points
					out the school’s legal and financial autonomy, and even a certain autonomy from
					the local bishop. The author draws parallels between the mechanisms of
					succession of leadership in Nisibis and the non-Christian Greek philosophical
					schools of <pb n="425"/> Athens and Alexandria, thus stressing the similarity
					between ES and Greek late antique school systems. </p>
				<p> The volume contains an extensive bibliography, divided into sources and
					scholarly literature, which covers works referenced in all the contributions. A
					short but informative general index helps navigating the volume. Both the
					bibliography and the index furnish English titles and keywords alongside the German ones, thus enlarging the
					possible audience of the publication. Overall, the book is a useful collection
					of studies which, taken together, give a systematic and up-to-date picture of
					the history of reception of Greek philosophy in the Church of the East and of
					its school system in the late antique and early medieval periods. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
