<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">The Syriacs of Kharberd (Kharput) on the Eve of the 1915 Genocide</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>Arman</forename>
						<surname>Akopian</surname>
					</name>
					<affiliation>
						<orgName>Independent Scholar</orgName>
					</affiliation>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2akopian</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Arman Akopian, PhD</author>
						<title level="a">The Syriacs of Kharberd (Kharput) on the Eve of the 1915 Genocide</title>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2Akopian.pdf</idno>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23>">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="279" to="321">279&#8211;321</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="3"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
				<!-- ILeave this as is -->
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:lang="en">
					<term>Sayfo</term>
					<term>1915 Genocide</term>
					<term>Ottoman Empire</term>
					<term>Millet System</term>
					<term>Kharberd</term>
					<term>Kharput</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
<change when="2020-09-07">File updated and published by James E. Walters</change>
			<change when="2020-08-09">?File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="article">
		<front>
			<div type="abstract">
				<head>Abstract</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The paper addresses the plight of the Syriac communities in the
					Ottoman Empire in the 19th century and on the eve of the 1915 Genocide. In
					particular, it addresses the status of these communities within the Ottoman
					millet system, discusses the spoken languages of the Syriacs, and their
					relations with the Armenians. As for the specific case of the Syriacs of
					Kharberd (Kharput), the paper presents historical evidence of their presence in
					the city, provides snapshots of their social, economic and religious lives,
					educational system and local press. The paper shows that the Syriacs of Kharberd
					were destined to share the fate ofthe Armenians during the 1915 Genocide and
					briefly presents their expatriate communities in the United States. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2akopian.1" xml:lang="en">
				<p> Before World War I, the estimated number of Syriac Christians in the Ottoman
					Empire was approximately 619,000 <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 1 D. Gaunt, <hi rend="italic">Massacres, resistance,
								protectors: Muslim-Christian relations in Eastern Anatolia during
								World War I</hi>, (Gorgias Press, 2006), 28. The author proposed but
							did not insist on this number after a thorough analysis of all available
							data which eventually resulted in combining the data of the <pb n="280"
							/> Assyro-Chaldean delegation at the Paris peace conference with those
							of the Armenian Patriarchate of Constantinople. </p></note> . <pb
						n="280"/> According to the Armenian Patriarchate of Constantinople, more
					than one fifth of them lived in the Armenian vilayets: 60,000 in Diyarbakir,
					25,000 in Sebastia, 18,000 in Van, 15,000 in Bitlis and 5,000 in Kharberd. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> 2 M. Léart, (Krikor
							Zohrap), <hi rend="italic">La question armeniénne à la lumière des
								documents</hi> (Paris, 1913) (<ref
								target="http://armenews.com/IMG/La_question_Armenienne_a_la_lumiere_des_documents_1913.pdf"
								>http://armenews.com/IMG/La_question_Armenienne_a_la_lumiere_des_documents_1913.pdf</ref>);
							J. McCarthy, <hi rend="italic">Muslims and Minorities: The Population of
								Ottoman Anatolia and the End of the Empire</hi> (New York University
							Press, 1983), 102-03. </p></note> The followers of the Syriac Orthodox
					Church of Antioch were the majority among the Ottoman Syriacs. The areas of
					their compact habitation included Tur-Abdin (in Aramaic, “a mountain of [God’s]
					worshipers”, east of Mardin), which is a part of the ancient Aramean homeland
					and one of the oldest centers of Syriac monasticism. </p>
				<p> The followers of the Church of the East mostly lived in the vilayet of Van,
					including the highlands of Hakkari (from Syriac <hi rend="italic">akkareh</hi>,
					“farmers, ploughmen” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p xml:lang="en"> 3
							S. Brock, G. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Gorgias concise
								Syriac-English/English-Syriac dictionary</hi> (Gorgias Press, 2015),
							6; M. Sokoloff, <hi rend="italic">A Syriac lexicon</hi>
							(Eisenbrauns/Gorgias Press, 2009), 46. </p></note> ), and the
					surrounding lowlands. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p xml:lang="en"> 4
							In the early Middle Ages (from the 5th century onward) the Eastern
							Syriacs of the southern regions of Armenia were put under the
							jurisdiction of the Church of the East Metropolitans of Nisibis, who
							were thenceforth titled ‘Metropolitan of Nisibis and Armenia.’ From the
							5th to at least the end of the 13th century, the Metropolitanate of
							Nisibis comprised a diocese in Armenia itself, centered on the town of
							Khlat of the Bznunik province, in the vicinity of Lake Van. From the
							beginning of the 11th century, this diocese also covered the city of
							Van. Khlat was the birthplace of Metropolitan Solomon of Basra
							(12th-13th centuries) of the Church of the East, who is best known for
							his Biblical commentaries entitled “Book of the Bee” (<hi rend="italic"
								>Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</hi>
							(Gorgias Press, 2011), 378). </p></note> They were divided into several
					tribes and were relatively independent of the Ottoman authorities, yet heavily
						<pb n="281"/> influenced by the surrounding Kurds. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"> 5 For the details of the history, way
							of life, and customs of ‘Nestorians’ of Hakkari, see <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Ե. Լալայան, Վասպուրականի ասորիները, Ազգագրական
								հանդես</foreign> (Y. Lalayan, <hi rend="italic">The Syriacs of
								Vaspurakan</hi> (Ethnographic Magazine, 24 (I) [1913]), 181-232
								(<ref target="http://ethno.asj-oa.am/644/"
								>http://ethno.asj-oa.am/644/</ref>), as well as the books by Western
							missionaries. </p></note> Another large group lived in Iran, in the
					western coastal areas of Lake Urmia and the city of Urmia itself. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p xml:lang="en"> 6 After the Russo-Iranian
							war of 1828, several hundred Urmian Syriac families migrated to Eastern
							Armenia, establishing the ‘Nestorian’ villages of Koylasar (later
							Dimitrov), Dvin-Asori (Upper Dvin), Arzni, Shahriyar, Gyol-Assori, and
							Urmia, and the Chaldean village of Siyaghut; the first four of these
							villages still exist. Two more Syriac-populated villages, Samavat and
							Beghra-Khatun, were located in the Armenian province of Kars; they were
							founded in the aftermath of the Russian-Ottoman war of 1877-78 by the
							refugees from Hakkari. After the Soviet Russia ceded the Kars province
							to Turkey in 1921, the local Christian population was either massacred
							or forced to emigrate to Russia. In the context of Eastern Armenia, it
							is also worth mentioning that in the 10th-11th centuries the Church of
							the East had a diocese comprising parts of the former territory of
							Caucasian Albania with the center in Partav. Since there were no Syriac
							Christians in this region, it is safe to assume that the diocese was
							established with the aim of promoting the missionary activity in the
							adjacent regions of the Caucasus. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The Chaldeans lived mainly in the north of the vilayet of Mosul, in some
					localities of the vilayets of Bitlis and Diyarbakir, and some villages in the
					Urmia region. Today, the Chaldeans are Iraq’s largest Christian community. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p xml:lang="en"> 7 <hi rend="italic"
								>Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary ofthe Syriac Heritage</hi> (Gorgias
							Press, 2011), 92. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Compared with the followers of the Church of the East, the Syriac Orthodox and
					Chaldeans were better integrated into Ottoman society. Their intellectuals,
					especially after the Young Turks revolution, nurtured the idea that it might be
					possible to achieve peaceful coexistence and equality with Muslims in a
					‘reformed’ and ‘democratic’ Ottoman Empire. Openness and integration put the
					Western Syriacs, like the Armenians, within the reach of foreign Catholic and
					Protestant missionaries, who registered considerable success in their midst.
					Thus, a large portion of the Armenians and Syriacs of Mardin <pb n="282"/>
					adopted Catholicism, while Kharberd and Urfa produced large communities of
					Armenian and Syriac Protestants. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 8 A. Akopian, <hi rend="italic">to Aramean and Syriac
								Studies</hi> (Gorgias Press, 2017), 383. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> In the Ottoman Empire, the Syriac Orthodox who shared the same creed with
					Apostolic Armenians formed part of the Armenian <hi rend="italic">millet</hi>,
					that is, a formally recognized religious community with some degree of internal
					autonomy. In official documents, they were sometimes referred to as <hi
						rend="italic">yaghubi ermeniler</hi>, or ‘Jacobite Armenians’, although a
					more common designation was <hi rend="italic">süryeni qadim</hi>, that is, ‘old
					Syriacs,’ meaning those Syriacs who remained within their original denomination
					and did not switch to Catholicism or Protestantism. To communicate with the
					authorities the Orthodox had to turn to the services of the Armenian Patriarch
					of Constantinople, who represented all Miaphysite Christians in the capital
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en"> 9 W. Taylor, <hi
								rend="italic">The Syrian Orthodox Church and the Church of England
								1895-1914</hi> (Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2013), 83-84, 86; J.
							Joseph, <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations and Inter-Christian
								Rivalries in the Middle East</hi> (Albany, State University of New
							York Press, 1983), 29. </p></note> (the situation was the same in
					Jerusalem, where the Syriac, Coptic and Ethiopian clergy were subjected to the
					Armenian Patriarch <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p xml:lang="en"> 10
							D. Tsimhoni, “The Armenians and the Syrians: ethno-religious communities
							in Jerusalem,” (<hi rend="italic">Middle Eastern Studies</hi> Vol. 20
							No. 3 [Jul., 1984]), 352. </p></note> ). Since 1872, the Syriac Orthodox
					Patriarchate continuously petitioned the Ottoman authorities for the official
					recognition as a separate millet, which the government eventually did in 1882
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p xml:lang="en"> 11 J. Joseph, <hi
								rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations</hi>, 29. Both 1873 and
							1882 are mentioned in publications as the official date of the creation
							of the Syriac Orthodox millet. </p></note> . </p>
				<p> The Chaldeans and Syriac Catholics were initially part of the Armenian Catholic
					millet established in 1831 (in Mardin, the incorporation of Catholic Syriacs
					into the Armenian Catholic community was attested yet in the 18th century <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> 12 S. de Courtois, <hi
								rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide: Eastern Christians, the Last
								Arameans</hi> (Gorgias Press, 2004), 171. </p></note> ). In <pb
						n="283"/> 1846, the Chaldeans were separated from the Armenians within their
					own millet. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p xml:lang="en"> 13 A.
							Becker, <hi rend="italic">Revival and awakening: American Evangelical
								missionaries in Iran and the origins of Assyrian nationalism</hi>
							(The University of Chicago Press, 2015), 50. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> In 1864, an attempt was made to establish a separate millet for the followers of
					the Church of the East but failed. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 14 Ibid. </p></note> Because of their geographical
					isolation and higher degree of autonomy from the central government, the
					‘Nestorians’ were in fact left out of the Ottoman millet system. </p>
				<p> In 1850, under British pressure, the Ottoman Empire announced the establishment
					of a Protestant millet, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 15 S. Shaw, E. Shaw, <hi rend="italic">History of the
								Ottoman Empire and Modern Turkey: Volume 2 </hi>(Cambridge
							University Press, 2002), 127. </p></note> but it was not officially
					recognized. The majority of Protestants in the Empire were Armenians, and the
					Syriacs who adopted Protestantism were actually absorbed into their communities
					(in Urfa, however, the Syriac Protestants had their own church <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p xml:lang="en"> 16 H.-L., Kieser,
							“Ottoman Urfa and its Missionary Witnesses,” in <hi rend="italic"
								>Armenian Tigranakert/Diarbekir and Edessa/ Urfa</hi>, ed. R.
							Hovannisian (Mazda Publishers, Costa Mesa, California, 2006), 413.
						</p></note> ). </p>
				<p> The Armenian Apostolic Church would not usually interfere in the affairs of the
					Syriac Orthodox Church of Antioch, albeit there were unfortunate exceptions,
					mostly on the issue of the management of church property <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en"> 17 W. Taylor, <hi rend="italic">The
								Syrian Orthodox Church</hi>, 84. </p></note> . Those continued well
					into the 20th century with Armenians and Syriac Orthodox engaged in conflict
					over the Chapel of St. Nicodemus in the Church of the Holy Sepulcher in
					Jerusalem in 1933 <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p xml:lang="en"> 18
							J. Joseph, <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations</hi>, 196.
						</p></note> . These conflicts caused tensions and even forced some Syriacs
					to see Armenians as a threat. The prominent intellectual and journalist Naum
					Faiq (1868-1930), a native of Diyarbakir, wrote in one of his articles that
					Armenians, seeing themselves and the Syriacs as one and the same, “ruined our
					millet, our kind and our language and allowed [the Armenians] <pb n="284"/> to
					occupy our churches, monasteries and religious foundations, making us their
					subordinates, and to conceal what was rightfully ours.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> 19 B. Trigona-Harrany,<hi
								rend="italic"> The Ottoman Süryânî from 1908 to 1914</hi>
							(Gorgias Press, 2009), 199. </p></note> After the Armenian massacres of
					1895- 96, the Patriarch of the Syriac Orthodox Church Ignatius Abdelmashih was
					prompt to express allegiance to the Ottoman authorities and, in one of his
					letters addressed to the grand vizier, wrote that “Armenians have for some time
					past endeavored to Armenianize our language and religion, so long preserved
					thanks to the Mussulman law. &gt;...&lt; Letters of our spiritual chiefs at Urfa
					and Bitlis, amongst other places, signed by many respectable persons, have
					reached us which prove that the Armenians have slain and plundered many of our
					community and that their design is to completely annihilate it by famine and by
					other means.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p xml:lang="en"> 20 J.
							Joseph, <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations</hi>, 92-93.
						</p></note> In this regard, the British consul in Diyarbakir informed his
					embassy in Constantinople that those and other similar reports were written at
					the instigation of local Ottoman authorities. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
						n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> 21 Ibid. </p></note> Despite occasional tensions,
					however, the Armenians and Syriacs in the Ottoman Empire and elsewhere always
					remained on very friendly terms because of cultural and religious similarities
					and common threats and challenges. </p>
				<p> A notable feature of the Western Syriacs was their linguistic diversity. Modern
					Aramaic dialects had survived only in Tur- Abdin and the vicinity of Diyarbakir.
					The rural Syriacs of the eastern vilayets mainly spoke Turkish and Kurdish. In
					Syria, Arabic was the dominant language. Arabic in the form of the Anatolian
					dialect was also spoken in Mardin and Siirt, not only by the Syriacs but also
					the Armenians. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en"> 22
							Arabic-speaking Catholic Armenians, who trace their ancestry all the way
							to Mardin and Siirt, can still be found as distinct sub-communities
							within larger Armenian communities of the Middle East, and are sometimes
							referred to as “old Armenians.” </p></note>
				</p>
				<pb n="285"/>
				<p> A very distinct and sizeable community were the Syriacs who spoke Armenian as
					their first language. Manuscripts in Armenian language written in Syriac
					characters (Armenian Garshuni) attest to the existence of large communities of
					Armenian-speaking Syriacs in the area between Malatya and Kharberd at least from
					the mid-16th century on. The area also housed the Mor Abhay Syriac Orthodox
					Monastery, which was apparently one of the major centers of Armenian Garshuni.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> 23 H. Takahashi,
							J. Weitenberg, “The Shorter Syriac-Armenian Glossary in Ms. Yale Syriac
							9, Part 1” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac
								Studies</hi> Volume 10 [2010]), 68-83. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> In the 19th century, Armenian was the first language of the Syriacs of Kharberd
					and Urfa, and in Diyarbakir, it was spoken by all Christians regardless of their
					nationality <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p xml:lang="en"> 24 R.
							Kévorkian, “Demographic Changes in the Armenian Population of
							Diarbekir, 1895-1914,” in <hi rend="italic">Armenian
								Tigranakert/Diarbekir and Edessa/Urfa</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian
							(Mazda Publishers, Costa Mesa, California, 2006), 265. </p></note> .
					There were also many Armenian-speaking Syriacs in Bitlis, Malatya, Marash, and
					Adana. In fact, in all the Armenian-dominated areas, the Syriacs spoke Armenian
					and Kurdish. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en"> 25 S. de
							Courtois, <hi rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide</hi>, 17, 64.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The Syriac presence in Kharberd has been recorded since the beginning of the
					11th century, when the city was mentioned in the list of the dioceses of the
					Syriac Orthodox Church of Antioch as <hi rend="italic">Hesna d-Ziyad </hi>(“The
					fortress of Ziyad”). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="en">
							26 J.-M., Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Pour un Oriens Christianus Novus:
								répertoire des diocèses syriaques orientaux et occidentaux</hi>
							(Orient-Institut, 1993), 216. </p></note> The great Syriac polymath
					Grigorios bar Ebraya (1226-1286) referred to the city as <hi rend="italic">Hesna
						d-Zaid</hi>. Later, the Arabic version <hi rend="italic">Hisn Ziyad</hi>
					became prevalent. In reference to the city in his <hi rend="italic">Dictionary
						of Countries</hi>, renowned Arab geographer Yaqut al-Hamawi (1179-1229)
					said: “Hisn Ziyad, in Armenian lands, today known as Khartbirt” (<foreign
						xml:lang="ar">حصن زياد بأرض أرمينية ويعرف اليوم بخرتبرت</foreign>). Another
					prominent Arab geographer, Shamsuddin al- <pb n="286"/> Dimashqi (1256-1327),
					clarified that <hi rend="italic">Khartbirt</hi> was the name of the city, while
						<hi rend="italic">Hisn Ziyad</hi>—the name of its ancient citadel. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p xml:lang="en"> 27 J. H. Kramers,
							“Kharput” in <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of Islam</hi>, First
							Edition (1913-1936), eds. M. Houtsma, T. Arnold, R. Basset, R. Hartmann
							(Brill Online), <ref
								target="http://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopaedia-of-islam-1/k-h-arpu-t-SIM_4127"
								>http://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopaedia-of-islam-1/k-h-arpu-t-SIM_4127</ref>.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> In the 12th-13th centuries the number of Syriacs in the region increased, and
					its center, Malatya, became the scene of the final rise of the Syriac culture.
					During this period, the residence of the Patriarch of the Syriac Orthodox Church
					was transferred to the monastery of Mar Barsauma near Malatya. The Syriac
					diocese of Kharberd was mentioned once again in the 13th-14th centuries. Thus,
					Dioscoros Theodoros is known to have been the metropolitan of Kharberd in the
					mid-13th century. He was a native of the city, born into the family of priest
					Michael bar Basil. Later in life, he became a monk in the (Bani) Baʽuth
					monastery in or near Kharberd; the monastery, first mentioned in 1057, was
					conquered by Muslims in 1311, and produced four bishops <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p xml:lang="en"> 28 I. A. Barsoum, <hi rend="italic"
								>The Scattered Pearls</hi>, second revised edition (Gorgias Press,
							2003), 562. </p></note> . He mastered the Syriac language, as well as
					miniature painting, and before becoming a bishop, collected and copied
					manuscripts. Six manuscripts are known to have been copied by him, one of which
					was kept in the Syriac church in Kharberd. Grigorios bar Ebraya mentions
					Dioscoros in his <hi rend="italic">Church History</hi>, calling him “a renowned
					Doctor of the Church.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en"
							> 29 I. A. Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 462-63.
						</p></note> In the 14th century, a cleric named Joseph headed the local
					diocese; he left a record of the trials that befell the city during his
					lifetime. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p xml:lang="en"> 30 I. A.
							Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 155. </p></note>
					In the early 16th century, there was said to have been a Syriac monastery in
					Kharberd, possibly the same Baʽuth monastery, where for some time the Tur-Abdin
					Patriarch <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en"> 31 In
							1364-1816, in Tur-Abdin there was a parallel line of Syriac Orthodox
							Patriarchs of Antioch. </p></note> Ignatius Mas’ud of Zaz (1492-1512)
					lived in seclusion. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en">
							32 In 1364-1816, in Tur-Abdin there was a parallel line of Syriac
							Orthodox Patriarchs of Antioch. </p></note> Kharberd is also known as
					the <pb n="287"/> birthplace of one of several ‘traditions’ of Syriac liturgical
					music. </p>
				<p> The American Protestant missionary Horatio Southgate, who visited Kharberd in
					the mid-1840s, was told by a local that “there were no more than 45 Syrian (sic)
					families in the town, and a few in four of the villages, in all about 150
					families in the district of Kharput.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 33 H. Southgate, <hi rend="italic">Narrative of Visit
								to the Syrian [Jacobite] Church of Mesopotamia</hi> (New York,
							1856), 87. </p></note> The author goes on to say that “such statements,
					however, are not to be depended upon, as the poor oppressed Christians
					throughout the interior [of the Ottoman Empire] almost uniformly, through fear,
					make their numbers appear as small as possible.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p xml:lang="en"> 34 Ibid. </p></note> According to a
					Turkish source, there were about 60 Syriac households in Kharberd <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en"> 35 İ. Sunguroğlu, <hi
								rend="italic">Harput Yollarında</hi> (Istanbul, Yeni Matbaa, 1958),
							cited in Trigona-Harrany, 50. </p></note> ; the Ottoman authorities, for
					their part, were also known for diminishing the actual number of Christians.
					According to Vahe Haig, there were more than 800 Syriacs in Kharberd, and more
					in the nearby town of Mezireh or Mamuretülaziz (today Elazığ), 5 km to the
					south-west of Kharberd, and its surrounding villages; the largest Syriac
					population, 160 people, was recorded in the village of Ayvoz. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p xml:lang="en"> 36 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ,
								Խարբերդ եւ անոր ոսկեղէն դաշտը </foreign>(V. Haig, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd and her golden plain</hi>, New York, 1959), 509.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Since the late 1890s, the Syriacs of Kharberd had been emigrating to the United
					States, where on the eve of World War I there was a small Syriac community in
					Massachusetts, mostly in Worcester and Boston <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37"
						n="37"><p xml:lang="en"> 37 For more on this subject see G. Kiraz, <hi
								rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America (1895-1995); a
								short history</hi> (Gorgias Press, 2019). </p></note> . According to
					the 1910 US census, 2,832 immigrants from “Asian Turkey” lived in Worcester; by
					their overwhelming majority those had to be Armenians and Syriacs from the
					vilayet of Kharberd. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p xml:lang="en">
							38 All the US census data according to <ref target="www.census.gov"
								>www.census.gov</ref>. In North America, the Ottoman Syriacs
							established their communities based on the ‘fellow-townsmanship’
							principle. Thus, the natives of Kharberd settled <pb n="288"/> down in
							Massachusetts, and later in California, those of Tur-Abdin in Rhode
							Island, those of Diyarbakir in New Jersey and New York, those of Mardin
							in Montreal, those of Homs in Detroit and Florida. </p></note> In the
						<pb n="288"/> 1920s, some families moved to Fresno, California, where their
					main occupation was horticulture, and later to Los Angeles. The number of
					Kharberd Syriacs in the US totaled 600-700. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39"
						n="39"><p xml:lang="en"> 39 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ, <hi
									rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd</hi>), 513. </p></note> Manuk Gismegian breaks down this
					total into 200 people in Worcester, 250 in Fresno, and 150 in Los Angeles. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p xml:lang="en"> 40 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ եւ իր
									զաւակները</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd and its children</hi>, Fresno, 1955), 312-314. </p></note>
					In Boston, the Syriacs published two Armenian-language periodicals (<hi
						rend="italic">Babylon</hi> in 1919-1921 <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41"
						n="41"><p xml:lang="en"> 41 For more information about <hi rend="italic"
								>Babylon</hi> see A. Akopian, “<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, an
							Armenian-language Syriac periodical: some remarks on milieu, structure
							and language” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for
								Syriac Studies</hi> Vol. 10 [2010]), 83-98. </p></note> and <hi
						rend="italic">Nineveh</hi> in 1927-1928) and another one in English in Los
					Angeles (<hi rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>, 1933-1938), which provide
					rich material on their lives in Kharberd and the United States. </p>
				<p> In Kharberd, the Syriacs, called in Armenian <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi>, had
					their own district (<hi rend="italic">asorwots tagh</hi> in Armenian, <hi
						rend="italic">süryani qadim mahallesi</hi> in Turkish); it was situated
					between the districts of Sinamut and St. Karapet’s. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p xml:lang="en"> 42 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ,
									<hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 508. </p></note> These districts were
					part of the <hi rend="italic"/> (“The Lower Quarter”) of the city; another large
					district was the <hi rend="italic">Veri Tagh</hi>, or “The Upper Quarter.” The
						<hi rend="italic">asorwots tagh</hi> was not a ghetto-type neighborhood, as
					its inhabitants maintained active daily contacts with Armenians and Muslims. The
					Syriacs were mostly craftsmen, but several merchants were also active in the
					region. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p xml:lang="en"> 43 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V.
							Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 509. </p></note> They were
					particularly famed for their weaving and dying skills and produced their own
					variety of chintz (a plain-woven textile made of roughly processed cotton),
					which was known as “Syriac chintz” (<hi rend="italic">asorwots chit</hi>). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p xml:lang="en"> 44 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign>
							(M. Gismegian, Kharberd), 87-88. The author provides the following
							details: “This water-related industry was in the hands of Syriacs,
							centered on the <hi rend="italic">Asorwots Chay</hi>, the “Syriac
							River,” a <pb n="289"/> spring and a brook in a gully. Since their
							settlement in the city, the Syriacs concentrated their efforts on this
							craft, producing the “red Syriac chintz,” a canvas decorated with red
							and black flowers. The craftsmen worked with their whole families, the
							women at home, and the men in the gully, where they produced the red
							canvas and chintz adorned with flowers, birds and other beautiful
							patterns out of their own stencils. This product was widely consumed in
							the provinces and in remote cities, especially by Kurds and peasants.
							&gt;...&lt; They used to collect canvases from villages and settlements
							in the spring without signature or guarantee and return them dyed to
							their owners in the fall. Syriacs’ cooperation in this industry is
							remarkable. It was based on trust and confidence, and the protection of
							goods was the responsibility of the whole community. Canvases
							whitewashed in the brook were spread out near the mountain slopes under
							the sun and often remained there at night, attracting thieves. The
							Syriacs were watching over the canvases in turn, and thieves, unaware of
							this, would always be ambushed. When the guards sounded the alarm, all
							the Syriacs of the quarter would come running, armed with sticks and
							clubs, and woe to the robber who would fall into their hands. The
							notable persons in this craft were: the Chatalbash brothers, Minas,
							Poghos, and Martiros; the Donabed brothers, Karapet, Georg and Avetis;
							the Perdj brothers, Hakob and Poghos; the Dashos, Yaghub and his son
							Surian; the Chtchi brothers, Aghayek, Givargis and Gaspar, and others.”
							Gismegian, who calls Syriacs “energetic people,” also informs that in
							the 1850s, the Syriacs, funded by the Church, built a big bathhouse,
							which fell into decay after some time. </p></note> For the needs of that
					particular craft, Syriacs produced and held a monopoly on a special red dye
					based on herbs, including walnut crusts and gallnuts. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p xml:lang="en"> 45 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ,
									<hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 509. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> There was at least one wealthy Syriac landowner family, the Namans (Naʽman?),
					which rose to prominence thanks to connections to the Ottoman government. Their
					mansion, the Chiftliq, with surrounding beautiful garden, was widely known in
					the region. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p xml:lang="en"> 46 Ibid,
							510. </p></note> Hajji Daud Naman Efendi and his son-in-law from the
					Dasho family were particularly important. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
						n="47"><p xml:lang="en"> 47 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi
									rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, Kharberd),
							88. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The Syriacs were united with Armenians, who formed the majority of the
					Kharberd’s Christian population, into a socio-economic, religious, and cultural
					entity, which had to face the challenges of coexisting with the local Muslims.
					According to <pb n="290"/> Horatio Southgate’s informant, the Armenians and
					Syriacs “live together on terms of the closest intimacy, and go to each other’s
					churches, but do not intermarry.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 48 H. Southgate, <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi>, 87.
						</p></note> The last statement, however, has been refuted by <hi
						rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Nineveh</hi>, and <hi
						rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>, which mention numerous Armenian-Syriac
					marriages. Such marriages were also common in other parts of the Ottoman Empire.
					Thus, according to De Courtois, “the Diyarbakir and Mardin Armenian communities
					were very large, and also often made up the social elite of bankers, merchants,
					doctors, and intellectuals, with whom the important Syriac families had mixed.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p xml:lang="en"> 49 S. de
							Courtois, <hi rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide</hi>, 44. </p></note>
					Eden Naby, an American historian of Assyrian descent, also notes that due to the
					close affiliation of the Armenian Apostolic and Syriac Orthodox Churches, “not
					only was intermarriage possible but it also occurred with some frequency where
					proximity provided the necessary circumstances.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p xml:lang="en"> 50 E. Naby , “ Almost Family:
							Assyrians and Armenians in Massachusetts” in <hi rend="italic">The
								Armenians of New England</hi>, ed. M. Mamigonian (Armenian Heritage
							Press, 2004), 45-46. </p></note> She then adds that “Assyrians who had
					already become Presbyterians, married other Presbyterians whether they were
					Assyrian or not. The likeliest marriage partners in the past were Armenians.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p xml:lang="en"> 51 Ibid, 46.
						</p></note> As mentioned above, the Ottoman Syriacs who adopted
					Protestantism, were united with Armenians in a single community, which would
					have been Armenian in essence. For these reasons, they displayed a much stronger
					tendency to assimilate into the Armenian majority than those Syriacs who
					remained faithful to traditional Syriac denominations. </p>
				<p> By the end of the 19th century, there were 49 primary, 5 middle and 1 high
					registered Syriac schools in the Ottoman Empire. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p xml:lang="en"> 52 B. Trigona-Harrany, <hi
								rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî</hi>, 74, footnote 186.
						</p></note> According to Vahe Haig, the Syriacs of Kharberd were initially
					“backward in education, but later schooling and <pb n="290"/> education gained
					more importance among them.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 53 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ, <hi rend="italic"
									>Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd</hi>), 512. </p></note> The Syriacs had at least one
					school in their quarter, which Haig describes as a “preschool”, <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p xml:lang="en"> 54 Ibid. </p></note>
					and Alek Sodo of Kharberd calls “humble.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55"
						n="55"><p xml:lang="en"> 55 <foreign xml:lang="hy"
								>Ա.Սօտօ,“ԱշուրՍ.Եուսուֆ”</foreign> (A.Sodo,“AshurS.Yusuf”)(<hi
								rend="italic">Nineveh</hi> Vol. I, No.12 [1927]). </p></note> In
					1909, the Syriac ladies’ <hi rend="italic">Mart Shimuni</hi> (“Saint Shimuni”)
					association, headed by Hanim Barsum and Meryem Donabed, founded a separate
					female school. In 1912, that school, with Srbuhi Dasho as the chairperson of the
					board, had 60 students and six teachers, five of whom were women. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p xml:lang="en"> 56 B. Trigona-Harrany,
								<hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî</hi>, 175. </p></note> At
					the same time, Armenian schools, especially those founded by foreign
					missionaries, were open to Syriacs <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 57 J. Joseph, <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian
								Relations</hi>, 78. </p></note> and employed Syriac teachers. Thus,
					two young Syriac ladies, Sara and Shamiram, are mentioned among the teachers of
					the St. Clair maidens’ secondary school founded by the Capuchins <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p xml:lang="en"> 58 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign>
							(M. Gismegian, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 160. </p></note> ;
					incidentally, the school buildings surrounded by gardens, just beneath the
					citadel of Kharberd, were formerly owned by the wealthy Naman Syriac family
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p xml:lang="en"> 59 Ibid.
						</p></note> ; one can only guess if this was the same Chiftliq. </p>
				<p> The Syriac school of the <hi rend="italic">asorwots tagh</hi> lasted until 1912.
					Its main objective was to provide literacy in the Armenian and Turkish
					languages; an attempt was made to introduce the Syriac language <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p xml:lang="en"> 60 It is interesting to
							note that the Kharberd Syriacs called their classical language in
							Armenian <hi rend="italic">asorén</hi>, and not <hi rend="italic"
								>asorerén</hi>, which is the correct form. </p></note> but failed.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p xml:lang="en"> 61 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V.
							Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 512. </p></note> The pupils,
					however, would leave the school with sufficient practical knowledge of the
					Syriac script, which was widely used by the Syriacs for writing in Turkish and
					Arabic. In Kharberd, there were three Syriac Garshuni periodicals (see below);
					Turkish written in Syriac script could also be found on tombstones and other <pb
						n="292"/> inscriptions. It was even used by the Syriac Orthodox Church of
					Antioch in its internal correspondence and other paperwork. There is no evidence
					of the use of the Syriac script for writing in Armenian in the period under
					consideration, although it may be assumed that it might have been occasionally
					used as cryptography. Obviously, it made no sense to give up the Armenian script
					in favor of the difficult-to-read Armenian Garshuni, especially in an
					overwhelmingly Armenian environment. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 62 In contrast, numerous examples of “reversed Garshuni”,
							which is Syriac written in Armenian script, can be found in <hi
								rend="italic">Babylon</hi>. </p></note> In the case of the Turkish
					language, the substitution of its Arabic script with the Syriac one, which is
					very similar to Arabic in general principles and structure, did not present any
					difficulty. </p>
				<p> The Syriac school also provided elementary religious studies, most certainly
					administered by a local priest, which meant having to learn by heart in
					Classical Syriac the main prayers and Psalms and most frequently used hymns of
					the Syriac Orthodox Church (this practice is still alive in Syriac Sunday
					schools in the Middle East and Diaspora). Very few laymen were able to display
					any knowledge of Classical Syriac that went beyond these mechanically memorized
					religious texts. </p>
				<p> It is not clear when the Syriacs of Kharberd lost their native speech, if we are
					to assume that Aramaic was spoken by them in the past. One of the articles in
						<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> states: “It was about two centuries ago that
					our race lost its language in Kharberd and its surroundings, and to this day
					only the <hi rend="italic">olafbet</hi> [the alphabet] has remained as our
					heritage.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p xml:lang="en"> 63
								<foreign xml:lang="hy">Ն. Գոյուն, “Ասորեն թերթը, որ պիտի
								գայ”</foreign> (N. Goyun, “The Syriac newspaper that is to come”)
								(<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. 1, No. 16 [1920]). </p></note>
					This implies that the Syriacs of Kharberd had lost their language sometime after
					the first quarter of the 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century (it should be
					noted once again that the earliest manuscript to contain a text in Armenian <pb
						n="293"/> Garshuni dates back to 1574/5 <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64"
						n="64"><p xml:lang="en"> 64 S. Brock, “Armenian in Syriac Script,” in <hi
								rend="italic">Armenian Studies. Études arméniennes. In Memoriam
								Haïg Berbérian</hi>, ed. D. Kouymjian (Lisbon, Calouste Gulbenkian
							Foundation, 1986), 78. </p></note> ). Taking into account that <hi
						rend="italic">Turoyo,</hi> a modern Aramaic language, is still spoken today
					to the south of the Kharberd area, in Tur-Abdin, and a closely related dialect,
						<hi rend="italic">Mlahso</hi>, was spoken in at least two villages in the
					region of Diyarbakir until the end of the 20th century, <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p xml:lang="en"> 65 O. Jastrow, <hi rend="italic">Der
								neuaramäische Dilekt von Mlahso</hi> (Harrassowitz Verlag,
							Wiesbaden, 1994), 6. </p></note> it can be assumed that an Aramaic
					dialect could have existed in the Kharberd region prior to the 17th century,
					although this assumption cannot presently be confirmed in any way. In any case,
					this dialect had to have been ‘imported,’ as Kharberd, unlike Tur-Abdin and
					Diyarbakir, was far beyond the ancient Aramean homeland in North Mesopotamia,
					and had no indigenous Aramaic dialect. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 66 Before studying all of the available material in
							detail, we had theorized that Syriacs of Kharberd could have had a
							specific Armenian slang of their own, in one way or another influenced
							by Aramaic. It is obvious that because of a different church tradition
							they used some words and expressions of religious character that were
							not understood by Armenians (and we find them in <hi rend="italic"
								>Babylon</hi>), yet the thorough analysis of available data leaves
							little doubt that the Syriacs, who had been using Armenian in the city
							for at least two hundred years, were not distinguishable from Armenians
							in their everyday speech. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Eden Naby points out that the Syriacs of Kharberd were under the general Middle
					Eastern language paradigm, “that saw men learn the language of public places,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p xml:lang="en"> 67 In the case of
							Kharberd, that would be Armenian and Turkish. In Diyarbakir, as another
							example already mentioned above, all Christians spoke Armenian, and in
							public places, like bazaars and markets, used Kurdish (S. de Courtois,
								<hi rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide</hi>, 17, 64). </p></note>
					while women remained within the security of the wider family and neighborhood
					setting and maintained the ethnic language” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68"
						n="68"><p xml:lang="en"> 68 E. Naby, <hi rend="italic">Almost Family</hi>,
							47. S. De Courtois mentions an Orthodox Syriac in the vicinity of
							Mardin, whose mother, a native of Diyarbakir, still only spoke Armenian
							(S. de Courtois, <hi rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide</hi>, 17,
							footnote 2). </p></note> , in this case, Armenian. In other words, the
					Syriac women in <pb n="294"/> Kharberd and surrounding villages were almost
					exclusively Armenian-speaking, while the men also knew Turkish; the existence of
					Turkish-language Syriac journals in Kharberd leaves no doubt of that. The same
					situation was attested in the 1870s in Tur-Abdin by German Semitologist Edward
					Sachau, who noted that “in Tur-Abdin, in addition to Turoyo, men also usually
					speak Kurdish and Arabic, while women and children only speak Turoyo.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p xml:lang="en"> 69 E. Sachau, <hi
								rend="italic">Reise in Syrien und Mesopotamien</hi> (Leipzig, 1883),
							420 (“Während die Männer meistens neben dem Ṭôrânî noch Kurdisch
							oder Arabisch können, sprechen die Weiber und Kinder nur Ṭôrânî”).
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> At the same time, several articles in <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> mention
					songs with Turkish names sung by the Syriacs, which suggests that Naby’s
					assumption should be taken with certain caution. Sargon Donabed mentions at
					least two Armenian-language songs <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 70 S. Donabed, <hi rend="italic">Remnants of Heroes: The
								Assyrian Experience</hi> (Assyrian Academic Society, 2003), 77; the
							book is largely based upon the family archives of the natives of
							Kharberd who had emigrated to the US and recollections of their
							descendants. </p></note> . Several examples of Syriac childlore in
					Armenian can be found in <hi rend="italic">Collection of Meditations</hi>, an
					Armenian-language book by Ezekiel Maljan, the editor of <hi rend="italic"
						>Assyrian Progress</hi> (see below). </p>
				<p> In addition to speaking Armenian, the Syriacs of Kharberd often had Armenian
					names or Armenian versions of Biblical names. Of those recorded in <hi
						rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Nineveh</hi> and <hi
						rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>, the most frequently used ones are
					Azniv, Aghavni, Andranik, Arakel, Avetis, Artin, Donabed, Gevorg, Zaruhi, Toros,
					Lusik, Karapet, Kirakos, Harutun, Hovakim, Hovhannes, Manuk, Markos, Martiros,
					Melkon, Nshan, Petik, Perch, Poghos, Satenik, Sahak, Srbuhi, Ohan and others. It
					appears that Syriacs could be called any Armenian name, with perhaps a few
					exceptions, that were “too Armenian”, such as Hayk or Armenak. Several first
					names were also used as surnames. Thus, some of the prominent Syriac families in
					Kharberd bore the surnames of Donabed, Perch, Manuk, Arakel and so on. The <hi
						rend="italic">-ian</hi> ending of Armenian surnames was rare among the
					Syriacs, who, despite speaking Armenian, <pb n="295"/> strongly clung to their
					ethnic identity, nevertheless. Some Syriacs would add <hi rend="italic"
						>-ian</hi> to their last names, or adopt original Armenian last names to
					make it easier for them to emigrate to the United States. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p xml:lang="en"> 71 S. Donabed, M. Shamiran, “Harput,
							Turkey to Massachusetts: Notes on the Immigration of Jacobite
							Christians” (<hi rend="italic">Chronos: Revue d’Histoire de
								l’Université de Balamand</hi>, No. 23 [2011]), 21; G. Kiraz, <hi
								rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 14. There was
							at least one Kharberd Syriac who had a last name with a Russian <hi
								rend="italic">–ov</hi> ending. It was Naum Besharov, the second
							editor of <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, who had spent some time in the
							Russian-controlled Caucasus before emigrating to the United States and
							apparently received Russian citizenship. In the Russian Empire the
							Syriac Christians were almost exclusively registered under Russified
							last names which are still very common in post-Soviet countries.
						</p></note> Priests and deacons apparently used the traditional Syriac <hi
						rend="italic">bar</hi> (“son of”) patronymic in official documents, like
					deacon Ya’kub bar Toma. </p>
				<p> The prevalence of Armenian names obviously sparked the displeasure of some
					nationalistic-minded circles and the Syriac Orthodox Church. One of the
					editorials of <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> contains the following quote: “Not
					in the least remarkable are our names: produce at least one Armenian who is
					called Yuhanna, Fawlos, Sargon, Ashur, or Afrem, but too many are amongst us
					those called Hovhannes, Poghos, Karapet, Markos, Kirakos.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p xml:lang="en"> 72 <foreign xml:lang="hy">“Մեզի ի՞նչ
								պետք է”</foreign> (Editorial, “What do we need?”) (<hi rend="italic"
								>Babylon</hi> Vol. I, No. 27 [1920]). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The situation, however, was not that dramatic, as, in addition to Armenian
					names, the Syriacs also used traditional Syriac names and surnames, such as
					Barsam, Beshara, Dasho, Denho, Givargis, Hanna, Malke, Maruta, Naman, Naum,
					Sodo, Shmuni, Surian, Tuma, Yuhanna, as well as names of Arab-Turkish origin or
					appearance, such as Chatalbash, Davud, Elbi, Goyun, Ibrahim, Iskander, Keshish,
					Khory, Lutfi, Nuri, Rasin, Safar, Tumajan, Ya’kub, Yulbek, Yusuf. European names
					or Biblical names in their European versions also were not uncommon. </p>
				<p> Despite having spoken Armenian for several generations, the Syriacs of Kharberd
					did not consider Armenian their maternal tongue. To them, it always remained a
					‘foreign’ <pb n="296"/> language <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 73 B. Trigona-Harrany, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman
								Süryânî</hi>, 193. </p></note> to which they rarely expressed any
					emotional attachment. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p xml:lang="en">
							74 <hi rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi> provides one such rare
							manifestation: a report from a community event organized by a youth
							group in Los Angeles and partially conducted in Armenian says that the
							older audience “enjoyed the Armenian language.” </p></note> The loss of
					their own language was nothing short of a fixation that haunted the learned
					Syriacs. One of the <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> authors wrote: “We have a
					language that is not used by anyone; we have adopted the languages of others.
					One speaks one people’s language, another speaks another’s. Some speak Turkish,
					some Persian, some Armenian, some Arabic. &lt;…&gt; We do not know and
					understand each other, we are divided into a thousand and one branches, into a
					thousand and one groups. The Melkites believe themselves to be different from
					others, the Chaldeans believe the same. The <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi> in
					Persia call themselves ‘Nestorians’ and completely disassociate themselves from
					those in Mesopotamia.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p xml:lang="en"
							> 75 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ռասին, “Դեպ ո՞ւր կը քալենք”</foreign>
							(Rasin, “Where are we heading?”) (<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. I,
							No. 5 [1919]). </p></note> The hope of seeing the mother tongue
					resurrected in the future continually surfaced on <hi rend="italic"
					>Babylon</hi>’s pages, although in the case of the Kharberd Syriacs this hope
					had very little ground to become a reality. Another author proclaimed: “The <hi
						rend="italic">asorí</hi> nation is not without tongue but has a language
					with its own opulent literature. While other nations had no language, the <hi
						rend="italic">asorí</hi> had one and enlightened others. &lt;…&gt; It is as
					rich as Arabic, Greek or any other European language. &lt;…&gt; Dominated by
					other nations, we were forced to use their languages. &lt;…&gt; Like any other
					language which is now simpler and reformed, better suited to the present
					situation, so Syriac too can become simpler and better suited to our times. For
					that purpose, a group of linguists can reform it so that it becomes a common
					tongue for Nestorians, Jacobites, and Chaldeans.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p xml:lang="en"> 76 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ա. Գ.
								Եուսուֆ, “Նամակ Փարիզեն”</foreign> (A. G. Yusuf, “A letter from
							Paris”) (<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. I, No. 8 [1919]).
						</p></note> The publishers and correspondents of <hi rend="italic"
						>Babylon</hi> would occasionally <pb n="297"/> voice the idea of turning the
					periodical into a Syriac-language one in the future. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p xml:lang="en"> 77 The publishers actually did try
							to do just that by introducing Syriac words written in Armenian letters
							into the Armenian text and by publishing Armenian-Syriac word lists. The
							first list was accompanied by an editorial notice which urged the
							readers to memorize the Syriac words in order to be able to understand
							future articles. It appears that the idea was to gradually increase the
							number of Syriac words up to a proportion that would allow declaring <hi
								rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, at least partially, a Syriac-language
							periodical. A total of five word lists appeared, after which the
							publishers apparently gave up the idea, either because of the lack of
							enthusiasm on the part of the readers or simply because the whole idea,
							albeit inventive and ingenious, was basically nonsensical and
							unrealizable. </p></note> One of the readers wrote to the editor: “It is
					with the immense joy of heart that I have the privilege of reading your
					patriotic semi-monthly [journal], with the trust that, in the near future, the
					result of your painstaking efforts will be publishing <hi rend="italic"
						>Babylon</hi> in our maternal language.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78"
						n="78"><p xml:lang="en"> 78 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Տոնապետ, “Նամակ
								«Բաբելոնին»”</foreign> (M. Donabed, “A letter to ‘Babylon’”) (<hi
								rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. I, No. 6 [1919]). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The main token of the national identity of the Kharberd Syriacs and the factor
					distinguishing them from Armenians was their national Church, the Syriac
					Orthodox Church of Antioch. Up to 1915 and probably sometime beyond, Kharberd
					had a Syriac Orthodox bishop assisted by a number of priests and deacons. It
					appears, however, that the Syriac Orthodox Church held Kharberd in certain
					disregard and did not delegate clergy endowed with much competency there, as <hi
						rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, with its strong anti-clerical inclinations,
					constantly criticized them for the low level of education and even open
					ignorance. </p>
				<p> The <hi rend="italic">Mart Maryam</hi>, St. Mary church in <hi rend="italic"
						>asorwots tagh</hi>, also known under the Turkish name of <hi rend="italic"
						>Meryem Ana Kilesi</hi>, was a solid, unpretentious building with thick
					walls, that had little architectural value. The Syriacs considered it to be very
					ancient and attributed its foundation to 179 AD. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p xml:lang="en"> 79 J.-M., Fiey, <hi rend="italic"
								>Pour un Oriens Christianus Novus</hi>, 216-217. </p></note> Some
					also believed that the church was the very Bnai Baʽuth monastery mentioned <pb
						n="298"/> in medieval sources or a surviving part of it. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p xml:lang="en"> 80 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ,
									<hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 511; I. A. Barsoum, <hi rend="italic"
								>The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 462; <hi rend="italic">Ե. Մալճան, <hi
									rend="italic">Հաւաքածոյ խորհրդոց</hi></hi> (E. Maljan, <hi
								rend="italic">Collection of Meditations</hi>) (Los Angeles, 1954),
							25. </p></note> According to another version, this was the former <hi
						rend="italic">Surb Astvatsatsin</hi>, Holy Mother of God Armenian church,
					which Armenians yielded to the Syriacs in exchange for a church in the nearby
					village of Morenik. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p xml:lang="en">
							81 Ch. Moranci, “The Medieval Architecture of Kharpert” in <hi
								rend="italic">Armenian Tsopk/Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian
							(Mazda Publishers, Costa Mesa, California, 2002), 187; <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V.
							Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 512. </p></note> Such
					assumptions seem to be corroborated by the fact that the church contained the
					tomb of a certain princess Helen Khatun who according to the accompanying
					inscription died in 1320 AD; <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 82 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ե. Մալճան,<hi rend="italic">
									Հաւաքածոյ</hi></foreign> (E. Maljan, <hi rend="italic"
								>Collection</hi>), 26. </p></note> in the region of Karberd, a
					Christian noblewoman bestowed with the female honorific <hi rend="italic"
						>khatun</hi> could only be Armenian. </p>
				<p> The church had a richly decorated altar with oil lanterns burning around it day
					and night. There were three narrow windows behind the altar, upon which a wider
					window was added in 1800. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 83 Ibid. </p></note> In 1273, a valuable Gospel was
					donated to St. Mary, and eventually ended up in the Deir al-Zaafaran monastery;
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p xml:lang="en"> 84 Ibid.
						</p></note> this should have been one of the manuscripts produced by the
					then metropolitan of Kharberd, Dioscoros Theodoros. Because of its allegedly
					strong healing powers the church attracted many pilgrims. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p xml:lang="en"> 85 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Վ. Հայկ,
									<hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi>
							</foreign>(V. Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 512. </p></note>
					The blind, handicapped and especially the mentally ill would come from the
					surrounding regions hoping to find cures for their ailments. Among them were not
					only Christians but also Turks and Kurds. The pilgrims, who generated a
					considerable income for the church, stayed for up to three days, and the church
					provided 20 cell-like rooms for their lodging. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86"
						n="86"><p xml:lang="en"> 86 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi
									rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 62. </p></note> It should also be
					noted that, in <pb n="299"/> Kharberd, the Syriac saints were revered both by
					the Syriacs themselves and the Armenians. </p>
				<p> There was a church in the Sinamut district of the city, known as the St. Shmon
					Church, which could have originally belonged to the Syriacs. Ezekiel Maljan
					mentions it together with the Syriac churches that were restored in 1134. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p xml:lang="en"> 87 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy">Ե. Մալճան, <hi rend="italic">Հաւաքածոյ</hi></foreign>
							(E. Maljan, <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>), 26. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Unlike the overwhelming majority of laymen, the local Syriac clergy had enough
					knowledge of Classical Syriac to use it during the services at the St. Mary
					church. The people did not understand what was being said but knew it to be the
					language of Jesus Christ, and for that reason “it touched them in a mystic way.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p xml:lang="en"> 88 Ibid.
						</p></note> As already mentioned, the knowledge of Classical Syriac among
					laymen was mainly confined to several mechanically memorized prayers and hymns.
					Several articles in <hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> indicate that, even in the
					United States, the social gatherings usually began with the collective recital
					of the Lord’s Prayer (<hi rend="italic">Abund Bashmayn</hi> in Armenian
					transliteration) in Syriac. During family feasts and other similar events, the
					deacons would also recite Syriac hymns. Thus, one of the articles informs:
					“After the meals were served, the celebration began with three deacons reciting
					the <hi rend="italic">Teshbokhto </hi>glorification rite.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p xml:lang="en"> 89 <foreign xml:lang="hy">“Տարեդարձի
								մը առթիվ”</foreign> (“On the occasion of a birthday) (<hi
								rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. I, No. 13 [1920]). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> However, it is also known that in Bitlis, for example, the Syriacs not only
					spoke Armenian but also used it in their church services. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p xml:lang="en"> 90 M. Krikorian, <hi rend="italic"
								>Armenians in the Service of the Ottoman Empire </hi>(London,
							Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1977), 117. </p></note> Armenian was also
					used in the Syriac Church of Forty Martyrs in Mardin; <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p xml:lang="en"> 91 B. Trigona-Harrany, <hi
								rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî</hi>, 199, footnote 549.
						</p></note> this is particularly remarkable, given that the Armenians and
					Syriacs of that city, especially the Catholics, were speakers of Arabic. In its
					issue no. 24 from 1914, the <hi rend="italic">Armenia </hi>newspaper of
					Marseille contains a report from Diyarbakir about an Armenian-language Gospel
					written in Syriac characters that was used by the Ottoman Syriacs; in <pb
						n="300"/> all probability, this was the last example of Armenian Garshuni in
					use. </p>
				<p> The Turkish language also appears to have occupied a certain place in the
					religious practices of the Kharberd Syriacs. Thus, at the beginning of the 20th
					century, the above-mentioned deacon Ya’kub bar Toma compiled a prayer-book in
					which the prayers and hymns written in Syriac were accompanied by their Turkish
					translation in the Syriac script. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 92 E. Naby and M. Hopper, eds., <hi rend="italic">The
								Assyrian Experience: Sources for the Study of the 19<hi
									rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
								Centuries</hi> (Harvard College Library, Cambridge, 1999), 12-13.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p> As was the case with the Armenians, in the second half of the 19th century,
					Protestantism became widespread among the Syriacs of Kharberd, mostly as a
					result of the American missionary activities. Several prominent Syriac ministers
					and preachers, such as Gavmeh Ablahad, Hovhannes Chatalbash, Arakel Petikian,
					Maljan Chavoor, were active not only among Syriacs, but also Armenians, both in
					Kharberd and the United States <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 93 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi rend="italic"
									>Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd</hi>), 311. </p></note> . As previously noted, compared
					with the Orthodox, the Protestant Syriacs were more influenced by the Armenians
					because they were united with them in a common congregation. It is obvious that
					in Kharberd there were ‘Armenized’ Syriacs. Thus, one of the articles states:
					“Many [of our] people would treat <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi> as a derogatory
					name. In the homeland, if you called them <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi>, it would
					anger them. “It is you, who is <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi>, I am a Christian
					Armenian,” they would say.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 94 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ն. Բեշարով, “Բաց նամակ
								վերապատվելի Գավմէ Ապլահատի”</foreign> (N. Besharov, “An open letter
							to Reverend Gavme Ablahad) (<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. I, No.
							21 [1920]). </p></note> Another article states: “I have the conviction
					that the <hi rend="italic">asorí</hi> nation will come to its senses and become
					aware once and for all of the poisonous microbes against which only a national
					paper can vaccinate. If not, then it is better to follow right away the nation
					[Armenians] whose language, literature, and <pb n="301"/> customs we already
					use, than to do it a quarter of a century later.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p xml:lang="en"> 95 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ն. Գոյուն,
								“Ասորեն թերթը, որ պիտի գա”</foreign> (N. Koyun, “The Syriac paper
							that is to come”) (<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. II, No. 4
							[1920]). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Catholic missionaries were also active in Kharberd, especially in the field of
					education, but they were not as successful as the Americans in attracting the
					locals into their denomination. There were only a few cases of conversion under
					the influence of the Capuchins. Among the Syriacs, those converted included one
					Safer Agha Safer and members of the Dasho family—Yaghub Agha Dasho and his
					brother Nazar Efendi Dasho, who was engaged in the tobacco trade. One of Nazar’s
					sons, Poghos, graduated from the Dominican Seminary of Mosul and became a priest
					under the name of Père Paul; his other son, Petros, became a physician and was
					known as Pierre Dasho. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p xml:lang="en"
							> 96 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi rend="italic"
								>Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, <hi rend="italic"
								>Kharberd</hi>), 160. </p></note> However, there is no evidence of
					the presence in Kharberd of the Syriac Catholic Church. </p>
				<p> There have been cases where Syriacs passed under the jurisdiction of the
					Armenian Apostolic Church. It happened, in particular, in the village of Aghvan,
					not far from Kharberd, where it was done not only by the laymen, but also the
					local Syriac Orthodox priest named Zeytun, apparently due to discords with
					Dionysius Abdenur Aslan, Bishop of Kharberd in 1896-1913. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p xml:lang="en"> 97 B. Trigona-Harrany, <hi
								rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî</hi>, 202. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Conversions and ‘Armeniazation’ were undoubtedly causes of great dissatisfaction
					for the Syriac clergy. According to one of Sargon Donabed’s elderly informants,
					Bishop Dionysius Abdenur Aslan threatened those Syriacs who would be caught
					speaking Armenian with monetary penalties. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98"
						n="98"><p xml:lang="en"> 98 S. Donabed, <hi rend="italic">Remnants of
								Heroes</hi>, 41. </p></note> The validity of this testimony is very
					difficult to confirm today, but in any case, it seems unlikely that a
					high-ranking clergyman would really rely on threats and penalties to force the
					Syriacs out of their spoken language of several centuries. In all probability,
					this is an echo of a distorted memory of certain <pb n="302"/> sanctions that
					the Church was trying to impose on the ‘renegade’ Syriacs. Bishop Dionysius, who
					was born in Urfa in 1851, meaning that himself he had hailed from an
					Armenian-speaking milieu, is indeed known for his attempts to limit the Armenian
					influence on Syriacs, opposing mixed marriages, and having serious problems with
					his own flock. The Syriac intellectuals of the city accused him of being overly
					pro-Ottoman and wasting church funds. After Kharberd, Dionysius Abdenur Aslan
					was the Bishop of Homs and then the Bishop of Diyarbakir until his death in
					1933. He is occasionally remembered for his rich collection of Syriac
					manuscripts. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p xml:lang="en"> 99 The
							fate of the Kharberd Bishopric after Dionysius Abdenur Aslan remains
							uncertain. According to some testimonies, the next Bishop was Kurillos
							Mansour, who was martyred during the 1915 Genocide, and according to
							others, the seat remained vacant until the final destruction of
							Kharberd. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> The educational and cultural upsurge of Western Armenians in the second half of
					the 19th century left positive impacts on the Syriacs as well. As previously
					mentioned, many Syriacs received good education in Armenian schools, including
					the ones founded by foreign missionaries. Some continued their education at the
					famous Euphrates College of Kharberd (originally, Armenia College), which was
					founded in 1878 by American missionaries and occupied a compound of more than
					ten buildings in the Upper Quarter. Essentially a missionary institution, the
					College became the leading provider of higher education in all of Western
					Armenia and was open to Christians of all denominations of both sexes. Manuk
					Gismegian provides the names of several male and female Syriac graduates of the
					Euphrates College: Sultan Maljan, Margrit Awkinian, Nazli Chatalbash, Mariam
					Kherpez, Elmas and Mariam Habib, Abraham Safer, Harutyun Barsam, Ezekiel Maljan,
					Alexianos Safer, Georg Habib, Mariam Barsam, <pb n="303"/> Maritza Aslan,
					Maritza Safer, Nazli Gevork. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 100 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Մ. Ճիզմէճեան, <hi
									rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (M. Gismegian, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 311. Gismegian specifies that Margrit
							Awkinian was a teacher, but it is not clear where and what exactly she
							taught. </p></note> The <hi rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>
					mentions another female graduate of the Euphrates College, Srbuhi Arslan. Of the
					47 graduates of 1912, two were Syriacs, one male and one female. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p xml:lang="en"> 101 B.
							Trigona-Harrany, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî</hi>, 176,
							footnote 488. </p></note> The Syriacs also studied at other
					Armenian-language educational institutions of Kharberd, including the Central
					College, the Smbatian Seminary, the school at St. Karapet church, the Girls’
					School of the Lower Quarter, the Capuchins’ and Franciscan Sisters’ schools.
					They also had access to another Armenian-language provider of higher education,
					the Central Turkey College of Aintab (today Gaziantep), which had a medical
					faculty. The impressive number of authors, correspondents and contributors of
						<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nineveh</hi> and their
					high proficiency in the Armenian language, including writing poems, testify to a
					large number of Syriacs who were well-educated in Armenian. </p>
				<p> Kharberd produced one of the most prominent Syriac intellectuals in the Ottoman
					Empire, Ashur Yusuf. He was born Abraham Yusuf <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p xml:lang="en"> 102 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ե.
								Մալճան, “Անտիպ նոթեր”</foreign> (E. Maljan, “Unpublished notes”)
								(<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi> Vol. II, No. 17 [1921]). </p></note>
					in 1858 into the family of tailor Sahak Yusuf. Having graduated from a school in
					Kharberd, he entered the Central Turkey College in Aintab but did not complete
					his studies. For many years, he worked as a teacher in various schools, while
					simultaneously engaging in self-education. Eventually, he became professor of
					Classical Armenian and calligraphy at the Euphrates College. </p>
				<p> Ashur Yusuf was a Protestant <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 103 Ibid. </p></note> . His wife, Arshaluys Oghkasian,
					with whom he had seven children, was the daughter of an Armenian Evangelical
					minister. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p xml:lang="en"> 104
							Information about Ashur Yusuf's family can be found in <hi rend="italic"
								>The Bloody Smile</hi>, an Armenian-language book written by his
							daughter, Alice Nazarian, and published in Beirut in 1963, as well as in
							the unpublished Armenian- language diary by his eldest son, Rasin.
						</p></note> This and the <pb n="304"/> fact that Ashur Yusuf’s knowledge of
					the Syriac language was limited to the alphabet only, did not prevent him from
					becoming the first prominent advocate of nationalist ideas based largely on
					Assyrianism among Western Syriacs; hence the adoption of the pen-name ‘Ashur’
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p xml:lang="en"> 105 Unlike the
							intellectuals of Urmia, whose Assyrianism was largely sparked by the
							terminology used by English missionaries, Ashur Yusuf apparently
							proceeded from his fellow countrymen’s claim of being the “sons of
							Ashur” (H. Southgate, <hi rend="italic">Narrative</hi>, 80). Since this
							claim among Syriac Orthodox is not recorded anywhere else, it is safe to
							assume that it was a reflection of the old Armenian tradition that, at
							the popular level, identified Syriacs with ancient Assyrians. The
							enduring popularity of the legend of Semiramis and Ara the Handsome,
							King of Armenia, would on occasion urge Armenians to remind the Syriacs
							of being “Semiramis’s people.” Having “Assyrians” in their midst was
							important for Armenians (and remains so today in Armenia) for sustaining
							and nourishing their collective historical memory and sense of living
							history. </p></note> . After the Young Turk Revolution of 1908, he
					founded and edited the first Western Syriac periodical in the Ottoman Empire,
					the <hi rend="italic">Mürşid-i-Asiriyun </hi>(“Guide of the Assyrians”), which
					was published in Kharberd in Ottoman Turkish in Syriac script. Most of the
					articles were authored by Ashur Yusuf himself. In the April of 1915, Ashur Yusuf
					was arrested by Ottoman authorities and executed without trial a few days later
					together with all Armenian professors of the Euphrates College. In addition to
					articles, Ashur Yusuf’s surviving legacy includes poems in Armenian and Turkish,
					often imbued with the spirit and imagery typical of Protestant hymns. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p xml:lang="en"> 106 <foreign
								xml:lang="hy"><hi rend="italic">Ասորվոց անզուգական ռահվիրան
								</hi></foreign>(<hi rend="italic">The Inimitable Assyrian
								Pioneer</hi>) (Assyrian Five Association, Boston, 1919). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> Ashur Yusuf’s cousin, Abraham Yusuf (1866-1924), studied medicine at the Central
					Turkey College. He continued his education in the United States and later joined
					the US military rising to the rank of Major. Abraham Yusuf was one of the
					Syriacs delegated to the 1918 Paris Peace Conference. </p>
				<p> Ashur Yusuf was not the only Syriac professor at the Euphrates College. The
					other was Dr. Pierre Dasho, a Catholic mentioned above, who taught French at the
					College in addition <pb n="305"/> to his medical practice. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p xml:lang="en"> 107<foreign xml:lang="hy"> Վ.
								Հայկ, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 335. </p></note> He also published
					health-related articles in Kharberd’s <hi rend="italic">Yeprat</hi>
					(“Euphrates”) Armenian newspaper <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 108 B. Trigona-Harrany, <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman
								Süryânî</hi>, 107. </p></note> , one of which was reproduced in
						<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi>. Incidentally, his brother, priest Poghos
					Dasho (Père Paul), for two years taught French and ancient history at the French
					College of Mezireh <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p xml:lang="en">
							109 <foreign xml:lang="hy"> Վ. Հայկ, <hi rend="italic"
								>Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>),
							417. </p></note> . </p>
				<p> Another prominent Syriac intellectual from Kharberd was Rev. Arakel Petikian
					(1860-1902), a graduate of the Syriac school and the Smbatian Seminary of
					Kharberd. A Protestant minister, he was also a prolific author in the Armenian
					language under the pen-name ‘Gisak’ and is considered to be a part of Western
					Armenian literature. His book <hi rend="italic">Gisakaran, Words and Advices
						from the Bottom of Heart of Gisak</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="hy">Գիսակարան՝
						խօսք եւ խորհուրդք ի խորոց սրտի Գիսակի</foreign>) <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p xml:lang="en"> 110 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ա.
								Տագէսեան, Ա. Իւրնէշլեան, <hi rend="italic">Լիբանանահայ գիրքը
									1894-2012. մատենագիտական ցանկ</hi></foreign> (A. Dagesian, A.
							Eurneshlian, <hi rend="italic">The Lebanese-Armenian Books in 1894-2012:
								a Bibliographic List</hi> (Beirut, Haykazian University Press,
							2013), 44. </p></note> was particularly popular. A more modest man of
					letters and lesser contributor to the Armenian literature was Ezekiel Maljan
					(1880-1965), a graduate of the Euphrates College and the editor of the <hi
						rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>, who published his collected works in
					Armenian entitled <hi rend="italic">Collection of Meditations</hi> (<foreign
						xml:lang="hy">Հաւաքածոյ խորհրդոց</foreign>) <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p xml:lang="en"> 111 <foreign xml:lang="hy"> Վ.
								Հայկ, <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ</hi></foreign> (V. Haig, <hi
								rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>), 508. </p></note> in California in
					1954. </p>
				<p> Ashur Yusuf’s <hi rend="italic">Mürşid-i-asiriyun</hi> was not the only
					periodical published in Kharberd by Syriacs. In 1910, Bishop Dionysius Abdenur
					Aslan published a nine-page periodical, <hi rend="italic">Kawkva d-Suryaye
					</hi>(“Star of the Syriacs”), apparently trying to counterbalance Ashur Yusuf’s
					journal in which he was often severely castigated. The languages were Ottoman
					Turkish and Arabic written in Syriac script. That same year, a four-page
					periodical <hi rend="italic">Hayat</hi> (“Life”) was published in Kharberd, with
					the same text both in Turkish and Arabic Garshuni. The publisher <pb n="306"/>
					was a certain Paulos, who was supposedly another clergyman. Although there were
					printing houses in Kharberd, including the one at the Euphrates College, due to
					the lack of Syriac types, all three Kharberd periodicals were produced manually
					and then duplicated by a mimeograph machine. </p>
				<p> During the 1915 Genocide, the Syriacs of Kharberd eventually shared the fate of
					the Armenians. On June 26, Sabit Bey, the governor of Kharberd, issued a decree
					that Armenians and Syriacs should be exiled to Mesopotamia. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p xml:lang="en"> 112 L. Davis, <hi rend="italic"
								>The Slaughterhouse Province: an American Diplomat’s Report on the
								Armenian Genocide, 1915-1917 </hi>(New Rochelle, New York, Aristide
							D. Caratzas, 1989), 143-144. </p></note> But that same day, the Syriacs
					were allowed to stay in the city for a while, and the gendarmerie had to face
					the challenge of distinguishing them from Armenians, which, according to Henry
					Riggs, the President of the Euphrates College at that time, “was not as easy as
					it might seem.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p xml:lang="en"> 113
							H. Riggs, <hi rend="italic">Days of Tragedy in Armenia: Personal
								Experiences in Harpoot (1915-1917)</hi> (Gomidas Institute, 1997),
							119. Gismegian notes, that “compared to Armenians, they [Syriacs] are
							better built and healthier; even the simplest outfit on a Syriac looks
							very nice, very decent” (M. Gismegian, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>,
							88). Vahe Haig describes Syriacs as “pugnacious and unbridled, but also
							enduring and sturdy” (V. Haig, <hi rend="italic">Kharberd</hi>, 512).
						</p></note> Riggs then adds that Turkish gendarmes forced Syriac boys to
					collect abandoned Armenian property in the Armenian churches of the city. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p xml:lang="en"> 114 H. Riggs, <hi
								rend="italic">Days of Tragedy in Armenia</hi>, 135. </p></note> The
					second wave of arrests of Armenians and Syriacs occurred in the November of the
					same year, mainly in Mezireh, where the local Ottoman authorities and the US
					Consulate were located. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 115 Ch. Walker, “Kharbert in 1915-1916,” in <hi
								rend="italic">Armenian Tsopk/Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian
							(Mazda Publishers, Costa Mesa, California, 2002), 334.- </p></note> In
					the early 1920s, there were still some Syriacs in Kharberd who, with the help of
					their compatriots in the United States, were trying to preserve their
					traditional way of life. Eventually, they too had to leave the city. </p>
				<p> Many Syriacs managed to make it to the United States, which contributed to the
					process of institutionalization of their communities. In the English-speaking
					milieu, they chose to be <pb n="307"/> called “Assyrians,” for a number of
					possible reasons <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p xml:lang="en">
							116 For more on the name issue in the United States see G. Kiraz, <hi
								rend="italic">Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 185-204.
						</p></note> , but also because the impact of Ashur Yusuf’s ideas remained
					very strong (in fact, the Kharberdian communities in Massachusetts and New
					Jersey resisted the longest the switch to ‘Syriac’ nomenclature initiated by the
					Syriac Orthodox Church in the middle of the century). In 1924, the first Syriac
					Orthodox church of the Western Hemisphere was inaugurated in Worcester and named
					after the St. Mary church of Kharberd. The unofficial leader of the
					Massachusetts community was Ashur Yusuf’s cousin, Dr. Abraham Yusuf; Armenian on
					his mother’s side, he was equally involved with the local Armenian community. As
					mentioned above, in the 1920s, an expatriate Syriac community also emerged in
					California with many Syriacs here eventually assimilating into the Armenian
					community because of the big number of intermarriages <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p xml:lang="en"> 117 G. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic"
								>Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 33. </p></note> . </p>
				<p> The English-speaking second generation of the Kharberd Syriacs in the United
					States retained some knowledge of the Armenian language and was even able to
					stage and perform amateur plays and make public speeches in Armenian, as clearly
					indicated by the <hi rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>. Armenian was, after
					all, the only language in which they could communicate with their seniors who
					did not speak English. Armenian, however, was not inherited by the third
					generation. Together with the constant influx of Syriac immigrants from the
					Middle East, this led to the loss of the Armenian language, which was an
					important part of the unique identity of the natives of Kharberd, and the
					eventual disintegration of their old communities. Although in the Middle East
					and Diaspora there are many Syriacs who can converse in Armenian, as a rule,
					that ability is not inherited but acquired through close contacts with
					Armenians. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p xml:lang="en"> 118 In
							contrast, many of the descendants of the Armenian-speaking Syriacs of
							Urfa still preserve Armenian as a “family language” in Syria and <pb
								n="308"/> the Diaspora. The author had an opportunity to communicate
							freely in Armenian with the <hi rend="italic">urfali</hi> Syriacs living
							in Toronto. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p> After the 1915 Genocide, a number of Kharberd Syriacs moved to the Republic of
					Armenia, settling in the <hi rend="italic">Nor Kharberd</hi> (New Kharberd)
					suburb of the capital, Yerevan. Among them was Ashur Yusuf’s eldest son Rasin,
					joined later by his mother, Arshaluys Oghkasian. Because of their Armenian
					language and inevitable intermarriages, these Syriacs were eventually
					assimilated by the Armenians, with very few people in Nor Kharberd preserving
					the memory of their Syriac ancestry today. </p>
				<p> Of the major cities of Western Armenia, Kharberd is perhaps the only one that
					was not only purged of its Christian population as a result of the Genocide but
					was also physically eliminated. In the 1920s, its Muslim population and several
					surviving Syriac families were resettled in Elazığ, while the buildings,
					including the Euphrates College compound and parts of the ancient Kharberd
					citadel, were dismantled and used as building blocks by the Turks. Today, there
					are only naked hillsides where Kharberd once stood, and by some irony, the only
					surviving building is the St. Mary Syriac Orthodox church, which was open to
					visitors until 1998, then locked, and then ‘repaired’ and partially made
					accessible again in the early 2000s. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 119 R. Hewsen, “Golden Plain: the Historical
							Geography of Tsopk/Karbert,” in <hi rend="italic">Armenian
								Tsopk/Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian (Mazda Publishers, Costa
							Mesa, California, 2002), 50. </p></note> Ezekiel Maljan left this elegy
					for the St. Mary church: “For seventeen long centuries, the church of the Holy
					Mother of God stood like a faithful soldier on a rock beside the citadel. It
					witnessed victories and defeats, massacres and oppression, it was the object of
					the devotion of her faithful children, and that of the destruction of barbarous
					hands. Always standing, always vigilant in defending the faith of our
					forefathers who fought and became martyrs for that faith. She is still there
					like a true soldier. The centuries left her a kiss and are gone. Rain and flood,
					snow and storm danced on her roof and left too. Generations came and are gone,
					but the church <pb n="309"/> of the Holy Virgin is still there, nowadays like a
					wounded soldier whose arms and legs are cut off, and the body is broken and
					soaked with blood. The city lay ruined, and only she remains there as if to
					guard the destroyed city that once boasted in its own glory. Her door is firmly
					closed, and pigeons nest on her chest. Slowly she decays like a soul in agony.
					If only a person or institution could be found that, if not out of love for
					religion, but out of love for antiquity and the arts would extend a hand to
					prolong her life just a little bit.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 120 <foreign xml:lang="hy">Ե. Մալճան,
								Հաւաքածոյ</foreign> (E. Maljan, <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>),
							28-29. </p></note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
				<head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
				<listBibl>
					<bibl>Akopian A. <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Aramean and Syriac
							Studies</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2017.</bibl>
					<bibl>
						<hi rend="italic">Assyrian Progress</hi>, California (1933-1938). </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<hi rend="italic">Babylon</hi>, Boston (1919-1921). </bibl>
					<bibl> Barsoum I. A. <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>. Gorgias Press,
						2003. </bibl>
					<bibl> Becker A. <hi rend="italic">Revival and awakening: American Evangelical
							missionaries in Iran and the origins of Assyrian nationalism</hi>. The
						University of Chicago Press, 2015. </bibl>
					<bibl> Brock S. “Armenian in Syriac Script.” In <hi rend="italic">Armenian
							Studies. Études arméniennes. In Memoriam Haïg Berbérian</hi>, ed. D.
						Kouymjian. Lisbon: Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, 1986. </bibl>
					<bibl> Brock S., Kiraz G. <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Concise
							Syriac-English/English-Syriac Dictionary</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2015. </bibl>
					<bibl> Courtois S. de. <hi rend="italic">The Forgotten Genocide: Eastern
							Christians, the Last Arameans</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2004. </bibl>
					<bibl> Davis L. <hi rend="italic">The Slaughterhouse Province: an American
							Diplomat’s Report on the Armenian Genocide, 1915-1917.</hi> New
						Rochelle, New York: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1989. </bibl>
					<pb n="310"/>
					<bibl> Donabed S. and Shamiran M. “Harput, Turkey to Massachusetts: Notes on the
						Immigration of Jacobite Christians.” <hi rend="italic">Chronos: Revue
							d’Histoire de l’Université de Balamand</hi>, No. 23 (2011). </bibl>
					<bibl> Donabed S. <hi rend="italic">Remnants of Heroes: The Assyrian
							Experience</hi>. Assyrian Academic Society, 2003. </bibl>
					<bibl> Fiey J.-M. <hi rend="italic">Pour un Oriens Christianus Novus:
							répertoire des diocèses syriaques orientaux et occidentaux</hi>.
						Orient-Institut, 1993. </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary ofthe Syriac
						Heritage</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2011. </bibl>
					<bibl> Gaunt D. <hi rend="italic">Massacres, resistance, protectors:
							Muslim-Christian relations in Eastern Anatolia during World War I</hi>.
						Gorgias Press, 2006. </bibl>
					<bibl> Hewsen R. “Golden Plain: the Historical Geography of Tsopk/Karbert.” In
							<hi rend="italic">Armenian Tsopk/ Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian.
						Costa Mesa, California: Mazda Publishers, 2002. </bibl>
					<bibl> Jastrow O.<hi rend="italic"> Der neuaramäische Dilekt von Mlahso</hi>.
						Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 1994. </bibl>
					<bibl> Joseph J. <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations and
							Inter-Christian Rivalries in the Middle East</hi>. Albany: State
						University of New York Press, 1983. </bibl>
					<bibl> Kévorkian R. “Demographic Changes in the Armenian Population of
						Diarbekir, 1895-1914.” In <hi rend="italic">Armenian Tigranakert/Diarbekir
							and Edessa/Urfa</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian. Costa Mesa, California: Mazda
						Publishers, 2006. </bibl>
					<bibl> Kieser H.-L. “Ottoman Urfa and its Missionary Witnesses.” In<hi
							rend="italic"> Armenian Tigranakert/Diarbekir and Edessa/ Urfa</hi>, ed.
						R. Hovannisian. Costa Mesa, California: Mazda Publishers, 2006. </bibl>
					<bibl> Kiraz G. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America
							(1895-1995); a short history</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2019. </bibl>
					<pb n="311"/>
					<bibl> Kramers J. H. “Kharput.” In <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of
						Islam</hi>, eds. M. Houtsma, T. Arnold, R. Basset, R. Hartmann. Brill
						Online, 1913-1936. </bibl>
					<bibl> Krikorian M. <hi rend="italic">Armenians in the Service of the Ottoman
							Empire</hi>. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1977. </bibl>
					<bibl> Léart M. (Krikor Zohrap). <hi rend="italic">La question armeniénne à
							la lumière des documents</hi>. Paris, 1913. </bibl>
					<bibl> McCarthy J. <hi rend="italic">Muslims and Minorities: The Population of
							Ottoman Anatolia and the End of the Empire</hi>. New York: New York
						University Press, 1983. </bibl>
					<bibl> Moranci Ch. “The Medieval Architecture of Kharpert.” In <hi rend="italic"
							>Armenian Tsopk/Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian. Costa Mesa,
						California: Mazda Publishers, 2002. </bibl>
					<bibl> Naby E. “Almost Family: Assyrians and Armenians in Massachusetts.” In <hi
							rend="italic">The Armenians of New England</hi>, ed. M. Mamigonian.
						Armenian Heritage Press, 2004. </bibl>
					<bibl> Naby E. and Hopper M., eds. <hi rend="italic">The Assyrian Experience:
							Sources for the Study of the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 20<hi
								rend="superscript">th</hi> Centuries</hi>. Cambridge: Harvard
						College Library, 1999. </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<hi rend="italic">Nineveh</hi>, Boston (1927-1928). </bibl>
					<bibl> Riggs H. <hi rend="italic">Days of Tragedy in Armenia: Personal
							Experiences in Harpoot (1915-1917)</hi>. Gomidas Institute, 1997. </bibl>
					<bibl> Sachau E. <hi rend="italic">Reise in Syrien und Mesopotamien</hi>.
						Leipzig, 1883. </bibl>
					<bibl> Shaw S. and Shaw E. <hi rend="italic">History of the Ottoman Empire and
							Modern Turkey: Volume 2</hi>. Cambridge University Press, 2002. </bibl>
					<bibl> Sokoloff M. <hi rend="italic">A Syriac Lexicon</hi>. Eisenbrauns/Gorgias
						Press, 2009. </bibl>
					<bibl> Southgate H. <hi rend="italic">Narrative of Visit to the Syrian
							[Jacobite] Church of Mesopotamia</hi>. New York, 1856. </bibl>
					<bibl> Sunguroğlu İ. <hi rend="italic">Harput Yollarında</hi>. Istanbul: Yeni
						Matbaa, 1958. </bibl>
					<pb n="312"/>
					<bibl> Takahashi H. and Weitenberg J. “The Shorter Syriac-Armenian Glossary in
						Ms. Yale Syriac 9, Part 1.” <hi rend="italic">Journal ofthe Canadian Society
							for Syriac Studies</hi>, Volume 10 (2010). </bibl>
					<bibl> Taylor W. <hi rend="italic">The Syrian Orthodox Church and the Church of
							England 1895-1914.</hi> Cambridge Scholars Publishing, 2013. </bibl>
					<bibl> Trigona-Harrany B. <hi rend="italic">The Ottoman Süryânî from 1908 to
							1914</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2009. </bibl>
					<bibl> Walker Ch. “Kharbert in 1915-1916.” In <hi rend="italic">Armenian
							Tsopk/Kharpert</hi>, ed. R. Hovannisian. Costa Mesa, California: Mazda
						Publishers 2002. </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<foreign xml:lang="hy">Հայկ Վ. <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ եւ անոր ոսկեղէն
								դաշտը</hi>. Նիւ Եորք</foreign>, 1959 (Haig V. <hi rend="italic"
							>Kharberd and her golden plain</hi>. New York, 1959). </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<foreign xml:lang="hy">Ճիզմէճեան Մ. <hi rend="italic">Խարբերդ եւ իր
								զաւակները</hi>. Ֆրէզնո</foreign>, 1955 (Gismegian M. <hi
							rend="italic">Kharberd and its children</hi>. Fresno, 1955). </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<foreign rend="hy">Մալճան Ե. <hi rend="italic">Հաւաքածոյ խորհրդոց</hi>. Լոս
							Անջելես, </foreign>1954 (Maljan E. <hi rend="italic">Collection of
							Meditations</hi>. Los Angeles, 1954). </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<foreign xml:lang="hy">Նազարեան Ա. <hi rend="italic">Արիւնոտ ժպիտը</hi>.
							Պէյրութ</foreign>, 1965 (Nazarian A. <hi rend="italic">The Bloody
							smile</hi>. Beirut, 1965). </bibl>
					<bibl>
						<foreign xml:lang="hy">Տագէսեան, Ա. եւ Իւրնէշլեան, Ա. <hi rend="italic"
								>Լիբանանահայ գիրքը 1894-2012. մատենագիտական ցանկ</hi>. Պէյրութ,
							Հայկազեան Համալսարանի հայ տպագր.</foreign>, 2013 (Dagesian A. and
						Eurneshlian A. <hi rend="italic">The Lebanese-Armenian Books in 1894-2012: a
							Bibliographic List</hi>. Beirut: Haykazian University Press, 2013).
					</bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
			<pb n="313"/>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2akopian.images">
			<head>Images</head>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 1: The Syriac quarter of Kharberd (source: houshamadyan.org)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image1.jpg" rend="center"/>
			</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 2: The Mart Maryam Syriac church of Kharberd (on the left side, source: Haig V., Kharberd and her golden plain)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image2.png" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 3: The altar of the Mart Maryam church (source: Haig V., Kharberd and her golden plain)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image3.jpg" rend="center"/>
			</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 4: The Euphrates College of Kharberd (source: houshamadyan.org)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image4.jpg" rend="center"/>
			</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 5: Ashur Yusuf (the official Euphrates College photograph, source: Gismegian M., Kharberd and its children)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image5.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 6: Arakel Petikian (source: Gismegian M., Kharberd and its children)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image6.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 7: Gisakaran by Arakel Petikian</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image7.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 8: Ezekiel Maljan (standing far left) with his parents and brothers (source: Maljan E., Collection of Meditations)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image8.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 9: Collection of Meditations by Ezekiel Maljan</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image9.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 10: Dr. Abraham Yusuf (source: Gismegian M., Kharberd and its children)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image10.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 11: The Malke Syriac family of Kharberd (source: houshamadyan.org)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image11.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
				<p><hi rend="bold">Image 12: The Arslan Syriac family of Kharberd (source: houshamadyan.org)</hi></p>
				<p><graphic url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV23N2Akopian_image12.jpg" rend="center"/>
				</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
