<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Notes on the Sanctuary of St. Symeon Stylites at Qalʿat
					Simʿān</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>P. Corby</forename>
						<surname>Finney</surname>
					</name>
					<affiliation>
						<orgName>Princeton, NJ</orgName>
					</affiliation>
				</author>
				<sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
				<editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
				<editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2prfinney</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>P. Corby Finney</author>
						<title level="a">Notes on the Sanctuary of St. Symeon Stylites at Qalʿat
							Simʿān</title>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2PRFinney.pdf</idno>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="430" to="432">430-432</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="9"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
			<change when="2020-08-30">File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="review">
		<body>
			<div type="title" xml:lang="en">
				<ab type="review-title">Emma Loosley Lemming and John Tchalenko, <hi rend="italic"
						>Notes on the Sanctuary of St. Symeon Stylites at Qalʿat Simʿān</hi>
					(Leiden: Brill, 2019). Pp. x + 132; $179.00.</ab>
			</div>
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p> This splendid volume consists of three sections. First, a biographical overview
					(pp. 1-27) documenting the extraordinary life and brilliant work of Georges
					Tchalenko (1905-1987) written by Georges’ son John. Second, a short essay (pp.
					28-32) on the historiography of Qalʿat Simʿān written by Emma Loosely. And
					third, Georges’ <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (written in French) on the
					sanctuary of Qalʿat Simʿān with photographs and plans. Loosley and John
					Tchalenko have translated <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> into English and have
					included selected restoration and reconstruction drawings and photographs housed
					in the Beirut archive of Georges Tchalenko. </p>
				<p> The biographical section reveals first a man who was a gifted student. In 1928
					he earned a degree as a certified engineer at the University of Braunschweig.
					His German mentors praised his work. His sense of architectural design reflects
					the Bauhaus tradition during its initial decades – a connection that would be
					interesting to pursue. Georges Tchalenko also possessed considerable
					organizational talents. His political allegiance was liberal and anti-fascist.
					He was a Slavophile and at the end of the Second World War sought Russian
					citizenship which was twice denied. In 1933 Georges Tchalenko travelled to
					Palestine, and that pre-war date marks the beginning of his archaeological <hi
						rend="italic">magnum opus</hi>. In 1935 he married Gerda Mangold, a union
					that was marked by long bouts of separation. Georges Tchalenko comes across as a
					person of pessimistic, self-critical temperament, dissatisfied especially with
					his ex¬tended state of penury, with the quality of his own work, with his lonely
					life, with his want of a passport, with his longing for repatriation with his
					Motherland (he was born in St. Petersburg), and with lack of scholarly
					recognition. In fact, it is clear from the biographical section that his closest
					friend, Henri <pb n="431"/> Seyrig, Director of the French <hi rend="italic"
						>Services des Antiquités</hi>, held Georges Tchalenko in the highest regard. </p>
				<p> Loosley introduces the beginning of part 2 with a short – and in my view,
					disappointing – discussion of Qalʿat Simʿān as a sacred place. The
					historiography of sacred place begins not in the 1990s as she suggests but
					instead in a late 19<hi
						rend="superscript">th</hi> or early 20<hi
							rend="superscript">th</hi>-century context (cf. P. C. Finney, “TOPOS
					HIEROS und christlicher Sakralbau in vorkonstantinischer Überlieferung” <hi
						rend="italic">Boreas</hi> 7 [1984], 193-225). Loosley expresses the view
					that it was not the personhood of Symeon Stylites that formed the basis of
					Qalʿat Simʿān as a holy place, and this is incorrect. After Symeon’s death the
					only material evidence of his person that survived at Qalʿat Simʿān was the
					column which became the symbolic center of the cult devoted to the veneration of
					the saint. But the column was a holy place because a holy man had resided on it. </p>
				<p> The second part of Loosley’s discussion is biographical, focused on Georges
					Tchalenko’s struggle to bring his work to a successful conclusion. He worked
					with a typewriter and hand-written corrections. Georges Tchalenko wrote under
					difficult circumstances, including exile, war, conflict with his rivals at the
						<hi rend="italic">Institut français du Proche-Orient</hi>, and
					technological limitations. He was still at work on Qalʿat Simʿān and the Syrian
						<hi rend="italic">bêma</hi> churches into his early 80s. </p>
				<p> The third part of this remarkable volume gives Georges Tchalenko’s useful
					historiography of the excavation and restoration of the Qalʿat Simʿān sanctuary.
					The <hi rend="italic">martyrion</hi>, the monastery, the funerary chapel, the
					baptistery, the guest houses (cf. Rabun M. Taylor, “Xenodocheion,” <hi
						rend="italic">The Eerdmans Encyclopedia of Early Christian Art and
						Archaeology</hi> [Grand Rapids, 2017], s.v.) are at issue here. Georges
					Tchalenko gives a chronology of the sanctuary which extends over the 5<hi
						rend="superscript">th</hi> to 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> centuries. He
					traces the history of the sanctuary before and after its restoration. Throughout
					this discussion Georges Tchalenko’s photographs and plans accompany the text.
					The work of restoration is the most impressive part of this discussion. Part 3
					is an informative and important addition to the architectural history of early
					Christian Syria. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
