<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">When Ephrem Meets the Maya</title>
				<title type="sub">Defining and Adapting the Syriac Orthodox Tradition in
					Guatemala</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<forename>Anna</forename>
						<surname>Hager</surname>
					</name>
					<affiliation>
						<orgName>University of Vienna/FWF</orgName>
					</affiliation>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
					<name type="person">Joss Childs></name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition n="0.1"/>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
				<date>2020</date>
				<idno>Volume 23.2</idno>
				<availability>
					<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
						<p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
							license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
							copyright.</p>
					</licence>
				</availability>
				<idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv23n2hager</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>Anna Hager</author>
						<title level="a">When Ephrem Meets the Maya: Defining and Adapting the
							Syriac Orthodox Tradition in Guatemala</title>
						<idno type="URI"/>
						<idno type="PDF"
							>https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol23/HV23N2Hager.pdf</idno>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
							<date>2020</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope type="vol" n="23">23</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="pp" from="215" to="262">215&#8211;262</biblScope>
						<biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
					of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
					Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
					best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
				<!-- ILeave this as is -->
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en"/>
			</langUsage>
			<textClass>
				<keywords xml:lang="en">
					<term>Syriac Orthodox Church></term>
					<term>Guatemalan Syriac Orthodox</term>
					<term>Eduardo Aguirre Oestmann</term>
					<term>Catholic Chrismatic Renewal</term>
					<term>Archdiocese of Central America</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc status="Published">
<change when="2020-09-07">File updated and published by James E. Walters</change>
			<change when="2020-07-28">?File created by Joss Childs</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="article">
		<front>
			<div type="abstract">
				<head>Abstract</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The establishment of a Syriac Orthodox archdiocese in Guatemala
					and Central America in 2013 marked the appearance of Syriac Christianity in a
					context that is linguistically, historically, and ethnically radically different
					from communities in the Middle East and Western diasporas. These “Guatemalan
					Syriac Orthodox” are predominantly Maya and former Roman Catholics from mostly
					poor rural areas, displaying Catholic Charismatic-type practices. This article
					is concerned with Syriac Orthodoxy as a tradition defined by the Church
					leadership for the Guatemalan context, which was subsequently adapted in
					Guatemala through negotiation between the local clergy and lay communities.
					Through this union, the Syriac Orthodox Church has defined what she considers
					non-negotiable aspects of her tradition (liturgy, Syriac language, etc.) and,
					more importantly, she has been able to engage in a dynamic of growth outside the
					Middle East, India, and her diaspora communities and (re)claim a universal scope
					grounded in the biblical event of Antioch. This article adopts a
					pluri-disciplinary approach using field work conducted in Los <pb n="216"/>
					Angeles and Guatemala in late 2018 as well as sources in Spanish, Arabic,
					English. </p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.intro" xml:lang="en">
				<p> In March 2013 a Syriac Orthodox archdiocese was established in Central America,
					with the bulk of its over 500,000 members located in Guatemala. When I mention
					this to persons born into the Church or to scholars working in Syriac Studies,
					they often assume that a Syriac Orthodox diaspora has established itself there
					as a result of migration from the Middle East. When I reply that these are
					actually “new” Syriac Orthodox and overwhelmingly Maya and former Roman
					Catholics, my interlocutors then ask: What liturgy do they use? and, what role
					does the Syriac language have? </p>
				<p> The Syriac Orthodox Church of Antioch with its rich liturgical tradition in the
					Syriac language as well as its now-forming diasporas in the West seems so
					inherently consolidated that the establishment of an archdiocese in a population
					with no prior historical or cultural connection with it sounds somewhat odd.
					Previous scholarly work has shown the importance of liturgy, language, and
					Church institutions in maintaining cohesion in the community in both the Middle
					East <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p xml:lang="en"> 1 M. Calder,
							“Syrian Identity in Bethlehem: From Ethnoreligion to Ecclesiology” (<hi
								rend="italic">Iran and the Caucasus</hi> 20 [2016]), 297-323; T.
							Jarjour, “Ḥasho: Music Modality and the Economy of Emotional Aesthetics”
								(<hi rend="italic">Ethnomusicology Forum</hi>, 24:1 [2015]), 51-72;
							H. Murre-Van den Berg, “A Center of Transnational Syriac Orthodoxy: St.
							Marks’ Convent in Jerusalem” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Levantine
								Studies</hi> 3:1 [2013]), 59-81. </p></note> and the West <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p xml:lang="en"> 2 See H. Armbruster, “<hi
								rend="italic">Wir sprechen die Sprache, die Jesus gesprochen hat”:
								die Vergangenheit in der Gegenwart syrisch-orthodoxer ChristInnen,
								AssyrerInnen in Wien</hi> (Vienna: University of Vienna, Master’s
							thesis, 1994); N. Atto, <hi rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland,
								Orphans in the Diaspora: Identity Discourses among the
								Assyrian/Syriac Elites in the European Diaspora</hi> (Leiden: Leiden
							University Press, Doctoral thesis, 2011); S. Bakker Kellog, “Ritual
							sounds, political <pb n="217"/> echoes: Vocal agency and the sensory
							cultures of secularism in the Dutch Syriac diaspora” (<hi rend="italic"
								>American Ethnologist</hi> 42,3 [2015]): 431-445; G. Kiraz, <hi
								rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America (1895-1995). A
								Short History</hi> (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2019); A. Schmoller
							(ed.), <hi rend="italic">Middle Eastern Christians and Europe:
								Historical Legacies and Present Challenges</hi> (Vienna: Lit, 2018).
						</p></note> . However Western societies <pb n="217"/> pose challenges in
					“how to preserve the Syriac culture, the hallmark of the Syriac liturgical
					tradition, in the host societies.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 3 K. Dinno, <hi rend="italic">The Syrian Orthodox
								Christians in the Late Ottoman Period and Beyond. Crisis then
								Revival</hi> (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2017), 311. </p></note>
					Most studies on Syriac Orthodoxy emphasize its history of suffered violence as a
					“shared story of displacement” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 4 Calder, “Syrian Identity in Bethlehem,” 302.
						</p></note> (which includes <hi rend="italic">Sayfo</hi>, forced migration
					from Edessa, and the absence of official recognition under the Turkish
					Republic). As a result, religious traditions, such as the Beth Gazo (Syriac
					liturgical hymns), are envisioned as sources of healing: “The loss of the
					musical treasure of the church is a story of violence, repression, and
					marginalization. Singing the melodies that remain is an act of reconstructing
					identity out of history’s kaleidoscope,” writes Sarah Bakker Kellogg. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p xml:lang="en"> 5 Bakker Kellog, “Ritual
							sounds,” 441. </p></note> Mark Calder has shown in the case of the
					Syriac Orthodox in Bethlehem that the very notion of <hi rend="italic"
						>ecclesia</hi> facilitates the flexibility of community boundaries and the
					integration of Non-Syriac through the liturgy. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
						n="6"><p xml:lang="en"> 6 See Calder, “Syrian Identity in Bethlehem.”
						</p></note> Many of these studies also highlight the innovations taking
					place in the diasporas (they will be discussed elsewhere in this paper). </p>
				<p> Yet the absence of a Syriac Orthodox past and transmitted ritual practice makes
					the Guatemalan case fascinating. This article examines the emerging
					consolidation of a Syriac Orthodox archdiocese in Guatemala between the early
					2000s and late 2018, when the field work was carried out, with some reference to
					the visit of Patriarch Ephrem II Karim in November 2019. I am concerned with
					Syriac Orthodoxy as a tradition defined by Church leaders for Guatemala and
					subsequently adapted there as an alien <pb n="218"/> tradition through
					negotiation between the local clergy and lay people (including women). The
					process of “Syriacization” comprises not only the theology, the liturgy, the
					sacraments, but also visual, sensorial, and behavioral aspects. This raises the
					question of what the Church leadership considers necessary and contingent to its
					tradition. By the same token, Guatemalan Syriac Orthodoxy informs us about what
					makes its appeal to local communities. Through this union the Syriac Orthodox
					Church has been able to engage in a dynamic of growth outside the Middle East,
					India, and its diaspora communities, and (re)claim a universal scope grounded in
					the event of Antioch (Acts 11), where, for the first time, the disciples of
					Christ were called “Christians” and Gentiles incorporated into the nascent
					community </p>
				<p> The studies mentioned above highlight the tensions between innovation and
					traditional authority and have studied different aspects of tradition. For the
					late Patriarch Ignatius Zakka I Iwas tradition “is, basically, the spiritual
					teaching we have inherited from the Holy Apostles and Church Fathers. Tradition
					is divine, apostolic or patriarchal.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 7 Mor Ignatius Zakka I Iwas, “Tradition” (Patriarchal
							Magazine [January-March, 1990], pp. 91-93). </p></note> Though for the
					Patriarch “tradition” constituted foremost a source of legitimacy, the case of
					Guatemala questions “tradition” in its various dimensions; its content, its
					modes of transmission, its confrontation with other already-existing traditions,
					and the negotiations, tensions, and modifications resulting from it. Edward
					Shils defined “tradition” as “anything which is transmitted or handed down from
					the past to the present.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 8 E. Shils, <hi rend="italic">Tradition</hi> (Chicago:
							University of Chicago Press, 1981), 12. </p></note> Such a broad
					definition, together with his conceptual framework outlined in his article <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p xml:lang="en"> 9 E. Shils, “Tradition”
								(<hi rend="italic">Comparative Studies in Society and History</hi>
							13:2 Special Issue on Tradition and Modernity [1971]), 122-159.
						</p></note> and book provide a useful and complex approach to the evolution
					of Syriac Orthodoxy in Guatemala, starting with a “charismatic figure” who broke
					with the Roman Catholic Church (Part One of the article) <pb n="219"/> and
					subsequently needed “rationalization,” while Syriac Orthodox figures defined a
					tradition for Guatemala (Part Two). The concept elaborated by Shils questions
					the modes of transmission (Part Three) as well as the process of acceptance
					(Parts Four and Five), and examines the rationales behind accepting a tradition
					(Part Six). </p>
				<p> This study adopts a pluri-disciplinary approach using field work conducted in
					Los Angeles and Guatemala in 2018 (qualitative interviews, informal
					conversations, participant observation) <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 10 Persons under the rank of bishop are quoted
							anonymously. Field work was conducted in Los Angeles in August 2018 and
							in Guatemala in November 2018 in the city of San Juan Comalapa,
							Chimaltenango, and the municipality of San Juan Sacatepéquez, where I
							joined the bishop of the Archdiocese. I also carried out participant
							observations in the absence of the archbishop in both Los Angeles and
							Guatemala. Information was also gathered from the Roman Catholic Church
							in Guatemala through written statements from, and informal conversations
							with, Roman Catholics in Comalapa. </p></note> as well as sources in
					Spanish, Arabic, and English produced by the Archdiocese, <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p xml:lang="en"> 11 The website of the Archdiocese of
							Central America (icergua.com), in particular the <hi rend="italic"
								>noticias</hi> tracing the daily activities of the bishop since
							2003, as well as the handbooks for the liturgy, for baptism, etc., were
							useful in tracing the evolution of the movement which eventually became
							Syriac Orthodox. </p></note> by Syriac Orthodox Church figures, and by
					the Roman Catholic Church. Another source was the social media, in particular
					the Facebook pages of the clergy in Guatemala, of the Archdiocese, and of the
					Patriarchate. </p>
				<p> Part One of this study discusses the original break from the Roman Catholic
					Church. Part Two describes the search for an “apostolic” tradition in the
					context of the non-negotiable part of Syriac Orthodox tradition. Parts Three and
					Four are concerned with ritual and with the visual process of “Syriacization,
					respectively.” Part Five examines the ecclesiological framework of the
					Archdiocese. And Part Six explores the core narratives conveyed by the
					Archdiocese. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.1">
				<head>PART ONE: BREAKING WITH ROMAN CATHOLIC TRADITION</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> As Edward Shils noted in 1971, “A person who arrives in a
					situation which is new to him […] comes into an ongoing situation.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p xml:lang="en"> 12 E. Shils,
							“Tradition,” 125. </p></note> The story of the Syriac Orthodox
					Archdiocese in Guatemala starts with the tremendous religious shifts that took
					place in recent decades as a result of which the Roman Catholic Church lost its
					monopoly and new religious beliefs and practices emerged, creating tensions. A
					“charismatic” figure, the former Roman Catholic priest Eduardo Aguirre Oestmann,
					from a Guatemalan European upper middle-class background, became the driving
					force behind the movement, eventually joining the Syriac Orthodox Church in
					2013. Such charismatic figures appear as “breaker[s] of traditions,” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p xml:lang="en"> 13 E. Shils, <hi
								rend="italic">Tradition</hi>, 228. </p></note> who, according to
					Shils: </p>
				<cit>
					<quote><p xml:lang="en">may be regarded as both an exogenous and an
					endogenous change. It is exogenous in the sense that it probably occurs under
					particular circumstances of disorder and of the failure of institutions. But it
					is endogenous insofar as a personality and mind of originality of imagination
					perceives a profound gap in the adequacy of the prevailing tradition and seeks
					to fill that gap, while acknowledging his derivation from it <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p xml:lang="en"> 14 Ibid, 229. </p></note></p></quote>
				</cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In 2003, Fr. Eduardo Aguirre Oestmann (subsequently Fr. Eduardo)
					established a lay and clerical movement of “renewal” in Guatemala. He completed
					a doctorate in Sacred Theology at the Gregorian Institute in Rome <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p xml:lang="en"> 15 Bishop Mor Eduardo
							Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview, 23 November 2018 at San Lucas
							Sacatepéquez. Subsequently quoted as “Aguirre Oestmann, personal
							interview.” </p></note> and was among other things the director of a
					youth pastoral program <pb n="221"/> in a Roman Catholic diocese in Guatemala.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p xml:lang="en"> 16 Mor Santiago
							Eduardo, “Icergua: Introducción a la biografía de Monseñor Eduardo
							Aguirre Oestmann.” </p></note> He later founded a seminary. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p xml:lang="en"> 17 Aguirre Oestmann,
							personal interview. </p></note> The stated goal of the movement he
					established in 2003 was to shift the locus of the Church to the deep local
					level, following the supposed model of the early Church at Pentecost, and thus
					to “rediscover and again fully live with all its characteristics the one, holy,
					and apostolic Church that Christ established when he sent the Holy Spirit on the
					Apostles the day of Pentecost.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 18 Mor Santiago Eduardo, “Icergua: entrevista con el
							obispo en Ahuachapán el Salvador.” </p></note> The movement quickly
					attracted mostly poor rural Mayan communities in several parts of the country,
					particularly Huehuetenango near the Mexican border, El Quiché, and San Juan
					Comalapa. Fr. Eduardo’s activities caught the attention of the Propaganda de
					Fide in the early 2000s, which required him to profess the Catholic faith,
					submit to the authority of the Pope, and cease all pastoral activity. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p xml:lang="en"> 19 Aciprensa,
							“Sacerdote que fundó,” 2006. </p></note> Except for professing the
					Catholic faith, the priest rejected all these demands and was excommunicated in
					2006. This did not prevent the movement from growing: in 2004 it comprised 130
					communities of 50,000 persons, predominantly in the departments of Huehuetenango
					and El Quiché <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p xml:lang="en"> 20
							Icergua, “Asamblea Nacional 2005; informe sobre la situación de la
							comunión a la II asamblea nacional,” November 2005. </p></note> ; but by
					2010 it had half a million participants. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
						n="21"><p xml:lang="en"> 21 Icergua, “Icergua: llegua al medio millón de
							miembros,” 22 December 2010. </p></note> In a letter addressed to his
					followers in 2006, Fr. Eduardo wrote that he had answered “the clamor of
					hundreds of communities and 100,000s of brothers who […] were abandoned,
					marginalized, mistreated, rejected, and, in many cases, denied access to the
					sacraments.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p xml:lang="en"> 22
							Icergua, “Relación Con Roma,” 15 August 2006. </p></note> In an
					interview with the author, he recalled that in 2002, </p>
				<pb n="222"/>
				<cit><quote><p xml:lang="en"> I started having the experience that the Lord
					had entrusted me with a new mission […] I felt a call to resign from all my
					positions […]. [In] 2003 […] after eleven months of prayer, some people came to
					knock at our door: they have been left out of the [Church], because they were
					Charismatics […] [There] were many, many in that situation. The mission grew
					very, very fast, but the rough moment in the relationship with the [Roman]
					Catholic Church was when Comalapa joined us. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
						n="23"><p xml:lang="en"> 23 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview.
						</p></note>
				</p></quote></cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> As Fr. Eduardo mentioned here, his movement attracted two
					different groups, “Charismatics” and <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi> in the
					city of Comalapa, both of which had long-standing tensions with the Roman
					Catholic Church. In 2011, “traditional Catholics” constituted only 27% of the
					country’s Christian population, whereas the revivalist Pentecostals and
					Charismatic Catholics comprised 25% and 27% respectively. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p xml:lang="en"> 24 D. Jacobsen, <hi rend="italic"
								>The World’s Christians: Who They Are, Where They Are, and How They
								Got There</hi> (Chichester: Wiley-Blackwell, 2011), 207. </p></note>
					The Catholic Charismatic Renewal (<hi rend="italic">Renovación Carismática
						Católica</hi>, called “<hi rend="italic">la renovación,</hi>” subsequently
					CCR <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p xml:lang="en"> 25 To avoid
							ambiguities, “Charismatic” with a capital “C” refers to the Catholic
							Charismatic Renewal (CCR), whereas “charismatic” refers to the model of
							the charismatic figure described by Edward Shils. </p></note> ) is a
					movement that emerged within Roman Catholicism in reaction to, or in parallel
					with, the general rise of Pentecostal movements. It similarly emphasizes the
					working of the Holy Spirit and the idea of a personal “conversion experience,”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p xml:lang="en"> 26 O. Compagnon,
							“La crise du catholicisme latino-américain” (<hi rend="italic"
								>L'Ordinaire des Amériques</hi> 210 [2008]). </p></note> but insists
					on the importance of also receiving the sacraments and attending the liturgy.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p xml:lang="en"> 27 J-L Benoit,
							“Religion populaire et crise identitaire en Amérique latine” (<hi
								rend="italic">Amerika</hi> 6 [2012]). </p></note> The attitude of
					the Roman Catholic Church in Guatemala towards the CCR has been ambivalent,
					hesitating <pb n="223"/> between approval <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28"
						n="28"><p xml:lang="en"> 28 In 1986 the Episcopal Conference of Guatemala
							issued a document establishing the framework for Catholic Charismatic
							Renewal (see “66: Renovados en el Espíritu. Instrucción pastoral
							colectiva de los obispos de Guatemala sobre le renovación carismática”.
							In <hi rend="italic">Al servicio de la vida, la justicia y la paz
								(1956-1997)</hi>, 30 March 1986). </p></note> and condemnation. One
					area that eventually became Syriac Orthodox and joined the movement very early
					was Huehuetenango, where the CRR was forbidden until 2012 and developed
					illegally. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p xml:lang="en"> 29 J.
							Thorsen, “El impacto de la renovación carismática en la Iglesia católica
							de Guatemala” (<hi rend="italic">Anuario de Estudios
								Centroamericanos</hi> 42:1 [2016]), 213-236, 216. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In his comment above, Fr. Eduardo mentioned the mainly
					K’aqchiqel-Maya city of San Juan Comalapa, Chimaltenango, located 50 miles (80
					km) from Guatemala City in a somewhat isolated area. There the conflict with the
					Roman Catholic Church involved the role of the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi>,
					lay religious brotherhoods organized around local rites, in this case those of
					the colonial San Juan Bautista church, famous for its many wooden statues of
					Christ, Mary, and the saints. In the 1950s Catholic Action, a movement endorsed
					by the Church, arrived in Comalapa and, in an attempt to promote more orthodox
					Roman Catholic practices, alienated the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi>, who
					consider themselves the guardians of the syncretic Catholic-Mayan culture and
					the interests of the people. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 30 See Cofradía Catedral de San Juan Bautista, “La
							verdadera historia de la Iglesia San Juan Bautista. San Juan Comalapa,
							Chimaltenango, Guatemala Centro América,” 2008. </p></note> Tensions
					escalated and in 1968 one person was killed. Subsequently, people attending the
					San Juan church and attached to the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi> complained
					about pastoral neglect by the Roman Catholic Church. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p xml:lang="en"> 31 See Hager, “The Emergence of a
							Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala” (<hi rend="italic"
								>International Journal of Latin American Religions</hi> 3:2 [2019]),
							370–389, 374-375. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Another important factor was the civil war from the 1960s to the
					1990s, which severely affected the indigenous Mayas, who represent 45-60% of the
					population. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p xml:lang="en"> 32 H-J.
							Prien, <hi rend="italic">Das Christentum in Lateinamerika. IV.6.
								Kirchengeschichte in Einzeldarstellungen</hi> (Leipzig: Evangelische
							Verlagsanstalt, 2007), 395-6. </p></note> A fact-finding commission
					established that the violence on the part of the army constituted genocide
					against the Mayas: 100,000 to 150,000 people were killed or disappeared and
					200,000 Mayans fled to Mexico. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 33 V. Sandford, “From Genocide to Feminicide: Impunity
							and Human. Rights in Twenty-First Century Guatemala” (<hi rend="italic"
								>Journal of Human Rights</hi> 7 [2008]), 104–122, 106. </p></note>
					Although it is not possible to establish a direct causal relation between the
					violence and the communities joining Fr. Eduardo’s movement, many of them were
					located in the areas affected, including Chajul in El Quiché, Huehuetenango, and
					Comalapa. Also, though the Mayan population constitutes only around half of the
					general population, they comprise 95% of the Archdiocese. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p xml:lang="en"> 34 Aguirre Oestmann, personal
							interview. Currently 21 Mayan and two non-Mayan languages are officially
							recognized alongside Spanish (S. Davis, “Mouvement maya et culture
							nationale au Guatemala,” <hi rend="italic">Journal de la société des
								américanistes</hi> 90:2 [2004]). </p></note> In his first pastoral
					letter, issued in 2007, Fr. Aguirre explicitly connected the war with the growth
					of his movement: “A great many [communities] are in areas that suffered under
					the armed conflict, having been persecuted, slaughtered, and displaced: it is no
					coincidence.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p xml:lang="en"> 35 A.
							Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,”
							373. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Fr. Eduardo’s movement of <hi rend="italic">renovación </hi>thus
					filled needs felt by a diverse set of communities, Charismatics in Huehuetenango
					and syncretic Roman Catholic Mayas in Comalapa. These were spiritual,
					sacramental, and pastoral needs. All these communities displayed a deep
					attachment to the form of Christianity they practiced. The movement he
					envisioned in 2003, which he named <hi rend="italic">Santa María del Nuevo
						Éxodo</hi> (“Saint Mary of the New Exodus”) and later <hi rend="italic"
						>Iglesia Católica Ecuménica Renovada</hi> (“Catholic, Ecumenical, Renewed
					Church,” Icergua), was a <hi rend="italic">renovación </hi> to the extent that,
					like the Roman Catholic Church itself, he promoted conversion while <pb n="225"
					/> insisting on the importance of the sacraments and liturgy, especially the
					Eucharist: “The adoration of the Holy Sacrament constitutes the marker of our whole
					spirituality and the deeds of piety that we undertake.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p xml:lang="en"> 36 Icergua, “Acta Fundacional de la
							Comunión,” 25 March 2003. </p></note> A community leader in Los Angeles
					but originally from Huehuetenango recalled to the author that, as Charismatics,
					they were denied sacraments by the Roman Catholic Church. By contrast CCR, as
					defined by the Roman Catholic Church in 1986, decisively took Jesus Christ as
					the starting point for any type of renewal, something Fr. Eduardo did not. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p xml:lang="en"> 37 See Episcopal
							Conference of Guatemala, “66: Renovados en el Espíritu. Instrucción
							pastoral colectiva de los obispos de Guatemala sobre le renovación
							carismática,” 409. </p></note> Instead he focused on the work of the
					Holy Spirit: “Guided by the force of the Spirit, we offer our whole existence in
					order to be instruments [...] that the Gospel be perceived by every human being
					as the answer to the new realities, problems, and perspectives that have emerged in
					the contemporary world.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 38 Icergua, “Acta Fundacional de la Comunión,” 25 March
							2003. </p></note> He thus could appeal to the spiritual needs of the
					communities, while his commitment to return to the early Church appealed to a
					desire for local control and lay involvement in the communities’ rituals. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> As Edward Shils noted, “The charismatic message becomes
					rationalized, elaborated, clarified, fortified to withstand criticisms from
					rival traditions,” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p xml:lang="en"> 39
							E. Shils, <hi rend="italic">Tradition</hi>, 230. </p></note> such as
					excommunication by the Roman Catholic Church in 2006. Fr. Eduardo therefore
					began to examine other “apostolic” traditions. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.2">
				<head>PART TWO: TOWARDS UNION AND THE STRUCTURAL FRAMEWORK OF A NEW TRADITION</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> As more and more communities in Guatemala joined the movement,
					while rites were elaborated which apparently <pb n="226"/> differed from Roman
					Catholic practices, there arose a need for legitimization. Shils notes:
					“[R]ecommended is not a search for just any traditional belief or practice. […]
					Sometimes the search goes ʻabroad’ and finds once or still accepted beliefs and
					practices which are thought to be more valid than the current beliefs and practices” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p xml:lang="en"> 40 Shils, “Tradition,”
							133. </p></note> –something the Syriac Orthodox Church seemed to
					provide. There were, however, other factors explaining the choice of this Church
					over some other Eastern or Oriental Orthodox tradition. And, as of late 2018,
					incorporating with the Syriac Orthodox Church is an ongoing process. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> According to his own accounts, Fr. Eduardo always identified
					Orthodoxy as “the best expression of the early Church.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p xml:lang="en"> 41 Aguirre Oestmann, personal
							interview. </p></note> Contacts with the Eastern Orthodox Churches
					started in the late 2000s after prior contacts with the Old Catholic Church of
					Utrecht and the “Brazilian Catholic Church” (which ordained him Bishop). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p xml:lang="en"> 42 See A. Seraphim,
							“Orthodox Mission in the Twenty-First Century: Guatemala” (<hi
								rend="italic">The Glastonbury Review</hi> 126 [2015]). </p></note>
					Upon closer acquaintance, Fr. Eduardo came to consider the Old Catholics of
					Utrecht as “too close to the Anglicans and the Lutherans and we were looking for
					something more apostolic.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 43 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview. The term
							“apostolic” will be discussed in Part Six. </p></note> Dialogue with the
					Eastern Orthodox Church was well under way when the latter requested Fr. Eduardo
					and his clergy to be baptized and chrismated, something he rejected. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p xml:lang="en"> 44 Ibid. </p></note> In
					the end the bishop described his path towards the Syriac Orthodox Church
					(instead of another Oriental Orthodox Church) as the result of divine
					intervention: “To tell you the truth, it was nothing that came from readings, or
					from [the Church] Fathers, it was something that the Lord put into my heart […]
					I cannot tell you why we opted for the <pb n="227"/> Syriac Orthodox Church and
					not for the Coptic [Orthodox Church]. God put us in the presence of the SOC.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p xml:lang="en"> 45 Ibid.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The first contacts took place in 2010, when Fr. Eduardo approached
					the Syriac Orthodox bishop for the Western United States, Clemis Eugene Kaplan
					(subsequently “Bishop Clemis”). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="47"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 46 B. M. C. E. Kaplan, personal interview, 21 August 2018
							in Burbank. Cited subsequently as “Kaplan, personal interview.”
						</p></note> This was followed by a first official visit in April 2011. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p xml:lang="en"> 47 SOC-WUS, “His
							Eminence Mor Clemis Eugene welcomed Bishop Eduardo of Guatemala,” 9
							April 2011. </p></note> More than seven meetings took place in
					California, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p xml:lang="en"> 48
						SOC-WUS, ""<foreign xml:lang="ar">صفحةٌ تأريخية في تاريخ الكنيسة السريانية الأرثوذكسية</foreign>
						</p></note> followed by one in Guatemala in August 2012. As Bishop Clemis
					recalled, the dialogue initially emphasized matters of creed. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p xml:lang="en"> 49 Kaplan, personal interview.
						</p></note> Simultaneously, Fr. Eduardo and his clergy were submitted to an
					intense introduction to “the teachings of our Church,” “the “study of the holy
					book,” and “theological sources,” and for the first time celebrated a mass in
					Guatemala according to the Syriac liturgy–though in Spanish. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p xml:lang="en"> 50 SOC-WUS, “[From the Archive].”
						</p></note> This probably occurred in the summer of 2012, when the secretary
					of Bishop Clemis instructed Bishop Eduardo on how to perform the Syriac liturgy.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p xml:lang="en"> 51 Icergua, “02:
							Primera celebración de la divina liturgia de Santiago por nuestro
							Obispo,” 2 August 2012. </p></note> Following his visit to Guatemala in
					August 2012, Bishop Clemis submitted a report to the Holy Synod which, though it
					did not specify the exact changes implemented so far, stated that Fr. Eduardo
					and his clergy had been trained in “the proper procedures for the Syriac Rite.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p xml:lang="en"> 52 M.C.E. Kaplan,
							“Historical Moment in the History of the Syriac Orthodox Church,” given
							to the author on 21 August 2018 in Burbank. </p></note> An episcopal
					committee subsequently discussed this report and thoroughly questioned <pb
						n="228"/> Bishop Eduardo. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 53 Kaplan, personal interview. </p></note> During the
					same period, the Bishop reportedly consulted his communities, seeking their
					approval for the union. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 54 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview. </p></note> When
					the union was finalized in March 2013, he was only tonsured a monk and given the
					name of Jacob (Spanish Santiago) in memory of Jacob Baradeus (6<hi
						rend="superscript">th</hi> century). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55"
						n="55"><p xml:lang="en"> 55 Icergua, “05: Tonsura de nuestro obispo como
							monje, por su Santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I Iwas,” 5 March 2013. </p></note>
					Patriarch Ignatius Zakka I Iwas further recognized in the encyclical of March
					2013 that created the Archdiocese of Central America, comprising Guatemala,
					Mexico, Central America, the Caribbean islands, and Venezuela. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p xml:lang="en"> 56 Icergua, “05:
							Encíclicas de su santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I, concernientes a nuestra
							iglesia,” 5 March 2013. </p></note> This recognition as an <hi
						rend="italic">archdiocese</hi> rather than as a patriarchal vicariate
					ensures Fr. Eduardo of maintaining significant autonomy and leverage. Prior to
					the mid-1990s, the United States and Canada had formed a single archdiocese
					under Archbishop Samuel, which then split into three patriarchal vicariates
					(Canada, the Western United States under Bishop Clemis, and the Eastern United
					States under Bishop Cyril Karim until he was elected Patriarch Ephrem II Karim
					in 2014), ensuring more control by the Patriarchate in Damascus. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p xml:lang="en"> 57 Kiraz, <hi
								rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 256.
						</p></note> According to Bishop Eduardo, when Bishop Karim was elected
					Patriarch, he wished to turn the Archdiocese of Central America into a
					patriarchal vicariate, something the former refused; “If [the] archdiocese is
					not valid, we don’t know if [we are] still part of Syriac Orthodox [Church].”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p xml:lang="en"> 58 Aguirre
							Oestmann, personal interview. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The creation of the Archdiocese of Central America is thus the
					result of an increasingly global Syriac Orthodox Church, with Bishop Clemis and
					his secretary playing a major role. The early stages of the union indicated how
					the Syriac Orthodox hierarchy envisioned this unprecedented historical <pb
						n="229"/> event, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p xml:lang="en">
							59 Etienne Naveau studied the case of a priest in Indonesia who
							established a small Syriac Orthodox community and Institute for Syriac
							Christian Studies which has not been officially recognized by and
							integrated into the Syriac Orthodox Church (“Les orthodoxes syriaques
							d’Indonésie” (<hi rend="italic">Les Cahiers de l'Orient</hi> 93:1
							[2009]), 111-124). </p></note> the idea prevailing that the Church was
					answering a plea “after having studied the request asking to form part of our
					apostolic see of Antioch.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 60 Icergua, “05: Encíclicas de su santidad Ignacio Zaqueo
							I, concernientes a nuestra iglesia,” 5 March 2013. </p></note> Bishop
					Clemis’ secretary wrote, “The Syriac Orthodox see of Antioch empathizes with
					[the people in Guatemala], she is interested in their affairs and strives to
					improve their spiritual conditions.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 61 SOC-WUS, “[From the Archive].” </p></note> He also
					spoke of a “desire” for “complete fusion with [<hi rend="italic">indimāj</hi>]
					the body of our Syriac Church.” Similarly, in the document submitted to the Holy
					Synod, Bishop Clemis wrote of “com[ing] into the embrace of the Syriac Orthodox
					Church of Antioch.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p xml:lang="en">
							62 Kaplan, “Historical Moment in the History of the Syriac Orthodox
							Church.” </p></note> The terms used in Arabic and English by the Syriac
					Orthodox Church suggest a more far-reaching process than the word used in
					Spanish, <hi rend="italic">unión</hi>, which implies a certain level of
					equality. According to Bishop Clemis, this process further entailed a “total
					submission to the presidency of His Holiness the Supreme Pontiff of Mor Ignatius
					Zakaa I Iwas, the Supreme Head of the Universal Syriac Orthodox Church and its
					teachings-Semitism and the apostolic faith.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
						n="63"><p xml:lang="en"> 63 Ibid. The terms “Semitism” and “apostolic faith”
							will be discussed in Part Six. </p></note> The encyclical issued in
					March 2013 by the Patriarch also emphasized obedience to “the faith, doctrine,
					and liturgy of the One, Holy, Catholic, and Apostolic Church.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p xml:lang="en"> 64 Icergua, “05:
							Encíclicas de su santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I, concernientes a nuestra
							iglesia,” 5 March 2013. In the Spanish version all these adjectives are
							written with capital letters; but to avoid confusion with the Roman
							Catholic Church, “catholic” will be used here without a capital “c” when
							that Church is not explicitly meant. </p></note> Concerning the liturgy,
					Patriarch Igantius Zakka Iwas <pb n="230"/> declared, “In the Archdiocese the
					liturgical and sacramental rites followed in the Holy Apostolic See of Antioch will be
					gradually implemented and celebrated according to the texts that we have blessed
					and delivered to our brother Mor Jacob (Santiago) Eduardo.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p xml:lang="en"> 65 Icergua, “05: Encíclicas de su
							santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I, concernientes a nuestra iglesia,” 5 March
							2013. </p></note>
				</p>
				<pb n="230"/>
				<p xml:lang="en"> These non-negotiable parts of Syriac Orthodox tradition though are
					subject to the modes of transmission. Edward Shils notes, “The mechanisms of
					the traditional transmission are always bound to be faulty in some way.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p xml:lang="en"> 66 E. Shils,
							“Tradition,” 151. </p></note> They involved the transmission by Syriac
					Orthodox figures to Aguirre (and his clergy) in written and oral form based on a
					text. When dialogue was established, the Bishop of Western US began providing
					Bishop Eduardo with material and instructions in English (including Church
					Fathers like Philoxenos of Mabbug <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 67 Kaplan, personal interview. </p></note> and the three
					volumes of <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Pearl</hi>
					<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p xml:lang="en"> 68 Icergua, “07:
							Visita a Mor Clemis Eugene en su sede arzobispal de Burbank,
							California,” 7 December 2012. </p></note> ), these discussions again
					centering on “the differences between the Catholic and the Orthodox Churches.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p xml:lang="en"> 69 Kaplan,
							personal interview. </p></note> Bishop Eduardo also worked from Sunday
					School materials. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p xml:lang="en"> 70
							Icergua, “20: Visita a la comunidad de fieles de la catedral de San
							Efrén, Burbank, Californa,” 20 January 2014. </p></note> He then
					produced handbooks in Spanish for liturgy, baptisms, and weddings which have
					been revised by the Diocese of the Western United States <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p xml:lang="en"> 71 Icergua, “16: Reuniones en St.
							Ephrem’s Cathedral en Burbank, California,” 16 February 2013.
						</p></note> and approved by the Patriarch. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72"
						n="72"><p xml:lang="en"> 72 Icergua, “19: El patriarca envía la encíclica de
							bendición para la publicación del sacramentario de la arquidiócesis,” 19
							June 2017. </p></note> The handbooks employ drawings and very simple
					language (“the Holy Spirit is like the sun which provides energy to the grain
						<pb n="231"/> of faith” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 73 ICASOA, <hi rend="italic">Guía para la formación
								catequética en preparación a la iniciación cristiana</hi> (San Lucas
							Sacatepéquez: Editorial Nuevo Éxodo, colección didaché 1 [4]), 22.
						</p></note> ), and outline didactic training methods for clergy and
					catechists. Besides these handbooks, Bishop Eduardo also uses the website of the
					Archdiocese (icergua.com), which features all the material, Patriarchal
					encyclicals (translated into Spanish), and the Bishop’s activities (under the
					heading <hi rend="italic">noticias</hi>), which are also given on the latter’s
					Facebook page. Although the dissemination and use of the handbooks may be
					limited in the Archdiocese, their content is further promulgated through the
					Bishop’s sermons and talks during his travels through the Archdiocese performing
					church services and training clergy and active laity. Bishop Eduardo combines
					speeches and liturgy with didactic methods, thus closely interacting with the
					communities. Here language is crucial, for the clergy and laity rarely speak
					English and only have access to what is produced in Spanish by the Bishop or
					translated into a Mayan language for those–and there are still many, especially
					among the older generation–who are not fluent in Spanish. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p xml:lang="en"> 74 One priest told the author that,
							because they usually do not speak English, in Guatemala the priests and
							laity have access only to what is available in Spanish, which is
							exclusively produced by Bishop Eduardo (they do not seem to be aware of
							the material produced by the Syriac Orthodox diocese of Argentina). In
							contrast, the Roman Catholic Church produces a tremendous amount of
							material, including material in the Mayan languages. This situation
							produces a distorted perception: the priest told the author that he had
							the feeling Syriac theology was “poor” compared to Roman Catholic
							theology. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> This Part has presented, first, the motivations for union with the
					Syriac Orthodox Church, second, “Syriac Orthodoxy” as defined by the Church
					figures involved in the process of union, and, third, the tools of transmission
					of doctrine. But any discussion of “tradition” would be incomplete without
					describing how Syriac Orthodoxy was adapted and adopted in the context of
					Guatemala. </p>
				<pb n="232"/>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.3">
				<head>PART THREE: THE SACRAMENTAL AND LITURGICAL TRADITION</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Though the Syriac Orthodox Church leadership understood this union
					as an alien community <hi rend="italic">embracing</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
						>fusing with</hi> its tradition and thus <hi rend="italic">becoming</hi>
					full members of the Church, Syriac Orthodoxy in fact encountered in Guatemala
					“an ongoing situation” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p xml:lang="en"
							> 75 Shils, “Tradition,” 125. </p></note> that included traditional
					Roman Catholicism, Charismatic Roman Catholicism, and syncretic Roman
					Catholic-Mayan traditions. Plus, since the mid-2000s Bishop Eduardo had
					developed and gradually implemented a “renewed Catholic rite” (<hi rend="italic"
						>rito católico renovado</hi>); <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 76 Icergua, “Primera plática informe acerca de la
							situación actual de ICERGUA,” November 2008. </p></note> and in 2011 an
					“Old Catholic” rite was developed with old <hi rend="italic">anaphoras</hi>.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p xml:lang="en"> 77 Icergua, “23:
							Aprobación ʻad experimentum” del sacramentario católico ortodoxo
							latino,” 23 August 2011. </p></note> After contacts with the Syriac
					Orthodox Church were established, further changes were implemented in the
					sacraments and liturgy. An key element of the way in which changes were adapted
					and adopted is the strong attachment of the communities to the sacraments and
					proper pastoral care. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In a March 2013 encyclical, Patriarch Ignatius Zakka I Iwas
					stated: “In the archdiocese the liturgical and sacramental rites followed in the
					Holy See of Antioch will be gradually implemented and celebrated <hi
						rend="underline">according to the texts</hi> that we have blessed and
					delivered to our brother Mor Jacob (Santiago) Eduardo [my emphasis].” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p xml:lang="en"> 78 Icergua, “05:
							Encíclicas de su santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I, concernientes a nuestra
							iglesia,” 5 March 2013. </p></note> The sacraments of marriage and
					baptism have been adapted, the latter now also including Chrismation and First
					Communion in compliance with Syriac Orthodoxy, based on the presumed practice of
					the early Church and framed in opposition to both Roman Catholic and Pentecostal
					practices. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p xml:lang="en"> 79 ICASOA,
								<hi rend="italic">Guía […] preparación a la iniciación
								cristiana</hi>, 3, 8. </p></note> The handbook on baptism thus
					reflects Syriac Orthodox views: “Through <pb n="233"/> baptism we are born to a
					new life (see Jn 3:5), we are purified from sin (Acts 2:38), we achieve in
					Christ the condition of children of God (Rom. 8:15-16; Gal. 4:5-7), temples of
					the Holy Spirit (see Acts 2:38), and living members of the Church (1 Cor 12).”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p xml:lang="en"> 80 Ibid, 14.
						</p></note> The Syriac Orthodox practice of including Chrismation and First
					Communion emphasizes the central role of the Spirit: the handbook used in
					Guatemala states, “Through the anointment with Saint Chrism and the imposition
					of hands, the Holy Spirit and its gifts are received to grow in the life in the
					Spirit.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p xml:lang="en"> 81 Ibid, 9.
						</p></note> The Holy Spirit is indeed the main figure in Syriac Orthodox
					doctrine: “Anointing with Holy Chrism is considered like receiving the gifts of
					the Holy Spirit.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p xml:lang="en"> 82
							SOC-WUS; Rev. Father John Khoury, “The Seven Living Sacraments,” 29
							March 2010. </p></note> However, confirmation has been maintained and
					constitutes an important feature both of Bishop Eduardo’s narrative <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p xml:lang="en"> 83 See Part Six.
						</p></note> and of local community life. The church of San Juan de Comalapa
					was crowded for the confirmation of over 200 young people attended by the author
					and was an important event in local community cohesion because of the visible
					role played by the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi> in the Syriac Orthodox
					Church, though confirmation has also been introduced imitating the Roman
					Catholic rite <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p xml:lang="en"> 84
							Atto, <hi rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland</hi>, 245. </p></note>
					. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> A core element of Syriac Orthodoxy is the West Syriac liturgy of
					Antioch. In 2013 the late Patriarch Zakka I Iwas agreed to and blessed a special
					liturgy which included the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> (memorial of the
					Last Supper) and <hi rend="italic">epiclesis</hi> (invocation of the Holy Spirit
					on the bread and wine) of the liturgy of Saint James, <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p xml:lang="en"> 85 Icergua, “01: Encuentro de
							nuestro Arzobispo Mor Santiago Eduardo con su Santidad Ignacio Efrén
							II.,” 1 March 2014. </p></note> but “for pastoral reasons, given the
					culture and customs of the presbytery and faithful of the archdiocese of
					Central America, elements of the Western rite <pb n="234"/> were maintained
					in non-essential parts.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 86 Icergua, “Raíces históricas del proceso que nos ha
							llevado hasta ser constituidos en arquidiócesis de Centro América de la
							Santa Iglesia Católica Apostólica siro-ortodoxa de Antioquía,” November
							2014. </p></note> This “Western” rite was confirmed under Patriarch
					Ephrem II Karim. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p xml:lang="en"> 87
							Icergua, “01: Encuentro de nuestro Arzobispo Mor Santiago Eduardo con su
							Santidad Ignacio Efrén II.,” 1 March 2014. </p></note> The respect paid
					to local traditions was also emphasized by Bishop Clemis: “They have started to
					slowly change their rite, from Western to Eastern […] they have their own
					language, their own traditions, their own heritage.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p xml:lang="en"> 88 Kaplan, personal interview.
						</p></note> Currently in the Archdiocese the Saint James liturgy is
					performed every Thursday in the seminary run by Bishop Eduardo with the priest’s
					back to the congregation, <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 89 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview. </p></note>
					whereas the parishes and communities use the “Western” Syriac liturgy, during
					which the priest, following the Second Vatican Council, faces the community. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Overall, the theology of the “Western” rite is Syriac: the Credo
					does not mention the <hi rend="italic">Filioque</hi> (the Holy Spirit proceeding
					from the Father <hi rend="italic">and the Son</hi>); and the canon of the Living
					Fathers of the Church includes the Syriac Orthodox Patriarch. The sequence prior
					to the <hi rend="italic">anaphora</hi> closely follows the one of the Roman
					Catholic Church, whereas the actual liturgy (<hi rend="italic">anaphora</hi>)
					follows a Syriac Orthodox order, albeit much shortened. The <hi rend="italic"
						>epiclesis</hi> (the invocation of the Holy Spirit in the wine and bread)
					has both shorter and a longer versions, the latter strongly similar to the <hi
						rend="italic">epiclesis</hi> of Saint James as published by Bishop Mor
					Athanasius <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p xml:lang="en"> 90 Mar
							Athanasius Y. Samuel, <hi rend="italic">Saint James Liturgy Anaphora.
								The Divine Liturgy of Saint James</hi> (1967). </p></note> –bearing
					in mind that Bishop Eduardo based it on an English translation. The adoption of
					the Syriac <hi rend="italic">anaphoras</hi> finds its justification in its
					alleged authenticity: “The central and fundamental part of the liturgy comes
					from Jerusalem […] and subsequently, through Peter and other Apostles like
					Bernabe, was carried to <pb n="235"/> Antioch, where it was consolidated and
					developed.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p xml:lang="en"> 91
							Icergua. “Identidad y perspectivas pastorales de la arquidiócesis de
							Centro América,” November 2014.</p></note> Such a flexible approach to
					liturgy follows an established pattern in the Syriac Orthodox Church whose Grand
					Synod in 1930 expressed the need to harmonize the liturgy, which had been
					practiced differently in different churches for a long time. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p xml:lang="en"> 92 Majallat al-Hikma, “<foreign
								xml:lang="ar">خلاصة مقررات مجمع دير مار متى المقدس بالموصل
							</foreign> [Summary of the Decisions of the Synod at Mar Mattai
							Monastery in Mosul],” Nr. 9, Year 4, November 1930, Pages 516-523, 516.
						</p></note> The current Patriarch continued this process during his tenure
					as bishop of the Eastern United States when he shortened the liturgy and
					expanded the role played by lay people, such as singing. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p xml:lang="en"> 93 Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The
								Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 258-9. </p></note> By
					contrast, the diasporas tend to consider the liturgy as a fixed, repetitive
					practice. In her study on Syriac Orthodox from Tur Abdin in Austria, Heidemarie
					Armbrust quoted a priest as stating, “If a cleric happened to omit some sign or
					symbolic act in the liturgy, he would have to face strong resistance by the
					believers, even if they constitute only negligible accessory parts.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p xml:lang="en"> 94 Quoted in H.
							Armbruster: “Falls ein Geistlicher irgendwelche Zeichen oder
							Symbolhandlungen in der Liturgie entfallen ließe, hätte er mit großem
							Widerstand unter den Gläubigen zu rechnen, auch wenn sie nur
							unwesentliches Beiwerk wären.” (Armbruster, <hi rend="italic">"Wir
								sprechen die Sprache, die Jesus gesprochen hat"</hi>, 147).
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In the case of Guatemala there is not only a discrepancy between
					the written text and the reality of its practice, but also the liturgy is
					reinvented each time. Bishop Eduardo adapts his liturgy according to the
					audience. For instance, he said the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> in Syriac
					at the confirmation in Comalapa mentioned above, whereas when visiting remote
					rural communities in another part of Guatemala, he tended to use some words in
					Syriac for the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> and said the Lord’s Prayer in
					Syriac, introducing it with the explanation, “Do you know what was Jesus’
					language? Aramaic. Therefore for those who have the handbook, go to page 15.”
					Variations in the liturgy also occur when the clergy or community leaders <pb
						n="236"/> perform the service in the absence of the Bishop. The services I
					attended were exclusively in Spanish or bilingual Spanish-K’aqchiqel and no
					Syriac was used. At one service in Guatemala Pope Francis was explicitly
					mentioned in the Canon of the Living Fathers. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> A crucial element of traditional Syriac liturgy is the role and
					place of the Syriac language, even though the vernacular language is also used,
					particularly for the sermons. Studies have demonstrated the emotional importance
					of the Syriac liturgy: Mark Calder notes that “the most often-cited reason for
					pride in the Aramaic tongue is that it was ‘the language of our Lord’, and the
					Lord’s Prayer in Syriac is an especially intense moment.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p xml:lang="en"> 95 Calder, “Syrian Identity in
							Bethlehem,” p.309. </p></note> Heleen Murre-van den Berg, however,
					has shown that this attachment is more "symbolic and ideological" because few lay
					people are actually fluent in the language. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97"
						n="97"><p xml:lang="en"> 97 Murre-Van den Berg, “A Center of Transnational
							Syriac Orthodoxy,” 68. </p></note> The idea that the liturgy is
					inherently connected to the Syriac language was evident when Bishop Clemis’
					secretary taught the seminarians of the Archdiocese the Lord’s Prayer and the
						<hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> in Syriac. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p xml:lang="en"> 98 Icergua, “01: Llegada del
							coespiscopo Abdulahad Shara como envidao de su Santidad el patriarca,” 1
							September 2014. </p></note> In 2017 Patriarch Ephrem II Karim expressed
					his wish for Syriac content to be increased. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99"
						n="99"><p xml:lang="en"> 99 Icergua, “22: Su Santidad Ignacio Efrén II,
							recide a Mor Santiago Eduardo en el patriarcado de Damasco,” 22 January
							2017. </p></note> As of 2018-2019 this has been done for the <hi
						rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> and the Lord’s Prayer in the liturgy handbooks,
					which are in both Spanish and Syriac (Spanish transcription). As of November
					2018, the <hi rend="italic">Libro de Oración común</hi> had not yet been
					approved by the Patriarch though containing more Syriac content, such as the
					introduction and conclusion of daily prayers (including “<hi rend="italic">haḍ
						aloho sharīro</hi>” “one true God”) and the Ave Maria. Moreover, <pb n="237"
					/> during church services, sermons, and the training of clergy and active laity,
					Bishop Eduardo, though not fluent in Syriac, sometimes uses Syriac words (for
					instance <hi rend="italic">ruḥo</hi> for “spirit” when discussing the Holy
					Spirit). In Comalapa, where the changes have been implemented since the
					mid-2000s, he recites the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> in Syriac, whereas in
					the municipality of San Juan Sacatepéquez, where communities have joined more
					recently (just 1 to 7 years ago), he uses some Syriac during the liturgy (for
					instance <hi rend="italic">brikho</hi> instead of “blessed”) and, as has been
					related, he once interrupted his service at the moment of the Lord’s Prayer to
					ask the congregation, “Do you know what was Jesus’ language? Aramaic. Therefore
					for those who have the handbook, go to page 15.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p xml:lang="en"> 100 Also, the author witnessed
							seminarians saying the daily prayers in Syriac. </p></note> The Lord’s
					Prayer was then recited in Syriac. The introduction of Syriac is justified as
					“the Aramaic language, which is not only one of the treasures of our Church, but
					because it was the language of Jesus, the Virgin Mary, and the twelve Apostles.”
					<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p xml:lang="en"> 101 Icergua, "18: 
						Encuentro de Mor Santiago Eduardo con su Santidad el patriarca en Lancaster, Pensilvania, 
						USA," 18 July 2015. </p></note> However, the Bishop resists
					a too far-reaching use of Syriac, arguing that Syriac Orthodox who were born
					into the Church naturally insist on “work[ing] and worship[ing] as much as
					possible in Syriac. That is not possible here.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p xml:lang="en"> 102 Aguirre Oestmann, personal
							interview. When the Patriarch visited Guatemala in November 2019, he
							performed the “Western” Syriac liturgy, thus speaking most of the
							prayers, including the <hi rend="italic">epiclesis</hi>, in Spanish and
							facing the community. However the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> was
							delivered in Syriac. </p></note> An important aspect of this issue is
					that since the Second Vatican Council, Roman Catholic liturgy has been performed
					in the vernacular and while facing the community. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p xml:lang="en"> 103 See E. Hoenes del Pinal, “A
							Ritual Interrupted: A Case of Contested Ritual Practices in a
							Q’eqchi’-Maya Catholic Parish” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of
								Contemporary Religion</hi> 31:3 [2016]): 365-378; Hager, “The
							Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 380.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Another element of the liturgy is of course communion. In the
					Syriac tradition this is preceded by fasting and usually <pb n="238"/> not
					performed frequently. In 1988 Claude Sélis noted that communion could be
					received at most every forty days and only after confession and fasting. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p xml:lang="en"> 104 C. Sélis, <hi
								rend="italic">Les Syriens orthodoxes et catholiques</hi> (Turnhout:
							Brepols, 1988), 196. </p></note> In 1997, however, the Syriac Orthodox
					Church exhorted its clergy to “diligently urge the faithful to partake of the
					Holy Eucharist on Sundays and on the festivals of our Lord. Above all, they […]
					must confess their sins to the priests that, with purity of soul, they may be
					worthy to partake of the Holy Eucharist. […] observe a complete fast three hours
					prior.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p xml:lang="en"> 105 Syrian
							Orthodox Dioceses of North America and Canada, “The Sacrament of the
							Holy Eucharist,” 1998. </p></note> Although Bishop Clemis instructed
					Bishop Eduardo on fasting (an entry on the <hi rend="italic">noticias</hi> dated
					February 13<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 2014 explained the feast of Niniveh
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p xml:lang="en"> 106 Icergua,
							“13: Divina liturgia por el ayuno de Nínive y la solemnidad de San
							Ignacio Elías III.,” 13 February 2014. Heidemarie Armbruster noted that
							fasting was eased for the Syriac Orthodox community in Vienna originally
							from Tur Abdin (Armbruster, <hi rend="italic">"Wir sprechen die Sprache,
								die Jesus gesprochen hat"</hi>, 150). </p></note> ), fasting is
					hardly ever observed prior to communion. For one thing, according to the Bishop
					it is difficult to enforce the regulation. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107"
						n="107"><p xml:lang="en"> 107 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview.
						</p></note> Furthermore, communion is performed much more frequently in the
					absence of the Bishop (who often forbids communion to those whose marriage is
					not sacramental). Another element of “Syriacization” the Bishop and seminarians
					have been trying to implement, especially among children, is the crossing of the
					arms over the chest before receiving communion. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The theological and sacramental process of Syriacization is
					connected to a whole set of modifications relating to icons, imagery, incense,
					and other sensory aspects of worship. </p>
			</div>
			<pb n="239"/>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.4">
				<head>PART FOUR: THE CURRENT FACE OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF CENTRAL AMERICA</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> As Edward Shils noted, tradition includes “material objects,
					beliefs […], images of persons and events, practices and institutions.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p xml:lang="en"> 108 Shils, <hi
								rend="italic">Tradition</hi>, 12. </p></note> The Syriac Orthodox
					tradition as defined by the Church hierarchy also includes aural (the Syriac
					language) and olfactory (incense) features, many of which have become adopted in
					communities alongside already-existing traditions. First are the Syriac Orthodox
					imagery and icons. A priest of the Malankara Church in the US helped establish
					contacts with the Church in India for producing priestly vestments. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p xml:lang="en"> 109 Icergua, “21:
							Divina liturgia de bienvenida a los corepíscopos Mathews y Sabu Thomas
							en el seminario,” 21 April 2015. However, the vestments are now produced
							in Guatemala (Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview). </p></note> The
					priest visited Guatemala and celebrated a liturgy at the seminary. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p xml:lang="en"> 110 Icergua, “24:
							Divina liturgia en el seminario presidida por los corepíscopos Mathews y
							Sabu,” 24 April 2015. </p></note> A Comalapan priest recalled that
					vestments were among the first things they changed. A Syriac Orthodox “sister”
					who runs an NGO in Germany not only helped fund the construction of several
					churches in Guatemala but also presented various church communities with
					pictures of the Archangel Michael in the Syriac style. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p xml:lang="en"> 111 Icergua, “02: Visita a las
							obras de construcción del templo de Santa María, Cunén, el Quiché,” 2
							November 2016. Icergua, “15: Divina liturgia en San Miguel Chanquejelbé,
							Nentón, Huehuetenango,” 15 March 2017). </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Lay people play a major role in shaping “Syriac Mayan”
					Christianity and have a deep attachment to their local churches. They assert
					their communities in an environment that is also Roman Catholic and Evangelical,
					with music bands and church building programs (often beyond their financial
					means). <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p xml:lang="en"> 112 Such
							churches are often built by the members themselves with their own
							funding or with money provided from outside, such as from the previously
							mentioned Syriac Orthodox “sister” in Germany. </p></note> Thus, in the
					churches and temples there is <pb n="240"/> frequently a coexistence of local
					elements–such as doves representing the Holy Spirit, flowers, a visible altar
					(or table), the veneration of the images of saints and of the Virgin Mary, the
					blessing of seeds–alongside Syriac Orthodox features like calendars of the
					Archdiocese, handbooks (in particular the handbook for liturgy), pictures of the
					Bishop and sometimes of the Patriarch. In one community in Guatemala the Syriac
					liturgical tools were donated by a member. Bishop Eduardo, despite his personal
					disapproval, has taken a pragmatic attitude toward this synthesis, in particular
					to the veneration of the images in Comalapa. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113"
						n="113"><p xml:lang="en"> 113 Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview.
						</p></note> As was mentioned above, the confirmation of two hundred young
					people in Comalapa was an important local event during which the <hi
						rend="italic">cofradías</hi> played a conspicuous role. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The issue of incense illustrates that abstract theology can be
					easier to introduce than physical ritual. In some communities in Huehuetenango
					the (re)introduction of candles and incense constituted a challenge as a result
					of apparently Pentecostal influence. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"
							><p xml:lang="en"> 114 See Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox
							Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 382. </p></note> In Comalapa, on the other
					hand, incense is part of the syncretic Catholic-Mayan tradition and widely used
					by the Charismatics in the remote rural communities of San Juan Sacatepéquez.
					Thus one wonders whose tradition incense was in the first place. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The physical features of the union highlight the important but
					often ambivalent role the laity plays in the process by adopting or resisting
					change. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.5">
				<head>PART FIVE: WHAT CHURCH?</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The inexact translation from English into Spanish by Bishop
					Eduardo of one of Patriarch Ephrem II Karim’s sermons during his recent visit to
					Guatemala reveal the contrasting visions which the Syriac Orthodox hierarchy and
					the Guatemalan actors have concerning the roles of the clergy <pb n="241"/> and
					laity, including women, in the Church: the Patriarch asked the congregation to
					“pray for everyone of our clergy” as well as “for the seminarists and everyone
					of you”; but Bishop Eduardo amended this in his Spanish translation to “the
					deacons, the seminarists, the ministries, the catechists, the different
					ministries and every one of you.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 115 Icasoac Siro-Ortodoxo, Facebook entry 7 November
							2019, Alta Verapaz, Chisec. </p></note> For, unlike traditional Syriac
					Orthodox laity, the laity in Latin America plays an important religious role and
					has far-reaching prerogatives. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Although the Patriarch ordained eleven seminiarians during his
					recent visit, the Archdiocese is still understaffed. In 2018 the two priests in
					Huehuetenango served 70 different communities totaling 50,000 persons. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p xml:lang="en"> 116 Aguirre Oestmann,
							personal interview. </p></note> The clergy have been mainly trained at
					the seminary near Guatemala City founded by Bishop Eduardo, and are often of
					local Mayan origin or from other Central American countries. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p xml:lang="en"> 117 Ibid. </p></note> There is a
					need to distinguish between the younger generation of priests, which has been
					trained in an increasingly Syriac manner at the seminary (performing the Syriac
					Saint James liturgy on Thursdays, as was mentioned above) and an older, often
					former Roman Catholic, generation. The current Patriarch has attempted to
					facilitate the integration of this clergy into the main body of the Church. In
					2015 three seminarists were sent from Guatemala to Syria to learn Syriac “so
					that points of communications exist between the [Guatemalan] Church and the
					Patriarchate [and] those who are being trained for sacred orders can also know
					the Aramaic language.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 118 Icergua, “18: Encuentro de Mor Santiago Eduardo con
							su Santidad el patriarca en Lancaster, Pensilvania, USA,” 18 July 2015.
							Only one of the three seminarians sent to Syria subsequently remained
							active (Aguirre Oestmann, personal interview). </p></note> In March
					2014, the Patriarch asked to receive a short biography <pb n="242"/> on every
					candidate for ordination. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 119 Icergua, “01: Encuentro de nuestro Arzobispo Mor
							Santiago Eduardo con su Santidad Ignacio Efrén II.,” 1 March 2014.
						</p></note> The issue of the clergy is important because, due to their local
					origin and (in some cases) command of a Mayan language, they are powerful
					carriers of a “Syriacized” Christianity. At one of the liturgies attended by the
					author in the absence of the bishop, the priest delivered his sermon in both
					Spanish and K’aqchiqel-Maya. This is frequent practice throughout the
					Archdiocese, including trainings; and in 2009 the texts for the rituals were
					translated into Q’eqchi’-Maya, spoken in parts of Guatemala. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p xml:lang="en"> 120 Icergua, “1: Decanato de las
							Verapaces y Petén,” 1 May 2009. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In 1986 Patriarch Ignatius Zakka I Iwas wrote, “It is worth noting
					that what distinguishes our Holy Church from other Churches is the spiritual
					role to be played by the priest in the congregation. He is the spiritual father
					of every member of the family that belongs to this congregation. His
					relationship with each person must be deep and strong.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p xml:lang="en"> 121 Mor Ignatius Zakka I Iwas,
							“Identity of the Syrian Orthodox Church,” 1986. </p></note> This view,
					however, may not match the expectations people in Guatemala have towards their
					priests and their own role. One priest in Comalapa told the author that lay
					leaders had complained to Bishop Eduardo that they did not want a priest who
					only properly performs the liturgy, but one who takes care of his parish. In the
					Guatemalan context of profound religious shifts, the clergy of the Archdiocese
					acts more as an outside figure endorsing existing practices of the community,
					including the sacraments, processions (those of the <hi rend="italic"
						>cofradías</hi> in Comalapa), and Charismatic prayer groups. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p xml:lang="en"> 122 See Hager, “The
							Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 381.
						</p></note> This severely limits the means of coercion available to the
					clergy which, at its extreme within the Syriac Orthodox Church, resulted in the
					excommunication of supporters of <pb n="243"/> the Assyrian discourse in Sweden.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p xml:lang="en"> 123 See Atto,
								<hi rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland</hi>, 337. </p></note>
					The Church could take such drastic measures because traditional Syriac Orthodox
					communities largely depend on the clergy, as George Kiraz demonstrated in the
					case of the Syriac Orthodox migrants to the United States in the first half of
					the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century, who took great pains to establish
					ecclesiastic structures, requesting priests and a bishop from the Patriarchate.
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p xml:lang="en"> 124 See Kiraz,
								<hi rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>.
						</p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> In the Archdiocese of Central America, however, the heart of the
					Church is not the parish but the local lay community, as a result of tremendous
					religious shifts and Bishop Eduardo’s vision. Ever since he established his
					movement in 2003, he has strongly encouraged lay leaders to form regional <hi
						rend="italic">decanatos</hi> (deaconates, lay councils below the diocese and
					above the parishes) and to establish pastoral and financial councils at the
					community level. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p xml:lang="en">
							125 Icergua, “10: Reunión con los servidores de la parroquia de San
							Miguel, Los Ángeles, Calfornia,” 10 August 2014. </p></note> The
					authority of the clergy is further limited by the laity’s ritual and liturgical
					leverage–as illustrated by the greater frequency of communion in the absence of
					the bishop: <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p xml:lang="en"> 126 A
							Syriac Orthodox priest in Guatemala told the author he would give
							communion to Roman Catholics too (see Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac
							Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 385). </p></note> in the absence of
					a priest lay leaders can celebrate a form of liturgy that includes communion
					because they have retained the Roman Catholic practice of keeping hosties. This
					situation is the result of a historical expansion of the role played by the
					laity in Guatemala in the second half of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
					century. In the 1950s and 1960s, prior to the emergence of the CRR, Catholic
					Action had already promoted the role of lay persons as catechists, thus ensuring
					a structured religious framework below the parish on the local community level,
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127"><p xml:lang="en"> 127 E. Hoenes
							del Pinal, “From Vatican II to Speaking in Tongues: Theology and
							Language Policy in a Q’eqchi’-Maya Catholic Parish” (<hi rend="italic"
								>Language Policy</hi> 15:2 [2016]), 179-197, 186. </p></note>
					something Bishop Eduardo alluded to in his intentional mistranslation of <pb
						n="244"/> the Patriarch’s sermon. In both the Pentecostal and Catholic
					Charismatic movements, the performance of religious services like <hi
						rend="italic">oraciones</hi> (prayer groups) does not require ordination or
					theological training. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 128 See A. Althoff, “Divided by faith and ethnicity:
							religious pluralism and the problem of race in Guatemala” (<hi
								rend="italic">International Journal of Latin American Religions</hi>
							1 [2017]) 331–352, 340. </p></note> In the framework of official CCR,
					lay people are actively involved as “catechists” celebrating the liturgy <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129"><p xml:lang="en"> 129 E. Hoenes del
							Pinal, “A Ritual Interrupted,” 368. </p></note> and in leading <hi
						rend="italic">oraciones</hi>. Their role was even more important in areas
					where the CCR developed in the underground. Thus, although Patriarch Ephrem II
					Karim expanded the role of the laity during his tenure as Bishop of Eastern
					America, involving them in the singing of the liturgy, <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p xml:lang="en"> 130 Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The
								Syriac Orthodox in North America</hi>, 258-259. </p></note> the
					laity in Guatemala had already achieved even greater roles. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The role played specifically by women in the Guatemalan
					Archdiocese differs from that in the Syriac Orthodox Church even though their
					role had indeed expanded in the latter over recent decades through the
					rediscovery of ancient practices like Saint Ephrem’s instructions to women from
					the Bible <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p xml:lang="en"> 131
							Ignatius Zakka I Iwas, “The Role of Women in the Syrian Orthodox Church
							of Antioch,” 1996. </p></note> and the increasing use of women’s choirs
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132"><p xml:lang="en"> 132 See S.
							Ashbrook Harvey, “Women and Children in Syriac Christianity. Sounding
							Voices,” in T. King (ed.) <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World</hi>
							(London: Routledge, 2018), 554-566 </p></note> after the Grand Synod of
					1930 encouraged the admission of girls into choirs. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn133" n="133"><p xml:lang="en"> 133 Majallat al-Hikma, “[Summary
							of the Decisions],” 1930, 517. </p></note> Bishop Eduardo has integrated
					the role women play locally into the practices of the Archdiocese: “Incomplete
					approaches: thinking that the woman’s role in the community is merely limited to
					secondary activities such as cleaning, cooking and domestic services.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p xml:lang="en"> 134 Quoted in Hager,
							“The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 380.
						</p></note> Women are part of the <hi rend="italic">decanatos</hi>, where
					they receive theological training and serve on <pb n="245"/> various pastoral
					councils with men (the author, for example, talked to one Syriac Orthodox woman
					in Comalapa who had been a member of a liturgical council). They are also very
					visible during religious services, doing Bible readings (as was the case in all
					services attended by the author in Comalapa, San Juan Sacatepéquez, and Los
					Angeles) or as part of the <hi rend="italic">hermandades</hi> (the women’s
					adjunct to the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi>) in Comalapa. This is quite
					significant, suggesting that even in remote rural areas women are now
					sufficiently literate to do the readings. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135"
						n="135"><p xml:lang="en"> 135 In 1999, 29.7% of the population in Guatemala
							was still illiterate, 61% of them were indigenous (Davis, “Mouvement
							maya et culture nationale au Guatemala”). </p></note> They also
					participate in the preparation of the Eucharist, entering the sacred space of
					the altar (which is forbidden to women in traditional Syriac Orthodox churches).
					In some Charismatic communities (including Huehuetenango and one community in
					San Juan Sacatepéquez) some young women have started to wear white veils, as in
					Pentecostal and many traditional Syriac Orthodox churches. According to Bishop
					Eduardo, the frequency of this practice depends on the seminarian attending the
					community. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136"><p xml:lang="en"> 136 On
							the Facebook page of the Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate such women
							featured prominently. </p></note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.6">
				<head>PART SIX: RECOVERING THE CHURCH OF ANTIOCH</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The preceding descriptions of the adapted sacramental life, local
					cultural milieu, and particular ecclesiological reality defines the theological
					and doctrinal identity of the Archdiocese. The Syriacized rituals and liturgy
						<hi rend="italic">enhance</hi> an already existing narrative centered around
					the idea of reliving the early Church. In this part I will argue that one of the
					main reasons why so many communities in Guatemala have adopted Syriac Orthodoxy
					stems from its supposed embodiment of a much older tradition than that of the
					Syriac Orthodox Church Fathers, much older even than the Syriac <pb n="246"/>
					liturgy and language: it is a tradition believed to be from the primitive Church
					of Antioch itself. In the narrative Bishop Eduardo has been conveying, the
					Syriac Orthodox Church stands for the event in Antioch where a universal,
					catholic church was established and from which the Apostles were sent into the
					world to convert all people, including the then-unknown Mayans. Edward Shils
					noted, “The sought-for tradition is sometimes said to be the ʻreal’ tradition or
					the genuine source of temporary ʻdilapidated’ traditions, which have broken the
					lines of effective traditional transmission with the point of origin.” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137"><p xml:lang="en"> 137 E. Shils,
							“Tradition,” 133. </p></note> Antioch therefore becomes the archetype
					for the life of mission which local Guatemalans should reproduce every day. As a
					result, through Antioch, these communities do not consider themselves <hi
						rend="italic">excommunicated</hi> Catholics, but the <hi rend="italic"
						>true</hi> Catholics. Although, as we will see, terms like “catholic,”
					“apostolic,” “orthodox” may cover different nuances for Church leaders and
					Bishop Eduardo (and even more so for the laity), this union signals a new
					dynamic within the Church which claims a universal scope. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> One of the first topics discussed by Bishop Clemis and Bishop
					Eduardo were theological differences, especially miaphysitism. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p xml:lang="en"> 138 Icergua, “05:
							Diálogos con el patriarcado ortodoxo siriano de Antioquía,” 5 November
							2011. </p></note> This doctrine was adopted into the statutes of the
					Church in 2015 and featured on the Archdiocese’ website with the doctrine of <hi
						rend="italic">Theotokos</hi>, the sacraments, and the daily prayers. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p xml:lang="en"> 139 Icergua, “06:
							Publicación del estatuto oficial de la arquidiócesis de Centro América,”
							6 June 2015. </p></note>
					<hi rend="italic">Theotokos</hi> and miaphysitism do not represent a radical
					break with Roman Catholicism because the Roman Catholic Church also recognizes
					Mary as God-bearer; and in one of his sermons in Guatemala Patriarch Ephrem II
					Karim alluded to the agreement reached between Patriarch Zakka and Pope John
					Paul II in 1984, acknowledging that the Christological disagreements of the <pb
						n="247"/> early centuries did not affect faith. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p xml:lang="en"> 140 Atto, <hi rend="italic"
								>Hostages in the Homeland</hi>, 535. </p></note> Bishop Eduardo
					mentions such theological beliefs in his sermons and in the theological training
					of the laity. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141"><p xml:lang="en"> 141
							One feature which the author did not witness in her 2018 fieldwork in
							such a consistent way, was the insistence by Bishop Eduardo during the
							Patriarch’s visit of the sign of the cross, including “<hi rend="italic"
								>un solo Dios verdadero</hi> (one true God, “<hi rend="italic">haḍ
								aloho sharīro</hi>”), something peculiar to the Syriac Orthodox
							tradition. </p></note> Another doctrine which has been adopted is the
					rejection of <hi rend="italic">filioque</hi> (the Holy Spirit proceeding from
					both the Father <hi rend="italic">and Son</hi>) mentioned earlier in the context
					of liturgy. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Beyond the theological adaptations, however, there are subtle
					differences concerning the purpose of rituals, in particular the liturgy, which
					in the traditional Syriac Orthodox view is not merely an outward display by the
					congregation: the theologian Baby Varghese writes that “doctrine is inextricably
					bound with a liturgical action.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 142 In B. Varghese, <hi rend="italic">West Syrian
								Liturgical Theology</hi> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 2004), 47. </p></note>
					According to him, the Syriac <hi rend="italic">anaphora</hi> embodies the
					economy of salvation, the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi> especially forming an
					“integral part of the narration of God’s loving-kindness towards humanity.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143"><p xml:lang="en"> 143 Ibid, 66.
						</p></note> However, in Bishop Eduardo’s approach to the liturgy the role of
					Christ becomes secondary, even more so if the <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi>
					is pronounced in Syriac–something people don’t understand if they do not follow
					the liturgy book. By contrast, the <hi rend="italic">epiclesis</hi>, which
					remains in Spanish, is centered around the vitalizing of the bread and wine by
					the Holy Spirit, in compliance with Syriac Orthodox liturgy. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn144" n="144"><p xml:lang="en"> 144 Ibid, 85. </p></note> The
					central role of the Holy Spirit is also emphasized in other sacraments in the
					Archdiocese. Although the theology and practice of baptism has been Syriacized,
					in oral sources the idea of it as conversion prevails: “Baptism [means]
					incorporating as members of the new alliance and receiving the Holy Spirit in
						<pb n="248"/> order to live as authentic children of God and give witness to
					the Gospel.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145"><p xml:lang="en"> 145
							Icergua, “01: Divina liturgia en la parroquia de Guaxacaná, Nentón,
							Huehuetenango,” 1 January 2018. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Such subtle differences occur on many other levels and illustrate
					the desire to return, through Syriac Orthodoxy, to a much older, supposedly
					genuine, past which legitimizes the existing narrative. This is evident in the
					Archdiocese’s treatment of the figure of Mary: in addition to naming her <hi
						rend="italic">theotokos</hi> or <hi rend="italic">yoldath aloho</hi>, Bishop
					Eduardo opposes both the Roman Catholic doctrine of Immaculate Conception and
					the Protestant positions demystifying her; <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146"
						n="146"><p xml:lang="en"> 146 Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox
							Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 383. </p></note> yet, unlike Syriac Orthodox
					understanding, he turns Mary into a <hi rend="italic">model of action</hi>. By
					contrast, Patriarch Zakka I Iwas described her as a <hi rend="italic">model of
						virtue</hi>, “Our Lord Jesus Christ […] chose her to be His Mother because
					of her chastity and godliness so that she deserved that the Holy Spirit descend
					on her, purify her, absolve her from sin and sanctify her.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p xml:lang="en"> 147 Iwas, “The Role of Women in
							the Syrian Orthodox Church of Antioch,” 1996. </p></note> During
					confirmation in Comalapa though, Bishop Eduardo exhorted the young candidates to
					follow the action of the Virgin: “Convert yourself like the Virgin Mary did to
					become persons who carry this Gospel so that all can believe, change their
					lives, and become children of God.” </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> While there is nevertheless some common ground concerning Mary,
					the almost total absence in the Guatemalan Archdiocese of a narrative on
					martyrdom is striking, especially given that many areas of the Archdiocese were
					severely affected by the civil war and the ethnic cleansing. Yet this
					constitutes a prime element in both the Syriac Orthodox Church and the
					communities born into her, as well as in scholarly works. In a speech in
					Colombia in 2018 at the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Global Christian Forum,
					Patriarch Ephrem II Karim stated, “Because of our history of persecution and
					martyrdom, <pb n="249"/> whenever I think of the marks of the church being One,
					Holy, Catholic and Apostolic, I immediately add to it ‘Persecuted’. The true
					church that is faithful to her Lord and Savior has to be a persecuted one.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148"><p xml:lang="en"> 148 Mor
							Ignatius Aphrem II Karim, “Following Christ together in discrimination,
							persecution, martyrdom: What does this mean for the global church
							today?” 25 April 2018. </p></note> He emphasized this theme in his
					sermons during his visit to Guatemala, especially at Chajul, El Quiché, where 70 to
					80 people had been killed by the army in 1983. This community petitioned Bishop
					Eduardo to have the victims recognized as martyrs, which he granted in 2007 and
					every year on April 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> these “blessed” are
					remembered. The picture of the martyrs also appears in the confirmation
					handbook. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149"><p xml:lang="en"> 149 See
							Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,”
							382. </p></note> Yet the importance of this event remains limited to
					Chajul and the emphasis on martyrdom in the Guatemalan Archdiocese thus stays
					local. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Since 2003 Bishop Aguirre has been urging in his handbooks,
					sermons, trainings, <hi rend="italic">noticias</hi>, etc., and, in connection
					with Mary, the liturgy, and the sacraments, a call to emulate the Apostles—and,
					to a certain extent, the Virgin Mary and Jesus Christ—as models of the ethical
					and moral attitudes proper to a Christian in Guatemala in the 21<hi
						rend="italic">st</hi> century, drawing on the themes of repentance and
					conversion not clearly identifiable with any specific Christian tradition,
					whether Roman Catholic, Charismatic, Pentecostal, Syriac, or Eastern Orthodox
					and his call has gained more legitimacy as a result of the union in 2013. It is
					a Christian ethic which includes both <hi rend="italic">epistrophe
					</hi>(“turning back to the origin or to oneself or to the perfect ideal”) and
						<hi rend="italic">metanoïa</hi> (“to repent,” “to be born again”). <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150"><p xml:lang="en"> 150 Distinction made
							by William Barylo, quoted in Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox
							Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 378. </p></note> In his sermon during
					confirmation in Comalapa, Bishop Eduardo called on the candidates: </p>
				<cit><quote><p xml:lang="en"> ‘Authentic Christian’ means authentically
					anointed by the Spirit of God. And what is the consequence of one having been
					anointed, precisely by the Spirit of God? [It means] that every one of us turns
					[converts] into a living Gospel in his life. Every one of you is called to make
					this Word alive, this presence, this Good News of God […] Convert yourself like
					the Virgin Mary did to become persons who carry this Gospel so that all can
					believe, change their lives, and become children of God. </p></quote></cit>
				<p xml:lang="en"> This conforms more with Syriac Orthodox ideas of collective
					salvation rather than with the Roman Catholic and Protestant emphasis upon
					individual salvation: “We are saved not as individuals but as members of the
					Body of Christ.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151"><p xml:lang="en">
							151 Quoted in Calder Calder, “Syrian Identity in Bethlehem,” 316.
						</p></note> Yet it focuses on this life rather than on the after-life, and
					on action in the world towards others rather than on inner attitude. By
					insisting on the work of the Holy Spirit, Bishop Eduardo posits an intimate,
					growing relationship between God and the individual; 
					“Implying promoting a life of personal veneration in the Holy Spirit [<hi rend="italic"
						>oración personal en el Espíritu Santo</hi>], nourished by a sacramental
					life, as occurred in the first Christian community.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn152" n="152"><p xml:lang="en"> 152 Icergua, “03: Exhortación
							pastoral ʻEl Evangelio de la Renovación,’” 3 April 2014. </p></note> This resonates among the clergy and lay
					people and was the main theme of the sermon in Spanish and K’aqchiqel-Maya
					attended by the author. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The official name of the Archdiocese is “Catholic Apostolic Syriac
					Orthodox Church of Antioch/Archdiocese of Central America (<hi rend="italic"
						>Iglesia católica apóstolica siro-ortodoxa de Antioquía/Arquidiócesis de
						Centro América</hi>, ICASOAC).” This appears on the churches and in the
					communities in Guatemala, though the name “Iglesia Católica ecuménica
					renovada–ICERGUA” continues to be used in the <pb n="251"/> handbooks with the
					official name. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153"><p xml:lang="en"> 153
							Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,”
							377. </p></note> Bishop Eduardo himself hardly ever uses the term
					“Syriac Orthodox:” “I always insist very much that they have [to] give everybody
					[the] experience of [the] Early Apostolic church: [it is a] term they understand
					but we do not use <hi rend="italic">siro-orthodoxo</hi>. I have always
					understood orthodox in [its] etymological meaning.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn154" n="154"><p xml:lang="en"> 154 Aguirre Oestmann, personal
							interview. </p></note> He thus breaks with the ethnic and linguistic
					link between Syriac Orthodoxy and the Church of Antioch, though this constituted
					one condition for union with the Church: in his letter to the Holy Synod, Bishop
					Clemis insisted upon submission to “its teachings: Semitism and the apostolic
					faith,” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155"><p xml:lang="en"> 155 Kaplan,
							“Historical Moment.” </p></note> implying that the Syriac Orthodox
					Church considers herself heir to a “pure” Semitic form of Christianity. <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156"><p xml:lang="en"> 156 See Atto, <hi
								rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland</hi>, 531; Dinno, <hi
								rend="italic">The Syrian Orthodox Christians</hi>, 260. </p></note>
					In 1981 Patriarch Zakka affirmed this link more clearly: “Our Church is known as
					the Syrian Orthodox Church of Antioch […], and its language is known as the
					Syriac language […], and its people by the Syrian people […].” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157"><p xml:lang="en"> 157 Quoted in Atto,
								<hi rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland</hi>, 555. </p></note>
					The “apostolic” part of the Archdiocese’s name is justified by Bishop Clemis’
					demand that the Archdiocese adhere to the teachings of “the apostolic faith.”
						<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158"><p xml:lang="en"> 158 Kaplan,
							“Historical Moment.” </p></note> In a short document given to the author
					and addressed to Syriac Orthodox priests in the US outlining the differences
					between the SOC and the Roman Catholic and Protestant Churches, Bishop Clemis
					wrote: “Our Church prides herself as being <hi rend="underline">one of the
						earliest Apostolic Churches</hi> […] In Antioch, the followers of Jesus were
					called Christians for the first time [underlining by the author].” <note
						place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159"><p xml:lang="en"> 159 M.C.E. Kaplan,
							“Comparison between the Syriac Orthodox Church and the Roman Catholic
							and Protestant Churches in Brief,” sent to the author in August 2018.
						</p></note> This seems to echo Bishop Eduardo, who calls on his followers to
					turn <pb n="252"/> into Apostles: “the holy Syriac Orthodox See of Antioch, the
					very Church to which the twelve Apostles belonged.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn160" n="160"><p xml:lang="en"> 160 Icergua, “11: Renovación de
							los compromisos presbiterales, vicaría de Huehuetenango, San Rafael de
							la Independencia,” 11 April 2017. </p></note> However “apostolic” means
					different things in the Syriac Orthodox tradition and to Bishop Eduardo: for the
					latter it is a call for action, whereas for the Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate it
					is the source of legitimacy–“Tradition is, basically, the spiritual teaching we
					have inherited from the Holy Apostles and Church Fathers,” wrote Patriarch
					Zakka. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161"><p xml:lang="en"> 161 Iwas,
							“Tradition.” </p></note> The Church considers herself heir and
					representative of an unbroken chain of transmission from the <hi rend="italic"
						>primus inter pares</hi> of the Apostles, Peter, first bishop of Antioch. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> By joining a tradition directly linked to Peter, members of the
					Archdiocese are able to reassert their catholicity. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn162" n="162"><p xml:lang="en"> 162 In informal conversations with
							members in Guatemala and Los Angeles, most identified as “catholics”
							(See Hager, “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in
							Guatemala,” 377). </p></note> Bishop Eduardo justifies his consistent
					use of the term “catholic” as “universal” by reference to Patriarch Ignatius:
					“Starting in 69 C.E., the Church of Antioch was called ‘Catholic’ (with Saint
					Ignace, the third successor of Peter).” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163"
						n="163"><p xml:lang="en"> 163 Icasoac Siro-Ortodoxo, Facebook entry 10
							November 2019, “Santa Eucaristía precidida por Su Santidad Ignacio Efrén
							II, Estadio Los Cuchumatanes Huehuetenango Guatemala.” </p></note> This
					claim was evident in one of the sermons by Patriarch Ephrem II Karim in
					Guatemala: “You, the people of Guatemala and members of the archdiocese of
					Central America are very dear to our hearts [because you] represent the
					universality, the catholicity of our Church, the Church of Antioch which was
					founded as a catholic church.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 164 Icasoac Siro-Ortodoxo, Facebook entry 10 November
							2019, “Santa Eucaristía precidida por Su Santidad Ignacio Efrén II,
							Estadio Los Cuchumatanes Huehuetenango Guatemala.” </p></note> This idea
					of regaining the universal and catholic scope of a missionary Church seems to be
					gaining ground within the Syriac Orthodox hierarchy. <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn165" n="165"><p xml:lang="en"> 165 In an unpublished paper given
							at the Institute for Eastern Christian Studies, Nijmegen, Netherlands,
							Naures Atto discussed the <pb n="253"/> trend within the Syriac Orthodox
							Church advocating a stronger emphasis on Syriac language and culture.
							But during the Q&amp;A session, the bishop of the Netherlands, Mor
							Polycarpus Augin Aydin, underlined the importance of a more spiritual
							emphasis by the Church as a global catholic body transcending boundaries
							(Naures Atto, “Challenges for the Syriac Orthodox Church: Encounters
							with Secularism,” January 31<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>-February 1<hi
								rend="superscript">st</hi>, 2019, Workshop “Redefining Syriac
							Christianity in a Globalized 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> Century:”
							workshop organized by Anna Hager and Heleen Murre-van den Berg).
						</p></note> Another hint <pb n="253"/> of this is the name Bishop Eduardo
					was given when he was tonsured a monk in 2013: Jacob (Spanish Santiago), in
					memory of Jacob Baradeus (6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century) who
					reorganized the Church. <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166"><p
							xml:lang="en"> 166 Icergua, “05: Tonsura de nuestro obispo como monje,
							por su Santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I Iwas,” 5 March 2013. </p></note>
				</p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> Therefore within the Archdiocese the idea prevails that they have
					joined <hi rend="italic">the</hi> Mother Church: A priest in Comalapa indeed did
					identify himself as “orthodox” because of belonging to “[the] Mother Church
					which maintained the correct doctrine, the true doctrine.” <note place="foot"
						xml:id="ftn167" n="167"><p xml:lang="en"> 167 Hager, “The Emergence of a
							Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala,” 377. </p></note> Thus the
					Syriac Orthodox Church of Antioch legitimizes the movement of <hi rend="italic"
						>renovación</hi> initiated by Bishop Eduardo in 2003 and which attracted so
					many communities. </p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.conclusion">
				<head>CONCLUSION</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> With the establishment of a new Archdiocese of over half a million
					people, the Syriac Orthodox Church has grown tremendously. But the Guatemalan
					Archdiocese has challenged key assumptions about Syriac Orthodox traditions, the
					Church supposedly embodying foremost a tradition, in the sense of <hi
						rend="italic">preserving</hi> something. It has also raised questions about
					the content of these traditions, their mode of transmission, and who has the
					authority to define, transmit, and adapt them. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The Syriac Orthodox Church (including the late Patriarch Ignatius
					Zakka I Iwas, Patriarch Ephrem II Karim, Bishop <pb n="254"/> Clemis, etc.) have
					considered the union with the Guatemalan church as an “embracing” or “fusion
					with” the body of the Church, tacitly implying the new Archdiocese’s submission
					to the authority of the Patriarch, acceptance of the Church’s doctrinal beliefs
					as well as the Syriac <hi rend="italic">anamnesis</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
						>epiclesis</hi>, and (with reservations) the Syriac language, and a
					negotiated adoption of sacraments. This means that the Syriac Orthodox Church
					considers the Syriac language an important aspect of her identity, even for
					formerly alien communities. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The tradition defined by Syriac Orthodoxy is subject to its tools
					of transmission, which in Guatemala include Bishop Eduardo as the only point of
					contact and the languages through which it is transmitted (and understood).
					Although Edward Shils has underlined “faulty transmissions” as the main
					motivation for modifying a tradition, in the case of the Archdiocese the
					modifications are the result of the specific interests of Bishop Eduardo and his
					followers, as the result of which some aspects of Syriac Orthodoxy are resisted
					(such as incense and fasting prior to communion), while others are more easily
					accepted (such as Syriac tools for liturgy, the picture of the Patriarch in some
					communities, “<hi rend="italic">haḍ aloho sharīro</hi>”). Consequently elements
					of Syriac Orthodoxy merge with existing traditions: communities continue to
					practice Charismatic prayers; the <hi rend="italic">cofradías</hi> remain active; and Bishop Eduardo
					continues preaching his view of Christian ethics. But the role the laity plays
					in traditional Syriac Orthodox congregations and in the Archdiocese are so
					different that this could lead to tensions. </p>
				<p xml:lang="en"> The core rational for the Archdiocese’s members in accepting
					Syriac Orthodox tradition does not rest on liturgy or the Church Fathers, but on
					a much older past: Antioch. Whether reaching this far back can meet the desire
					of the Guatemalan Church for regeneration only the future will tell. </p>
			</div>
			<pb n="255"/>
			<div xml:id="hv23n2hager.acknowledgments">
				<head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head>
				<p xml:lang="en"> This article was completed during a postdoctoral fellowship at the
					Institute of Eastern Christian Studies (IVOC), Radboud University, Netherlands.
					I would like to thank Prof. Heleen Murre-van den Berg, Dr. George Kiraz and the three anonymous
					reviewers for their valuable comments as well as Mor Eduardo and Mor Clemis for
					their help, and all those individuals I had a chance to meet in the course of
					this project who provided me with their valuable insight and support. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="bibliography">
				<head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
				<listBibl>
					<bibl> Aciprensa, “Sacerdote que fundó secta en Guatemala quedó excomulgado,” 18
						October 2006: <ref
							target="https://www.aciprensa.com/noticias/sacerdote-que-fundo-secta-en-guatemala-quedo-excomulgado"
							>https://www.aciprensa.com/noticias/sacerdote-que-fundo-secta-en-guatemala-quedo-excomulgado</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Aguirre Oestmann, Bishop Mor Eduardo. Personal interview, 23 November
						2018. San Lucas Sacatepéquez. </bibl>
					<bibl> Althoff, A. “Divided by faith and ethnicity: religious pluralism and the
						problem of race in Guatemala.” <hi rend="italic">International Journal of
							Latin American Religions</hi> 1 (2017): 331–352, 340. </bibl>
					<bibl> Armbruster, H. <hi rend="italic">“Wir sprechen die Sprache, die Jesus
							gesprochen hat” : die Vergangenheit in der Gegenwart syrisch-orthodoxer
							ChristInnen, AssyrerInnen in Wien</hi>, Vienna: University of Vienna,
						Master’s thesis, 1994. </bibl>
					<bibl> Ashbrook Harvey, S. “Women and Children in Syriac Christianity. Sounding
						Voices,” in T. King (ed.)<hi rend="italic"> The Syriac World</hi>, London:
						Routledge, 2018: 554-566. </bibl>
					<bibl> Atto, N. <hi rend="italic">Hostages in the Homeland, Orphans in the
							Diaspora: Identity Discourses among the Assyrian/Syriac Elites in the
							European Diaspora</hi>, Leiden: Leiden University Press, Doctoral
						thesis, 2011. </bibl>
					<bibl> Bakker Kellog, S. “Ritual sounds, political echoes: Vocal agency and the
						sensory cultures of secularism in the <pb n="256"/> Dutch Syriac diaspora.”
							<hi rend="italic">American Ethnologist</hi> 42,3 (2015): 431-445. </bibl>
					<bibl> Benoit, J.L. “Religion populaire et crise identitaire en Amérique
						latine.” <hi rend="italic">Amerika</hi> 6 (2012): <ref
							target="https://journals.openedition.org/amerika/3110"
							>https://journals.openedition.org/amerika/3110</ref> (accessed 9 January
						2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Calder, M. “Syrian Identity in Bethlehem: From Ethnoreligion to
						Ecclesiology.” <hi rend="italic">Iran and the Caucasus</hi> 20 (2016),
						297-323. </bibl>
					<bibl> Cofradía Catedral de San Juan Bautista, “La verdadera historia de la
						Iglesia San Juan Bautista. San Juan Comalapa, Chimaltenango, Guatemala
						Centro América” (2008): <ref
							target="http://www.albedrio.org/htm/otrosdocs/comunicados/IGLESIASANJUANBAUTISTAENLAHISTORIA.pdf"
							>http://www.albedrio.org/htm/otrosdocs/comunicados/IGLESIASANJUANBAUTISTAENLAHISTORIA.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Compagnon, O. “La crise du catholicisme latino-américain.” <hi
							rend="italic">L'Ordinaire des Amériques</hi> 210 (2008): 9-25: <ref
							target="http://journals.openedition.org/orda/2613"
							>http://journals.openedition.org/orda/2613</ref> (accessed 9 January
						2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Davis, S. H. “Mouvement maya et culture nationale au Guatemala.” <hi
							rend="italic">Journal de la société des américanistes</hi> 90-2 (2004):
							<ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jsa/1724"
							>http://journals.openedition.org/jsa/1724</ref> (accessed 9 January
						2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Dinno, K. <hi rend="italic">The Syrian Orthodox Christians in the Late
							Ottoman Period and Beyond. Crisis then Revival</hi>. Piscataway: Gorgias
						Press, 2017. </bibl>
					<bibl> Episcopal Conference of Guatemala, “66: Renovados en el Espíritu.
						Instrucción pastoral colectiva de los obispos de Guatemala sobre le
						renovación carismática.” In <hi rend="italic">Al servicio de la vida, la
							justicia y la paz (1956-1997)</hi>, 30 March 1986: <ref
							target="http://www.iglesiacatolica.org.gt/CEGsvjp.pdf"
							>http://www.iglesiacatolica.org.gt/CEGsvjp.pdf</ref> (accessed 9 January
						2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Hager, A. “The Emergence of a Syriac Orthodox Mayan Church in Guatemala.”
							<hi rend="italic">International Journal of Latin American Religions</hi>
						3:2 (2019), 370–389. </bibl>
					<pb n="257"/>
					<bibl> Hoenes del Pinal, E. “A Ritual Interrupted: A Case of Contested Ritual
						Practices in a Q’eqchi’-Maya Catholic Parish.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
							Contemporary Religion</hi> 31:3 (2016): 365-378 </bibl>
					<bibl> -“From Vatican II to Speaking in Tongues: Theology and Language Policy in
						a Q’eqchi’-Maya Catholic Parish.” <hi rend="italic">Language Policy</hi>
						15:2 (2016), 179-197 </bibl>
					<bibl> ICASOA. <hi rend="italic">Guía para la formación catequética en
							preparación a la iniciación cristiana</hi>. San Lucas Sacatepéquez:
						Editorial Nuevo Éxodo, colección didaché 1:4. </bibl>
					<bibl> Icasoac Siro-Ortodoxo. Facebook entry 7 November 2019, Alta Verapaz,
						Chisec: <ref
							target="https://www.facebook.com/498235783665202/videos/404401483770752/"
							>https://www.facebook.com/498235783665202/videos/404401483770752/</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -Facebook entry 10 November 2019, “Santa Eucaristía precidida por Su
						Santidad Ignacio Efrén II, Estadio Los Cuchumatanes Huehuetenango
						Guatemala:” <ref
							target="https://www.facebook.com/498235783665202/videos/410119743001759/"
							>https://www.facebook.com/498235783665202/videos/410119743001759/</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Icergua. “Acta Fundacional de la Comunión,” 25 March 2003: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/actacomunion.html"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/actacomunion.html</ref> (accessed 7
						February 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Asamblea Nacional 2005; informe sobre la situación de la comunión a la
						II asamblea nacional,” November 2005: <ref
							target="http://icergua.org/latam/asamblea05.html"
							>http://icergua.org/latam/asamblea05.html</ref> (accessed 9 January
						2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Relación Con Roma,” 15 August 2006: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/Relacion_roma.html"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/Relacion_roma.html</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Primera plática informe acerca de la situación actual de ICERGUA,”
						November 2008: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/vasambleanacional/01primeraplatica.pdf"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/vasambleanacional/01primeraplatica.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“1: Decanato de las Verapaces y Petén,” 1 May 2009: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/09-noticias/09-notagosto.html#13"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/09-noticias/09-notmayo.html#23</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<pb n="258"/>
					<bibl> -“Icergua: llegua al medio millón de miembros,” 22 December 2010: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/10-noticias/12-diciembre.html#21"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/10-noticias/12-diciembre.html#21</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“23: Aprobación ʻad experimentum’ del sacramentario católico ortodoxo
						latino,” 23 August 2011: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/11-noticias/08-agosto.html#27"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/11-noticias/08-agosto.html#27</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“05: Diálogos con el patriarcado ortodoxo siriano de Antioquía,” 5
						November 2011: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/11-noticias/11-noviembre.html#6"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/11-noticias/11-noviembre.html#6</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“02: Primera celebración de la divina liturgia de Santiago por nuestro
						Obispo,” 2 August 2012: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/12-noticias/08-agosto.html#1"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/12-noticias/08-agosto.html#1</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“07: Visita a Mor Clemis Eugene en su sede arzobispal de Burbank,
						California,” 7 December 2012: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/12-noticias/12-diciembre.html#4"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/12-noticias/12-diciembre.html#4</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“16: Reuniones en St. Ephrem’s Cathedral en Burbank, California,” 16
						February 2013: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/02.html#28"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/02.html#28</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“05: Tonsura de nuestro obispo como monje, por su Santidad Ignacio
						Zaqueo I Iwas,” 5 March 2013: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/03.html#2"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/03.html#2</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“05: Encíclicas de su santidad Ignacio Zaqueo I, concernientes a nuestra
						iglesia,” 5 March 2013: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/03.html#7"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/13/03.html#7</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“20: Visita a la comunidad de fieles de la catedral de San Efrén,
						Burbank, Californa,” 20 January 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/01.html#45"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/01.html#45</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<pb n="259"/>
					<bibl> -“13: Divina liturgia por el ayuno de Nínive y la solemnidad de San
						Ignacio Elías III.,” 13 February 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/02.html#17"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/02.html#17</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“01: Encuentro de nuestro Arzobispo Mor Santiago Eduardo con su Santidad
						Ignacio Efrén II.,” 1 March 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/04.html#1"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/04.html#1</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“03: Exhortación pastoral ʻEl Evangelio de la Renovación,’” 3 April
						2014: <ref target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/04.html#5"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/04.html#5</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“01: Llegada del coespiscopo Abdulahad Shara como envidao de su Santidad
						el patriarca,” 1 September 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/09.html#1"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/09.html#1</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Identidad y perspectivas pastorales de la arquidiócesis de Centro
						América,” November 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/14-11-14-identidad-perspectiva-arquidiocesis.pdf"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/14-11-14-identidad-perspectiva-arquidiocesis.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Raíces históricas del proceso que nos ha llevado hasta ser constituidos
						en arquidiócesis de Centro América de la Santa Iglesia Católica Apostólica
						siro-ortodoxa de Antioquía,” November 2014: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/14-11-13-historiaarquidiocesis.pdf"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/pdf/14-11-13-historiaarquidiocesis.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 9 January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“21: Divina liturgia de bienvenida a los corepíscopos Mathews y Sabu
						Thomas en el seminario,” 21 April 2015: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/04.html#47"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/04.html#47</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“24: Divina liturgia en el seminario presidida por los corepíscopos
						Mathews y Sabu,” 24 April 2015: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/04.html#53"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/04.html#53</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“06: Publicación del estatuto oficial de la arquidiócesis de Centro
						América,” 6 June 2015: <pb n="260"/>
						<ref target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/06.html#2"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/06.html#2</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“18: Encuentro de Mor Santiago Eduardo con su Santidad el patriarca en
						Lancaster, Pensilvania, USA,” 18 July 2015: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/07.html#29"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/15/07.html#29</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“02: Visita a las obras de construcción del templo de Santa María,
						Cunén, el Quiché,” 2 November 2016: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/16/11.html#5"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/16/11.html#5</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“22: Su Santidad Ignacio Efrén II, recibe a Mor Santiago Eduardo en el
						patriarcado de Damasco,” 22 January 2017: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/01a.html#53"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/01a.html#53</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“15: Divina liturgia en San Miguel Chanquejelbé, Nentón, Huehuetenango,”
						15 March 2017: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/03a.html#4"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/03a.html#4</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“11: Renovación de los compromisos presbiterales, vicaría de
						Huehuetenango, San Rafael de la Independencia,” 11 April 2017: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/04.html#24"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/04.html#24</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“19: El patriarca envía la encíclica de bendición para la publicación
						del sacramentario de la arquidiócesis,” 19 June 2017: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/06a.html#10"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/17/06a.html#10</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“01: Divina liturgia en la parroquia de Guaxacaná, Nentón,
						Huehuetenango,” 1 January 2018: <ref
							target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/18/01.html#2"
							>http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/18/01.html#2</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl>“10: Reunión con los servidores de la parroquia de San Miguel, Los Ángeles,” 10 
						August 2014: <ref target="http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/08.html#15">
							http://www.icergua.org/latam/noticias/14/08.html#15</ref> (accessed 29 July 2020)</bibl>
					<pb n="261"/>
					<bibl> Iwas, Mor Ignatius Zakka I. “Identity of the Syrian Orthodox Church,”
						1986: <ref target="http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/IdentityofSOC.htm"
							>http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/IdentityofSOC.htm</ref> (accessed
						19 December 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Tradition” (<hi rend="italic">Patriarchal Magazine</hi> (January -
						March, 1990): <ref
							target="http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/Artilces/TraditionSOC.pdf"
							>http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/Artilces/TraditionSOC.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 18 December 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> -“The Role of Women in the Syrian Orthodox Church of Antioch,” 1996: <ref
							target="http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/Artilces/WomeninSOC.pdf"
							>http://syriacchristianity.info/PZakka/Artilces/WomeninSOC.pdf</ref>
						(accessed 19 December 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Jacobsen, D. <hi rend="italic">The World’s Christians: Who They Are,
							Where They Are, and How They Got There</hi>. Chichester:
						Wiley-Blackwell, 2011. </bibl>
					<bibl> Jarjour, J. “Ḥasho: Music Modality and the Economy of Emotional
						Aesthetics.” <hi rend="italic">Ethnomusicology Forum</hi>, 24:1 (2015),
						51-72. </bibl>
					<bibl> Kaplan, Bishop Mor Clemis Eugene. Personal interview, 21 August 2018,
						Burbank. </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Historical Moment in the History of the Syriac Orthodox Church,” given
						to the author on 21 August 2018, Burbank. </bibl>
					<bibl> -“Comparison between the Syriac Orthodox Church and the Roman Catholic
						and Protestant Churches in Brief,” sent to the author in August 2018. </bibl>
					<bibl> Karim, Mor Ignatius Aphrem II. “Following Christ together in
						discrimination, persecution, martyrdom: What does this mean for the global
						church today?” 25 April 2018: <ref
							target="https://syriacpatriarchate.org/2018/04/following-christ-together-in-discrimination-persecution-martyrdom-what-does-this-mean-for-the-global-church-today/"
							>https://syriacpatriarchate.org/2018/04/following-christ-together-in-discrimination-persecution-martyrdom-what-does-this-mean-for-the-global-church-today/</ref>
						(accessed 19 December 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Kiraz, G. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Orthodox in North America
							(1895-1995). A Short History</hi>. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2019. </bibl>
					<bibl> Majallat al-Hikma, “<foreign xml:lang="ar">خلاصة مقررات مجمع دير مار متى
							المقدس بالموصل</foreign> [Summary of the Decisions of the Synod at Mar
							<pb n="262"/> Mattai Monastery in Mosul],” Nr. 9, Year 4, November 1930,
						Pages 516-523. </bibl>
					<bibl> Murre-Van den Berg, H. “A Center of Transnational Syriac Orthodoxy: St.
						Marks’ Convent in Jerusalem.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Levantine
							Studies</hi> 3:1 (2013), 59-81. </bibl>
					<bibl> Naveau, E. “Les orthodoxes syriaques d’Indonésie.” <hi rend="italic">Les
							Cahiers de l'Orient</hi> 93:1 (2009), 111-124 <ref
							target="https://www.cairn.info/revue-les-cahiers-de-l-orient-2009-1-page-111.htm#"
							>https://www.cairn.info/revue-les-cahiers-de-l-orient-2009-1-page-111.htm#</ref>
						(accessed 7 April 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Prien, H.-J. <hi rend="italic">Das Christentum in Lateinamerika. IV.6.
							Kirchengeschichte in Einzeldarstellungen</hi>. Leipzig: Evangelische
						Verlagsanstalt, 2007. </bibl>
					<bibl> Samuel, M. A. Y. <hi rend="italic">Saint James Liturgy Anaphora. The
							Divine Liturgy of Saint James </hi>(1967) </bibl>
					<bibl> Sandford, V. “From Genocide to Feminicide: Impunity and Human. Rights in
						Twenty-First Century Guatemala.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Human
							Rights</hi> 7 (2008), 104–122. </bibl>
					<bibl> Santiago Eduardo, Mor. “Icergua: Introducción a la biografía de Monseñor
						Eduardo Aguirre Oestmann:” <ref
							target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yazgw4Mxy_Y"
							>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yazgw4Mxy_Y</ref> (accessed 7 February
						2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Mor Santiago Eduardo, “Icergua: entrevista con el obispo en Ahuachapán el
						Salvador,” published 2 June 2012, <ref
							target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SqyGU_mluRA"
							>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SqyGU_mluRA</ref> (accessed 7 February
						2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Schmoller, A. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Middle Eastern Christians and
							Europe: Historical Legacies and Present Challenges</hi>. Vienna: Lit,
						2018. </bibl>
					<bibl> Claude, S. <hi rend="italic">Les Syriens orthodoxes et catholiques</hi>.
						Turnhout: Brepols, 1988 </bibl>
					<bibl> Seraphim, A. “Orthodox Mission in the Twenty-First Century: Guatemala.”
						The Glastonbury Review 126 (2015): <ref
							target="http://britishorthodox.org/glastonburyreview/issue-126-orthodox-mission-in-the-twenty-first-century-guatemala/"
							>http://britishorthodox.org/glastonburyreview/issue-126-orthodox-mission-in-the-twenty-first-century-guatemala/</ref>
						(accessed 25 March 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Shils, E. “Tradition.” <hi rend="italic">Comparative Studies in Society
							and History</hi> 13:2 Special Issue on Tradition and Modernity (1971),
						122-159. </bibl>
					<pb n="263"/>
					<bibl> -<hi rend="italic">Tradition</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
						1981. </bibl>
					<bibl> SOC-WUS; Rev. Father John Khoury, “The Seven Living Sacraments,” 29 March
						2010: <ref
							target="http://syrianorthodoxchurch.org/2010/03/the-seven-living-sacraments/"
							>http://syrianorthodoxchurch.org/2010/03/the-seven-living-sacraments/</ref>
						(accessed 7 February 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> SOC-WUS, “His Eminence Mor Clemis Eugene welcomed Bishop Eduardo of
						Guatemala,” 9 April 2011: <ref
							target="http://www.soc-wus.org/2011News/4102011163933.htm"
							>http://www.soc-wus.org/2011News/4102011163933.htm</ref> (accessed 7
						February 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> -"<foreign xml:lang="ar">صفحةٌ تأريخية في تاريخ الكنيسة السريانية الأرثوذكسية</foreign> [From the Archive of the
						Patriarchate: a Historic Page in the History of the Syriac Orthodox
						Church],” 7 August 2012: <ref
							target="http://www.soc-wus.org/2012News/8112012115231.htm"
							>http://www.soc-wus.org/2012News/8112012115231.htm</ref> (accessed 9
						January 2020). </bibl>
					<bibl> Syrian Orthodox Dioceses of North America and Canada, “The Sacrament of
						the Holy Eucharist,” 1998: <ref
							target="http://sor.cua.edu/Liturgy/Anaphora/Eucharist.html"
							>http://sor.cua.edu/Liturgy/Anaphora/Eucharist.html</ref> (accessed 18
						December 2019). </bibl>
					<bibl> Thorsen, J. “El impacto de la renovación carismática en la Iglesia
						católica de Guatemala” <hi rend="italic">Anuario de Estudios
							Centroamericanos</hi> 42:1 (2016), 213-236 </bibl>
					<bibl> Varghese, B. <hi rend="italic">West Syrian Liturgical Theology</hi>.
						Aldershot: Ashgate, 2004. </bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
