<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Georgia Frank, Susan R. Holman, and Andrew S. Jacobs, eds.,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Garb of Being: Embodiment and the Pursuit of Holiness in
                        Late Ancient Christianity</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>J. Edward</forename>
                        <surname>Walters</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript Library</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2prwalters</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>J. Edward Walters</author>
                        <title level="a">Georgia Frank, Susan R. Holman, and Andrew S. Jacobs, eds.,
                            <hi rend="italic">The Garb of Being: Embodiment and the Pursuit of Holiness in
                                Late Ancient Christianity</hi></title>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2PRWalters.pdf</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="558" to="562">558-562</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="14"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>

                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <ab type="review-title">Georgia Frank, Susan R. Holman, and Andrew S. Jacobs, eds.,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Garb of Being: Embodiment and the Pursuit of Holiness in
                            Late Ancient Christianity</hi> (New York: Fordham University Press, 2020). Pp.
                        ix + 409; $65.00</ab>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                <p xml:lang="en">The present volume, a collection of essays organized
                    around the theme of “embodiment” as a way of studying the texts, beliefs, and
                    practices of late ancient Christians, serves as a fitting gift of scholarship to
                    honor the work and career of its dedicatee: Susan Ashbrook Harvey. The theme of
                    embodiment runs through Harvey’s own work, perhaps seen most clearly in her 2015
                    monograph <hi rend="italic">Scenting Salvation</hi>, where Harvey demonstrates that
                    careful attention to embodied practices of Christian worship and devotion in late
                    antiquity can reframe modern scholarly discussions of holiness, ritual, and worship.
                    All of the entries in this volume, in some way, pick up on these themes and develop
                    them further.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The editors of the volume have provided an elegant introductory
                    essay that justifies the dual theme of “garbs” and embodiment for the volume,
                    inviting the reader to consider different “bodies” and “garments” that form objects
                    of study in late ancient Christianity. They also discuss the rationale for the three
                    parts into which the essays are organized. In Part I, <hi rend="italic">Making
                        Bodies</hi>, the essays “consider the varied ways Christians approached the
                    production of individual bodies <hi rend="italic">as</hi> Christian bodies” (p. 5).
                    In Part II, <hi rend="italic">Performing Bodies</hi>, the essays are organized
                    around the theme of “public performance of bodies” (p. 6) and explore how Christians
                    rhetorically used physical bodies as means of persuasion. And in Part III, <hi
                        rend="italic">Scripting Bodies</hi>, the definition of “body” broadens to
                    include bodies of textual production, as the authors explore questions related to
                    written corpora and Christian embodiment.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">There are three essays in Part I. In the first, Frances Young
                    (“Body and Soul: Union in Creation, Reunion at Resurrection”) surveys opinions and
                    arguments about the union of body and soul in early and late ancient Christian
                    authors, with particular attention to how these authors subtly reframe the common
                    “soul-body dualism” of antiquity through their theological views about creation and
                    the resurrection. In Arthur Urbano’s essay (“Jesus’s Dazzling Garments: Origen’s
                    Exegesis of the Transfiguration in the <hi rend="italic">Commentary on
                        Matthew</hi>”), we catch a glimpse—through Origen’s eyes—of the transfiguration
                    scene as a moment of early Christian theological speculation. Building upon his own
                    work on dress/garb, Urbano walks the reader carefully through Origen’s detailed
                    exegesis, noting the ways that Origen plays with the clothing metaphor throughout.
                    In the final essay of Part I, Thomas Arentzen (“Conversing with Clothes: Germanos
                    and Mary’s Belt”) offers a fascinating examination of a particular piece of clothing
                    as relic and the surprising way it is invoked in a homily by Germanos I, patriarch
                    of Constantinople. Through Germanos’s invocation of Mary’s belt and other garments
                    on display in Constantinople, Arentzen invites the reader to consider the embodied
                    practice of relic devotion in late antiquity and the ways in which people would have
                    encountered relics, both physically and rhetorically.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In the first essay of Part II, Sidney Griffith
                    (“ ‘Denominationalism’ in Fourth-Century Syria: Readings in Saint Ephraem’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Hymns Against Heresies</hi> 22–24”) examines three <hi
                            rend="italic">madrāshe</hi> from Ephrem’s cycle on heresies, noting how his
                    accusations against Mani, Marcion, and Bardaisan functioned in Ephrem’s attempts to
                    define the “orthodox” Christian community around him as the true, legitimate
                    Christian community, while others were considered heretical offshoots. Rebecca
                    Falcasantos (“A School for the Soul: John Chrysostom on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mimēsis</hi> and the Force of Ritual Habit”) examines how John Chrysostom
                    employed <hi rend="italic">mimēsis</hi> as a model for how Christians learn to be
                    Christian in the context of worship, as opposed to other social habits they might
                    learn to mimic elsewhere. Rebecca Krawiec (“A Question of Character: The ‘Labor of
                    Composition’ as ‘Preventative Medicine’ in Theodoret of Cyrrhus’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Religious History</hi>”), analyzes the biographical sketches of monks provided
                    by Theodoret and argues that the small details and variations that distinguish the
                    holy people from one another allows them to serve as “preventative medicine,” as
                    different readers are able to locate and admire particular characters that appeal to
                    them. Applying the modern lens of “celebrity” studies, Andrew Jacobs (“ ‘I Wan t to
                    be Alone’: Ascetic Celebrity and the Splendid Isolation of Simeon Stylites”)
                    explores the “paradox” of ascetic celebrities (that is, ascetics who claimed to
                    desire solitude yet drew large crowds of onlookers and admirers nonetheless), taking
                    Simeon the Stylite as a case study. Through this analysis, Jacobs asks the reader to
                    reconsider the economy of production for hagiographic texts and to shift analysis of
                    those texts accordingly. Through a broad reading of the liturgical hymns of Romanos
                    the melodist, Georgia Frank (“Crowds and Collective Affect in Romanos’s Biblical
                    Retellings”) emphasizes the affective role that Romanos’s lyrics might have played
                    for those who participated in his worshipping community, drawing attention to the
                    embodied nature of worship in late antiquity. Jeanne-Nicole Mellon Saint-Laurent
                    (“Christian Legend in Medieval Iraq: Siblings, Sacrifice, and Sanctity in <hi
                        rend="italic">Behnam and Sarah</hi>”) reads a twelfth-century Syriac martyrdom
                    legend not as a straightforward account of historical events, but as a reflection of
                    a particular community at a particular time. This essay also explores the
                    relationship between textual production and sites of martyrdom commemoration in the
                    medieval Middle East. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Part III begins with an essay from Sebastian Brock (“Five Women
                    Martyrs: From Persia to Crete”), in which he builds on his own prior work with
                    Harvey on women martyrs in the Syriac tradition. Here Brock connects the dots
                    between a Syriac martyrdom account, a story in the Greek synaxarion, and a small
                    shrine on the island of Crete. Suzanne Rebillard (“Gregory of Nazianzus’s Poetic
                    Ascetic Aesthetic”) provides a close reading of the poetry of Gregory of Nazianzus,
                    highlighting the ways in which his rhetorical poetic skill engages the reader as an
                    active participant. Bernadette McNary-Zak (“Eclipsed in Exile: In Defense of
                    Athanasius and the Ethiopians”) interprets the three letters of Athanasius known as
                    the <hi rend="italic">Defense before Constantius</hi> in light of Athanasius’s
                    status among Ethiopian Christians, and thus imperial fears about Athanasius’s
                    support outside the Roman Empire. Constance M. Furey (“Sacred Bonds: Religion,
                    Relationships, and the Art of Pedagogy”) examines the Sidney-Pembroke Psalter as a
                    site of “sacred bonding,” wherein human relationships shed light on the production
                    of Christian books in the early modern period. Also working with sources well beyond
                    late antiquity, Susan R. Holman (“ ‘And Yet the Books’: Patristics in the
                    Footnotes”) compares three modern users of patristic texts, specifically for how
                    they apply these ancient witnesses to modern concerns. Finally, Caroline T.
                    Schroeder (“Cultural Heritage Preservation and Canon Formation: What Syriac and
                    Coptic Can Teach Us about the Historiography of the Digital Humanities”) provides a
                    new overview of the history of the field of digital humanities that incorporates
                    Syriac and Coptic projects, not just as small-scale offshoots from more well-known
                    projects, but as significant developments in digital humanities scholarship in their
                    own right.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Overall, this volume is a pleasure to read, and the wide
                    variety of approaches and sources discussed makes it accessible to readers with
                    diverse interests in the texts and people of late antiquity. Through her teaching
                    and writing, Susan Ashbrook Harvey has continually invited others to see the innate
                    relationship between embodied, physical existence in the world and the religious
                    experience of the supernatural. This volume extends this invitation even further,
                    and many scholars of late ancient Christianity to come will benefit from it.</p>
                
                </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

