<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Men of Letters in the Syriac Scribal Tradition</title>
                <title type="sub">Dawid bar Pawlos, Rabban Rāmišoʿ, and the Family of Beṯ
                    Rabban</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Nick</forename>
                        <surname>Posegay</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Cambridge</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n1posegay</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Nick Posegay</author>
                        <title level="a">Men of Letters in the Syriac Scribal Tradition: Dawid bar
                            Pawlos, Rabban Rāmišoʿ, and the Family of Beṯ Rabban</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N1Posegay.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="127" to="186">127-186</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="4"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Vocalization</term>
                    <term>Grammar</term>
                    <term>David bar Pawlos</term>
                    <term>Beth Rabban</term>
                    <term>Rabban Rāmišoʿ</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-02-12">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Dawid bar Pawlos’ Letter on Dots is an eighth-century text that
                    purportedly describes the introduction of some of the dots used in Syriac
                    writing. It also sheds light on the life of a certain Rāmišoʿ of Beṯ Rabban,
                    apparently the same man as the master of pointing named in MS BL Add. 12138.
                    However, most studies of Syriac dots either neglect or completely discount this
                    letter as a reliable source, since it suggests that Miaphysite scribes had a
                    direct influence on East Syriac reading traditions. This article provides a more
                    critical analysis of the letter, first examining the problematic state of its
                    extant manuscripts, and then evaluating the text to determine its historical
                    plausibility in the context of seventh-century northern Mesopotamia.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.0" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> I would like to
                        thank Prof. Sebastian Brock, Prof. Jonathan Loopstra, Dr. Nadia Vidro, Fr.
                        Roger-Youssef Akhrass, and Fr. Joseph Bali for sharing their expertise and
                        for their assistance in accessing resources for this article. This work was
                        supported by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation [OPP1144]. Any errors
                        within are mine alone.</p></note>
                <p rend="H Normal First">Dawid bar Pawlos was a Miaphysite monk, poet, and
                    grammarian who flourished in northern Mesopotamia in the second half of the
                    eighth century. Much of his extant work is contained in a book of more than 60
                    Syriac letters that he exchanged with people of his time. One of these is the
                        <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> to the Bishop Yoḥannān, in which Dawid
                    claims to tell the story of one Rabban Saḇroy and his son Rāmišoʿ who invented
                    some points for use in Syriac manuscripts. This account seems to imply that a
                    family of Miaphysites made direct contributions to what is ostensibly the
                    “Eastern” system of reading and vocalisation, and this fact has led some
                    scholars to dismiss the entire story as a fantasy.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> Arthur Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">History of the School of Nisibis</hi>, Corpus
                            Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 26 (Louvain: American Catholic
                            University; Louvaine Catholic University, 1965), 201–2, nn.
                        32–33.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Despite this sectarian discrepancy, the letter is a major source of
                    biographical details about Dawid, and while questions about his motivations for
                    writing it remain, it is also practically the exclusive source for information
                    on Beṯ Rabban Saḇroy. Modern understandings of its contents have depended on the
                    editions of Ignatius Ephrem II Rahmani and Philoxenus Yuḥanon Dolabani, both of
                    whom lacked manuscripts that contained the complete letter, as well as the
                    analysis of Afram Barsoum, whose interpretations have been muddled in
                        translation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Unless otherwise noted, all quotations of non-English sources below are
                            my own translations.</p></note> As a result of these problems, the
                    letter has long avoided close analysis, even in studies that aim to recover the
                    finest details of Syriac pointing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See J.B. Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                Point and the Accents in Syriac</hi> (London; New York: Oxford
                            University Press, 1953); and George A. Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Syriac Dot: A Short History</hi> (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015),
                            neither of whom consults the letter. See also, Adam H. Becker, <hi
                                rend="italic">Fear of God and the Beginning of Wisdom: The School of
                                Nisibis and Christian Scholastic Culture in Late Antique
                                Mesopotamia</hi> (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                            2006), 91, 238, n. 90.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The following discussion resolves some of these issues in order to
                    clarify the status of the <hi rend="italic">Letter </hi>as a potentially
                    valuable source for an obscure period in the development of Syriac writing. It
                    first traces the known manuscripts of Dawid’s book of letters to show that
                    Rahmani and Dolabani’s two editions are based on the same incomplete manuscript,
                    as are all extant copies (§1). It then analyses the text of the letter to
                    correct certain misinformation in secondary literature and to establish a
                    chronology of the events that Dawid describes (§2), including the family history
                    of Beṯ Rabban (§2.1), an anecdote about Rāmišoʿ bar Saḇroy’s reading tradition
                    at Mar Mattai monastery (§2.2), and the invention of some Syriac vowel points in
                    Nineveh (§2.3). In doing so, this paper demonstrates that while we cannot
                    confirm for certain that Dawid’s story is true, he does provide a plausible
                    account for the spread of a particular recitation tradition and vowel points in
                    the context of late seventh-century northern Mesopotamia.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1 The Manuscripts</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">There are three extant manuscripts and two printed editions of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi>. Although their editors do not make it
                    clear, all of these texts are based on the same deficient source. As such, they
                    are missing a substantial amount of text in the middle of the letter, and no
                    known manuscripts can supplement this lacuna.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The two editions of the letter are both derived from a larger “book
                    of letters” by Dawid bar Pawlos. Ignatius Ephrem II Rahmani published the first
                    edition in 1904 while he was the Syriac Catholic Patriarch of Antioch and All
                    the East.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Sebastian P. Brock and George A. Kiraz, “Raḥmani, Ignatius Ephrem II,”
                            in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho),
                            accessed April 28, 2020,
                            https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Rahmani-Ignatius-Ephrem-II. This and
                            several other articles cited below are found in George A. Kiraz et al.,
                            eds., <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac
                                Heritage (GEDSH): Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho, 2011),
                            https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/ index.html.</p></note> This version
                    appeared along with three other extracts from Dawid’s letters in <hi
                        rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ignatius Ephraem II Rahmani, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Studia Syriaca: Collectio Documentorum Hactenus Ineditorum Ex
                                Codicus Syriacis</hi> (Sharfeh: Sharfeh Patriarchal Seminary, 1904),
                            ܡܗ-ܡܙ; with Latin translation, 44-46.</p></note> Philoxenus Yuḥanon
                        Dolabani,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Known variously as F.Y. Dolabani and by the surname Dolapönu. See George
                            A. Kiraz, “Dolabani, Philoxenos Yuḥanon,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                            https://gedsh. bethmardutho.org/Dolabani-Philoxenos-Yuhanon.</p></note>
                    the Syriac Orthodox Bishop of Mardin, published the second edition in 1953 along
                    with the entirety of the book of letters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> P.Y. Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh
                                d-Dawid bar Pawlos d-Metidaʿ d-Bet Rabban</hi> (Mardin: The Syriac
                            Printing Press of Wisdom, 1953), 44–49.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Dolabani reports that his edition is based on a 14th-century codex
                    in the monastery known as Dayr al-Zaʿfarān outside of Mardin, Turkey.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., B-C. See
                            George A. Kiraz, “Al-Zaʿfarān, Dayr,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                            https://gedsh. bethmardutho.org/al-Zafaran-Dayr.</p></note> He says that
                    this manuscript has 222 pages, measures 15.5 x 12.5 cm, and contains 69 of Dawid
                    bar Pawlos’ letters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                        C.</p></note> He also refers to this manuscript as no. 74/20 in his 1928
                    catalogue of Dayr al-Zaʿfarān’s manuscripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                        n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> P.Y. Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue
                                of Syriac Manuscripts in Zaʿfaran Monastery (Dairo dMor
                                Hananyo)</hi>, ed. Gregorios Yuhanna Ibrahim (Damascus: Sidawi
                            Printing House, 1994), 287. Reprinted by Gorgias Press, Piscataway 2009.
                            A label at the beginning of CFMM 158 confirms this classmark.</p></note>
                    It is now in the Church of the Forty Martyrs in Mardin, where Arthur Vööbus
                    identifies it as MS Mardin Orth. 158.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                School</hi>, 201–2, nn. 32–33; Arthur Vööbus, “Entdeckung des
                            Briefkorpus des Dawid bar Paulos,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens
                                Christianus</hi>, no. 58 (1974): 45–50.</p></note> The classmark
                    currently on the codex is “MS 158,” and the Hill Museum and Manuscript Library
                    identifies it as Church of the Forty Martyrs Mardin (CFMM) 158 in their digital
                        archive.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">
                            The HMML has digitised the entire CFMM collection: https://www.
                            vhmml.org/readingRoom/. Dolabani’s given dimensions match those of CFMM
                            158.</p></note> The <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots </hi>occupies
                    folios 36v-41r,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Paginated as 54-62, added in pencil.</p></note> but two folios are lost
                    and have been replaced by blank modern paper (ff. 39r-40v).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> See Dolabani, <hi
                                rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 48, n. 1.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Rahmani is less precise. He does not give a classmark or
                    measurements in <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, and he only says that his
                    extracts of Dawid’s letters are “from an old and damaged codex of the Jacobite
                    Patriarchal Library.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                            67. Nöldeke glosses over this point in his review; Theodor Nöldeke,
                            “Bibliographische Anzeigen: Studia Syriaca seu collectio documentorum
                            hactenus ineditorum. Ex codicibus syriacis primo publicavit, latine
                            vertit notisque illustravit Ignatius Ephraem II Rahmani patriarcha
                            Antiochenus Syrorum. Typis patriarchalibus in seminario Scharfensi in
                            Mont Libano 1904,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen
                                Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 58 (1904): 495.</p></note> He
                    published his edition via the Patriarchal Press of the Syriac Catholic seminary
                    in Charfet, Lebanon,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                            frontmatter. Charfet is also transliterated as Sharfeh and
                        Sharfah.</p></note> so some scholars have assumed that his source manuscript
                    was from Charfet.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> E.g. Anton Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                                der syischen Literatur</hi> (Bonn: A. Marcus &amp; E. Webers, 1922),
                            272, nn. 4–6.</p></note> However, I can find no record of the book of
                    letters in Isaac Armalet’s 1936 catalogue of manuscripts at the Charfet
                        monastery.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Isaac Armalet, <hi rend="italic">al-Ṭarfah fī Makhṭūṭā‎t Dayr
                                al-Sharfah</hi> (Jounieh, Lebanon: Maṭbaʻat al-Ābā‎’ al-Mursalīn
                            al-Lubnā‎niyyīn, 1936). Reprinted by Gorgias Press, Piscataway 2006. See
                            also, George A. Kiraz, “Armalah, Isḥāq,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed May 14, 2020,
                            https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Armalah-Ishaq. Armalet is also known as
                            Isḥaq Armaleh or Armalah.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The only evidence of Dawid’s letters at Charfet in Rahmani’s time
                    is the ninth section of MS Charfet 19/1,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Armalet, <hi rend="italic">al-Ṭarfah</hi>,
                            278.</p></note> which Armalet says contains four letters and replies
                    that he published in 1908.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Isaac Armalet, <hi rend="italic">Reggath
                                Shabrē</hi>, vol. II (Sharfeh: Syriac Patriarchal Press, 1908),
                            180–82.</p></note> He then published them again in 1928,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> Isaac Armalet,
                                <hi rend="italic">Lettres de Josué, fils de David, surnommé
                                Bar-Kilo, de Sévère Jacques de Bartelli, surnommé Bar-Chacaco, et de
                                David de Beit-Rabban</hi> (Beirut: Syriac Patriarchal Press, 1928),
                            123–32.</p></note> this time attributing them to Dawid bar Pawlos, and
                    indicating that they are from MS Charfet 10/1 (a typo for 19/1).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., 6;
                            Armalet, <hi rend="italic">al-Ṭarfah</hi>, 206. Armalet’s own
                            description of Charfet 10/1 states that it consists of several other
                            texts unrelated to Dawid’s letters.</p></note> At least two of these
                    letters correspond to letters in Dolabani’s <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, but
                    Armalet’s versions are shorter and have many variations that indicate a source
                    that differed from CFMM 158.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Compare Armalet’s second and sixth letters in <hi
                                rend="italic">Lettres</hi> to Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Egroteh</hi>, 6-7 and 131-134, respectively.</p></note> That source
                    remains unaccounted for.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Meanwhile, Rahmani’s source manuscript actually matches CFMM 158 in
                    a number of physical details. He remarks that a note appears “at the end of the
                    first folio of the book”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                            ܡܕ, n. 1.</p></note> which includes a date for the year that Dawid bar
                    Pawlos briefly left his monastery in the 780s,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26"
                        n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Baumstark, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Geschichte</hi>, 272.</p></note> and he mentions that the final number
                    in the year is uncertain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                            ܡܕ, n. 2. See also his Latin discussion on 67. Barsoum makes the same
                            observation, but MS Mingana Syriac 29 indicates that the year should be
                            785 CE; Ignatius Aphram I Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                al-Manthūr fī Tārīkh al-ʿUlūm al-Ādāb al-Suriyāniyya</hi>, 5th ed.
                            (Aleppo: Silsila al-Turāth al-Suriyānī, 1987), 326, n. 1; Matti Moosa,
                            ed., <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls: A History of Syriac
                                Literature and Sciences</hi>, trans. Matti Moosa, 2nd revised
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2003), 372, n. 3; Alphonse Mingana, <hi
                                rend="italic">Catalogue of the Mingana Collection of Manuscripts:
                                Syriac and Garshūni Manuscripts</hi>, vol. I (Cambridge: W. Heffer
                            and Sons, 1933), 79. I give all citations of <hi rend="italic"
                                >al-Luʾluʾ</hi> with the corresponding page numbers in Moosa’s
                            translation, but the quoted translations of Barsoum’s Arabic are my own
                            unless otherwise stated.</p></note> Dolabani transcribes the same note
                    from the end of CFMM 158’s <hi rend="italic">second</hi> extant folio,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"> CFMM 158 f. 2v,
                            line 13-22. It is not clear to me how this discrepancy
                        occurred.</p></note> which is bracketed off by a red outline, where the
                    final number is also too damaged to read.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29"
                        n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 4,
                            n. 1.</p></note> Both editors also transcribe the same text as a
                    marginal insertion on CFMM 158 f. 38v (line 8), which has been written by two
                    different hands, the latter of which also restored text throughout the
                        codex.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Ibid., 47, line 22; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ,
                            line 16–17.</p></note> Then, in precisely the same place where the <hi
                        rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> in CFMM 158 is missing two folios (after
                    the catchword <hi rend="italic">rukkāḵā</hi> on f. 38v),<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> CFMM 158, f. 38v.</p></note>
                    Rahmani observes that “one or more folios are missing from the codex.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> Compare \
                            Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 21; Dolabani,
                                <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 48, line 7.</p></note> These
                    physical similarities suggest that Rahmani’s source was copied from CFMM
                    158.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Furthermore, while Rahmani did revive the Charfet press after he
                    became Patriarch in 1898, he did not move the seat of the Catholic Patriarchate
                    to Lebanon until after World War I. Prior to the 1920s, his Patriarchate was
                    still based in Mardin,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Amir Harrak, “Sharfeh,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28,
                            2020, https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Sharfeh; J. Gordon Melton and
                            Martin Baumann, <hi rend="italic">Religions of the World: A
                                Comprehensive Encyclopedia of Beliefs and Practices</hi>, 2nd ed.,
                            vol. VI (Santa Barbara; Denver; Oxford: ABC-CLIO, 2010),
                        2795.</p></note> and the seat of the Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate was based
                    just outside that city at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                        n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, “Al-Zaʿfarān, Dayr.”</p></note> It is
                    probable that the “Jacobite Patriarchal library” Rahmani refers to was actually
                    the library of the Orthodox Patriarchate at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, and his edition –
                    like Dolabani’s – is ultimately based on CFMM 158, though likely mediated by his
                    own handwritten copy. Besides a few isolated readings of individual words, the
                    only substantial difference between the two editions is that Rahmani leaves out
                    the bulk of the greetings at the beginning of the letter, whereas Dolabani
                    transcribes the entire extant text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> These greetings take up about 12 lines in
                            Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 44–45.</p></note> Rahmani’s
                    edition thus also confirms that CFMM 158’s <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi>
                    was already missing its middle pages before 1904.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ignatius Afram Barsoum, the Syriac Orthodox Patriarch from 1933 to
                    1957, also claims to have seen CFMM 158 and similar manuscripts. In 1917, he
                    wrote <hi rend="italic">Nuzhat al-Adhhān fī Tārīkh Dayr al-Zaʿfarān</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">A Tour of the Minds in the History of the Saffron
                        Monastery</hi>),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ignatius Aphram I Barsoum, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Nuzhat al-Adhhān fī Tārīkh Dayr al-Zaʿfarān</hi> (Mardin: The
                            Syriac Press at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, 1917).</p></note> a history of Dayr
                    al-Zaʿfarān based on the years he spent there as a monk and teacher
                        (1907-1917).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > George A. Kiraz, “Barsoum, Ignatius Afram,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28,
                            2020, https://gedsh. bethmardutho.org/Barsoum-Ignatius-Afram.</p></note>
                    He lists some of the monastic library’s most important works, including “two
                    rare copies of the letters of Ibn Fawlos;”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                        n="38"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">Nuzhat
                                al-Adhhān</hi>, 146.</p></note> that is, Bar Pawlos.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">One of these two manuscripts must be CFMM 158, but what is the
                    second “rare copy”? It probably did not have the missing pages of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi>, or else Rahmani would have used it to
                    supplement his 1904 edition<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Or perhaps it was the copy based on CFMM 158 that
                            Rahmani used for <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>.</p></note> – but
                    perhaps Barsoum only identified it after he arrived at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān in 1907.
                    He provided some clues 25 years later when he described what seems to be CFMM
                    158 in his <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The
                        Scattered Pearls</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Barsoum refers to this manuscript as no. 248 in
                            Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, but it is not clear where he got this number.
                            According to the HMML digital archive, the current Dayr al-Zaʿfarān MS
                            248 is a letter by Philoxenus of Mabbug
                            (https://w3id.org/vhmml/readingRoom/view/122647, accessed May 1, 2020);
                            Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 326, n. 4; Moosa,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 373, n. 4.</p></note>
                    Barsoum explains that Dawid’s letters are extant in a single fourteenth-century
                    copy at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, which has 218 pages, is damaged at both ends, and
                    contains more than 66 letters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                al-Manthūr</hi>, 326. He goes on: “Among these [letters] are 37
                            which he exchanged with authors of his time” (<hi rend="italic">minhā
                                sabaʿ wa-thalāthūn tabādalahā wa-adabāʾ ʿaṣrihi</hi>). Moosa
                            mistakenly translates <hi rend="italic">sabaʿ wa-thalāthūn </hi>as
                            “seventy-three;” Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>,
                            373.</p></note> It seems then that by 1943, Barsoum knew of only one
                    copy of the book still at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān. He also adds a footnote: “and three
                    modern copies: in our archive, Birmingham no. 29, and in the possession of
                    Professor Margoliouth at Oxford, which we gifted to him in 1913.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 326, n. 4; Moosa, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 373, n. 4.</p></note> He
                    does not indicate which – if any – of these three is the second “rare copy.”</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Barsoum was elected Patriarch in 1933, whereupon he moved the
                    Orthodox Patriarchate from Mardin to Ḥimṣ (his home),<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, “Barsoum, Ignatius
                            Afram.”</p></note> so his reference to “our archive” is the Orthodox
                    Patriarchal Library in Ḥimṣ. This library remained in Ḥimṣ until his death in
                    1957, but it was moved again after the Patriarchate transferred to Damascus in
                    1959. The copy in the archive is now known as MS Syriac Orthodox Patriarchate,
                    Damascus 3/18.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">
                            René Lavenant et al., “Catalogue des manuscrits de la bibliothèque du
                            patriarcat syrien orthodoxe à Ḥoms (auj. à Damas),” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Parole de l’Orient</hi> 19 (1994): 566. I am grateful to Fr.
                            Roger-Youssef Akhrass and Fr. Joseph Bali for providing a detailed
                            description of this codex.</p></note> This manuscript may be the second
                    of the “rare copies” that Barsoum listed in 1917, and perhaps he took it with
                    him when he left Dayr al-Zaʿfarān to become Bishop of Syria in 1918.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, “Barsoum,
                            Ignatius Afram”; Mingana, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, I:37, n.
                            1.</p></note> It is a close copy of CFMM 158, and is almost certainly
                    the reference that he used for his descriptions of Dawid’s letters in <hi
                        rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                al-Manthūr</hi>, 327–29; Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered
                                Pearls</hi>, 373–76.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The next “modern” copy is MS Mingana Syriac 29, currently held in
                    the Cadbury Research Library at the University of Birmingham. It is part of the
                    collection of Syriac manuscripts that Alphonse Mingana acquired, mostly around
                    Mosul in 1924 and in “Kurdistan and Upper Mesopotamia” in 1925.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text"> Mingana, <hi
                                rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, I:v.</p></note> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Letter on Dots</hi> is ff. 19a-21a in this codex.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., I:80, G.</p></note>
                    Mingana notes that it was “written in a modern West Syrian hand by the present
                    West Syriac Bishop of Mosul while he was still a monk in Dair uz-Zaʿfarān.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid.,
                        I:82.</p></note> This bishop was most likely Aṯanasius Tomā Qaṣīr, who was a
                    monk at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān from 1897 to 1908. He was appointed archbishop of Mosul
                    in 1917, and he retained that post until his death in 1951.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text"> Saliba Shamoon, <hi
                                rend="italic">Tārīkh Abrashiyya al-Mawṣil al-Suriyāniyya</hi>
                            (Mosul, 1984), 201–3.</p></note> He likely copied CFMM 158 himself, took
                    that copy with him when he left Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, and then gifted or sold it to
                    Mingana when the latter visited Mosul in 1924.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51"
                        n="51"><p rend="footnote text"> Kristian Heal, “Notes on the Acquisition
                            History of the Mingana Syriac Manuscripts,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Manuscripta syriaca: des sources de première main</hi>, ed.
                            Françoise Briquel Chatonnet and Muriel Debié, Cahiers d’études syriaques
                            (Paris: Geuthner, 2015), 14–15, 21.</p></note> Barsoum also likely saw
                    it when he traveled to visit European and American libraries that held Syriac
                    manuscripts (including Birmingham) in 1927.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                        n="52"><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, “Barsoum, Ignatius Afram”; Barsoum,
                                <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, ii (French
                            introduction); Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>,
                            xxii.</p></note> Aaron Butts has confirmed that this manuscript is
                    indeed based on CFMM 158,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Aaron M. Butts, “A Syriac Dialogue Poem between
                            the Vine and Cedar by Dawid Bar Pawlos,” in <hi rend="italic">The
                                Babylonian Disputation Poems</hi>, ed. Enrique Jiménez, Culture and
                            History of the Ancient Near East 87 (Leiden; Boston: Brill, 2017),
                            462–73.</p></note> but no study has compared the codices to determine if
                    any text was lost between the times that Ming. Syr. 29 (ca. 1897-1908) and
                    Damascus 3/18 (likely ca. 1907-1917) were copied.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"> There is a very small chance
                            that Qaṣīr copied a more complete version of CFMM 158, and that the
                            codex lost pages from the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> only
                            after that copy was finished, before Rahmani made his own edition (ca.
                            1904). Unfortunately, due to the COVID-19 pandemic, I was unable to
                            consult Ming. Syr. 29 prior to the publication of this
                        article.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Barsoum says the last “modern” copy is “in the possession of
                    Professor Margoliouth at Oxford, which we gifted to him in 1913.” Barsoum was
                    still a monk at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān in 1913, but it was before he mentioned the
                    “two rare copies” in <hi rend="italic">Nuzhat al-Adhhān</hi>, so this manuscript
                    is probably not one of those two. It seems most likely that Barsoum and the
                    other monks made a new copy of the book of letters to give to the visiting
                    Oxford professor David Samuel Margoliouth. However, from there the manuscript
                    has vanished, and Margoliouth might not have actually received it. Margoliouth
                    did have a small personal collection of Syriac manuscripts, and he bequeathed
                    this collection to Oxford’s Ashmolean Museum upon his death in 1940.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"> Three years
                            before Barsoum finished <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, so
                            it seems the two were not in touch during the late 1930s. See A.F.L.
                            Beeston, “Margoliouth, David Samuel (1858–1940), Orientalist,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography (Electronic
                                Version)</hi> (Oxford University Press, 2006),
                            https://www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-34874.</p></note>
                    The Ashmolean transferred this bequest to the Bodleian Library in 1959, where it
                    now forms part of a miscellaneous collection of Semitic manuscripts.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text"> Susan Thomas,
                            “Miscellaneous Syriac Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library,” Archives
                            Hub, accessed May 1, 2020,
                            https://archiveshub.jisc.ac.uk/search/archives/92baddd3-3c51-3c56-9070-1721bfe786cc.
                            Sebastian Brock produced a partial handlist of the “Margoliouth” portion
                            of this collection; see Sebastian P. Brock, “Margoliouth Collection of
                            Syriac Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, Oxford: A Handlist”
                            (Unpublished), accessed April 27, 2020,
                            https://libguides.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/ld.php?content_id=17931955. I am
                            grateful to Prof. Brock for helping me access the card catalogue of this
                            collection and for sharing his thoughts on Barsoum’s gift to
                            Margoliouth.</p></note> There is no trace of Dawid’s letters in this
                    collection, so it seems Margoliouth did not have a copy in 1940.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Dam. 3/18 is thus the most likely candidate to be the second “rare
                    copy,” especially if Barsoum took it with him to Ḥimṣ in 1918, since he seems to
                    be aware that only one copy (i.e. CFMM 158) remained at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān in
                    1943. If this assumption is incorrect, then the second manuscript that was in
                    Dayr al-Zaʿfarān in 1917 seems to be lost. In any case, all of these versions
                    were copied from CFMM 158 after the middle pages of the <hi rend="italic">Letter
                        on Dots</hi> were lost.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Fig. 1: Stemma of manuscripts of the </hi><hi
                        rend="italic bold">Letter on Dots</hi><hi rend="bold">.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text"> Aaron Butts
                            produced a similar diagram in Butts, “A Syriac Dialogue Poem,”
                        465.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">
                    <graphic
                        url="https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/resources/images/articles/HV24N1Posegay_image1.jpg"
                    />
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2 The <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> as a Historical Source</head>
                <p rend="H Normal First">The <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> has drawn
                    interest for the history of the East Syriac <hi rend="italic">mašlmānuṯā</hi>
                    and the development of the Syriac diacritic points, as it seems to describe a
                    particular reading tradition and the invention of some dots which appear in
                    Eastern manuscripts. Indeed, if Dawid bar Pawlos’ account in the letter is true,
                    then it is one of the closest extant witnesses to the introduction of the Syriac
                    vowel points. It is also the only known source that describes the biographies of
                    the family of Beṯ Rabban, including the Miaphysite teacher Rabban Saḇroy and his
                    son Rāmišoʿ. This son seems to be the same Rāmišoʿ named as a master of pointing
                    in the famous ninth-century manuscript of the Eastern <hi rend="italic"
                        >mašlmānuṯā</hi>, MS BL Add. 12138.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This detail is at odds with Dawid bar Pawlos’ status as a
                    Miaphysite monk, as it implies that a family of West Syrians directly influenced
                    the Eastern reading tradition. This fact has provoked some robust reactions,
                    leading some scholars to reject the <hi rend="italic">Letter</hi> as a reliable
                    source. As Arthur Vööbus writes:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>In a question as important as the origin of the East Syrian
                        Massorah, we are not prepared to fall into the arms of Dawid bar Paulos. It
                        is adventurous on the basis of his story alone to draw conclusions which are
                        so far-reaching. The proposition that other traditions in connection with
                        the work on the system of the accents and its systematic development are
                        undone by the story of Dawid is hardly probable, or even possible. One who
                        is aware of the rift between the separated confessions and of its
                        implications is rather cautious. The story is too splendid and too
                        talkative. And if, indeed, it has no inferior motivation and is based on
                        some historical facts, it may then enlighten some local phenomenon.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"> Vööbus, <hi
                                    rend="italic">History of the School</hi>,
                        202.</p></note></quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">He is right; it would indeed be too “far-reaching” to suggest that
                    this letter upsets the traditional history of the Eastern <hi rend="italic"
                        >mašlmānutā</hi> that stretches back to the School of Nisibis.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"> Jonathan
                            Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian Manuscript of the Syriac
                                “Masora” Dated to 899 CE: Introduction, List of Sample Texts, and
                                Indices to Marginal Notes in British Library, Additional MS
                                12138</hi>, vol. II (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015), VIII; Vööbus,
                                <hi rend="italic">History of the School</hi>, 196–200.</p></note>
                    However, nowhere in the letter does Dawid claim that his story is about that
                    tradition. Instead, it seems that Beṯ Rabban’s primary contributions to Syriac
                    were a variant reading tradition and some of the vocalisation points shared by
                    both East and West Syrians before the tenth century.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> For the chronology of the
                            vowel points, see J.F. Coakley, “When Were the Five Greek Vowel-Signs
                            Introduced into Syriac Writing?,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic
                                Studies</hi> 56, no. 2 (September 1, 2011): 307–17; George A. Kiraz,
                                <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā: A Grammar of the Syriac
                                Language</hi>, vol. I (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2012), 16,
                        79.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The following section evaluates the <hi rend="italic">Letter on
                        Dots </hi>to determine to what extent its claims about people, places, and
                    events may be considered plausible in the context of seventh-century northern
                    Mesopotamia. The events in Dawid’s story of Beṯ Rabban do not appear in
                    chronological order, so this discussion addresses some of the later passages
                    whenever they illuminate earlier parts of the letter. Dawid begins after the
                    introductory greetings by describing Beṯ Rabban’s history (§2.1). He then
                    recounts an anecdote from the family’s time at Mar Mattai Monastery (§2.2),
                    before flashing back to the time when Saḇroy and his sons supposedly invented
                    their vowel points (§2.3). The multi-page lacuna occurs after that, but the text
                    resumes with an account of some works written by the family, and concludes by
                    commenting on the purpose of their vowel points.</p>
                <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.2.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>2.1 The Family History of Beṯ Rabban</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots </hi>begins with an
                        address and subject heading: “From Dawid bar Pawlos to the Bishop Yoḥannān;
                        regarding dots, that is, <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmē</hi>, which are in the
                        holy books, and a look at those who made them.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 44, line 12–16; Rahmani, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line 1–3.</p></note>
                        Dawid corresponds with this Yoḥannān in other letters, and he seems to be
                        the one who requested that Dawid copy all of his letters into a single
                            book.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 328; Moosa,
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 375–76.</p></note>
                        He may also be the Bishop Yoḥannān from the Khanušiyā monastery on Mount
                            Sinjar,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 510; Moosa,
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 565.</p></note>
                        where Dawid studied Greek before he became the abbot of Mar Sergius
                            monastery.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Mar Sergius is on the Dry Mountain (<hi
                                    rend="italic">al-jabal al-qāḥil</hi>) of Sinjar, located above
                                Bālāḏ (modern Eski Mosul); Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Syriaca</hi>, 67, n. 3; Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                    al-Manthūr</hi>, 325–26, 515; Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The
                                    Scattered Pearls</hi>, 375–76, 566; Baumstark, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Geschichte</hi>, 272; Sebastian P. Brock, “Dawid Bar Pawlos,”
                                in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho),
                                accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dawid-bar-Pawlos.</p></note> Dawid
                        continues with a long list of greetings,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                            n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Egroteh</hi>, 44, line 17–45, line 1-9. Rahmani only transcribes
                                one line of this section; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line 4.</p></note> and then addresses a
                        question that Yoḥannān asked him: </p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>So then, holy one, you have asked: to what end is this
                            labour, and the burdening of these dots, which surely is not the chief
                            of recollection? This was well revealed, O holy one, and well-known
                            among the long-lived elders of our region. But now, my lord, as you say,
                            those tales in their generations have departed. The story has been
                            extinguished among current children, but I – who am proud of their
                            books, the ones which they made with their writings and their signatures
                            – have kept their tale. I will tell you the whole story in this
                                letter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                                    45, line 10–18; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                                    ܡܗ, line 5–10.</p></note>
                        </quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Yoḥannān is concerned with the Syriac dots, which cause him
                        more confusion than clarity. Dawid suggests that the story of the dots was
                        once well-known, but only among the oldest elders in his community. These
                        elders would have lived in either Beṯ Šehāq on the Nineveh plain, where
                        Dawid was born, or around the Sinjar mountains, where Dawid spent his
                        monastic life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Brock, “Dawid Bar Pawlos.”</p></note> They are
                        also his first hint at a timeline for these events. The oldest elders were
                        probably around two generations older than Dawid, and they were the last who
                        knew the story.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid’s tale then begins in earnest:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>Rabban Saḇroy is the root – that is, of the tree, and
                            the chain, and the Abrahamic loin; that one from which there was a
                            series of masters which was well-known, proud of the books and
                                tales.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                                    45, line 21–46, line 2; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                        Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line 11–13.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Saḇroy – a Miaphysite teacher – is the root of a family tree
                        that constitutes a long chain of Syriac masters, and “Beṯ Rabban” in this
                        letter refers back to him. Barsoum remarks that Saḇroy “was alive around
                        630, and in the middle of the seventh century,”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 287; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 329.</p></note> but it
                        is not clear where he got this date. The only source that he references for
                        Saḇroy’s biography is the <hi rend="italic">Letter of Dots
                        </hi>(specifically in CFMM 158 and Dam. 3/18),<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 287, n. 2; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 330, n. 1.</p></note>
                        and nowhere in the letter does the number 630 appear.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Still, Dawid sets Saḇroy’s life in the seventh century, during
                        which time:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>He went up from Beṯ Ramaṯšir, a village that is near
                            your [Yoḥannān’s] village, to Beṯ Šehāq, a village in Nineveh, where he
                            founded a great school from which there were many masters.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 46, line 2–6; Rahmani,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line
                                13–15.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Neither village can be located with certainty. Beṯ Šehāq is in
                        the Nineveh plain likely near Mar Mattai monastery, which is about 35 km
                        northeast of Mosul,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> George A. Kiraz, “Matay, Dayro d-Mor,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho),
                                accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Matay-Dayro-d-Mor. “Bȇt(h) Šàhàn” in
                                Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi>, 245.</p></note> but
                        Dawid gives no more specific details. J.M. Fiey suggests it might be
                        identified with the modern village of Bāʿšiqa, 21 km northeast of Mosul, but
                        this connection is uncertain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> J.M. Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Assyrie
                                    chrétienne, contribution á l’étude de l’histoire et de la
                                    géographie ecclésiastiques et monastiques du nord de
                                l’Iraq</hi>, vol. II, Recherches publiées sous la direction de
                                l’institut de lettres orientales de Beyrouth 23 (Beirut: Imprimerie
                                Catholique, 1966), 461–63.</p></note> If Yoḥannān was indeed the
                        bishop from Khanušiyā, then Beṯ Ramaṯšir is probably in the Sinjar region;
                        Rahmani suggests it is in “Assyria,” and Fiey concedes that it has not been
                            located.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text"
                                > Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, 68; Fiey, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne</hi>, 1966, II:463.</p></note>
                        This letter is Barsoum’s only source on Saḇroy, for whom he paraphrases
                        Dawid, stating: “He founded, in the village of Bayt Šāhāq in the region of
                        Nineveh, a school for the teaching of correct Syriac language.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 287; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 330.</p></note>
                        Baumstark’s information on Saḇroy is similarly thin, as he relies entirely
                        on Rahmani’s edition and subsequent discussion of the letter.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text"> Baumstark,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi>, 245, n. 8; Rahmani, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, 67–69.</p></note> There is no
                        other source that can confirm Saḇroy’s emigration from Beṯ Ramaṯšir.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid does, however, give details about Saḇroy’s arrival in Beṯ
                        Šehāq:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>And with him were his two sons, Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel,
                            who were named in the monastery of the holy Mar Mattai, and who also
                            have a record in many books, upon which is inscribed: “Rāmišoʿ collated
                            and corrected;” and likewise for Gabriel.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 46, line 6–10; Rahmani, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line
                                15–17.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">When he left Beṯ Ramaṯšir, Saḇroy must have already mastered
                        Syriac to a level that was sufficient for him to found a school, and he
                        already had two grown sons. We may estimate that he was no younger than 40,
                        and possibly much older. Like Saḇroy, this letter is the only source that we
                        have for Gabriel, and Dawid is short on details about him. After this brief
                        introduction, he does not appear again in the extant text, whereas his
                        brother Rāmišoʿ features prominently. Apparently they were both monks at Mar
                        Mattai, and Dawid implies that he saw evidence of their presence there,
                        including colophons from books that they copied.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid’s claim that Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel “collated and corrected”
                            (<hi rend="italic">paḥḥem wa-tarreṣ</hi>) at Mar Mattai indicates a
                        specific scribal activity known elsewhere in the seventh century. The verb
                            <hi rend="italic">paḥḥem</hi> literally means “to compare,” and in the
                        context of writing, it can mean “to punctuate” – that is, “to add points.”
                        For a copyist, it also means “to collate,” as in “to compare a copy with its
                        source manuscript.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> “Pḥm,” in <hi rend="italic">The Comprehensive
                                    Aramaic Lexicon</hi> (Cincinnati: Hebrew Union College: Jewish
                                Institute of Religion), accessed June 19, 2020,
                                http://cal.huc.edu/oneentry.php?lemma=pxm%20V&amp;cits=all; Georgius
                                Hoffmann, <hi rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi> (Paris, 1880),
                                VII.</p></note> In this sense, <hi rend="italic">paḥḥem
                            wa-tarreṣ</hi> is a sort of hendiadys: “he compared in order to
                        correct,” describing the last step of checking copies against their original
                        manuscripts. Jacob of Edessa, Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel’s contemporary, attests to
                        similar “collation and correction” in his <hi rend="italic">Letter to George
                            of Sarug</hi>:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>As for those points which are bound in the
                            aforementioned volume, most of which I have personally collated and
                            bound . . . leave them in it, just as they are. Do not erase a single
                            one of them, so that a copy is written as it is, and thus a copyist sees
                            those which are bound and those which replaced them.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"> George Phillips, ed.,
                                        <hi rend="italic">A Letter By Mār Jacob, Bishop of Edessa,
                                        on Syriac Orthography: Also a Tract by the Same Author, and
                                        a Discourse by Gregory Bar Hebræus on Syriac Accents.</hi>
                                    (London; Edinburgh: Williams and Norgate, 1869), ܝܒ, line
                                    10–18.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">For Jacob, “collated and bound” (<hi rend="italic">paḥmeṯ
                            wa-seṭmeṯ</hi>) is the typical act of checking a manuscript for mistaken
                        dots and then “binding” them with a circle.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80"
                            n="80"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., 11, n. M.</p></note> As such,
                        Dawid does not highlight Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel’s own collation work as an
                        innovative process, and he does not point to it as the resolution of
                        Yoḥannān’s inquiry about the dots.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">While no other sources describe Beṯ Saḇroy’s movements, the
                        late sixth and seventh centuries did see East Syrian Diophysites founding
                        many schools in northern Iraq. As Jack Tannous has pointed out, this move
                        prompted a commensurate surge in new schools founded by “zealous
                        Miaphysites,” and he notes that Saḇroy’s school at Beṯ Šehāq fits well with
                        this phenomenon.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Jack Tannous, <hi rend="italic">The Making of
                                    the Medieval Middle East: Religion, Society, and Simple
                                    Believers</hi> (Princeton; Oxford: Princeton University Press,
                                2018), 167–68.</p></note> In fact, Dawid explains Saḇroy’s
                        motivations in this way near the end of the letter:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>Beṯ ʿEḏrī was great like Beṯ Lapaṭ, and because of
                            this, that modest one shook with zeal. He took his sons, left the
                            village, and went up to Nineveh. He gathered 318 men for a school, and
                            he set his son over them as a leader.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82"
                                n="82"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 48, line 8–13; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 22–24. Rahmani indicates that
                                    one word cannot be read here, but the faint word <hi
                                        rend="italic">dukos</hi> (‘leader’), which he transcribes,
                                    fills the whole space in CFMM 158 (f. 41r, line 6); Ibid., ܡܘ,
                                    n. 2.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Beṯ ʿEḏrī is the location of Rabban Hormizd Monastery, near
                        Alqoš “nine hours north of Mosul.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Addai Scher, “Notice sur les manuscrits
                                syriaques conservés dans la bibliothèque du couvent des chaldéens de
                                notre-name-des-semences,” <hi rend="italic">Journal asiatique</hi>
                                VII, no. 1 (1906): 479.</p></note> It is only 45-50 km from Mar
                        Mattai, and presumably a similar distance from Beṯ Šehāq. It is now a
                        Chaldean site, but the Diophysite Rabban Hormizd (from Beṯ Lapaṭ) founded it
                        in the late sixth or seventh century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84"
                            n="84"><p rend="footnote text"> Heleen L. Murre-van den Berg, “Hormizd,
                                Monastery of Rabban,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                                    Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed May 11, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hormizd-Monastery-of-Rabban.</p></note>
                        The monks of Mar Mattai even feature prominently in the medieval history of
                        Rabban Hormizd, where they are his monastery’s principle antagonists.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text"> See E.A.W.
                                Budge, <hi rend="italic">The Histories of Rabban Hôrmȋzd the Persian
                                    and Rabban Bar-‘Idtâ: The Syriac Texts Edited with English
                                    Translations</hi>, vol. II, Luzac’s Semitic Text and Translation
                                Series 10 (London: Luzac and Co., 1902), IX–XXI, esp.
                            XVI–XIX.</p></note> Meanwhile, Beṯ Lapaṭ, also called Gundešapur, is
                        well-known as a centre for East Syriac intellectual activity in the seventh
                            century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text"
                                > Nabia Abbott, “Jundī-Shāpūr: A Preliminary Historical Sketch,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Ars Orientalis</hi> 7 (1968): 72; Becker, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fear of God</hi>, 94–95; Sebastian P. Brock, “Beth
                                Lapaṭ,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth
                                Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Beth-Lapat.</p></note> Dawid’s
                        explanation that the success of these Eastern institutions pushed Saḇroy to
                        start his own school is thus believable within the known trends of
                        seventh-century Miaphysite school-founding.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">There is another relevant source that supports the existence of
                        a Syriac school at Beṯ Šehāq, as well as Dawid’s presence there.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text"> See Rahmani,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, 67.</p></note> In a
                        biography of the Miaphysite bishop Muše bar Kip̄o (813/833-903),<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text"> Extracts and
                                Latin translations published in Giuseppe Simone Assemani, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Bibliotheca Orientalis</hi>, vol. II (Rome:
                                Scriptoribus Syris Nestorianis, 1721), 218, n. 1. Full German
                                translation and commentary in Jobst Reller, <hi rend="italic">Mose
                                    bar Kepha und seine Paulinenauslegung: nebst Edition und
                                    Übersetzung des Kommentars zum Römerbrief</hi>, Göttinger
                                Orientforschungen (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1994). See Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 350–55; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 398–404.</p></note> the
                        anonymous author writes:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>He was born and grew up in the city of Bālāḏ. His
                            father’s name was Šemʿon, his mother’s name was Maryam, and he was
                            called Muše bar Kip̄o. Muše was the name of his ancestor, who was a
                            teacher in the great church of Beṯ Šāhāq, the master of Dawid of Beṯ
                                Rabban.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Assemani, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca
                                        Orientalis</hi>, 1721, II:218, n.1, line
                            33–39.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Bālāḏ is the closest town to Mar Sergius monastery, which Bar
                        Kip̄o joined as a monk in the middle of the ninth century.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text"> J.F. Coakley, “Mushe Bar
                                Kipho,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth
                                Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mushe-bar-Kipho; Sebastian P. Brock,
                                    <hi rend="italic">A Brief Outline of Syriac Literature</hi>,
                                Mōrān ’Eth’ō 9 (Kerala: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute,
                                1997), 69.</p></note> Bālāḏ was also his mother’s hometown,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text"> Assemani,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Orientalis</hi>, 1721, II:218,
                                n.1, line 33.</p></note> and Dawid was likely still the abbot of Mar
                        Sergius when she was young. While the biographer does not mention Saḇroy or
                        any other members of Beṯ Rabban, this passage suggests that there was a
                        Miaphysite school in Beṯ Šehāq known as the “great church,” and it had
                        active teachers in the middle of the eighth century.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid tells us that Saḇroy’s school had 318 members, which
                        Barsoum interprets to mean it “included more than 300 students.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 287; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 330.</p></note>
                        However, this number seems somewhat mythologised. As Dawid elaborates, 318
                        is also the number of men that fought with Abraham against the kings in
                        Genesis 14:13-17, and it is a traditional number of bishops at the Council
                        of Nicaea.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 48, line 13–14; Rahmani,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 25-ܡܙ, line
                                1.</p></note> He does not specify which son Saḇroy put in charge of
                        this group, but it is safe to assume it was Rāmišoʿ, the main star of the
                        letter. Dawid then reports:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>He wrote two books of questions and answers against
                            them, as well as three treatises which he wrote regarding 60 questions
                            which had been brought to him from one blind teacher of theirs. I think
                            these writings are in the monastery of Mar Mari, because there their
                            heart was bound.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                                    48, line 15–19; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                                    ܡܙ, line 1–3.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The “he” in this passage is ambiguous as to whether it was
                        Saḇroy or his appointed son who wrote these polemical works. The “them” is
                        more clear – whichever man wrote these books did so against the Diophysites
                        of Beṯ ʿEdri and Beṯ Lapaṭ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> See insertion “<hi rend="italic">i.e.
                                    nestorianos</hi>” in Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Syriaca</hi>, 45.</p></note> and it seems he was in contact with
                        members of those communities at the time. None of these writings are extant,
                        and Dawid only suggests that there are copies at the Mar Mari monastery.
                        This place is most likely the monastery of Dayr Qunnī, also known as the
                        “school of Mar Mari” after the famous disciple of Addai who spent the end of
                        his life there.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> J.M. Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Assyrie
                                    chrétienne, contribution á l’étude de l’histoire et de la
                                    géographie ecclésiastiques et monastiques du nord de
                                l’Iraq</hi>, vol. I, Recherches publiées sous la direction de
                                l’institut de lettres orientales de Beyrouth 22 (Beirut: Imprimerie
                                Catholique, 1965), 17; Sebastian P. Brock, “Mari, Acts Of,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho),
                                accessed May 12, 2020, https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Mari-Acts-of;
                                Becker, <hi rend="italic">Fear of God</hi>, 162; Adalbert Merx, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Historia Artis Grammaticae Apud Syros</hi>
                                (Leipzig, 1889), 125.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid continues the family history of Beṯ Rabban:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>Rāmišoʿ fathered a son, Saḇrišoʿ, while he was living
                            the way of the monks in the monastery. He toiled in many books, and his
                            name was also inscribed in those books which he wisely corrected. He
                            made an effort to the end, as was his way, but because he was moved by
                            his praise, he did not stay in Nineveh. He set off for Niram of the
                            free, which is in Margā, left his middle sister behind, and entered the
                            village of Murdani.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                                    46, line 10–16; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                                    ܡܗ, line 17–21.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Barsoum takes all of his information about Saḇrišoʿ from this
                        part of the letter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                    al-Manthūr</hi>, 313; Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered
                                    Pearls</hi>, 358.</p></note> He apparently grew up in Mar
                        Mattai, but left the monastery and went to Niram in Margā, northeast of
                        Nineveh. Thomas of Margā (d. 840) mentions two villages with this name in
                        his <hi rend="italic">Book of the Governors</hi>: Niram and Niram d-Raʿawāṯā
                        (‘Niram of the Shepherds’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> E.A.W. Budge, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Book
                                    of the Governors: The Historia Monastica of Thomas Bishop of
                                    Margå, A.D. 840</hi>, vol. I (London, 1893), 2, 592,
                            599.</p></note> The former can be identified with the village known by
                        the modern Kurdish name Gunduk, near Aqra, northeast of Mosul and west of
                        the Great Zab River. Niram d-Raʿawāṯā was a bit farther west in the district
                        of Birta.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Ran Zadok, “On Some Upper Mesopotamian Toponyms,” <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Nouvelles assyriologiques brèves et utilitaires</hi>, Notes
                                brèves, no. 3 (1998): 70; Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Assyrie
                                    chrétienne</hi>, 1965, I:224, 252–53.</p></note> Either of these
                        may be the part of Margā where Saḇrišoʿ travelled. The text specifies that
                        he entered Murdani,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> This name is unvocalised (CFMM 158, f. 38r). I
                                follow Rahmani’s transliteration; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Syriaca</hi>, 44.</p></note> but this village is more difficult
                        to locate. Dawid refers to it with the Persian loan word <hi rend="italic"
                            >rustāqā </hi>(‘village’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> J. Payne Smith, ed., <hi rend="italic">A
                                    Compendious Syriac Dictionary</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                                1903), 535.</p></note> as opposed to <hi rend="italic">qriṯā</hi>,
                        his word for every other village in the letter, which may indicate that it
                        was east of the Great Zab, closer to Iran.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid notes that Saḇrišoʿ “left his middle sister behind” when
                        he went to Margā, an odd detail given that she does not appear elsewhere in
                        the story. He may hint at how he knows about her in the next sentence: “And
                        there he [Saḇrišoʿ] was a citizen in my own village, and he was recorded in
                        the census in the time of Ḥur bar Yosep̄.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103"
                            n="103"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Egroteh</hi>, 46, line 17–18; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                    Syriaca</hi>, ܡܗ, line 21–22.</p></note> This name refers to
                        al-Ḥurr ibn Yusuf, the great nephew of Marwān I and the Umayyad governor of
                        Mosul from 727 to 731/32.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Paul G. Forand, “The Governors of Mosul
                                According to Al-Azdī’s Ta’rīkh Almawṣil,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                                    of the American Oriental Society</hi> 89, no. 1 (January 1969):
                                89–90. Due to some conflicting sources, Forand notes that al-Ḥurr’s
                                governorship in Mosul may have begun as early as 724/25. Barsoum
                                writes 725.</p></note> Barsoum mentions this fact when he
                        paraphrases Dawid’s statement, saying: “and he was recorded in the tax
                        registry in the days of al-Ḥurr ibn Yusuf, the governor of Mosul (<hi
                            rend="italic">wa-ktataba fī daftar al-kharāj ʿalā ayyām al-Ḥurr ibn
                            Yūsuf</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ʿāmil al-Mawṣil</hi>).<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 313.</p></note> He
                        directly translates the Syriac Gt-stem verb, <hi rend="italic">eṯkṯeḇ</hi>
                        (‘he was recorded’), with the equivalent Arabic Gt-stem, <hi rend="italic"
                            >iktataba</hi> (‘he was recorded’). Despite this, Moosa renders
                        Barsoum’s Arabic as: “He was employed as a clerk at the Register of Kharaj
                        in the days of al-Ḥurr ibn Joseph, the Governor of Mosul.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text"> Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 358.</p></note> This
                        translation is mistaken. All we can say is that, according to Dawid, al-Ḥurr
                        performed a census (<hi rend="italic">ksep̄ rišā</hi>, lit. ‘silver per
                        head’ for tax purposes) in which Saḇrišoʿ was recorded.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">By saying that Saḇrišoʿ was a citizen (<hi rend="italic"
                            >ʿāmurā</hi>) in “my own village,” Dawid likely means Beṯ Šehāq, his
                        birthplace. This statement seems to contradict the previous sentence about
                        Margā, but it makes sense through the lens of Umayyad census policy. Some of
                        the most important sources for Umayyad tax appraisal censuses are Syriac
                        chroniclers, who recorded three censuses in upper Mesopotamia between 692
                        and 711.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Specifically, the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of Zuqnin</hi> (ca.
                                775 CE), the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of 819</hi>, the <hi
                                    rend="italic">Chronicle of 846</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Chronicle of 1234</hi>. See Wadād al-Qādī, “Population Census
                                and Land Surveys under the Umayyads (41–132/661–750),” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Der Islam</hi> 83, no. 2 (2008):
                            366–72.</p></note> These sources indicate that as part of a census,
                        every man would “go to his region, village, and father’s house, so that
                        everyone would register his name, his lineage, his crops and olive trees,
                        his possessions, his children, and everything he owned.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., 366. Al-Qādī
                                quotes this passage from the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of
                                    Zuqnin</hi> as translated in Chase Robinson, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Empire and Elites after the Muslim Conquest</hi> (Cambridge:
                                Cambridge University Press, 2000), 45. See also, Amir Harrak,
                                “Zuqnin, Chronicle Of,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                                    Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed May 10, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Zuqnin-Chronicle-of; Brock, <hi
                                    rend="italic">A Brief Outline</hi>, 62.</p></note> They also
                        show that throughout this period, the Umayyad state was transitioning from
                        reliance on local authorities to count their own communities, to sending
                        professional officers who would count the locals on behalf of the
                        government. Moreover, by the second decade of the eighth century, provincial
                        governors were directly involved in ordering censuses.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p rend="footnote text"> al-Qādī, “Population
                                Census and Land Surveys,” 366–71.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">As governor of Mosul, al-Hurr ibn Yusuf’s administrative
                        control covered the province of al-Jazīra, which included “al-Karkh, Daqūqā,
                        Khānijār, Šahrazūr, al-Ṭirhān, . . . Takrīt, al-Sinn, Bājarmā, Qardā [<hi
                            rend="italic">sic</hi>] (or Jazīrat ibn ʿUmar), and Sinjār, to the
                        borders of Aḏarbayjān.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Forand, “The Governors of Mosul,”
                            90.</p></note> As such, his census – ordered between 727 and 732 –
                        included all of Margā, where Saḇrišoʿ apparently was at the time. If he
                        returned to the house of his father for counting, he would have been
                        recorded as a citizen of Beṯ Šehāq – just as Dawid says. Furthermore, if
                        al-Ḥurr still relied on local leaders to report census data, then the local
                        priests and the abbot of Mar Mattai may well have been the ones collecting
                        that information. If, as implied by his description of books that Rāmišoʿ
                        copied, Dawid knew the contents of Mar Mattai’s library, then it is possible
                        he had access to such census records. They would have contained information
                        on Saḇrišoʿ as well as any other of Rāmišoʿ’s children, like the middle
                        sister who stayed behind in Beṯ Šehāq. This chain of reasoning is highly
                        speculative, but it is not clear how else Dawid could have learned such
                        specific information about a census ordered by a short-reigned governor who
                        died before he was born.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">From all of this material it is possible to estimate a timeline
                        of events in the history of Beṯ Rabban. The current consensus is that Dawid
                        himself was active in the second half of the eighth century and the first
                        few decades of the ninth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Brock, “Dawid Bar Pawlos.”</p></note> This
                        range is based on a few pieces of evidence. First, Dawid corresponded with
                        Thomas the Stylite, who was still alive in 837.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 326; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 373.</p></note> Second,
                        the colophonic note at the end of the second folio of CFMM 158 (and more
                        clearly in Ming. Syr. 29) indicates that Dawid left Khanušiyā monastery with
                        a group of forty monks in the year 785.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113"
                            n="113"><p rend="footnote text"> Mingana, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Catalogue</hi>, I:79; Brock, “Dawid Bar Pawlos”; Baumstark, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Geschichte</hi>, 272.</p></note> As such, in 785
                        he must have been old enough to hold a substantial following, and he was
                        likely still alive in the early ninth century. Third, there is a metrical
                        polemic in Ming. Syr. 29, ff. 38v-42v, the end of which (f. 42v) indicates
                        the author’s current year is 770 CE.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114"
                            n="114"><p rend="footnote text"> Mingana, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Catalogue</hi>, I:80–81.</p></note> If this date is genuine,
                        then Dawid must have been old enough to compose such a work in 770. We may
                        thus estimate that Dawid bar Pawlos was born between 740 and 750. This range
                        would mean he was between 20 and 30 when he wrote the polemic, between 35
                        and 45 when he led his followers out of Khanušiyā, and he became abbot of
                        Mar Sergius sometime after that.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In the part of the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> that
                        is actually about dots (see §2.3), Dawid writes the following about his own
                        lineage:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>For when my own father entered Nineveh – that one from
                            whom I am for five generations now – and when he settled in Beṯ Šehāq,
                            according to the tale that I heard from my elders…<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 47, line 13–15; Rahmani, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line
                                11–13.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Given its context in the story, his “own father” (<hi
                            rend="italic">āḇā dil</hi>(<hi rend="italic">y</hi>)) is clearly a
                        reference to Saḇroy, and <hi rend="italic">āḇā dil</hi>(<hi rend="italic"
                            >y</hi>) must be understood as “my forefather” or “my ancestor” of five
                            generations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Loopstra describes this connection as a
                                “distant relation;” Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                                    Manuscript</hi>, II:IX, n. 46.</p></note> This statement concurs
                        with numerous medieval sources that refer to Dawid as “of Beṯ Rabban.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p rend="footnote text"> See
                                Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi>, 272, n. 4; Richard
                                Gottheil, “Dawidh Bar Paulos, a Syriac Grammarian,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi> 15
                                (1893): cxi, cxv.</p></note> In this case, the moniker indicates
                        that he is descended from Rabban Saḇroy.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Barsoum’s statements on this passage have caused some
                        confusion. Relying on the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> for his
                        entry on Saḇroy in <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ</hi>, he writes: “His
                        descendent, Rabbān Dāwud ibn Bawlūs, said regarding him [Saḇroy] in his
                        letter to the bishop Yūḥannā…” (<hi rend="italic">qāla ḥafīduhu al-rabbān
                            Dāwud ibn Bawlūs fī ḥaqqihi fī risālatihi ilā al-usquf
                            Yūḥannā</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                    al-Manthūr</hi>, 287.</p></note> Moosa’s translation makes the
                        passage ambiguous: “In a letter to the Bishop John, Saḇroy's grandson, Dawid
                        Bar Paul, had this to say about him…”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119"
                            n="119"><p rend="footnote text"> Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered
                                    Pearls</hi>, 329–30.</p></note> Besides “grandson,” the word <hi
                            rend="italic">ḥafīd</hi> can also mean “descendent,”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p rend="footnote text"> Hans Wehr, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Hans Wehr Dictionary of Modern Written
                                    Arabic</hi>, ed. J. M. Cowan, 4th ed. (Urbana: Spoken Language
                                Services, 1993), 219.</p></note> and that must be what Barsoum
                        intended here. Barsoum’s Arabic is also clear that Dawid is that descendent,
                        not Yoḥannān. Then in his entry for Dawid bar Pawlos, Barsoum says he was
                        “descended from the family of Saḇroy ibn Ibrāhīm, his ancestor” (<hi
                            rend="italic">mutaḥaddir</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">an</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">min bayt Sabrūy ibn Ibrāhīm jaddihi al-aʿlā</hi>).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum,
                                    <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 326.</p></note>
                        Moosa also translates this line ambiguously: “He was descended from Beṯ
                        Saḇroy, the son of Abraham, Dawid's great-grandfather.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="footnote text"> Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 372.</p></note> He
                        glosses <hi rend="italic">jadd aʿlā</hi> as “great-grandfather,” but it can
                        also mean “ancestor” more generally,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123"
                            n="123"><p rend="footnote text"> Wehr, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi>, 135.</p></note> and again that must be what
                        Barsoum meant. In what is, as far as I can tell, an unrelated error that may
                        have informed Moosa’s translation, Baumstark remarks that “Rabban Saḇroy of
                        Ramaṯšir became known as the ancestor in the third generation through Dawid
                        bar Pawlos” (<hi rend="italic">Rabban Sabroy aus Ramatshir wird als dessen
                            Vorfahre in der dritten Generation durch einen Dawid b Paulos
                            bekannt</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Baumstark, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi>,
                                245.</p></note> Baumstark cites only Rahmani’s edition of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Letter of Dots </hi>to support this claim,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p rend="footnote text"> He also
                                cites Nöldeke’s review of <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca </hi>and
                                the sixth chapter of Duval’s <hi rend="italic">La littérature
                                    syriaque</hi>, but neither comments on the number of generations
                                between Saḇroy and Dawid; Nöldeke, “Bibliographische Anzeigen:
                                Studia Syriaca,” 495; Rubens Duval, <hi rend="italic">La littérature
                                    syriaque</hi>, 3rd ed., vol. II (Paris: Librairie Victor
                                Lecoffre, 1907), 56.</p></note> but again, in the letter Dawid
                        claims to be a fifth generation descendent of Saḇroy.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid seems to be on a separate branch of the family tree, not
                        descended through Ramishoʿ and Saḇrišoʿ, but if we take him at his word
                        here, we can estimate a timeline for the letter. Assuming 25-30 years
                        between generations, then Dawid’s father, Pawlos, was born ca. 720-725. One
                        generation before Pawlos would be the same generation as Saḇrišoʿ and his
                        sister, born ca. 690-700. Before them, Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel would have been
                        born ca. 660-675, and their father, Rabban Saḇroy, would have been born ca.
                        630-650. Taking our earlier assumption into account, if Saḇroy was at least
                        40 when he founded his school, the earliest he would have done so is ca.
                        670-690. Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel were probably young adults at the time, and
                        Saḇrišoʿ was born soon after that. He then grew up at Mar Mattai, moved to
                        Margā, and was recorded in the census of al-Ḥurr ibn Yūsuf between 727 and
                        732. He may have been in his late twenties then, and no older than his
                        forties. Finally, if the local elders who told Dawid this story were in fact
                        two generations older than him, then they would have grown up in Beṯ Šehāq
                        at roughly the same time as Saḇrišoʿ.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.2.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>2.2 An Anecdote from Mar Mattai Monastery</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid proceeds with several achievements in the lives of Beṯ
                        Rabban. After mentioning al-Ḥurr’s census, the letter picks up again with an
                        anecdote from Rāmišoʿ’s time at Mar Mattai:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>In the days when Beṯ Rāmišoʿ was in the monastery . . .
                            When the head monk saw that they were more eloquent speakers than the
                            people of their time, he gave them each a cell in the monastery. The two
                            of them each took a single book without any dots of relation or
                            correction, then each one entered a cell and added dots. When the pair’s
                            correction was done, there was no difference from one to the other, and
                            thus they did for many books.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126"
                                    ><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 46, line 19 and 46 line 22 - 47, line 7;
                                    Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 1 and
                                    line 3-7. Barsoum paraphrases this entire passage; see Barsoum,
                                        <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 313; Moosa, <hi
                                        rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>,
                            359.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The “Beṯ Rāmišoʿ” in this passage (notably not “Beṯ Rabban” or
                        “Beṯ Saḇroy”) must be Rāmišoʿ and Saḇrišoʿ,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn127" n="127"><p rend="footnote text"> Rahmani interprets this
                                line as “when the sons of Rāmišoʿ were in the monastery” (<hi
                                    rend="italic">tempore quo Ramjesu filii errant in
                                coenobio</hi>), even though only one son of Rāmišoʿ appears in the
                                story. Perhaps he also counted Saḇrišoʿ’s sister as “offspring of
                                Rāmišoʿ.” See Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, 44.
                                Meanwhile, Barsoum paraphrases Dawid and interprets “Beṯ Rāmišoʿ” as
                                Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel, saying, “when the two masters of language,
                                Rāmišoʿ and Gabriel, arrived at the monastery of Mar Mattai…;”
                                Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 313; Moosa,
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 359. It is more
                                plausible to me that “the house of Rāmišoʿ” designates Rāmišoʿ and
                                his son, rather than his brother.</p></note> whom the head of Mar
                        Mattai recognised as the most eloquent Syriac reciters at the monastery. He
                        sent each of them to a cell with a book (presumably a bible) that did not
                        have “any dots of relation or correction” (<hi rend="italic">nuqzē meddem
                            d-puḥḥāmā aw d-turrāṣā</hi>), whereupon they engaged in “adding dots”
                            (<hi rend="italic">mp̄aḥḥem</hi>).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">But what exactly did Rāmišoʿ and Saḇrišoʿ do to these codices?
                        J.B. Segal highlights the importance of the word <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā
                        </hi>(lit. “relationship” or “comparison”) in the history of Syriac
                        philology. He explains: “The name <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>is
                        significant; the accents, like the diacritical point which is also given
                        this name, are intended to classify or collate related linguistic
                            phenomena.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                    Point</hi>, 59, 172.</p></note> It is easy to see how the idea
                        of “collation” as comparing dots between two copies of a manuscript – like
                        we saw with Jacob of Edessa – could lead to Syriac scribes broadly
                        associating “comparison” with dotted markers. Thus, as Georgius Hoffman
                        already observed in 1880, <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>may refer to nearly
                        all types of points, including vowels and accent dots.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn129" n="129"><p rend="footnote text"> Hoffmann, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi>, VII.</p></note> The
                        medieval Syriac-Arabic lexica of ʿIsho bar ʿAlī and Ḥasan bar Bahlul both
                        demonstrate this mix of categories, identifying <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā
                        </hi>with vowels, accents, diacritics, and even Arabic inflectional
                            endings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Richard Gottheil, <hi rend="italic">Bar ʿAli
                                    (Ishoʿ): The Syriac-Arabic Glosses</hi>, vol. II (pe-taw),
                                Classe Di Scienze Morali, Storiche et Filologiche Ser. 5 13 (Rome:
                                Atti della R. Accademia dei Lincei, 1928), 246, line 6–9; Rubens
                                Duval, ed., <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum Auctore Hassano Bar
                                    Bahlule</hi> (Paris, 1901), 1502–3,
                                http://www.dukhrana.com/lexicon/BarBahlul/index.php.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Despite this variation, <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>does not
                        mean all types of dots at equal rates. In fact, Hoffman brings only a few
                        examples of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>indicating “vowel points.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p rend="footnote text"> Hoffmann,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi>, VII–VIII.</p></note>
                        Most immediately relevant to our discussion, he suggests that the short
                        explanation of the pointing system in BL Add. 12138 (ff. 309v-310r) could be
                        interpreted as referring to vowel points. It has the heading: “The sign of
                        the <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>of the books of the teachers and of
                        Rabban Rāmišoʿ,” but Jonathan Loopstra has shown that the system described
                        here relates to accent dots, not vowels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132"
                            n="132"><p rend="footnote text"> William Wright, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum</hi>,
                                vol. I (London: Gilbert and Rivington, 1870), 105b; Vööbus, <hi
                                    rend="italic">History of the School</hi>, 200; Loopstra, <hi
                                    rend="italic">An East Syrian Manuscript</hi>, II:IX,
                                XXXIV–XXXVI.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Much more often than not, the word <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmā</hi> refers to these “accent”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133"
                            n="133"><p rend="footnote text"> Also called “reading dots.” See Kiraz,
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>, 114; Jonathan Loopstra,
                                “The Syriac Reading Dot in Transmission: Consistency and Confusion,”
                                in <hi rend="italic">Studies in Biblical Philology and
                                    Lexicography</hi>, ed. Daniel King (Piscataway: Gorgias Press,
                                2019), 159–76.</p></note> dots that convey the sense and meaning of
                        a text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Hoffmann, <hi rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi>,
                            VIII.</p></note> This is the case in another annotation from BL Add.
                        12138 (f. 308v), which begins: “On the <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>of <hi
                            rend="italic">ʿelāyā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">teḥtāyā</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">zawgā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ʿeṣyānā</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">rāhṭā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mziʿānā</hi>, and all the
                            others.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>,
                                I:105a.</p></note> Additionally, the Eastern metropolitan Elias of
                        Nisibis (d. 1046) dedicates the twelfth chapter of his Syriac grammar to the
                        accents, titling it “On the dot-based types of <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmā</hi>” (<hi rend="italic">ʿal gensē nuqzānāyē
                            d-puḥḥāmā</hi>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> William Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
                                    Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum</hi>, vol. III (London:
                                Gilbert and Rivington, 1872), 1175b. Gottheil’s edition from MS
                                Sachau 5 (f. 32v) has <hi rend="italic">nuqzāyē</hi>; Richard
                                Gottheil, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on Syriac Grammar by Mâr Eliâ
                                    of Ṣóbhâ</hi> (Berlin: Peiser, 1887), ܠܓ, line 14–15. See Herman
                                G. B. Teule, “Eliya of Nisibis,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                    Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed May 10, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eliya-of-Nisibis.</p></note>
                        Similarly, the Eastern monk Yoḥannān bar Zoʿbi (ca. 1200), apparently
                        quoting Elias of Tirhan,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Compare Friedrich Baethgen, ed., <hi
                                    rend="italic">Syrische Grammatik des Elias of Tîrhân</hi>
                                (Leipzig: Hinrichs, 1880), ܠܗ, line 18–19. See also, J.F. Coakley,
                                “An Early Syriac Question Mark,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic
                                    Studies</hi> 10, no. 2 (2012): 193–213.</p></note> refers to
                        “the names of the <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>of the great dots” (<hi
                            rend="italic">šmāhayhon d-puḥḥāmā d-nuqzē rāwrḇē</hi>) for the
                            accents.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> BL Add. 25876, f. 170r; Wright, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, III:1176b.</p></note> There is
                        also an Eastern <hi rend="italic">scholion</hi> in Arabic that credits
                        Yosep̄ Huzāyā with creating nine accents, calling him <hi rend="italic"
                            >ṣāḥib al-fuḥḥām</hi> (‘the master of <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmē</hi>’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Giuseppe Simone Assemani, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Bibliotheca Orientalis</hi>, vol. III (Rome: Scriptoribus Syris
                                Nestorianis, 1725), 64b; J.P.P. Martin, <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                                    de la ponctuation ou de la Massore chez les Syriens.</hi>
                                (Paris: Impr. Nationale, 1875), 105–6. I read الفحام here as <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-fuḥḥām</hi>, either as a direct loan of <hi
                                    rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi> or as the plural form of a presumed
                                    <hi rend="italic">fāḥim</hi>, an active participial form which
                                would indicate one of the accent marks.</p></note> Segal has
                        identified several other examples, including instances where Bar Zoʿbi calls
                        the accents <hi rend="italic">nišē d-puḥḥāmā</hi> (‘signs of relation’), a
                        phrase which he shares with Bar Hebraeus (d. 1286). Likewise, both Bar Šakko
                        and the Išoʿyahḇ bar Malkon (ca. 1200) call the accents <hi rend="italic"
                            >nuqzē d-puḥḥāmā </hi>(‘points of relation’).<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 59, nn. 2–3. See also,
                                Merx, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi>, 262–63.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">One earlier example that Hoffman mentions is a quotation that
                        has been appended to a fragmentary grammatical work by Dawid bar Pawlos
                            himself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Published by Gottheil, “Dawidh Bar Paulos, a
                                Syriac Grammarian.”</p></note> This text reads: “Ḥunayn said that
                        Galen said, regarding the points which the Syrians call <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmē</hi>: when they are placed in difficult books, their readers do
                        not need a guide and an interpreter.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142"
                            n="142"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibid., cxviii, line 10–12. Segal takes
                                this passage as a genuine eighth-century statement from Dawid bar
                                Pawlos, but Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq was not born until 809. If Dawid is
                                really the author, then he must have been at least 80 years old when
                                he wrote it. See Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                Point</hi>, 61.</p></note> Hoffman argues correctly that this
                        passage implies an understanding of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmē</hi> as accent
                        dots based on a relationship with Greek prosody.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn143" n="143"><p rend="footnote text"> Hoffmann, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi>, VIII–VIV.</p></note> The
                        “Ḥunayn” here is Ḥunayn ibn Isḥāq (d. 873), the famous Christian physician
                        who translated most of Galen’s works into Arabic.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn144" n="144"><p rend="footnote text"> Aaron M. Butts, “Ḥunayn
                                b. Isḥāq,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth
                                Mardutho), accessed May 15, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Hunayn-b-Ishaq.</p></note> This
                        particular quote refers to a passage in Ḥunayn’s grammar of Classical
                        Arabic, <hi rend="italic">Kitāb Aḥkām al-Iʿrāb ʿalā Madhhab
                            al-Yūnāniyyīn</hi> (<hi rend="italic">The Book of the Rules of
                            Inflection According to the System of the Greeks</hi>),<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145"><p rend="footnote text"> Nadia
                                Vidro recently recovered the extant portions of this book from a
                                Judaeo-Arabic manuscript in the Cairo Genizah. See Nadia Vidro, “A
                                Book on Arabic Inflexion According to the System of the Greeks: A
                                Lost Work by Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift Für
                                    Arabische Linguistik</hi> 72, no. 2 (2020): 26–58. I am
                                extremely grateful to Dr. Vidro for providing me with a pre-print
                                version of this article.</p></note> which reads:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>The benefit and establishment of pointing is very
                            significant for this chapter, such that Galen says: when the signs of
                            those units were set, i.e. three dots which the Greeks knew, [. . .]
                            them in obscure books which were difficult to understand and comprehend.
                            This is because they guide one the right way, and indicate the meanings
                            of speech, all while holding one back, preventing one from moving away
                            to something different from what the author of the speech intended.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146"><p rend="footnote text"> My
                                    translation from Vidro’s edition of MS New York, JTS ENA
                                    3173.1v, line 3-10, but reliant on her own translation and
                                    discussion; Ibid., 31, 37, 50–51.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ḥunayn’s statement that these dots remove the need for an
                        “interpreter” (<hi rend="italic">mp̄ašqānā</hi>)<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p rend="footnote text"> On this role in the
                                Eastern school system, see Becker, <hi rend="italic">Fear of
                                    God</hi>, 71.</p></note> again indicates that they were related
                        to meaning, not vocalisation. Even earlier than Ḥunayn is Thomas of Margā
                        (d. 840), Dawid’s younger contemporary, who calls the accents <hi
                            rend="italic">nišay puḥḥāmā</hi> (‘signs of <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmā</hi>’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Budge, <hi rend="italic">The Book of the
                                    Governors</hi>, I:142, line 6; “Nyš, Nyš<hi rend="superscript"
                                    >ʔ</hi>,” in <hi rend="italic">The Comprehensive Aramaic
                                    Lexicon</hi> (Cincinnati: Hebrew Union College: Jewish Institute
                                of Religion), accessed June 14, 2020,
                                http://cal.huc.edu/oneentry.php?lemma=ny%24%20N&amp;cits=all.</p></note>
                        It is thus highly likely that Dawid’s phrase <hi rend="italic">nuqzē
                            d-puḥḥāmā</hi> also refers to accent dots in the work of Rāmišoʿ and
                        Saḇrišoʿ.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">However, what is remarkable for Dawid is not that Rāmišoʿ and
                        Saḇrišoʿ use dots of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>to record their
                        recitation, but rather that their recitation is exceptionally eloquent. They
                        could convey that eloquence by adding accent dots to an entire book without
                        errors, which allowed other people to repeat their recitation tradition.
                        Dawid thus lists where that tradition spread:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>Many people knew of their tradition in their time, as
                            well as after them: Išoʿ Saḇran Rabban, Aṯanasius of Kuḵta, Severus bar
                            Zaddiqā, Elias Ardāyā, Ep̄rem the Monk, and many others imitated those
                            of Beṯ Rabban. They also corrected according to their [Beṯ Rabban’s] <hi
                                rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149"
                                n="149"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 47, line 7–12; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 8–10.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Beṯ Rabban’s “tradition” (<hi rend="italic">mašlmānutā</hi>)
                        spread to communities outside of Mar Mattai, who corrected their own books
                        according to the accent dots that conveyed Rāmišoʿ’s eloquent reading. This
                        reading may have been particularly authoritative – perhaps buoyed by
                        Saḇroy’s school – but without more information, there is not much to be said
                        about the people named here.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> I have been unable to identify any of them for
                                certain. Compare with Fiey’s biographical index and Chabot’s <hi
                                    rend="italic">Livre de la chasteté</hi>; Fiey, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Assyrie chrétienne</hi>, 1966, II:829–58; J.B. Chabot, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Livre de la chasteté par Jésusdenah, évéque de
                                    Baçrah</hi>, Extrait des mélanges d’archéologie et d’histoire
                                publiés par l’ecole française de Rome, 16 (Rome, 1896).</p></note>
                        However, while Aṯanasius of Kuḵta is unknown, Kuḵta itself is not. Taking
                        note of Dawid’s reference and other descriptions in medieval histories, Fiey
                        proposes that Kuḵta corresponds to the ruined Orthodox site of Tell Dayrā on
                        the northwest side of Mount Maqlūb.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151"
                            n="151"><p rend="footnote text"> Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Assyrie
                                    chrétienne</hi>, 1966, II:774–75. In 774, n. 5, Fiey implies
                                that he has access to some portion of the <hi rend="italic">Letter
                                    on Dots</hi> in a French translation of a Syriac manuscript of
                                    <hi rend="italic">Livre de la chasteté</hi>, which was given to
                                him by Raymond-Marie Tonneau in Mosul. There is no version of the
                                letter or even a reference to Dawid bar Pawlos in J.B. Chabot’s
                                edition of that text, but it only contains 140 biographies, whereas
                                Fiey says that there are 150 in Tonneau’s version. See Fiey, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne</hi>, 1965, I:22; Chabot, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Livre de la chasteté</hi>.</p></note> Mar Mattai
                        is on the southeast side of the same mountain, so Kuḵta would be a
                        reasonable location for one of the first adopters of Rāmišoʿ’s reading
                        tradition.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The philological material at the end of Add. 12138 also
                        supports Dawid’s account that Rāmišoʿ’s reading spread beyond Mar Mattai. As
                        mentioned above, one note reads: “The sign of the <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā
                        </hi>of the books of the <hi rend="italic">maqryānē </hi>and of Rabban
                            Rāmišoʿ.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Add. MS 12138, f.309v; Wright, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, I:105b; Vööbus, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >History of the School</hi>, 200. The <hi rend="italic"
                                    >maqryānē</hi> were the reading teachers of the Eastern school
                                system; see Becker, <hi rend="italic">Fear of God</hi>, 71, 84, 125;
                                Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian Manuscript</hi>, II:VIII;
                                Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>, 62–64.</p></note> “<hi
                            rend="italic">Puḥḥāmā</hi> of the books of Rāmišoʿ” corresponds neatly
                        with the part of Beṯ Rabban’s tradition – its <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi>
                        – that Dawid claims was copied outside of Mar Mattai. Babai, the copyist of
                        Add. 12138,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>,
                                I:106a; Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian Manuscript</hi>,
                                II:VIII.</p></note> then explains the system of marks that he
                        employs to represent variant readings. This system records the base readings
                        of the Eastern <hi rend="italic">maqryānē</hi> with black ink, but
                        supplements them with red marks for Rāmišoʿ’s reading, and indicates which
                        readings are preferable.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                                    Manuscript</hi>, II:VIII–X, XXXIV–XXXVI; Gustav Diettrich, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Die Massorah der öslichen underwestlichen Syer in
                                    ihren anagaben zum propheten Jesaia nach fünf handscriften der
                                    British Museum</hi> (London; Edinburgh; Oxford: Williams and
                                Norgate, 1899), xx–xxii. See Vööbus and Segal’s translations and
                                discussions of this passage; Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of
                                    the School</hi>, 198–201; Segal, <hi rend="italic">The
                                    Diacritical Point</hi>, 78–79. See also Merx, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Historia</hi>, 29–30. A similar practice for recording multiple
                                reading traditions is found among early Qurʾān vocalisers, who
                                layered variant <hi rend="italic">qiraʾāt </hi>(‘readings’) in
                                individual manuscripts with colour-coded dots. See Yasin Dutton,
                                “Red Dots, Green Dots, Yellow Dots and Blue: Some Reflections on the
                                Vocalisation of Early Qur’anic Manuscripts (Part I),” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Journal of Qur’anic Studies</hi> 1, no. 1 (1999):
                                115–40.</p></note> Babai further notes that the books of the <hi
                            rend="italic">maqryānē</hi> are traceable to Narsai, Abraham, and
                        Yoḥannān, leaders of the School of Nisibis from the late fifth and sixth
                            centuries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>,
                                I:105b, n. ‡; Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>,
                                79; Lucas Van Rompay, “Narsai,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                    Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28,
                                2020, https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Narsai; Lucas Van Rompay,
                                “Abraham of Beth Rabban,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                                    Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/ Abraham-of-Beth-Rabban; Lucas Van
                                Rompay, “Yoḥannan of Beth Rabban,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                                    Electronic Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28,
                                2020, https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yohannan-of-Beth-Rabban. See
                                also, Vööbus, “Briefkorpus des Dawid bar Paulos,” 177–87.</p></note>
                        This situation suggests that Rāmišoʿ’s additions to the tradition of <hi
                            rend="italic">puḥḥāmā </hi>occurred after the peak period of the School
                        of Nisibis, either during or after its decline in the seventh century.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156"><p rend="footnote text"> Adam H.
                                Becker, “Nisibis, School Of,” in <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                                    Edition</hi> (Beth Mardutho), accessed April 28, 2020,
                                https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/ Nisibis-School-of; Becker, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Fear of God</hi>, 202–3; Vööbus, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >History of the School</hi>, 318–20; G.J. Reinink, “‘Edessa Grew
                                Dim and Nisibis Shone Forth’: The School of Nisibis at the
                                Transition of the Sixth-Seventh Century,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Centres of Learning: Learning and Location in Pre-Modern Europe
                                    and the Near East</hi>, Brill’s Studies in Intellectual History
                                61 (Leiden, 1995), 77–89.</p></note> Such a chronology is compatible
                        with our estimated timeline, which expects that Rāmišoʿ was active in the
                        last quarter of the seventh century.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">There is one other Rāmišoʿ connected with the School of
                        Nisibis, listed as one of the students of Mar Abā, a teacher at the School
                        who died in 552.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Assemani, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca
                                    Orientalis</hi>, 1725, III:86, n. 1; Kiraz et al., <hi
                                    rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>.</p></note> Prior
                        to Rahmani’s publication of the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi>,
                        Diettrich and Merx identified this man with the Rāmišoʿ who Babai names in
                        Add. 12138. Later scholars, like Vööbus and Loopstra, leave the question up
                        for debate.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Merx, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi>, 30;
                                Diettrich, <hi rend="italic">Die Massorah der öslichen
                                    underwestlichen Syer</hi>, xx; Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History
                                    of the School</hi>, 176, 200; Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An
                                    East Syrian Manuscript</hi>, II:IX.</p></note> However, Add.
                        12138 corresponds with Dawid’s claim that Rāmišoʿ had an authoritative
                        tradition of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi>, whereas there is no indication
                        that Abā’s student had a unique reading. If the reading of the Rāmišoʿ in
                        Add. 12138 indeed represents a later addition to the <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmā </hi>of the School of Nisibis, then he fits better with the
                        timeline indicated in the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi> than the
                        lifetime of Mar Abā’s student (d. ca. 570, according to Diettrich).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Vööbus was particularly incredulous of the possibility that the
                        reading of a Miaphysite like Rāmišoʿ could be the origin of the Eastern <hi
                            rend="italic">mašlmānuṯā</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                    School</hi>, 200–201.</p></note> but Babai is careful to note
                        where the <hi rend="italic">maqryānē</hi> and Rāmišoʿ disagree, and whose
                        reading he prefers. This practice shows that his ninth-century Eastern
                        tradition had not accepted Rāmišoʿ’s <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi>
                        wholesale, but rather critically evaluated which readings were superior.
                        Evidently, in spite of Rāmišoʿ’s miaphysitism and more than a century after
                        his death, some of his readings were still considered the most eloquent,
                        even in the Church of the East. Loopstra thus offers an alternative
                        viewpoint:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>One may suggest, however, that the situation in the
                            seventh and eighth centuries between East- and West-Syrian communities
                            may have been more permeable than Vööbus would have allowed. In fact,
                            later East-Syrian writers such as Bar Malkon and Bar Zoʿbi have clearly
                            heard of Rāmišoʿ. The later West-Syrian polymath Bar ʿEbrāyā mentions
                            Rāmišoʿ by name in his grammar, labeling him as an influential
                            ‘scholastic’ in respect to the East-Syrian accents. Bar ʿEbrāyā even
                            seems to excerpt a rule of accentuation he attributes to Rāmišoʿ . . .
                            Although our present sources do not allow us to resolve this apparent
                            discrepancy in the life of Rāmišoʿ completely, it is clear that the
                            later Syriac grammatical traditions, both East and West, perceived a
                            scribe named Rāmišoʿ as an authority on punctuation and
                                accentuation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Loopstra, <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian
                                        Manuscript</hi>, II:IX–X.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">This situation may have been especially true for
                        “West-Syrians,” like Dawid and Rāmišoʿ, who lived on the edge of East Syrian
                        territory. Even as late as the thirteenth century, Bar Šakko reports that
                        Miaphysites in these places used the “Eastern” vowel points, and West Syriac
                        writers in all regions commonly used “Eastern” vowel points until at least
                        the tenth century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                    Point</hi>, 48; Coakley, “When Were the Five Greek Vowel-Signs
                                Introduced into Syriac Writing?,” 307–17; Kiraz, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>, I:16, 79. Kiraz emphasises that such
                                vocalisation practices continue to the present day; Kiraz, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>, 106. See also, Martin, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Histoire de la ponctuation</hi>, 92.</p></note>
                        Certainly, in spite of theological differences, there was some crossover
                        between East and West Syrians in the realm of seventh- and eighth-century
                        dots. This interpretation corresponds with other accounts of intellectual
                        contact between East and West Syrians during the late antique and early
                        Islamic periods.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> E.g. see Lucas Van Rompay, “La littérature
                                exégétique syriaque et le rapprochement des traditions
                                syrienne-occidentale et syrienne-orientale,” <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Parole de l’Orient</hi> 20 (1995): 221–35; Reinink, “Edessa
                                Grew Dim,” 87–89.</p></note> The narrative in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Letter on Dots </hi>may thus be considered a further example of such
                        relationships.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.2.3" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>2.3 The Flashback and the Vowel Points</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Having addressed the eloquent tradition of <hi rend="italic"
                            >puḥḥāmā </hi>that Rāmišoʿ propagated with his son, Dawid returns to an
                        earlier achievement of Rāmišoʿ and his father. The next section of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Letter </hi>describes an event shortly after Beṯ Saḇroy’s
                        arrival in Beṯ Šehāq, where they met a group of locals who could not read
                        properly, and so “invented” vowel points to aid in their recitation. Dawid
                        begins it thus:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>But besides that, there is something that I left out.
                            For when my own father entered Nineveh – that one from whom I am for
                            five generations now – and when he settled in Beṯ Šehāq, according to
                            the tale that I heard from my elders, he found Ninevites who were
                            deprived of the fine language that binds the scripture, and [only] with
                            difficulty did they reach literacy and accurate recitation.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 47, line 12–18;
                                    Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line
                                    11–14.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">According to Dawid’s older relatives, when Saḇroy entered Beṯ
                        Šehāq, he found a group of Ninevites<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164"
                            n="164"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani reads “Ninevites” here (<hi
                                    rend="italic">ninewiyē</hi>) while Rahmani reads “students” (<hi
                                    rend="italic">yallupē</hi>), but CFMM 158 clearly has <hi
                                    rend="italic">ninewiyē</hi> (CFMM 158 f. 38v, line 5). This is
                                likely a mistake in Rahmani’s copy of the manuscript.</p></note> who
                        did not know “the fine language that binds the scripture;” that is, the
                        Syriac of the Bible. To alleviate their struggles:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>They devised that they could grasp them with some small
                            dots; so for he who distinguishes them – that is, who learns them – a
                            small dot is like a guide which is placed for correctness, and it shows
                            the eminent path without much labour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165"
                                n="165"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 47, line 18–21; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 14–16.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Interestingly, the “they” here is ambiguous, and could be the
                        group of illiterate Ninevites. More likely, it refers to Saḇroy, his sons,
                        and perhaps some of the locals in Beṯ Šehāq, who worked together to design
                        “some small dots” (<hi rend="italic">nuqzē meddem zʿorē</hi>) that guided
                        the recitation of the biblical text. These dots are distinct from the “dots
                        of comparison” that Dawid mentioned earlier. They must be vowel points,
                        which Syriac grammarians often called “small dots” and associated with an
                        easing of labour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> BL Add. 25876, ff. 155v, 276v; Segal, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 6, 27, 52–53, 62, 80;
                                Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, I:101b, n. *; Wright, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, III:1175a; Axel Moberg, “Zur
                                Terminologie,” in <hi rend="italic">Der Buch der Strahlen, die
                                    grössere Grammatik des Barhebraeus</hi>, vol. I (Leipzig: Otto
                                Harrassowitz, 1907), 66*; Merx, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi>,
                                262–63.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid then waxes poetic in celebration of Beṯ Rabban’s great
                        accomplishment:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>{On account of that, they were careful,} {{those monks
                            whom we mentioned}}.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn167" n="167"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> The text in {single brackets} is from a
                                    marginal correction inserted by the original scribe. Text in
                                    {{double brackets}} was added to that marginal correction by a
                                    later hand; CFMM 158 f. 38v, line 11. Rahmani transcribes the
                                    entire note, but Dolabani did not manage to decipher the final
                                    words of the second hand.</p></note> They sat down and made
                            milestones in the books, and with them they marked the meanings that are
                            known to the wise. They restored the obscured courses like the masters
                            in the scriptures, and they confirmed the parting of the ways, so that
                            those who continue on will have them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168"
                                n="168"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 47, line 22- 48, line 4; Rahmani, <hi
                                        rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܘ, line 16–19. Dolabani
                                    indicates that there is a short lacuna after this passage, but
                                    there is no text missing from CFMM 158.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">This passage may seem a bit hyperbolic – as Vööbus might say,
                        “too splendid and too talkative”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn169" n="169"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">History of the
                                    School</hi>, 202.</p></note> – but it is consistent with the
                        attitude of Syriac grammarians towards the vowel dots that facilitate easy
                        reading. For example, Jacob of Edessa describes the struggle of reading
                        without vowels in his <hi rend="italic">Turrāṣ Mamllā Nahrāyā</hi>:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>. . . so I say, this Edessan speech, their language
                            does not impede them, but rather this script of theirs, due to its
                            incompleteness and the insufficiency of the vowel letters in it. As I
                            said before, it is not possible to read anything properly, except from
                            these three things mentioned above: whether by divination, because of
                            the aptitude and intelligence which the reading of discourse demands,
                            whatever is set down; or by the tradition of others, those who preceded
                            them in the discourse and the readings in it, who were able to say the
                            sounds properly and pass them on to others – not from the
                            straightforwardness of the reading of the letters, for they lack that,
                            but again [only] by the tradition of others; or by much toil. . .<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn170" n="170"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    William Wright, ed., <hi rend="italic">Fragments of the Syriac
                                        Grammar of Jacob of Edessa</hi> (Clerkenwell: Gilbert and
                                    Rivington, 1871), ܒ, column a, line 9–24.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">This attitude must have contributed to Jacob’s impulse to write
                        his own letter on dots to George of Sarug,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn171"
                            n="171"><p rend="footnote text"> See Phillips, <hi rend="italic">A
                                    Letter By Mār Jacob</hi>.</p></note> as he fully believed that
                        proper pointing was critical to correct reading. Elias of Nisibis alludes to
                        Jacob’s statement again in his <hi rend="italic">Turrāṣ Mamllā
                            Suryāyā</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn172" n="172"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Gottheil, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on
                                    Syriac Grammar</hi>, ܘ, line 7–10.</p></note> and Bar Hebraeus
                        echoes the same sentiment in <hi rend="italic">Ktāḇā d-Ṣemḥē</hi>.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn173" n="173"><p rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 8.</p></note> For
                        these grammarians, the utility of the points that indicate vocalisation
                        bordered on miraculous, allowing the Syrian people to read as easily as
                        nations with more “sufficient” alphabets. Dawid is no different. For him,
                        the small points – the “milestones” of Beṯ Rabban – enabled Syriac
                        Christians to read like the masters of the Bible, without great labour or
                        need for interpreters.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Dawid then begins to explain the benefits of the dots for the
                        people who come after Saḇroy:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>Whenever a book that is corrected by them is opened, it
                            is as if they are speaking along with the one who recites, and they are
                            telling him just how it is recited, when he does not soften <hi
                                rend="italic">quššāyā</hi>, and does not harden <hi rend="italic"
                                >rukkāḵā</hi>. . . <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn174" n="174"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>,
                                    48, line 4–7; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca</hi>,
                                    ܡܘ, line 19–21.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">A person who recites from a Bible “corrected” (<hi
                            rend="italic">mṯarraṣ</hi>) with these points does so as if Beṯ Rabban
                        itself was speaking through them, and they know for certain which <hi
                            rend="italic">bgdkpt</hi> letters are pronounced fricative and which are
                            plosive.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn175" n="175"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> It seems Dawid was especially concerned with
                                the pronunciation of the <hi rend="italic">bgdkt </hi>letters, and
                                he composed a separate <hi rend="italic">scholion </hi>on the topic.
                                See MS Jerusalem, St. Mark’s Monastery, 356 ff. 164v-166r; MS
                                Mardin, Dayr al-Zaʿfarān 192, ff. 199r-200r; MS Mingana 475 ff.
                                164v-166v; Mingana, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, I:855–56, text
                                B. In all three manuscripts, Dawid’s <hi rend="italic">scholion</hi>
                                appears alongside other short grammatical works appended to a larger
                                lexicographical text by Eudoxus of Melitene.</p></note> It also
                        seems that Dawid is about to launch into a list of other functions that the
                        new dots perform for a diligent reader (an apt response to Yoḥannān’s
                        inquiry), but the major lacuna occurs here. Two folios – between 72 and 76
                        lines, representing more than 40 percent of the original text – are missing
                        from CFMM 158 after the word <hi rend="italic">rukkāḵā</hi>. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The text does not resume until Dawid’s elaboration about
                        Saḇroy’s school (see §2.1), and by this point it seems Yoḥannān’s question
                        has been resolved. Dawid briefly mentions that Saḇroy’s family composed
                        several liturgical works,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn176" n="176"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic">Egroteh</hi>, 48,
                                line 19 - 49, line 1; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic">Studia
                                Syriaca</hi>, ܡܙ, line 4. See Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ
                                    al-Manthūr</hi>, 71, 277; Moosa, <hi rend="italic">The Scattered
                                    Pearls</hi>, 73–74, 330. Dawid’s letter is the only source that
                                Barsoum cites for the existence of these works. As far as I know,
                                none of them are extant.</p></note> and then concludes the
                        letter:</p>
                    <cit>
                        <quote>They even arranged the urban worship service, due to
                            the increases and ostentation of the heretics. For this purpose, the
                            steadfast ones devoted themselves to making <hi rend="italic"
                                >puḥḥāmē</hi>, as well as the dots which are suitable for learners.
                            For the sages did not toil in vain, those who are in your prayers, who
                            are saints and teachers, whose memories I have glorified.<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn177" n="177"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    Dolabani reads <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܐܘܪܒܬ</foreign> here,
                                    while Rahmani has <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܨܒܬܘ</foreign>. The
                                    word is now too badly faded in CFMM 158 to decipher (f. 41r,
                                    line 21), but I have gone with Dolabani’s transcription due to
                                    the sense of the passage.</p></note> May they be deemed worthy
                            by the kingdom of heaven. Amen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn178"
                                n="178"><p rend="footnote text"> Dolabani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Egroteh</hi>, 49, line 1–6; Rahmani, <hi rend="italic"
                                        >Studia Syriaca</hi>, ܡܙ, line 4–8.</p></note></quote>
                    </cit>
                    <p xml:lang="en">This conclusion suggests that an increase in “heretics” –
                        whether that means East Syrians, Muslims, or some other group – motivated
                        Beṯ Rabban to use both accent dots and their new vowel dots in order to
                        ensure that readers could reproduce proper recitation. If these “learners”
                        were students at Saḇroy’s school, then they were likely Miaphysites.
                        However, the dots must have spread relatively quickly away from Beṯ Šehāq
                        and Mar Mattai, since it is clear that Eastern scribes utilised a full set
                        of vowel points in the eighth century. Barsoum remarks at the end of his
                        entry on Rāmišoʿ that “The two Syriac traditions – Orthodox and Eastern –
                        agreed on considering Rāmišoʿ an inventor of dots which may designate the
                            <hi rend="italic">matres lectionis</hi>.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn179" n="179"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                    rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi>, 287; Moosa, <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls</hi>, 330.</p></note> This
                        fact is not stated anywhere in the extant letter. On the slim chance that
                        Barsoum saw a more complete version of the text (recall his second “rare
                        copy”), a similar line might have been there. If not, then this sentence is
                        his own conclusion.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">One interesting pattern here is Dawid’s emphasis on the dots as
                        devices for teaching students, and not as silver bullets to clarify all
                        written Syriac. This matches the feelings of other Middle Eastern scholars
                        towards new vocalisation systems. Most notable is Jacob of Edessa, who
                        invented a set of vowel letters to record grammatical forms in his <hi
                            rend="italic">Turrāṣ Mamllā</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn180"
                            n="180"><p rend="footnote text"> Wright, <hi rend="italic">Fragments of
                                    the Syriac Grammar of Jacob of Edessa</hi>, 4; Rafael Talmon,
                                “Jacob of Edessa the Grammarian,” in <hi rend="italic">Jacob of
                                    Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His Day</hi>, ed. Bas ter Haar
                                Romeny (Leiden; Boston: Brill, 2008), 164–65.</p></note> He writes:
                        “[only] for the sake of the meaning and construction of the rules are the
                        letters added – insofar as they may show the change and pronunciation of the
                        forms – and not for the sake of completing or constructing the script.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn181" n="181"><p rend="footnote text"> Wright,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Fragments of the Syriac Grammar of Jacob of
                                    Edessa</hi>, ܐ, column b, line 10–14. See also, Kiraz, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>, I:73–74.</p></note> The Arabic
                        grammarian al-Khalīl ibn Aḥmad (d. 786/791), Dawid’s Mesopotamian
                        contemporary, was similarly cautious. He supposedly designed a set of Arabic
                        vowel signs in the mid-eighth century for use in poetry, but these signs did
                        not see regular use in the Qurʾān until the tenth or eleventh century.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn182" n="182"><p rend="footnote text"> Nabia
                                Abbott, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of the North Arabic Script and
                                    Its Ḳurʾānic Development</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago:
                                Oriental Institute, 1939), 39; Nabia Abbott, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Studies in Arabic Literary Papyri</hi>, vol. III (Chicago:
                                University of Chicago Press, 1972), 7–11; Rafael Talmon, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Arabic Grammar in Its Formative Age</hi> (Leiden:
                                Brill, 1997), 41–42. Alain George, “Coloured Dots and the Question
                                of Regional Origins in Early Qurʾans (Part I),” <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Journal of Qur’anic Studies</hi> 17, no. 1 (February 2015):
                                13–14; François Déroche, “Manuscripts of the Qurʾān,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Encyclopaedia of the Qurʾān</hi>, ed. Jane Dammen
                                McAuliffe et al. (Leiden: Brill, 2003),
                                http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1875-3922_q3_EQCOM_00110.</p></note>
                        Similarly, the eleventh-century <hi rend="italic">tajwīd</hi> scholar Abū
                        ʿAmr al-Dānī (d. 1053) reports the opposition of earlier scholars towards
                        Qurʾānic vocalisation, but also notes: “Mālik said . . . but as for the
                        little codices which children learn from, as well as their tablets, I do not
                        think [pointing them] is so bad.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn183" n="183"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Abū ʿAmr al-Dānī, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Al-Muḥkam Fī Naqṭ al-Maṣāḥif</hi>, ed. ʿIzza Ḥasan (Damascus,
                                1960), 6a.</p></note> The same distinction existed (and still
                        exists) among Jewish scribes, who did not vocalise Torah scrolls meant for
                        public recitation, but frequently pointed Bible codices used in private
                            study.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn184" n="184"><p rend="footnote text"
                                > Geoffrey Khan, “Standardisation and Variation in the Orthography
                                of Hebrew Bible and Arabic Qurʾan Manuscripts,” <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Manuscripts of the Middle East</hi>, no. 5 (1990): 54. This
                                practice is readily observed in many thousands of vocalised Bible
                                manuscripts from the Cairo Genizah; see Benjamin Outhwaite, “The
                                Tiberian Tradition in Common Bibles from the Cairo Genizah,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Studies in Semitic Vocalisation and Reading
                                    Traditions</hi>, ed. Aaron D. Hornkohl and Geoffrey Khan,
                                Cambridge Semitic Languages and Cultures 3 (Cambridge: University of
                                Cambridge &amp; Open Book Publishers, 2020), 406–8; Estara Arrant,
                                “An Exploratory Typology of Near-Model and Non-Standard Tiberian
                                Torah Manuscripts from the Cairo Genizah,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Studies in Semitic Vocalisation and Reading Traditions</hi>,
                                ed. Aaron D. Hornkohl and Geoffrey Khan, Cambridge Semitic Languages
                                and Cultures 3 (Cambridge: University of Cambridge &amp; Open Book
                                Publishers, 2020), 467–548.</p></note> All of this is to say that
                        Dawid’s description of the Syriac dots’ pedagogical implementation is
                        consistent with parallel developments in other scribal traditions.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1posegay.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">While not a complete picture, the extant portions of Dawid bar
                    Pawlos’ <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots </hi>provide ample information about
                    the lives of potentially key figures in the history of the Syriac language. As
                    we have seen, Saḇroy’s biography cannot be precisely corroborated, but the
                    founding of a Miaphysite school in Beṯ Šehāq as a response to the schools of the
                    Church of the East fits well within established patterns of seventh-century
                    scholastic rivalries. According to Dawid, Saḇroy’s zeal was particularly against
                    the monks of Beṯ Eḏri. His son Rāmišoʿ, who was likely the head of the school,
                    was also a monk at Mar Mattai, and the later history of Rabban Hormizd confirms
                    a fierce rivalry between Mar Mattai and Beṯ Eḏri. The anonymous biography of Bar
                    Kip̄o also supports the idea that there was a school in Beṯ Šehāq during the
                    eighth century, and that Dawid of Beṯ Rabban was associated with that school.
                    Furthermore, Dawid reports direct knowledge of Rāmišoʿ’s children, apparently
                    recorded in a provincial census conducted by al-Ḥurr ibn Yūsuf, an Umayyad
                    governor who ruled only a short time and died at least a decade before Dawid was
                    born. These details suggest that most of Dawid’s story is plausible as a
                    depiction of events in northern Iraq in the late seventh and early eighth
                    centuries. At any rate, if Dawid is making up the whole story to glorify his
                    ancestors, then he manages to contrive an appropriate context for its
                    seventh-century setting.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Numerous sources, both Diophysite and Miaphysite, also corroborate
                    the notion that a certain Rabban Rāmišoʿ was a great pointer of manuscripts.
                    According to Dawid, Rāmišoʿ’s tradition of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi> – that
                    is, of accents dots – was so eloquent that it spread beyond Mar Mattai. Given
                    Dawid’s timeline in the letter, this chronology is feasible: there were already
                    plenty of accent dots prior to Rāmišoʿ’s life, and East Syriac accentuation
                    especially was consistent from the early seventh century onwards.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn185" n="185"><p rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 60–63, 78–80, 119–21;
                            Loopstra, “The Syriac Reading Dot in Transmission.”</p></note> Moreover,
                    BL Add. 12138 shows that prior to 899, some East Syrians incorporated a
                    tradition of <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi> associated with a Rāmišoʿ into their
                        <hi rend="italic">mašlmānuṯā</hi>, as a variant alongside the readings of
                    the Eastern <hi rend="italic">maqryānē</hi>.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This brings us to the vowel dots whose invention Dawid attributes
                    to Beṯ Rabban. He refers to them as “small dots,” a common term for vowel points
                    among later grammarians, and an appropriate description for the points that
                    consistently appear smaller than accent dots in Eastern manuscripts.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn186" n="186"><p rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 6, 27, 80.</p></note>
                    However, the Syriac writing system was not entirely devoid of “pronunciation”
                    dots at the time we expect Saḇroy settled in Beṯ Šehāq. For example, both <hi
                        rend="italic">rukkāḵā</hi> and <hi rend="italic">quššāyā </hi>appear around
                    the beginning of the seventh century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn187" n="187"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>,
                            I:20; J.B. Segal, “Quššaya and Rukkaḵa: A Historical Introduction,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi> XXXIV, no. 2 (1989):
                            485.</p></note> Also by the seventh century, scribes had developed the
                    diacritic dot system to distinguish the vocalisation of three-way homographs,
                    including a supralinear dot, a sublinear dot, and a two-dot sign with one
                    supralinear and one sublinear dot.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn188" n="188"><p
                            rend="footnote text"><seg> </seg>Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ
                                Mamllā</hi>, I:12, 20, 64; Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                                Dot</hi>, 36–37, 94–98; Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                Point</hi>, 28.</p></note> This three-way diacritic system is the
                    full extent of Syriac “vocalisation” points that Jacob of Edessa knew in the
                    second half of the seventh century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn189" n="189"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>, I:14;
                            Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>, 44; Phillips, <hi
                                rend="italic">A Letter By Mār Jacob</hi>, ܝܕ, line 8–15.</p></note>
                    Notably, Jacob seems to have no knowledge of another two-dot sign from the
                    seventh century, where a horizontal pair of sublinear dots also helped to
                    distinguish three-way homographs.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn190" n="190"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Segal, <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical
                                Point</hi>, 26–27; Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>,
                            41–47, 98.</p></note> These practices led to an increasing association
                    of the two-dot diacritic signs with the vowels that they most frequently
                    represented in homographs. As a result, by the end of the sixth century, a dot
                    above and below could represent the vowel /a/, and by the end of the seventh
                    century, two dots below could mean /e/.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn191"
                        n="191"><p rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                                Dot</hi>, 98–101; Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>,
                            I:70.</p></note> This development represents a shift from the earlier
                    “relative” diacritic system towards a new “absolute” vocalisation system, in
                    which each vowel was marked by a unique sign on a one-to-one basis.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn192" n="192"><p rend="footnote text"> See also, Nick
                            Posegay, “To Belabour the Points: Encoding Vowel Phonology in Syriac and
                            Hebrew Vocalization,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi>
                            LXVI, no. 1 (2021): 53–76.</p></note> This change necessitated the
                    introduction of two new signs – a vertical or oblique supralinear pair of dots
                    for /ɔ/, and a vertical or oblique sublinear pair for /e/ – which first appear
                    in eighth-century manuscripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn193" n="193"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā</hi>, I:12,
                            21, 70–71; Kiraz, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot</hi>, 101–2; Segal,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical Point</hi>, 29–30.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Dawid’s letter suggests that Saḇroy and Rāmišoʿ were active during
                    this late seventh-century transition period. It would thus be impossible that
                    they introduced all or even most of the vowel points, as those dots had already
                    evolved out of the diacritic dot system. Beṯ Rabban may have accelerated the
                    transition towards absolute vocalisation, but the only dots which had not been
                    invented by their time were the oblique pairs for /ɔ/ and /e/. We may recall,
                    however, that Dawid did not say Beṯ Rabban devised “all small dots” or even “the
                    small dots,” but rather “<hi rend="italic">some </hi>small dots” (<hi
                        rend="italic">nuqzē meddem zʿorē</hi>). If Saḇroy and his sons did introduce
                    new dots to Syriac, then these two signs are the most likely candidates.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">When Vööbus rejects the entire letter solely on the basis of
                    Dawid’s religion, he misses this possibility. In fact, immediately after his
                    passionate rebuke of the <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots</hi>, he laments over
                    the vowel points:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>Finally, there is another important event in the gradual
                        growth of the East Syrian Massorah, namely the introduction of the vowels.
                        This must be regarded as a revolutionary event, opening up an entirely new
                        phase in the history of the linguistic phenomena under inquiry. What we are
                        allowed to glimpse of this area is most unsatisfactory.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn194" n="194"><p rend="footnote text"> Vööbus, <hi
                                    rend="italic">History of the School</hi>,
                        202.</p></note></quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">This letter may be the best literary source that Vööbus could have
                    consulted here, and for an event that he expects to be “revolutionary,” surely
                    Dawid’s fanfare is not too overstated. If Beṯ Rabban’s vowel points spread in
                    the same way as Rāmišoʿ’s <hi rend="italic">puḥḥāmā</hi>, then they would have
                    first reached the monasteries near Mar Mattai, and then expanded outward to
                    other Syriac communities. Considering that some inter-sect intellectual exchange
                    was possible in seventh- and eighth-century Iraq, then the vowel points are
                    fairly innocuous items to share. After all, dots are just dots, regardless of
                    the theology of the scribes who use them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn195"
                        n="195"><p rend="footnote text"> The first Qurʾānic vocalisers even adapted
                            the Syriac diacritic dot for use in Arabic. See C.H.M. Versteegh, <hi
                                rend="italic">Arabic Grammar and Qurʾanic Exegesis in Early
                                Islam</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1993), 29–30; Abbott, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Rise of the North Arabic Script</hi>, 38; George, “Coloured
                            Dots (Part I),” 4–9.</p></note> If vowel pointing made reading
                    significantly easier – as many grammarians assert that it did – then perhaps
                    some Diophysite scribes adopted a few new signs while turning a blind eye
                    towards claims of Miaphysite origins. Moreover, as Yoḥannān first reported to
                    Dawid, the story of the dots’ origins was forgotten even among Miaphysites by
                    the end of the eighth century. In this sense, just as Vööbus suggests, the
                    letter does “enlighten some local phenomenon.” Even though the dots themselves
                    spread far beyond their original source, knowledge of their inventors remained
                    limited to just a few Miaphysite communities, far from their Western
                    heartland.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Dawid bar Pawlos’ <hi rend="italic">Letter on Dots </hi>is thus an
                    underutilised, albeit complicated, source for an important stage in the
                    development of the Syriac language, and it is worthy of critical evaluation in
                    any history of that development.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Works Cited</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Abbott, Nabia. “Jundī-Shāpūr: A Preliminary Historical Sketch.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Ars Orientalis</hi> 7 (1968): 71–73.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Studies in Arabic Literary Papyri</hi>. Vol. III.
                        Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1972.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">The Rise of the North Arabic Script and Its
                            Ḳurʾānic Development</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago: Oriental
                        Institute, 1939.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Armalet, Isaac. <hi rend="italic">al-Ṭarfah fī Makhṭūṭā‎t Dayr
                            al-Sharfah</hi>. Jounieh, Lebanon: Maṭbaʻat al-Ābā‎’ al-Mursalīn
                        al-Lubnā‎niyyīn, 1936.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Lettres de Josué, fils de David, surnommé Bar-Kilo,
                            de Sévère Jacques de Bartelli, surnommé Bar-Chacaco, et de David de
                            Beit-Rabban</hi>. Beirut: Syriac Patriarchal Press, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Reggath Shabrē</hi>. Vol. II. 2 vols. Sharfeh:
                        Syriac Patriarchal Press, 1908.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Arrant, Estara. “An Exploratory Typology of Near-Model and Non-Standard
                        Tiberian Torah Manuscripts from the Cairo Genizah.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Studies in Semitic Vocalisation and Reading Traditions</hi>, edited by
                        Aaron D. Hornkohl and Geoffrey Khan, 467–548. Cambridge Semitic Languages
                        and Cultures 3. Cambridge: University of Cambridge &amp; Open Book
                        Publishers, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Assemani, Giuseppe Simone. <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Orientalis</hi>.
                        Vol. II. Rome: Scriptoribus Syris Nestorianis, 1721.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Orientalis</hi>. Vol. III. Rome:
                        Scriptoribus Syris Nestorianis, 1725.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baethgen, Friedrich, ed. <hi rend="italic">Syrische Grammatik des Elias of
                            Tîrhân</hi>. Leipzig: Hinrichs, 1880.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Barsoum, Ignatius Aphram I. <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr fī
                            Tārīkh al-ʿUlūm al-Ādāb al-Suriyāniyya</hi>. 5th ed. Aleppo: Silsila
                        al-Turāth al-Suriyānī, 1987.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Nuzhat al-Adhhān fī Tārīkh Dayr al-Zaʿfarān</hi>.
                        Mardin: The Syriac Press at Dayr al-Zaʿfarān, 1917.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Baumstark, Anton. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der syischen
                        Literatur</hi>. Bonn: A. Marcus &amp; E. Webers, 1922.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Becker, Adam H. <hi rend="italic">Fear of God and the Beginning of Wisdom:
                            The School of Nisibis and Christian Scholastic Culture in Late Antique
                            Mesopotamia</hi>. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                        2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Nisibis, School Of.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Nisibis-School-of.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Beeston, A.F.L. “Margoliouth, David Samuel (1858–1940), Orientalist.” In
                            <hi rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography (Electronic
                            Version)</hi>. Oxford University Press, 2006.
                        https://www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-34874.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Berg, Heleen L. Murre-van den. “Hormizd, Monastery of Rabban.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed
                        May 11, 2020. https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/
                        Hormizd-Monastery-of-Rabban.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, Sebastian P. <hi rend="italic">A Brief Outline of Syriac
                            Literature</hi>. Mōrān ’Eth’ō 9. Kerala: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research
                        Institute, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Beth Lapaṭ.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>.
                        Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Beth-Lapat.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Dawid Bar Pawlos.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Dawid-bar-Pawlos.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Margoliouth Collection of Syriac Manuscripts in the Bodleian
                        Library, Oxford: A Handlist.” Unpublished. Accessed April 27, 2020.
                        https://libguides.bodleian .ox.ac.uk/ld.php?content_id=17931955.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mari, Acts Of.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>.
                        Beth Mardutho. Accessed May 12, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Mari-Acts-of.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Brock, Sebastian P., and George A. Kiraz. “Raḥmani, Ignatius Ephrem II.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed
                        April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/
                        Rahmani-Ignatius-Ephrem-II.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Budge, E.A.W., ed. <hi rend="italic">The Book of the Governors: The
                            Historia Monastica of Thomas Bishop of Margå, A.D. 840</hi>. Vol. I.
                        London, 1893.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">The Histories of Rabban Hôrmȋzd the Persian and
                            Rabban Bar-‘Idtâ: The Syriac Texts Edited with English
                        Translations</hi>. Vol. II. 2 vols. Luzac’s Semitic Text and Translation
                        Series 10. London: Luzac and Co., 1902.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Butts, Aaron M. “A Syriac Dialogue Poem between the Vine and Cedar by
                        Dawid Bar Pawlos.” In <hi rend="italic">The Babylonian Disputation
                            Poems</hi>, edited by Enrique Jiménez, 462–73. Culture and History of
                        the Ancient Near East 87. Leiden; Boston: Brill, 2017.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed May 15, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Hunayn-b-Ishaq.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Chabot, J.B. <hi rend="italic">Livre de la chasteté par Jésusdenah, évéque
                            de Baçrah</hi>. Extrait des mélanges d’archéologie et d’histoire publiés
                        par l’ecole française de Rome, 16. Rome, 1896.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Coakley, J.F. “An Early Syriac Question Mark.” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic
                            Studies</hi> 10, no. 2 (2012): 193–213.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Mushe Bar Kipho.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Mushe-bar-Kipho.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “When Were the Five Greek Vowel-Signs Introduced into Syriac
                        Writing?” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi> 56, no. 2
                        (September 1, 2011): 307–25.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dānī, Abū ʿAmr al-. <hi rend="italic">Al-Muḥkam Fī Naqṭ al-Maṣāḥif</hi>.
                        Edited by ʿIzza Ḥasan. Damascus, 1960.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Déroche, François. “Manuscripts of the Qurʾān.” In <hi rend="italic"
                            >Encyclopaedia of the Qurʾān</hi>, edited by Jane Dammen McAuliffe,
                        Claude Gilliot, William A. Graham, Wadad Kadi, Andrew Rippin, Monique
                        Bernards, and John Nawas. Leiden: Brill, 2003.
                        http://dx.doi.org/10.1163/1875-3922_q3_EQCOM_ 00110.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Diettrich, Gustav. <hi rend="italic">Die Massorah der öslichen
                            underwestlichen Syer in ihren anagaben zum propheten Jesaia nach fünf
                            handscriften der British Museum</hi>. London; Edinburgh; Oxford:
                        Williams and Norgate, 1899.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dolabani, P.Y. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in
                            Zaʿfaran Monastery (Dairo dMor Hananyo)</hi>. Edited by Gregorios
                        Yuhanna Ibrahim. Damascus: Sidawi Printing House, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Egroteh d-Dawid bar Pawlos d-Metidaʿ d-Bet
                            Rabban</hi>. Mardin: The Syriac Printing Press of Wisdom, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Dutton, Yasin. “Red Dots, Green Dots, Yellow Dots and Blue: Some
                        Reflections on the Vocalisation of Early Qur’anic Manuscripts (Part I).” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Qur’anic Studies</hi> 1, no. 1 (1999):
                        115–40.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Duval, Rubens. <hi rend="italic">La littérature syriaque</hi>. 3rd ed.
                        Vol. II. Paris: Librairie Victor Lecoffre, 1907.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———, ed. <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum Auctore Hassano Bar
                            Bahlule</hi>. 2 vols. Paris, 1901. http://www.dukhrana.com/lexicon/
                        BarBahlul/index.php.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Fiey, J.M. <hi rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne, contribution á l’étude de
                            l’histoire et de la géographie ecclésiastiques et monastiques du nord de
                            l’Iraq</hi>. Vol. I. Recherches publiées sous la direction de l’institut
                        de lettres orientales de Beyrouth 22. Beirut: Imprimerie Catholique,
                        1965.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Assyrie chrétienne, contribution á l’étude de
                            l’histoire et de la géographie ecclésiastiques et monastiques du nord de
                            l’Iraq</hi>. Vol. II. Recherches publiées sous la direction de
                        l’institut de lettres orientales de Beyrouth 23. Beirut: Imprimerie
                        Catholique, 1966.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Forand, Paul G. “The Governors of Mosul According to Al-Azdī’s Ta’rīkh
                        Almawṣil.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi>
                        89, no. 1 (January 1969).</bibl>
                    <bibl>George, Alain. “Coloured Dots and the Question of Regional Origins in
                        Early Qurʾans (Part I).” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Qur’anic Studies</hi>
                        17, no. 1 (February 2015): 1–44.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Gottheil, Richard. <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on Syriac Grammar by Mâr
                            Eliâ of Ṣóbhâ</hi>. Berlin: Peiser, 1887.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Bar ʿAli (Ishoʿ): The Syriac-Arabic Glosses</hi>.
                        Vol. II (pe-taw). II vols. Classe Di Scienze Morali, Storiche et Filologiche
                        Ser. 5 13. Rome: Atti della R. Accademia dei Lincei, 1928.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Dawidh Bar Paulos, a Syriac Grammarian.” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            of the American Oriental Society</hi> 15 (1893): cxi–cxviii.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Harrak, Amir. “Sharfeh.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Sharfeh.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Zuqnin, Chronicle Of.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed May 10, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Zuqnin-Chronicle-of.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Heal, Kristian. “Notes on the Acquisition History of the Mingana Syriac
                        Manuscripts.” In <hi rend="italic">Manuscripta syriaca: des sources de
                            première main</hi>, edited by Françoise Briquel Chatonnet and Muriel
                        Debié. Cahiers d’études syriaques. Paris: Geuthner, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hoffmann, Georgius. <hi rend="italic">Opusculo Nestoriana</hi>. Paris,
                        1880.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Khan, Geoffrey. “Standardisation and Variation in the Orthography of
                        Hebrew Bible and Arabic Qurʾan Manuscripts.” <hi rend="italic">Manuscripts
                            of the Middle East</hi>, no. 5 (1990): 53–58.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kiraz, George A. “Al-Zaʿfarān, Dayr.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                            Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/al-Zafaran-Dayr.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Armalah, Isḥāq.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                        Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed May 14, 2020. https://gedsh.
                        bethmardutho.org/Armalah-Ishaq.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Barsoum, Ignatius Afram.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Barsoum-Ignatius-Afram.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Dolabani, Philoxenos Yuḥanon.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                            Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Dolabani-Philoxenos-Yuhanon.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Matay, Dayro d-Mor.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Matay-Dayro-d-Mor.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Dot: A Short History</hi>. Piscataway:
                        Gorgias Press, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Tūrrāṣ Mamllā: A Grammar of the Syriac
                            Language</hi>. Vol. I. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kiraz, George A., Sebastian P. Brock, Aaron M. Butts, Lucas Van Rompay,
                        David A. Michelson, Ute Possekel, and Daniel L. Schwartz, eds. <hi
                            rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage
                            (GEDSH): Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho, 2011.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/index.html.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lavenant, René, P.Y. Dolabani, Sebastian Brock, and Samir Khalil Samir.
                        “Catalogue des manuscrits de la bibliothèque du patriarcat syrien orthodoxe
                        à Ḥoms (auj. à Damas).” <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 19 (1994):
                        555–661.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Loopstra, Jonathan. <hi rend="italic">An East Syrian Manuscript of the
                            Syriac “Masora” Dated to 899 CE: Introduction, List of Sample Texts, and
                            Indices to Marginal Notes in British Library, Additional MS 12138</hi>.
                        Vol. II. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “The Syriac Reading Dot in Transmission: Consistency and Confusion.”
                        In <hi rend="italic">Studies in Biblical Philology and Lexicography</hi>,
                        edited by Daniel King, 159–76. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2019.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Martin, J.P.P. <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la ponctuation ou de la
                            Massore chez les Syriens.</hi> Paris: Impr. Nationale, 1875.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Melton, J. Gordon, and Martin Baumann. <hi rend="italic">Religions of the
                            World: A Comprehensive Encyclopedia of Beliefs and Practices</hi>. 2nd
                        ed. Vol. VI. 6 vols. Santa Barbara; Denver; Oxford: ABC-CLIO, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Merx, Adalbert. <hi rend="italic">Historia Artis Grammaticae Apud
                            Syros</hi>. Leipzig, 1889.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Mingana, Alphonse. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Mingana Collection
                            of Manuscripts: Syriac and Garshūni Manuscripts</hi>. Vol. I. Cambridge:
                        W. Heffer and Sons, 1933.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moberg, Axel. “Zur Terminologie.” In <hi rend="italic">Der Buch der
                            Strahlen, die grössere Grammatik des Barhebraeus</hi>, I:1*-120*.
                        Leipzig: Otto Harrassowitz, 1907.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Moosa, Matti, ed. <hi rend="italic">The Scattered Pearls: A History of
                            Syriac Literature and Sciences</hi>. Translated by Matti Moosa. 2nd
                        revised. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Nöldeke, Theodor. “Bibliographische Anzeigen: Studia Syriaca seu collectio
                        documentorum hactenus ineditorum. Ex codicibus syriacis primo publicavit,
                        latine vertit notisque illustravit Ignatius Ephraem II Rahmani patriarcha
                        Antiochenus Syrorum. Typis patriarchalibus in seminario Scharfensi in Mont
                        Libano 1904.” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen
                            Gesellschaft</hi> 58 (1904): 494–96.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Nyš, Nyš<hi rend="superscript">ʔ</hi>.” In <hi rend="italic">The
                            Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon</hi>. Cincinnati: Hebrew Union College:
                        Jewish Institute of Religion. Accessed June 14, 2020.
                        http://cal.huc.edu/oneentry.php?lemma=ny %24%20N&amp;cits=all.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Outhwaite, Benjamin. “The Tiberian Tradition in Common Bibles from the
                        Cairo Genizah.” In <hi rend="italic">Studies in Semitic Vocalisation and
                            Reading Traditions</hi>, edited by Aaron D. Hornkohl and Geoffrey Khan,
                        405–66. Cambridge Semitic Languages and Cultures 3. Cambridge: University of
                        Cambridge &amp; Open Book Publishers, 2020.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Payne Smith, J., ed. <hi rend="italic">A Compendious Syriac
                            Dictionary</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1903.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Phillips, George, ed. <hi rend="italic">A Letter By Mār Jacob, Bishop of
                            Edessa, on Syriac Orthography: Also a Tract by the Same Author, and a
                            Discourse by Gregory Bar Hebræus on Syriac Accents.</hi> London;
                        Edinburgh: Williams and Norgate, 1869.</bibl>
                    <bibl>“Pḥm.” In <hi rend="italic">The Comprehensive Aramaic Lexicon</hi>.
                        Cincinnati: Hebrew Union College: Jewish Institute of Religion. Accessed
                        June 19, 2020. http://cal.huc.edu/oneentry.php?
                        lemma=pxm%20V&amp;cits=all.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Posegay, Nick. “To Belabour the Points: Encoding Vowel Phonology in Syriac
                        and Hebrew Vocalization.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi>
                        LXVI, no. 1 (2021): 53–76.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Qādī, Wadād al-. “Population Census and Land Surveys under the Umayyads
                        (41–132/661–750).” <hi rend="italic">Der Islam</hi> 83, no. 2 (2008).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rahmani, Ignatius Ephraem II. <hi rend="italic">Studia Syriaca: Collectio
                            Documentorum Hactenus Ineditorum Ex Codicus Syriacis</hi>. Sharfeh:
                        Sharfeh Patriarchal Seminary, 1904.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reinink, G.J. “‘Edessa Grew Dim and Nisibis Shone Forth’: The School of
                        Nisibis at the Transition of the Sixth-Seventh Century.” In <hi
                            rend="italic">Centres of Learning: Learning and Location in Pre-Modern
                            Europe and the Near East</hi>, 77–89. Brill’s Studies in Intellectual
                        History 61. Leiden, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Reller, Jobst. <hi rend="italic">Mose bar Kepha und seine
                            Paulinenauslegung: nebst Edition und Übersetzung des Kommentars zum
                            Römerbrief</hi>. Göttinger Orientforschungen. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz,
                        1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Robinson, Chase. <hi rend="italic">Empire and Elites after the Muslim
                            Conquest</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Scher, Addai. “Notice sur les manuscrits syriaques conservés dans la
                        bibliothèque du couvent des chaldéens de notre-name-des-semences.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal asiatique</hi> VII, no. 1 (1906): 479–512.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Segal, J.B. “Quššaya and Rukkaḵa: A Historical Introduction.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Journal of Semitic Studies</hi> XXXIV, no. 2 (1989):
                        483–91.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">The Diacritical Point and the Accents in
                            Syriac</hi>. London; New York: Oxford University Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Shamoon, Saliba. <hi rend="italic">Tārīkh Abrashiyya al-Mawṣil
                            al-Suriyāniyya</hi>. Mosul, 1984.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Talmon, Rafael. <hi rend="italic">Arabic Grammar in Its Formative
                        Age</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Jacob of Edessa the Grammarian.” In <hi rend="italic">Jacob of
                            Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His Day</hi>, edited by Bas ter Haar
                        Romeny, 159–76. Leiden; Boston: Brill, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tannous, Jack. <hi rend="italic">The Making of the Medieval Middle East:
                            Religion, Society, and Simple Believers</hi>. Princeton; Oxford:
                        Princeton University Press, 2018.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Teule, Herman G. B. “Eliya of Nisibis.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                            Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed May 10, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Eliya-of-Nisibis.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Thomas, Susan. “Miscellaneous Syriac Manuscripts in the Bodleian Library.”
                        Archives Hub. Accessed May 1, 2020.
                        https://archiveshub.jisc.ac.uk/search/archives/92baddd3-3c51-3c56-9070-1721bfe786cc.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Van Rompay, Lucas. “Abraham of Beth Rabban.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH:
                            Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Abraham-of-Beth-Rabban.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “La littérature exégétique syriaque et le rapprochement des
                        traditions syrienne-occidentale et syrienne-orientale.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Parole de l’Orient</hi> 20 (1995): 221–35.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Narsai.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic Edition</hi>. Beth
                        Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020. https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/
                        Narsai.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. “Yoḥannan of Beth Rabban.” In <hi rend="italic">GEDSH: Electronic
                            Edition</hi>. Beth Mardutho. Accessed April 28, 2020.
                        https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Yohannan-of-Beth-Rabban.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Versteegh, C.H.M. <hi rend="italic">Arabic Grammar and Qurʾanic Exegesis
                            in Early Islam</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vidro, Nadia. “A Book on Arabic Inflexion According to the System of the
                        Greeks: A Lost Work by Ḥunayn b. Isḥāq.” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift Für
                            Arabische Linguistik</hi> 72, no. 2 (2020): 26–58.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vööbus, Arthur. “Entdeckung des Briefkorpus des Dawid bar Paulos.” <hi
                            rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi>, no. 58 (1974): 45–80.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">History of the School of Nisibis</hi>. Corpus
                        Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 26. Louvain: American Catholic
                        University; Louvaine Catholic University, 1965.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wehr, Hans. <hi rend="italic">The Hans Wehr Dictionary of Modern Written
                            Arabic</hi>. Edited by J.M. Cowan. 4th ed. Urbana: Spoken Language
                        Services, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wright, William. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the
                            British Museum</hi>. Vol. I. London: Gilbert and Rivington, 1870.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the British
                            Museum</hi>. Vol. III. London: Gilbert and Rivington, 1872.</bibl>
                    <bibl>———, ed. <hi rend="italic">Fragments of the Syriac Grammar of Jacob of
                            Edessa</hi>. Clerkenwell: Gilbert and Rivington, 1871.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Zadok, Ran. “On Some Upper Mesopotamian Toponyms.” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Nouvelles assyriologiques brèves et utilitaires</hi>, Notes brèves, no.
                        3 (1998): 69–71.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
