<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Anxious Vigilance: Heresy and Ritual Pollution in John of Tella
                    and Severus of Antioch</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Christine</forename>
                        <surname>Shepardson</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Tennessee, Knoxville</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n1shepardson</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Christine Shepardson</author>
                        <title level="a">Anxious Vigilance: Heresy and Ritual Pollution in John of Tella
                            and Severus of Antioch</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N1Shepardson.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="3" to="34">3-34</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>John of Tella</term>
                    <term>Orthodoxy</term>
                    <term>Heresy</term>
                    <term>Purity</term>
                    <term>Didascalia</term>
                    <term>Severus of Antioch</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-02-12">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Anti-Chalcedonian Christians like John of Tella, Severus of
                    Antioch, Philoxenos of Mabbug, and John Rufus were concerned about orthodox
                    Christians mingling with heretics. This essay argues that John of Tella combined
                    narratives of heresy with those of bodily purity and pollution, such as those
                    related to menstruation, to frame heretics as dangerous to orthodox Christians not
                    only in their beliefs that could lure an unsuspecting Christian to accept heretical
                    views, but in their very bodies whose proximity brought the threat of contamination.
                    John integrated expectations of bodily purity and doctrinal orthodoxy in ways that
                    suggested that heresy could physically contaminate, while Severus tried to calm his
                    congregants’ fears about the same. The spread of COVID-19 and the global responses
                    to it have heightened our awareness of the dynamics of fear and anxiety that can be
                    produced by threats of physical contamination. The global pandemic in 2020 thus
                    helps to clarify the power that the rhetoric of these sixth-century
                    anti-Chalcedonian texts had to confront the spread of what John of Tella implied was
                    the dangerous physical pollution of Christian heresy.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>

               <div xml:id="hv24n1shepardson.1" xml:lang="en">         
            <p xml:lang="en">The spread of COVID-19 and the global responses to it have
                heightened our awareness of some of the dynamics of fear and anxiety produced by
                threats of physical contamination. As we learn new habits of social distancing, and
                experience the anxiety and vigilance produced by the potentially fatal spread of an
                unseen contagion, we are better able to imagine some of the social dynamics that
                early Christian rhetoric around heresy and ritual pollution, such as in relation to
                menstruating bodies, might have hoped to produce. Sixth-century anti-Chalcedonian
                leaders claimed that heresy threatened Christians’ eternal salvation and warned that
                it was often difficult for the untrained eye to distinguish a heretic from an
                orthodox Christian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">
                        In this essay I use “anti-Chalcedonian” to refer to what some scholars call
                        Miaphysite (or, earlier, Monophysite) or sometimes non-Chalcedonian
                        Christianity. No terminology is without complications, but this term
                        accurately highlights the individuals’ hostile relation to the Council of
                        Chalcedon (451). Volker Menze recommends the term “non-Chalcedonian” in his
                        study of this period, concerned that “anti-Chalcedonian” retains too much
                        emphasis on doctrinal issues for his study, which “deals mainly with
                        historical and not Christological issues,” but the focus on doctrinal issues
                        is appropriate in this present essay: Volker Menze, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Justinian and the Making of the Syrian Orthodox Church</hi> (New York:
                        Oxford University Press, 2008), 2. Furthermore, “non-Chalcedonian” could
                        also describe the churches in Persia that became the Church of the East,
                        which are not intended here. Cornelia Horn addresses similar concerns and
                        likewise prefers “anti-Chalcedonian”: Cornelia Horn, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Asceticism and Christological Controversy in Fifth-Century
                            Palestine</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2006), 8-9. On the
                        terminology used for one’s adversaries more generally, see Muriel Debié
                        “Désigner l’adversaire: La guerre des noms dans les controverses,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Les controverses religieuses en syriaque</hi>, ed. Flavia
                        Ruani, 307-48 (Paris: Geuthner, 2016). On the terminology for the Christians
                        at the center of this project, see Fergus Millar, “The Evolution of the
                        Syrian Orthodox Church in the Pre-Islamic Period: From Greek to Syriac?” <hi
                            rend="italic">JECS</hi> 21.1 (2013): 43-92.</p></note> John of Tella
                combined this argument with familiar concepts of purity and pollution in order to
                suggest that physical proximity to heresy could pose a risk of contamination. In
                contrast, John’s colleague Severus of Antioch downplayed the danger that heresy
                posed as a form of pollution in an effort to calm the fears of his congregants. As a
                novel Coronavirus spreads through our world, health officials warn us about this
                sometimes invisible contagion, and the safety precautions that should be taken at
                all times because so many people who have the virus are asymptomatic. We are warned
                to keep our distance from others to protect ourselves and the small communities with
                whom we interact most closely. The global pandemic in 2020 thus helps to clarify the
                power that the rhetoric of these sixth-century anti-Chalcedonian texts had to
                confront the spread of what John of Tella implied was the dangerous physical
                pollution of Christian heresy.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">John of Tella (Yuḥanon bar Qursus) was fundamental to the development of the West
                Syrian church, but his story is much less well known outside of that tradition.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> Volker Menze and Kutlu
                        Akalin, <hi rend="italic">John of Tella’s Profession of Faith: The Legacy of
                            a Sixth-Century Syrian Orthodox Bishop</hi> (Gorgias Press, 2009), 1.
                        Joseph Ghanem traced a history of the modern western study of John of Tella
                        through 1970, and offered a historical background for John’s life: Joseph R.
                        Ghanem, “The Biography of John of Tella (d. AD 537) by Elias, Translated
                        from the Syriac with a Historical Introduction and Historical and Linguistic
                        Commentaries.” PhD Dissertation, University of Wisconsin, 1970, esp.
                        1-39.</p></note> John was born in 482 in Callinicus (Raqqa, Syria) in the
                Roman province of Osrhoene, and knew both Syriac and Greek.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> Ghanem, “The Biography of John of
                        Tella,” 13.</p></note> In 507 when he was twenty-five years old, John joined
                a monastery near his hometown where he stayed until he was ordained as the bishop of
                Tella (near modern Aleppo) in 519 by the famous seventy-year old scholar and poet
                Jacob of Serugh (d. 521) and his colleagues.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"
                        ><p rend="footnote text"> Regarding his title, see Menze and Akalin,
                        <hi rend="italic">John of Tella’s Profession of </hi>Faith,
                        7-8. See also Volker Menze, “The <hi rend="italic">Regula ad Diaconos</hi>:
                        John of Tella, his Eucharistic Ecclesiology and the Establishment of an
                        Ecclesiastical Hierarchy in Exile,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens
                            Christianus</hi> 90 (2006): 46-8.</p></note> John briefly lived in
                residence as bishop of Tella from 519-521/2 but then he was sent into exile under
                the emperor Justin I.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">
                        Menze and Akalin, <hi rend="italic">John of Tella’s Profession of
                        Faith</hi>, 5.</p></note> It was in exile, though, that John solidified his
                place in history with the astonishing number of ordinations he performed, bringing
                countless lay people and monks into the diaconate and the priesthood in an effort to
                help the anti-Chalcedonian church not only survive but flourish.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> Yonatan Moss, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Incorruptible Bodies: Christology, Society, and Authority in Late
                            Antiquity</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2016), 62.
                    </p></note> Volker Menze and Kutlu Akalin outline “John’s role in establishing
                the first independent non-Chalcedonian ecclesiastical hierarchy,” a goal for which
                by all accounts he worked tirelessly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Menze and Akalin, <hi rend="italic">John of Tella’s
                            Profession of Faith</hi>, 7-8.</p></note> John spent his exile primarily
                in the Sasanian Empire’s western borderland region, including near modern-day
                Mardin, Turkey. Early in 537, however, Roman leaders arranged for John’s capture in
                the mountains of Persia, and he was brought as a prisoner to Antioch, which was
                under the control of the staunchly Chalcedonian bishop Ephraim, whom
                anti-Chalcedonian writers like John of Ephesus describe as a vicious
                    persecutor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> See,
                        for example, John of Ephesus, <hi rend="italic">Lives</hi>, PO 17.21;
                        18.608; 17.293-4; cf., 17.125.</p></note> John of Tella died in 538 in his
                mid-fifties while in Ephraim’s custody in Antioch. Warning of the danger that
                physical proximity to heretics or other material objects associated with heresy
                posed to orthodox Christians helped John in his relentless efforts to expand and
                preserve the anti-Chalcedonian community during his itinerant exile.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Severus of Antioch, on the other hand, has remained better known. A Greek-speaker
                born in the mid-460s in Sozopolis in the region of Pisidia, in western modern
                Turkey, he was educated at some of the best schools in the Roman Empire, first in
                Alexandria and then in the famous law school in Berytus (Beirut).<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> On Severus’s life and works, see,
                        for example, Pauline Allen and C.T.R. Hayward, <hi rend="italic">Severus of
                            Antioch</hi> (New York: Routledge, 2004), 3-55; John D’Alton and
                        Youhanna Youssef, eds., <hi rend="italic">Severus of Antioch: His Life and
                            Times</hi> (Boston: Brill, 2016); Sebastian Brock and Brian Fitzgerald,
                            <hi rend="italic">Two Early Lives of Severos, Patriarch of Antioch</hi>
                        (Liverpool: Liverpool University Press, 2013), 1-29; Moss, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Incorruptible Bodies</hi>; Iaian Torrance, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Christology after Chalcedon: Severus of Antioch and Sergius the
                            Monophysite</hi> (Eugene, OR: Wipf &amp; Stock, 1988), 3-25; Lucas Van
                        Rompay, “Severus, Patriarch of Antioch (512-538), in the Greek, Syriac, and
                        Coptic Traditions,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian Society for
                            Syriac Studies</hi> 8 (2008): 3-22; René Roux, <hi rend="italic"
                            >L’Exégèse Biblique dans les Homélies Cathédrales de Sévère
                            d’Antioche</hi>, Studia Ephemerides Augustinianum 84 (Rome: Institutum
                        Patristicum Augustinianum, 2002), 5-19; and Aryeh Kofsky, “Severus of
                        Antioch and Christological Politics in the Early Sixth Century,” <hi
                            rend="italic">Proche-Orient Chrétien</hi> 57 (2007): 43-57.</p></note>
                According to his hagiographers, Severus was baptized in 488 at the church of St.
                Leontius in Tripolis (Tripoli, Lebanon) and committed himself to a life of
                asceticism as Ambrose, Augustine, and many other elite Romans also did. Soon after
                this, a side-trip to Peter the Iberian’s monastery near Gaza during a pilgrimage to
                Jerusalem changed Severus’s plans to practice law, and he spent the next twenty
                years as an ascetic in southern Palestine where he was also ordained as a
                    priest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> Brouria
                        Bitton-Ashkelony and Aryeh Kofsky, <hi rend="italic">The Monastic School of
                            Gaza</hi> (Boston: Brill, 2006), 33.</p></note> In 508, Severus began a
                new and more public and politically involved phase of his life when he led a large
                delegation of monks to Constantinople. In 512 the emperor Anastasius deposed Flavian
                II from the see of Antioch, thanks in large part to the maneuverings of Philoxenos
                of Mabbug, and appointed Severus as the city’s new bishop. Severus was forced into
                exile in 518 upon Justin I’s accession to the throne, and lived most of the rest of
                his episcopacy in Egypt until he died in 538, within days of John of Tella’s death
                in Severus’s episcopal home of Antioch.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> On Severus’s exile, see Allen and Hayward, <hi
                            rend="italic">Severus of Antioch</hi>, 25-30.</p></note> Severus’s
                influence in the controversies over the definition of Christian orthodoxy and
                orthopraxy was far-reaching, particularly in the West Syrian tradition of Syrian
                Orthodoxy. Severus differed from John of Tella, though, in his insistence that
                anti-Chalcedonian orthodoxy remained a universal church, and as a result Severus was
                sometimes more flexible and willing to compromise than John.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> On Severus’ willingness to
                        compromise in order to preserve his coherence within imperial orthodoxy, see
                        Moss, <hi rend="italic">Incorruptible </hi>Bodies, 1-6,
                        44-74.</p></note> This, along with his context in residence as bishop of
                Antioch, could explain Severus’s efforts to calm rather than stoke his audience’s
                fears about heresy’s ability to pollute the liturgy and congregation.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Anti-Chalcedonian leaders like Philoxenos of Mabbug (d. 523), John Rufus (fl.
                500-18), Severus, and John of Tella all expressed concern about anti-Chalcedonian
                Christians mingling with heretics, and as late antique Christians they inherited a
                variety of ways to think about retaining the spiritual purity and health of their
                community. New Testament comments attributed to Paul offered one relevant discourse,
                such as of their community as a body in which the spiritual health of one part
                affected the whole.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">
                        1 Cor 5-6. See also 1 Cor 6.15-16. All biblical quotations are from the
                        NRSV. </p></note> Paul asked, “Do you not know that a little yeast leavens
                the whole batch of dough?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> 1 Cor 5.6.</p></note> When Paul taught his audience 
                “not to associate with anyone
                who bears the name of brother or sister who is sexually immoral
                or greedy, or is an idolater, reviler, drunkard, or robber. Do not
                even eat with such a one,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor 5.11.</p></note> 
                he established a method of defining
                and defending community boundaries that prioritized
                associating only with those who were spiritually healthy, which
                anti-Chalcedonian leaders insisted did not include Chalcedonian heretics or
                “Nestorian” Persian Christians. Like Paul, later Christians also inherited
                scriptural teachings about bodily purity, reinterpretations of which kept them
                relevant long past the destruction of the Temple in Jerusalem. John of Tella drew on
                familiar narratives of bodily purity and pollution, such as those related to
                menstruation, to frame heretics as dangerous to orthodox Christians not only in
                their beliefs that could lure an unsuspecting Christian to accept heretical views,
                but in their very bodies whose proximity brought the threat of contamination. In two
                letters from his time in residence as Antioch’s powerful bishop, Severus, in
                contrast, wrote to counter the fear that the perception of heresy as a physical
                pollution had provoked in his own congregants.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                    n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> That these letters (Severus, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ep.</hi> 44, 45) date from Severus’s time in Antioch is suggested in
                        part by his address of his congregation regarding their concerns over the
                        names read in the liturgical diptychs, which implies that Severus is
                        currently leading the services. E.W. Brooks dates Severus, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ep.</hi> 44 and 45 to 516-7 in his edition and translation (PO
                        12.310-15)</p></note> These texts suggest that the idea that heresy was a
                contaminating pollution was a particularly powerful tool for besieged leaders like
                John during his long exile, because it inspired vigilant boundary-maintenance among
                Christians who faced pressure to abandon anti-Chalcedonian teachings in favor of the
                imperially sanctioned Chalcedonian church.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1shepardson.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Purity and Pollution: Regulating Menstruating Bodies</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Interpretations of biblical regulations involving the ancient contact-contagion
                    of ritual impurity provide a critical contextual frame for understanding John of
                    Tella’s rhetoric about the dangers of proximity posed by heresy, and the related
                    concerns of Severus’s congregants. While metaphors of heresy as an illness or
                    disease were familiar in late antiquity,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, for example, referred to the
                            “disease” of Arius, and referred to Eusebius as “contaminated by the
                            sickness of Arius.” Severus, <hi rend="italic">Hom</hi> 30 (PO
                            36.4.610-11). Translations of this text are from the Syriac edition and
                            French translation by M. Brière and F. Graffin in PO 36.4. Jennifer
                            Barry notes, “Heresy, imagined as a disease, was a popular concept that
                            flourished after the second half of the fifth century…. by overlapping
                            the medical with the theological, Christian authors helped their readers
                            to distinguish the guilty from the innocent”: Jennifer Barry,
                            “Diagnosing Heresy: Ps.-Martyrius’s <hi rend="italic">Funerary Speech
                                for John Chrysostom</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">JECS</hi> 24.3 (2016):
                            395-418, at 402. </p></note> in Greek traditions illness was not
                    consistently understood to be contracted through person-to-person contact.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text"> Vivian Nutton
                            notes that many Greek medical writers were influenced by Aristotelian
                            and Platonic ideas and not the “mechanistic view” of the universe of
                            many Epicureans; as a result they often did not describe diseases
                            passing through human-to-human contact. Nevertheless, Nutton admits that
                            many Greek authors who were not medical experts did believe that
                            proximity to a sick person could pose a risk to one’s health. Vivian
                            Nutton, “Did the Greeks Have a Word for It? Contagion and Contagion
                            Theory in Classical Antiquity,” in <hi rend="italic">Contagion:
                                Perspectives from Pre-Modern Societies</hi>, ed. Lawrence Conrad and
                            Dominik Wujastyk, 137-62 (Burlington, Vt: Ashgate, 2000). On the Greek
                            concept of <hi rend="italic">miasma</hi>, which often stood in place of
                            human contact to explain disease spread, see Jacques Jouanna, “Air,
                            miasma and Contagion in the Time of Hippocrates and the Survival of
                            Miasmas in Post-Hippocratic Medicine,” in <hi rend="italic">Greek
                                Medicine from Hippocrates to Galen: Selected Papers</hi>, ed. Philip
                            van der Eijk, trans. Neil Allies, 121-36 (Boston: Brill, 2012).
                        </p></note> Moral impurities, on the other hand, could be described as being
                    transmitted from one person to another along the lines of ritual bodily
                    impurities. As Naomi Koltun-Fromm and Christine Hayes note, the apostle Paul
                    left Christians with the concept that “the individual body can contract ‘moral’
                    impurities from others who are ‘morally impure’.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> Naomi Koltun-Fromm, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Hermeneutics of Holiness: Ancient Jewish and
                                Christian Notions of Sexuality and Religious Community</hi> (New
                            York: Oxford University Press, 2010), 88; Koltun-Fromm relies on
                            Christine Hayes, <hi rend="italic">Gentile Impurities and Jewish
                                Identities: Intermarriage and Conversion from the Bible to the
                                Talmud</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002). Nutton agrees
                            that in antiquity, “Whether pagan or Christian, heretic or libertine,
                            the views of one’s opponents are characterized by the metaphors of
                            disease and contagion, of pollution and contamination,” such that
                            “physical and moral diseases are almost interchangeable” (Nutton, “Did
                            the Greeks Have a Word for It,” 153).</p></note> More consistently than
                    metaphors of sickness, it seems to have been the language of purity and
                    pollution that provoked a heightened sense of Christian vigilance about physical
                    proximity. Mira Balberg has discussed concepts of purity and impurity that lived
                    on in rabbinic traditions after the Temple’s destruction, especially “as
                    powerful conceptual and hermeneutic tools through which ideas about self and
                    other can be manifested, through which one’s body and environment can be
                    scrutinized and manifested, and through which one constitutes and forms oneself
                    as a subject.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Mira Balberg, <hi rend="italic">Purity, Body, and Self in Early Rabbinic
                                Literature</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2014),
                            3.</p></note> Early Christians – despite a frequent rhetorical disdain
                    for a “Jewish” focus on ritual, purity laws, and the body – likewise continued
                    to see religious significance in the perceived state of a person’s body, whether
                    it was praising the virginal body, preventing certain types of bodies from
                    ordination, or regulating the participation of bodies with discharges in the
                    rituals of baptism and the Eucharist. Tracking some of the expectations that
                    sixth-century anti-Chalcedonian Christians inherited regarding perceptions of
                    ritual purity and the pollution caused by bodily discharges such as menstruation
                    provides a new lens for understanding their concerns about the risk that bodies
                    contaminated by heresy could pose.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Late antique readers of scripture, of course, like readers in any period, updated
                    the biblical rhetoric around bodily purity for their own context. Balberg notes
                    that the early rabbis inherited a variety of narratives about bodily purity “as
                    one of the pivots of the consistent effort to distinguish ‘us’ from ‘them’,” and
                    she demonstrates that “the rabbis posit the engagement with impurity… as a
                    critical component in one’s formation as a committed rabbinic Jewish
                        subject.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Balberg, <hi rend="italic">Purity, Body, and Self</hi>, 15. </p></note>
                    She argues that these post-Temple leaders transformed earlier conversations to
                    be newly focused on the purity of a religious self under the authority of the
                        rabbis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Balberg, <hi rend="italic">Purity, Body, and Self</hi>, 4-5.</p></note>
                    Among these discussions, Balberg notes mishnaic descriptions of Gentiles as
                    those who were “considered to convey the same impurity as persons with abnormal
                    genital discharges, regardless of their physical condition,” such that “if a Jew
                    or a Jew’s property comes into physical contact with a Gentile, the Jew or her
                    property is immediately rendered impure.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
                        n="23"><p rend="footnote text"> Balberg, <hi rend="italic">Purity, Body, and
                                Self</hi>, 16, 124.</p></note> Balberg argues, “the rabbis’
                    insistence that Gentiles are categorically impure seems geared to cultivating a
                    particular way of <hi rend="italic">thinking</hi> about Gentiles.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> Balberg<hi
                                rend="italic">, Purity, Body, and Self</hi>, 131.</p></note> I
                    suggest that John of Tella deployed “heretics” in a way similar to these
                    rabbinic texts’ use of Gentiles by suggesting that heresy was a form of
                    pollution that could contaminate orthodox bodies, which would have had the
                    benefits of sharpening a distinction between “us” and “them,” thus encouraging
                    Christians to keep their distance from heretics, and giving John the authority
                    to define those boundaries.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Early Christian readers, like the rabbis, interpreted these biblical texts about
                    bodily discharges for their own historical and theological contexts. Some
                    Christians believed that honoring God required approaching the divine with a
                    pure body as well as soul, based on early biblical traditions where, as Naomi
                    Koltun-Fromm says, “It is assumed that human bodily impurities, such as semen,
                    are anathema in some way to God’s presence and must be neutralized through
                    purification rites before a divine encounter.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Koltun-Fromm, <hi rend="italic">Hermeneutics
                                of Holiness</hi>, 40. </p></note> Koltun-Fromm argues that in the
                    early biblical priestly tradition “purity functions as a means to protect the
                    holy,” while “nonpriestly biblical narratives in general have a looser notion”
                    in which “purity is something one does in order to handle holy items such as a
                        sacrifice.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Koltun-Fromm, <hi rend="italic">Hermeneutics of Holiness</hi>,
                        37.</p></note> Eastern Christian responses to menstruating women’s bodies in
                    late antiquity provide some relevant interpretive context for thinking of heresy
                    as a physical, polluting contaminant among Severus’s congregants and in John of
                    Tella’s sixth-century Syriac texts. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The third-century <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi>, for example, offers two ways
                    in which biblical purity laws were interpreted by Christ-followers, one through
                    the voice of the narrator and the other through the arguments attributed to some
                    women in the community. As Charlotte Fonrobert explains, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didascalia</hi> argues against women whom the text claims “keep themselves
                    from prayer and from receiving the Eucharist [<hi rend="italic"
                    >eucharistia</hi>], or from reading the Scriptures” during the “seven days of
                    their menstrual period.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Charlotte Elisheva Fonrobert, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Menstrual Purity: Rabbinic and Christian Reconstructions of
                                Biblical Gender</hi> (Stanford University Press, 2000), 173; <hi
                                rend="italic">Didascalia</hi> 26 (Vööbus, 255-63/238-45, cited by
                            the page of the Syriac/English edition and translation). Translations of
                            this text in this essay are revised from the edition and English
                            translation in Arthur Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">The Didascalia
                                Apostolorum in Syriac II</hi>, CSCO 407-8 (Louvain: Secrétariat du
                            Corpus SCO, 1979). </p></note> Fonrobert usefully compares this with a
                    passage from the early rabbinic Tosefta that allows menstruating women to study
                    and read the scripture, noting that here the Tosefta and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didascalia</hi> agree with each other against the behavior attributed to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi>’s women, although the Tosefta expects
                    women to keep other “biblical regulations concerning menstruation” whereas the
                        <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi> does not.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28"
                        n="28"><p rend="footnote text"> Fonrobert, <hi rend="italic">Menstrual
                                Purity</hi>, 173-4; tBer 2:13.</p></note> The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didascalia</hi> argues that unlike earlier ablutions for ritual impurity
                    that were temporary, Christian baptism, with its subsequent indwelling of the
                    Holy Spirit, protects an upright Christian for the long term and removes the
                    need for further purification, including from menstruating.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Didascalia </hi>26 (Vööbus,
                            255/238). Fonrobert also details the arguments in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Didascalia</hi>, and the ways in which the text’s logic is tied to
                            its representation of what it calls the “second legislation,” that is,
                            some biblical expectations that the author believes to have been
                            abrogated by the resurrection of the messiah in the person of Jesus
                            (Fonrobert, <hi rend="italic">Menstrual Purity</hi>, 172-85).</p></note>
                    This relation between bodily and spiritual purity relies on what Jonathan
                    Klawans notes seems to have been an innovation by John the Baptist to advocate
                    for a ritual cleansing that was “more frequently associated in the past with
                    ritual impurity” as newly a one-time means “of achieving moral purity” through
                        baptism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Jonathan Klawans, <hi rend="italic">Impurity and Sin in Ancient
                                Judaism</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2000), 160. See
                            also Hayes, <hi rend="italic">Gentile Impurities</hi>. </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi> critiques these women “because of the
                    observances that you keep,” arguing that “all these observances are foolish and
                    hurtful,” and reminds the women of all the other laws they would also have to
                    keep if they followed this one aspect of what the text calls the former
                        legislation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Didascalia </hi>26 (Vööbus,
                            258-9/241-2). </p></note> The <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi> asks the
                    women to “flee and avoid such observances…. do not observe these things, nor
                    think them pollution [<hi rend="italic">ṭamutā</hi>]; and do not refrain
                    yourselves on their account, nor seek after sprinklings, or baptisms, or
                    purifications [<hi rend="italic">dukaye</hi>] for these things;” but rather
                    “come together even in the cemeteries, and read the holy Scriptures, and without
                    hesitation perform your ministry and your supplication to God; and offer an
                    acceptable Eucharist [<hi rend="italic">eukarisṭia</hi>].”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Didascalia </hi>26 (Vööbus,
                            261/243).</p></note> Thus while these women are said to have kept
                    themselves from the Eucharist, prayer, and reading scripture during menstruation
                    as an extrapolation of biblical observances, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Didascalia</hi>’s narrator made a strong argument that bodily discharges
                    did not make a person impure, and therefore should not curtail Christians’
                    behavior, including in taking the Eucharist.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Despite the <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi>’s passionate argument and its
                    repetition in the late fourth-century <hi rend="italic">Apostolic
                        Constitutions</hi>, some church leaders did ask menstruating women, among
                    others with bodily discharges, to delay Christian rituals until their bodies
                    were cleansed. As Fonrobert notes, for example, “Whereas the Didascalia tried to
                    convince women in its community to partake in the Eucharist while they are
                    menstruating,” a nearly contemporary Greek text by Dionysius of Alexandria (d.
                    265) “attempts to keep them away from it, as well as from the altar and the
                    church altogether.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Fonrobert, <hi rend="italic">Menstrual
                            Purity</hi>, 196; text from Ross Kraemer, <hi rend="italic">Maenads,
                                Martyrs, Matrons, Monastics: A Sourcebook on Women’s Religions in
                                the Greco-Roman World</hi> (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1988), 43.
                            This text is attributed to Dionysius in a “larger collection of epistles
                            of the Greek church which served as one of the sources of that church’s
                            canon law” (Kraemer, <hi rend="italic">Maenads</hi>, 397); Kramer found
                            the text in Charles Feltoe,
                            <hi rend="italic">Dionusiou Leipsana: The Letters and Other Remains of Dionysius of Alexandria </hi>(Cambridge:
                            Cambridge University Press, 1904); ANF translation 6:94-96.</p></note>
                    The text described here is a letter attributed to Dionysius and written to the
                    Bishop Basilides, which comes to be part of later Greek canon law. It responds
                    to a question about whether “women in the time of their separation” can “enter
                    the house of God” by saying, “I do not think that, if they are believing and
                    pious women, they will themselves be rash enough in such a condition either to
                    approach the holy table or to touch the body and blood of the Lord…. For to
                    pray… in whatever condition a person may be” is blameless, but “the individual
                    who is not perfectly pure [<hi rend="italic">katharas</hi>] both in soul and in
                    body, shall be prohibited from approaching the holy of holies.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> Kraemer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Maenads</hi>, 43; Canon II (PG 10,
                        1272-77).</p></note> In this case, bodily purity is expected of Christians
                    approaching the divine.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The West Syrian <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>, a compilation of earlier
                    sources, reveals that the <hi rend="italic">Didascalia</hi>’s narrator did not
                    have the final say, such as in letters attributed to the anti-Chalcedonian
                    bishop-saints Timothy II (Aelurus) of Alexandria (d. 477) and Severus of
                    Antioch. The <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> says that Timothy II answered the
                    question, “If a woman… on the day of baptism is menstruating [<hi rend="italic"
                        >hawā lāh kepsā</hi>], is it lawful for her to be baptized or shall she be
                    postponed?” with the response, “It is lawful that she should be postponed until
                    she becomes purified [<hi rend="italic">metdakya</hi>].”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"> Timothy Aelurus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi>, in Arthur Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Synodicon in the West Syrian Tradition</hi>, CSCO
                            367-8, 375-6 (Leuven: Secrétariat du Corpus SCO, 197506), I.141/139,
                            cited by volume followed by the pages of Vööbus’s Syriac/English edition
                            and translation.</p></note> Similarly, he replied to the question, “If a
                    faithful woman is menstruating [<hi rend="italic">hawā lāh kepsā</hi>], is it
                    lawful for her to approach in order to approach the holy mysteries [<hi
                        rend="italic">rāze qadiše</hi>] on the same day or not?” with the answer,
                    “It is unlawful that she approach before she becomes purified.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"> Timothy Aelurus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.141/139).</p></note> The <hi
                        rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> attributes similar teachings to Severus in an
                    otherwise unattested letter to Caesaria: “it is not lawful for a woman who has
                    the usual flow of blood [<hi rend="italic">marditā dadmā</hi>] to participate
                        [<hi rend="italic">teštawtap</hi>] in the divine communion [<hi
                        rend="italic">šawtaputa alāhāitā</hi>] until the coming of blood
                        stops.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Severus of Antioch, <hi rend="italic">Letter to Caesaria</hi> (Vööbus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.144/141).</p></note> These
                    anti-Chalcedonian texts continue the tradition of separating bodies with
                    discharges from Christian rituals until they were cleansed.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> not only contains
                    similar expectations but also explains how they should be understood. As
                    Sebastian Brock has summarized, this text appears to have originated in Greek in
                    the late fourth or late fifth century and was translated into Syriac in 686/7 by
                    a man named Jacob, usually identified as Jacob of Edessa, and it became part of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Sebastian Brock, “Testament of our Lord Jesus
                            Christ,” in <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the
                                Syriac Heritage: Electronic Edition</hi>, edited by Sebastian P.
                            Brock, Aaron M. Butts, George A. Kiraz and Lucas Van Rompay,
                            https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Testament-of-our-Lord-Jesus-Christ.
                        </p></note> It teaches about widows, “If she is menstruating [<hi
                        rend="italic">kepsā</hi>], she shall abide in the temple [<hi rend="italic"
                        >haiklā</hi>], but shall not approach the altar [<hi rend="italic"
                        >madbḥā</hi>]. This is not because she has pollution [<hi rend="italic"
                        >saibutā</hi>], but in order that the altar shall have honor. Afterwards
                    when she fasts and washes herself,” she can approach.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.24/45). It is worth noting that this
                            text is unusual in signaling the pollution with the term <hi
                                rend="italic">saibutā</hi> rather than <hi rend="italic"
                            >ṭamutā</hi>, the former of which appears in Marcus Jastrow’s dictionary
                            of early rabbinic Hebrew, but is not in Brown, Driver, Briggs’s
                            dictionary of Biblical Hebrew. </p></note> A section on catechumens
                    teaches that if a woman is menstruating when the time comes for baptism, she
                    should wait an extra day for washing and cleansing.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.32/52); cf., Apostolic Tradition of
                            Hippolytus of Rome 20.6.</p></note> Finally, its canons include a
                    variety of teachings about bodily purity and the Eucharist, teaching that if a
                    priest has a nightly emission, he can neither give nor receive the Eucharist
                    until he has fasted and washed; likewise anyone of the <hi rend="italic">bnai
                        qyama</hi> in a similar condition cannot approach (the altar) without
                    fasting and washing, and a widow or any woman who is menstruating [<hi
                        rend="italic">kepsā</hi>] “shall not approach the communion of the mysteries
                        [<hi rend="italic">šawtaputā d-rāze</hi>] until she is cleansed and
                        washed.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.40/57).</p></note> As in the section
                    on widows, the text again stresses that these regulations are not because the
                    bodies are polluted [<hi rend="italic">saibutā</hi>] but for the honor of the
                        altar.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ</hi> (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.40/57).</p></note> Despite their
                    protests, these Christian texts recall biblical injunctions regarding pollution
                    by precluding bodies with discharges from having contact with, or even proximity
                    to, the altar and the Eucharist. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Like the letter attributed to Severus, John of Tella also kept menstruating women
                    from his liturgical rituals. While John normally allowed deaconesses to give the
                        <hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi> to children under five years old,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"> John of Tella,
                                <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #32 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.218/202); note that this is #33 in
                            Nau, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 16, who depended on the Syriac
                            edition in Thomas Lamy, <hi rend="italic">Dissertatio de Syrorum Fide et
                                Disciplina in Re Eucharistica</hi> (Louvain: Vanlinthout, 1859),
                            61-97.</p></note> he taught that for a deaconess, “It is not permissible
                    when she is menstruating to enter (the sanctuary) or draw near to the <hi
                        rend="italic">qudšā</hi>,” which he equates in a nearby passage with the <hi
                        rend="italic">qurbānā</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and
                                Answers</hi> #36 (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>
                            I.218/203); Nau, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 16; note is Question 37
                            in Nau. Note that the two Syriac editions allude to menstruation through
                            versions of a scriptural phrase: Lamy’s text retains “the way of women”
                                [<hi rend="italic">urḥā d-neše</hi>] (cf., Gen 18.11, 31.35 <hi
                                rend="italic">derek našim</hi>), and Vööbus’s “that of women” [<hi
                                rend="italic">hai d-neše</hi>]. The text conflates <hi rend="italic"
                                >qudšā</hi> with <hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi> in John of Tella,
                                <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #33 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.218/203).</p></note> This highlights
                    John’s concern for the physical purity of those approaching the divine. He is
                    asked with respect to the laity, “Is it permitted for a laywoman who is
                    menstruating [<hi rend="italic">hai d-neše</hi>] to enter the temple of God in
                    order to pray?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">
                            John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #31 (Vööbus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.218/202); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 16; note that it is Question 32 in Nau. I have
                            replaced Nau’s and Vööbus’s translation of “young woman” or “girl” with
                            “laywoman” because the Syriac in both Lamy and Vööbus is <hi
                                rend="italic">‘ālmāyātā</hi> not <hi rend="italic">‘alimtā</hi>.
                            Lamy’s Syriac edition with Latin translation commented on this word and
                            suggested the spelling <hi rend="italic">‘ālmāyātā</hi> in the
                            manuscript should be emended for ease of translation (Lamy, 86), and Nau
                            thus translated it as “young girl”; Vööbus retains the Syriac <hi
                                rend="italic">‘ālmāyātā</hi> without emendation but translates it as
                            “girl” without further comment. </p></note> John replies, “When she is
                    menstruating it is permitted for her to enter the temple of God to pray, but the
                    canons order her not to participate [<hi rend="italic">teštautap</hi>] in the
                    holy mysteries.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #31
                            (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.218/202); Nau, <hi
                                rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 16; note that it is Question 32 in Nau.
                        </p></note> In this case, John provides an explanation that echoes the
                    reason given in the <hi rend="italic">Testament of our Lord</hi>, explaining
                    that the delay is “not because of her pollution [<hi rend="italic">ṭamutā</hi>],
                    but out of honor for the divine mysteries,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                        n="47"><p rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions
                                and Answers</hi> #31 (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>
                            I.218/202); Nau, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 16; note that it is
                            Question 32 in Nau. Note that the women criticized in the <hi
                                rend="italic">Didascalia</hi> explicitly purport to consider
                            themselves impure: “according to your opinion you are unclean [<hi
                                rend="italic">ṭamutā</hi>]” and “do not observe these things, nor
                            think that it is uncleanness”
                            (<hi rend="italic">Didascalia </hi>26 [Vööbus,
                            259/242, 261/243]). </p></note> a tradition that continued according to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> in the seventh-century teachings of Jacob
                    of Edessa (d. 708), who translated the <hi rend="italic">Testament of our
                        Lord</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Jacob taught regarding the <hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi>, “She who has
                            the way of women shall not participate until the flow of blood stops –
                            if there is no emergency – and until she has washed, not because of
                            uncleanness but out of honor for the <hi rend="italic">qudshe</hi>”:
                            Jacob of Edessa, <hi rend="italic">Questions</hi> #24 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.262/239). Such concerns are also
                            visible in the Greek Chalcedonian late seventh-century <hi rend="italic"
                                >Questiones et responsiones</hi> of Anastasius of Sinai. </p></note>
                    Thus while these anti-Chalcedonian traditions explicitly claimed that bodily
                    impurity was not the reason for the separation, the end result is that these
                    same bodies were kept from participating in the central ritual that defined
                    membership in the orthodox community until they were cleansed.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"> As Derek Krueger has shown,
                            “sixth-century liturgists associated liturgical participation with the
                            shaping of affect and identity”: Derek Krueger, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Liturgical Subjects: Christian Ritual, Biblical Narrative, and the
                                Formation of the Self in Byzantium</hi> (Philadelphia: University of
                            Pennsylvania Press, 2014), 106.</p></note> John’s and Severus’s writings
                    suggest that these traditions that originated with ritual pollution came to
                    inform representations of heresy in some of the same ways that rabbis used them
                    to regulate interactions with Gentiles.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1shepardson.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Mind the Gap: Regulating Orthodoxy and Heresy</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The conflicts over the legitimacy of the Council of Chalcedon (451) were complex
                    and long-lived, and leaders from all sides wrote vigorously through the late
                    fifth and sixth centuries to argue for their own legitimacy and against the
                    heretical views of their opponents. The plethora of references in the writings
                    of Philoxenos, John Rufus, John of Tella, and Severus to concerns about the
                    unacceptable social and ritual mixing of people with different doctrinal
                    commitments suggests that these authors hoped to inspire greater vigilance,
                    separation, and distinction among some who currently socialized together.
                    Anti-Chalcedonian writings discouraged not only ritual submission to, but often
                    any social contact whatsoever with anyone outside of anti-Chalcedonian
                    orthodoxy. While all of these writers called for greater separation between
                    their anti-Chalcedonian listeners and their opponents, and reminded them of the
                    eternal reward or punishment they would earn through their zeal (or lack
                    thereof), they did not all describe the danger that heresy posed in the same
                    terms. Most often their writings reflect a concern that anti-Chalcedonian
                    Christians might be persuaded to abandon their doctrine and join the
                    Chalcedonian communion. John of Tella is unusual in encouraging the perception
                    of heresy as a physical contamination. Severus’s letters offer a glimpse of the
                    anxiety that such a notion could inspire. Under Justin I, anti-Chalcedonian
                    Christians faced a variety of pressures to join the Chalcedonian church, from
                    ridicule and peer pressure, to financial and material incentives (or
                    disincentives), to arrest and physical violence. Contrasting these authors’
                    different representations of Christian heresy suggests that the notion of heresy
                    as pollution could have been particularly useful in encouraging
                    anti-Chalcedonian zeal among John of Tella’s followers, scattered as doctrinal
                    and ritual minorities in the borderlands of the Roman and Sasanian empires,
                    during the years of his exile.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Philoxenos, John Rufus, and Severus, for example, all warned their audience about
                    the dangers of mingling with their doctrinal opponents, but primarily because
                    they might be persuaded to abandon their anti-Chalcedonian commitment.
                    Philoxenos wrote, “Do not associate [<hi rend="italic">ḥulṭānā</hi>] with any of
                    the heretics of the Persians, by communion [<hi rend="italic">šawtāputā</hi>],
                    or by being eager to ask after their welfare, or by gifts.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text"> Philoxenos, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Particular Chapters [that We Should Anathematize Each One Who is
                                Nestorian]</hi> in British Library, MS Add. 14529, ff. 66v-68r, ed.,
                            and with a partial English transl. E. A. Wallis Budge, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Discourses of Philoxenos, Bishop of Mabbôgh, A.D. 485-519</hi>,
                            vol. 2 (London, 1894), Syriac cxx-cxxiii, English xxxvii-xxxix, at
                            xxxix, cxxii. </p></note> As Philoxenos wrote with hope at the end of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Letter to Abu Ya‘fur</hi>, “My Lord God will deliver us
                    just as all the children of the holy church, from association [<hi rend="italic"
                        >ḥulṭānā</hi>] and communion [<hi rend="italic">šawtāputā</hi>] with” the
                        heretics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Philoxenos, <hi rend="italic">Letter to Abu Ya‘fur</hi>, published as
                            “Lettre de Philoxène de Mabbûg au phylarque Abū Ya‘fūr de Hīrtā de
                            Bētna’mān (selon le manuscrit no 115 du fond patriarcat de Šarfet),” ed.
                            and French transl. Paul Harb, <hi rend="italic">Melto</hi> 3.1-2 (1967):
                            183-222, at 221.</p></note> In other cases Philoxenos criticized those
                    who had relaxed their zeal on account of temporal presents,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text"> Philoxenos, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Letter concerning Zeal</hi>, in A. Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Syriac
                                and Arabic Documents Regarding Legislation Relative to Syrian
                                Asceticism</hi> (Stockholm: Estonian Theological Society in Exile,
                            1960), 51-54, at 53. </p></note> and praised others who had resisted the
                    impulse to do the same.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Philoxenos, <hi rend="italic">First Letter to the
                                Monks of Beth Gaugal</hi>, in Arthur Vaschalde, ed. and trans. <hi
                                rend="italic">Three Letters of Philoxenus, Bishop of Mabbogh
                                (485-519): Being the Letter to the Monks, the First Letter to the
                                Monks of Beth-Gaugal, and the Letter to Emperor Zeno</hi> (Rome:
                            Tipografia della R. Accademia dei Lincei, 1902), 105-18, 146-62, at 106.
                        </p></note> These examples imply that the danger of interacting was that the
                    Christian might cease to be zealous in defending anti-Chalcedonian doctrine and
                    might acquiesce, perhaps on account of pressure or bribes, to Chalcedonian
                    teachings and rituals. The danger, then, was not so much the physical body of
                    the heretic that threatened to pollute the orthodox body, but the potential of
                    the heretic to persuade the orthodox to abandon Philoxenos’s teachings and
                    Eucharist community.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severus and John Rufus likewise often focused on the danger of social
                    interactions for the person’s doctrinal commitment more than their bodily
                    purity. Severus addressed the noblewoman Caesaria by writing, “you ask whether
                    some of the orthodox are doing well in not communicating [<hi rend="italic"
                        >meštawtpein</hi>] with heretics but listening to the reading of the holy
                    Gospel or even staying during the time of the mysterious prayers but not
                    communicating in the rites that are being performed.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ep</hi>. 6.4.10, 306/272, in Ernest Brooks, ed. and trans., <hi
                                rend="italic">The Sixth Book of the Select Letters of Severus of
                                Antioch</hi>, vol. 2.1-2 (London: Williams and Norgate, 1904). This
                            citation represents Book 6, section 4, letter 10, followed by the pages
                            in Brooks’s Syriac/English edition and translation.</p></note> Echoing
                    Paul’s concerns in 1 Corinthians 5, Severus cited 2 John 10-11, and concluded,
                    “If then it is not right to offer even a bare greeting to those who bring
                    another teaching and do not teach the orthodox faith, how can one communicate in
                    prayers and in lessons or in any other such things with such as these?”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 6.4.10, 306-7/272-3.</p></note> Severus
                    relied on Titus 3.10, which he believed was written by the apostle Paul, to
                    argue, “Paul the wise commands us to turn away even the very face from those who
                    are in servitude to heresy,” leading Severus to conclude, “One therefore who
                    comes together [<hi rend="italic">metkanaš</hi>] with the guilty renders
                    themself subject to the same judgment.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 6.4.10,
                            307/273.</p></note> John Rufus presented a similar story that he
                    attributed to the famous ascetic Peter the Iberian who had a vision that he was
                    condemned after he unthinkingly returned a greeting in a tight alleyway where he
                    could not escape the notice of a former friend who had since joined the
                    “heretical” Chalcedonian community.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> John Rufus, <hi rend="italic">Plerophoriae</hi> 76
                            (PO 8.130-132). Although he does not engage with ancient medical
                            perceptions of illness and contagion and conflates them with pollution,
                            Jan-Eric Steppa has written about the rhetoric of John Rufus’s striking
                            “notion of heresy as a contagious disease that could affect even the
                            most holy and orthodox of God’s servants – a dangerous kind of pollution
                            that spread into the society of the orthodox through even the slightest
                            contact.” See Jan-Eric Steppa, “Heresy and Orthodoxy: The
                            Anti-Chalcedonian Hagiography of John Rufus,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Christian Gaza in Late Antiquity</hi>, ed. Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony
                            and Aryeh Kofsky, 89-106 (Boston: Brill, 2004), 103.</p></note> These
                    authors worked to keep their congregants from joining Chalcedonian services and
                    from associating with heretical Christians more generally, but in order that
                    they would not be persuaded to join the Chalcedonian church or even so they
                    would not be thought to have joined the competing communion. For these leaders,
                    proximity to heretics was dangerous because a person might be persuaded to
                    abandon their zeal and become (or appear to become) associated with the
                    communion of the heretics.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">John of Tella, on the other hand, encouraged Christians to keep their distance
                    from heretics and objects that had been used in heretics’ rituals in ways that
                    echo his teachings about keeping menstruating bodies from the orthodox altar,
                    suggesting a different kind of contamination. Some of John of Tella’s writings,
                    on the one hand, demonstrate that he considered the material objects of
                    heretics’ rituals, like Christian altars and the Eucharist itself, to be
                    contaminated and thus inappropriate for orthodox rituals. John’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi>, for example, have a series of
                    questions about what a priest should do if anything related to an altar or the
                    Eucharist should arrive in a community from outside. If its heretical past is
                    certain, then John’s answer is clear: “It is not allowed to put an altar [<hi
                        rend="italic">madbḥa</hi>] of the heretics of Persia in the sanctuary [<hi
                        rend="italic">beit qudšā</hi>],” although he does allow it to be placed
                    elsewhere for common or ordinary service [<hi rend="italic">ḥšaḥtā
                        šḥimtā</hi>].<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and
                                Answers</hi> #43 (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>
                            I.220/204). An earlier French translation is also in François Nau,
                            <hi rend="italic">Canons et les Résolutions Canoniques de Rabboula, Jean de Tella, Cyriaque d’Amid, Jacques d’Edesse, Georges des Arabes, Cyriaque d’Antioche, Jean III, Théodose d’Antioche, et des Perses </hi>(Paris:
                            P. Lethielleux, 1906), 18. John here seems most concerned about Persian
                            Christians whom we might associate with the Church of the East, though
                            he also was in exile because of his rejection of Chalcedonian
                            Christianity; anti-Chalcedonian leaders like John conflated both groups
                            as heretics who inappropriately followed the teachings of
                        Nestorius.</p></note> The same text also includes the question, “If one
                    finds a portable altar [<hi rend="italic">ṭablitā</hi>] and some people say they
                    heard from others that it was consecrated by the orthodox, what should one do
                    with it? Should one believe those who heard that it belonged to the orthodox
                    when they are trustworthy people, or rather leave it and not serve with it, as
                    if it came from the heretics?” to which John of Tella gives the answer, “As I
                    said above for the altars [<hi rend="italic">madbḥe</hi>] that come from the
                    Persians, the same one (Mar Abas) ordered certainly not to celebrate [the
                    Eucharist] on them. If, however, there are trustworthy people who say they heard
                    from others that a portable altar [<hi rend="italic">ṭablitā</hi>] was
                    consecrated by the orthodox, one can use it for the sanctuary without however
                    celebrating on it.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and
                                Answers</hi> #47 (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi>
                            I.220-1/205); Nau, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 19. </p></note>
                    Regarding the ritual components of heretics’ liturgy, John also teaches, “One
                    must flee their Eucharist [<hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi>] as a deadly
                        drug,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> John
                            of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #44 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.220/205); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 18. On the language of the deadly drug, see Ephrem,
                                <hi rend="italic">Azym</hi>. 19; Ignatius, <hi rend="italic">Letter
                                to the Trallians</hi> 6.</p></note> and if they should somehow
                    acquire a heretic’s Eucharist, “The <hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi> that is found
                    on [the altars (<hi rend="italic">madbḥe</hi>)] will be placed in an honorable
                    spot or hidden in the ground or in the wall, lest the orthodox approach
                        it.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> John
                            of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #46 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.220/205); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 18-9. </p></note> These material objects are in John’s
                    view compromised by their association with heresy and must be separated from
                    orthodox bodies and rituals.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">On the other hand, John of Tella also had a strong sense of the importance of
                    physical separation between people he considered to be heretics and those he
                    considered orthodox. In his <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, John of Tella wrote,
                    “Promise … to anathematize all heresies,” and he instructed his audience not to
                    “associate with their adherents.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi> #1
                            (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.147/143, 147/143-4); Nau,
                                <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 21.</p></note> John’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> say, “The canon does not allow
                    eating with heretics, whether the person makes the sign of the cross or not, and
                    even if it would be out of the necessity of a journey;”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi
                                rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #23 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.215/201); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 14; this is Question 24 in Nau.</p></note> and he
                    further stated, “If it is not necessary for lack of tombs for the faithful, it
                    is not permitted to inter a faithful in the tombs of the heretics.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text"> John of Tella,
                                <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #27 (Vööbus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.215/201); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 14-5; this is Question 28 in Nau. The question that
                            follows is also about burials. </p></note> John did make an exception
                    that he seemed to feel was unavoidable to allow greetings between heretics and
                    orthodox, “provided,” he said, “that we don’t give them a kiss on the
                        mouth.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">
                            John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Questions and Answers</hi> #25 (Vööbus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.216/201); Nau, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Canons</hi>, 14; this is Question 26 in Nau. On drawing community
                            boundaries through kissing, see Michael Penn,
                            <hi rend="italic">Kissing Christians: Ritual and Community in the Late Ancient Church </hi>(Philadelphia:
                            University of Pennsylvania Press, 2005).</p></note> In his <hi
                        rend="italic">Canons to Priests</hi>, John again instructed, “do not eat
                    with the heretics,” and this time he added, “and do not receive any blessing [or
                    gift], because their hand is the hand of the lawless one”; nor should the
                    orthodox give any blessing/gift to a heretic.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66"
                        n="66"><p rend="footnote text"> John of Tella, <hi rend="italic">Canons</hi>
                            #2 (Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon</hi> I.147/144); Nau, <hi
                                rend="italic">Canons</hi>, 21. </p></note> John thus sent a clear
                    message that his audience should avoid heretics as much as possible, in addition
                    to the material objects of their rituals. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">While John thus encouraged orthodox bodies to distance themselves from heretics
                    just as an orthodox altar was kept from contact with menstruating bodies, it is
                    through Severus’s letters explicitly about heresy as pollution that the fear and
                    anxiety that such rhetoric could produce becomes clear. The experience of the
                    global pandemic of 2020, and the anxiety that accompanies our efforts to
                    practice social distancing in order to avoid contracting the potentially fatal
                    virus, suggests that John’s rhetoric could likewise have caused anxiety as his
                    audience tried to avoid contamination, especially in a context where notoriously
                    unstable definitions of “orthodoxy” and “heresy” made it difficult to be certain
                    who posed a risk.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Barry notes that church leaders often used this
                            challenge in order to argue for their own role as specialists in
                            “diagnosing” heresy (Barry, “Diagnosing Heresy”).</p></note> Severus’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi> 44 and 45 confirm that anti-Chalcedonian
                    Christians in the early sixth century were indeed anxious that they might
                    unwillingly and unwittingly contract heresy in the manner of a bodily pollution.
                    Unlike John, however, Severus addressed these concerns in 516-7 as a bishop in
                    residence under the sympathetic emperor Anastasius. In this context, Severus
                    tried to calm his congregants’ worries rather than stoking their fears.
                    Severus’s discussion of the pollution associated with heresy highlights the
                    effects that John’s language could have had on his community.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Two letters from Severus, written in Greek but preserved in Syriac, provide
                    evidence that at least some of his congregants understood heresy to be a
                    dangerous form of pollution. In <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> 45, Severus
                    addressed congregants’ concern that Christians might find themselves polluted by
                    heresy despite their vigilance, a fear that suggests that such rhetoric could be
                    a powerful motivator for creating and maintaining clear boundaries between
                    competing doctrinal communities. Severus tried to assuage their concern by
                    explaining that despite their fears, the orthodox Eucharist would not be
                    polluted if the name of an earlier church leader whom Severus considered a
                    heretic was included in the liturgical diptychs that were read during the
                        service.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text"> On
                            Severus’s liturgy, see: G.C. Cuming, “The Liturgy of Antioch in the Time
                            of Severus (513-518),” in <hi rend="italic">Time and Community: In Honor
                                of Thomas Julian Talley</hi>, ed. J.N. Alexander, 83-103
                            (Washington, D.C.: Pastoral Press, 1980). </p></note> Severus supported
                    this opinion by means of Cyril of Alexandria’s defense of keeping Theodore of
                    Mopsuestia’s name in the liturgical diptychs despite the fact that, in Severus’s
                    words, Theodore “was the putrid sources of the hateful and putrid tenets of
                        Nestorius.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Severus, <hi rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 45 (PO 12.314). Translations of this
                            text in this essay are revised from the Syriac edition and English
                            translation by E.W. Brooks in PO 12.</p></note> Cyril allowed Theodore’s
                    name, Severus argued, “in order not to give an opportunity to those who wished
                    to disturb the church,” and even though the name was read, Christians did not
                    believe “that thereby some pollution [<hi rend="italic">ṭamutā</hi>] and stain
                        [<hi rend="italic">mumā</hi>] of heresy was inflicted on the <hi
                        rend="italic">qurbānā</hi> of the orthodox,” nor did such names “cause any
                    injury to the whole fullness of the body of Christ.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ep</hi>. 45 (PO 12.314).</p></note> Severus insisted, “They are not
                    acting rightly who think that our <hi rend="italic">qurbānā</hi> is not pure on
                    account of the names of those who have already died and who have fallen into
                    heretical tenets and have not been removed from the sacred tablets.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 45 (PO 12.313); cf. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ep</hi>. 44 (PO 12.310-12).</p></note> Contrary to what his audience
                    seemed to believe, Severus denied that the name of a heretic would contaminate
                    his orthodox Eucharist and thereby threaten the orthodoxy of his
                    congregants.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severus addressed the same concern in <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> 44, in this
                    case acknowledging that if orthodox Christians ever found themselves utterly
                    surrounded by those who were “sick [<hi rend="italic">krihā</hi>] with heresy,”
                    then they should indeed avoid that “dead body” that could “pollute” the purity
                    of their communion [<hi rend="italic">šawtaputā</hi>], using forms of <hi
                        rend="italic">ṭamutā</hi> throughout to refer to polluting.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 44 (PO 12.310-11). Translations of this text
                            in this essay are revised from the Syriac edition and English
                            translation by E.W. Brooks in PO 12.</p></note> But as with pollution in
                    water, the larger the body of clean water, the less harm a small pollutant could
                    do, so that “if the holding of the orthodox faith and an anathema of every
                    heresy reigns in the churches, and whole regions and provinces, and populous
                    churches confess one uncorrupted confession, then names that are thought to
                    pollute are inundated by the multitude of streams” and thus are safely diluted;
                    while ideally, Severus agreed, “no particle of a dead body” (that is, people
                    infected with heresy) “should be introduced even into a large quantity of water,
                    if perchance it in fact happens to be introduced, it is overpowered by the
                    quantity of streams and swamped by the quantity of cleansing.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ep</hi>. 44 (PO 12.311). </p></note> This echoes language in <hi
                        rend="italic">Epistle</hi> 45 where Severus argued, “when churches of many
                    provinces and of dioceses are held in one bond of faith, and resemble fair
                    fountains and pools and cisterns of water, the dead thing which has the property
                    of polluting if it fall cannot injure, for it is swamped by the flow, and by the
                    abundance of many streams.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 45 (PO
                            12.315). </p></note> In these letters, Severus explicitly described
                    those “infected with heresy” as the equivalent of a “dead body” that early
                    biblical traditions taught could pollute the purity of those who came into
                    contact with it. Writing from the comfort of his episcopal see, Severus argued
                    that the orthodox majority could accommodate and tolerate small amounts of the
                    pollution of heresy without harm.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Despite Severus’s pastoral efforts to calm congregants’ fears, though, he
                    nevertheless does in both of these letters equate heresy with a form of ritual
                    impurity, in this case from contact with a corpse rather than from menstruation
                    or the like. While Severus is willing to negotiate the degree of the threat that
                    heresy posed in a sea of orthodoxy, in <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi> 45 he
                    nevertheless maintains that it poses a significant risk when the proportions are
                    reversed. Severus wrote, “when certain people who are by themselves, in a church
                    for instance, or in one city or in monasteries perhaps make mention of the names
                    of those who are under suspicion and of dead men, like the similarly small
                    amount of water contained in a vessel they are polluted by the mention, as if
                    something dead had fallen in.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Severus, <hi rend="italic">Ep</hi>. 45 (PO
                            12.314-5). </p></note> While the contamination that Severus describes
                    happens aurally through hearing a heretic’s name as part of the liturgy, the
                    fact that he compares it to the ritual pollution of corpse impurity suggests
                    both that it could cause a person to be separated from the orthodox altar and
                    that its effects were independent of the hearer’s consent. Both factors would
                    have raised the stakes for orthodox Christians to take responsibility for
                    keeping themselves far from any manifestation of heresy on account of the risks
                    it could pose.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">John of Tella’s implied comparison of menstruating bodies and heretics is made
                    explicit in Severus’s letters and his congregants’ expectation that heresy could
                    contaminate the liturgy and its participants. John’s fervent interest in
                    increasing anti-Chalcedonian Christians’ vigilance in performing a sharp
                    distinction and separation between the bodies, rituals, and other material
                    manifestations of orthodoxy and heresy would have been magnified during his
                    exile during the hostile reign of Justin I. Unlike John of Tella, Severus
                    addressed the relation of heresy and pollution from his powerful see of Antioch
                    where the reign of Anastasius buoyed his belief that anti-Chalcedonian
                    Christianity represented the one universal church. In this more favorable
                    context, Severus took pains to reassure his nervous audience that any pollution
                    that might come through hearing a heretic’s name in the liturgy would be diluted
                    to safe levels by the flood of orthodoxy represented in his church, even if they
                    should still remain vigilant in less favorable circumstances. Severus’s writings
                    thus concurrently suggest the anxiety that associating heresy with the
                    contact-contagion of ritual pollution could inspire as well as his pastoral
                    decision to try to alleviate rather than foster his congregants’ fear.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n1shepardson.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">John of Tella is interesting not only for his sixth-century teachings about
                    menstruating bodies and other bodily discharges, but especially for how those
                    ideas interact with his understanding of the dangers of Christian heresy.
                    Rhetoric about ritual pollution and concerns about contamination were familiar
                    to these late antique Christians, particularly through the continuing
                    conversations about bodily purity and the Eucharist. John of Tella instructed
                    that orthodox Christians must not use the contaminated altars or oblations of
                    the heretics in their own rituals, that menstruating bodies should be separated
                    from the divine until they had been cleansed, and that orthodox bodies should
                    avoid heretics at meals, greetings, or burials, all of which his audience might
                    well have heard with concerns of pollution in mind. John’s teachings about
                    heretics parallel rabbinic teachings that hoped to preserve community identity
                    by equating Gentile bodies with those with abnormal genital discharges. Although
                    Severus did not want his congregants to worry about his own church services, he
                    and his audience both associated heresy with bodily pollution and his letters
                    reveal that this correlation caused such anxiety that Severus addressed the
                    issue twice in an effort to allay his congregants’ fears.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The global pandemic of 2020 provides a unique opportunity to grapple with the
                    effects of sixth-century anti-Chalcedonian warnings that heresy had the
                    potential to convey pollution to orthodox bodies – the anxiety that such a risk
                    could produce, and the behavioral responses that it could lead to if Christians
                    made an effort to avoid contamination. John asked his audience to put physical
                    distance between orthodox Christians and heretical objects and people. Since the
                    pollution of heresy shared with COVID-19 the possibility that those who carried
                    it might sometimes be indistinguishable to the layperson from those who did not,
                    John urged rigorous zeal in the face of imperial opposition. His rhetoric
                    encouraged anyone who wanted to be assured of their eternal salvation to
                    separate themselves physically from Chalcedonian and Church of the East altars
                    and neighbors. In a context where people of various doctrinal and ritual
                    commitments intermingled on a regular basis,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76"
                        n="76"><p rend="footnote text"> See, for example, Jack Tannous, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Making of the Medieval Middle East: Religion,
                                Society, and Simple Believers</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University
                            Press, 2018), e.g., 65-7, 105.</p></note> John of Tella strove to
                    preserve anti-Chalcedonian Christianity in challenging circumstances from his
                    nearly twenty years in exile. John seems to have hoped that rhetoric about
                    heresy that echoed concerns about bodily pollution could increase the perceived
                    risks and potential consequences of socializing with heretics, thereby
                    increasing his followers’ devoted vigilance to maintaining anti-Chalcedonian
                    orthodoxy in his absence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Allen, Pauline and C.T.R. Hayward. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Severus of Antioch</hi>. New York: Routledge, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl>Balberg, Mira. <hi rend="italic">Purity, Body, and Self in
                        Early Rabbinic Literature</hi>. Berkeley: University of California Press,
                    2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Barry, Jennifer. “Diagnosing Heresy: Ps.-Martyrius’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Funerary Speech for John Chrysostom</hi>.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >JECS</hi> 24.3 (2016): 395-418.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bitton-Ashkelony, Brouria and Aryeh Kofsky. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Monastic School of Gaza</hi>. Boston: Brill, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian. “Testament of our Lord Jesus Christ.” In
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage:
                        Electronic Edition</hi>. Edited by Sebastian P. Brock, Aaron M. Butts,
                    George A. Kiraz and Lucas Van Rompay.
                    https://gedsh.bethmardutho.org/Testament-of-our-Lord-Jesus-Christ.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian and Brian Fitzgerald. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Two Early Lives of Severos, Patriarch of Antioch</hi>. Liverpool: Liverpool
                    University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cuming, G.C. “The Liturgy of Antioch in the Time of Severus
                    (513-518).” In <hi rend="italic">Time and Community: In Honor of Thomas Julian
                        Talley</hi>. Ed. J.N. Alexander, 83-103. Washington, D.C.: Pastoral Press,
                    1980.</bibl>
                <bibl>D’Alton, John and Youhanna Youssef, eds. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Severus of Antioch: His Life and Times</hi>. Boston: Brill, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Debié, Muriel. “Désigner l’adversaire: La guerre des noms
                    dans les controverses.” In <hi rend="italic">Les controverses religieuses en
                        syriaque</hi>, ed. Flavia Ruani,
                    307-48<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Paris: Geuthner, 2016. </bibl>
                <bibl>Fonrobert, Charlotte Elisheva. <hi rend="italic">Menstrual
                        Purity: Rabbinic and Christian Reconstructions of Biblical Gender</hi>.
                    Stanford University Press, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ghanem, Joseph R. “The Biography of John of Tella (d. AD
                    537) by Elias, Translated from the Syriac with a Historical Introduction and
                    Historical and Linguistic Commentaries.” PhD Dissertation, University of
                    Wisconsin, 1970.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hayes, Christine. <hi rend="italic">Gentile Impurities and
                        Jewish Identities: Intermarriage and Conversion from the Bible to the
                        Talmud</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Horn, Cornelia. <hi rend="italic">Asceticism and
                        Christological Controversy in Fifth-Century Palestine</hi>. New York: Oxford
                    University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jouanna, Jacques. “Air, miasma and Contagion in the Time of
                    Hippocrates and the Survival of Miasmas in Post-Hippocratic Medicine.” In <hi
                        rend="italic">Greek Medicine from Hippocrates to Galen: Selected
                    Papers</hi>. Ed. Philip van der Eijk, trans. Neil Allies, 121-36. Boston: Brill,
                    2012.</bibl>
                <bibl>Klawans, Jonathan. <hi rend="italic">Impurity and Sin in
                        Ancient Judaism</hi>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2000). </bibl>
                <bibl>Kofsky, Aryeh. “Severus of Antioch and Christological
                    Politics in the Early Sixth Century.” <hi rend="italic">Proche-Orient
                        Chrétien</hi> 57 (2007): 43-57.</bibl>
                <bibl>Koltun-Fromm, Naomi. <hi rend="italic">The Hermeneutics of
                        Holiness: Ancient Jewish and Christian Notions of Sexuality and Religious
                        Community</hi>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2010.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kraemer, Ross. <hi rend="italic">Maenads, Martyrs, Matrons,
                        Monastics: A Sourcebook on Women’s Religions in the Greco-Roman World</hi>.
                    Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1988.</bibl>
                <bibl>Krueger, Derek. <hi rend="italic">Liturgical Subjects:
                        Christian Ritual, Biblical Narrative, and the Formation of the Self in
                        Byzantium</hi>. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menze, Volker. <hi rend="italic">Justinian and the Making
                        of the Syrian Orthodox Church</hi>. New York: Oxford University Press,
                    2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menze, Volker. “The <hi rend="italic">Regula ad
                        Diaconos</hi>: John of Tella, his Eucharistic Ecclesiology and the
                    Establishment of an Ecclesiastical Hierarchy in Exile.” <hi rend="italic">Oriens
                        Christianus</hi> 90 (2006): 46-8.</bibl>
                <bibl>Menze, Volker and Kutlu Akalin. <hi rend="italic">John of
                        Tella’s Profession of Faith: The Legacy of a Sixth-Century Syrian Orthodox
                        Bishop</hi>. Gorgias Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl>Millar, Fergus. “The Evolution of the Syrian Orthodox
                    Church in the Pre-Islamic Period: From Greek to Syriac?” <hi rend="italic"
                        >JECS</hi> 21.1 (2013): 43-92. </bibl>
                <bibl>Moss, Yonatan. <hi rend="italic">Incorruptible Bodies:
                        Christology, Society, and Authority in Late Antiquity</hi>. Berkeley:
                    University of California Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nutton, Vivian. “Did the Greeks Have a Word for It?
                    Contagion and Contagion Theory in Classical Antiquity.” In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Contagion: Perspectives from Pre-Modern Societies</hi>. Ed. Lawrence Conrad
                    and Dominik Wujastyk, 137-62. Burlington, Vt: Ashgate, 2000.</bibl>
                <bibl>Penn, Michael. <hi rend="italic">Kissing Christians: Ritual
                        and Community in the Late Ancient Church</hi>. Philadelphia: University of
                    Pennsylvania Press, 2005.</bibl>
                <bibl>Roux, René. <hi rend="italic">L’Exégèse Biblique dans les
                        Homélies Cathédrales de Sévère d’Antioche</hi>. Studia Ephemerides
                    Augustinianum 84. Rome: Institutum Patristicum Augustinianum, 2002.</bibl>
                <bibl>Steppa, Jan-Eric. “Heresy and Orthodoxy: The
                    Anti-Chalcedonian Hagiography of John Rufus.” In <hi rend="italic">Christian
                        Gaza in Late Antiquity</hi>. Ed. Brouria Bitton-Ashkelony and Aryeh Kofsky,
                    89-106. Boston: Brill, 2004.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tannous, Jack. <hi rend="italic">The Making of the Medieval
                        Middle East: Religion, Society, and Simple Believers</hi>. Princeton:
                    Princeton University Press, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl>Torrance, Iaian. <hi rend="italic">Christology after
                        Chalcedon: Severus of Antioch and Sergius the Monophysite</hi>. Eugene, OR:
                    Wipf &amp; Stock, 1988.</bibl>
                <bibl>Van Rompay, Lucas. “Severus, Patriarch of Antioch
                    (512-538), in the Greek, Syriac, and Coptic Traditions.” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 8 (2008): 3-22.
                </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
