<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Manichaeism and the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi></title>
                <title type="sub">Syriac "Christianities" in Late Antique Mesopotamia</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Timothy</forename>
                        <surname>Pettipiece</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Carleton University (Ottawa)</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2pettipiece</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Timothy Pettipiece</author>
                        <title level="a">Manichaeism and the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>: Syriac "Christianities" in Late Antique Mesopotamia</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2Pettipiece.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="411" to="452">411-452</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="5"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Manichaeism</term>
                    <term>Mani</term>
                    <term>Apocrypha</term>
                    <term>Early Christianity</term>
                    <term>Sassanian Empire</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        
            <front>
                <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
            <head>Abstract:</head>
            <p xml:lang="en">The recently published Syriac Revelation of the Magi has proven to
                be a remarkable addition to the corpus of early Christian apocryphal literature.
                This unique amplification of the traditional Nativity narrative recounts the Magi’s
                encounter with a “star-child” who leads them from their homeland in the far east to
                the birth of Jesus at Nazareth, where the polymorphic nature of Christ is revealed
                along with his message of universal salvation. Interestingly, the Revelation of the
                Magi contains several important points of contact with early Manichaean texts. This
                paper will examine what those shared motifs might tell us about the common milieu
                out of which both Manichaeism and the Revelation of the Magi might have emerged. </p>
                </div>
            </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                <p rend="H Normal First">Over-familiarity with the biblical narrative often obscures
                    the strangeness of the tradition, attested by the <hi rend="italic">Gospel of
                        Matthew</hi>, that the infant Jesus was visited by a group of Persian
                    priests. Stranger still, if the term <hi rend="italic">magos</hi> is interpreted
                    as “sorcerer.” Either way, the idea that the birth of Jesus was attended by a
                    group of travelling magicians or Zoroastrian clergy is an odd detail to be
                    included in the Christian foundation narrative. Unfortunately, Matthew’s account
                    is short on specifics, other than that they were led to Bethlehem from “the
                    east” by some astral event—an equally exotic motif—and that they brought with
                    them some rather impractical gifts. Over time, however, Christian tradition has
                    tried to fill in the blanks. Centuries of commentary and apocryphal mythmaking
                    have transformed the <hi rend="italic">magoi</hi> of the gospel account into the
                    “Three Wise Men” (or “Kings”) prominently featured in nativity scenes and
                    Christmas carols throughout many parts of the Christian world.</p>
                <p>In fact, the tradition of the magi developed in two divergent directions. Whereas
                    western Christian tradition saw them fashioned into Balthazar, Melchior, and
                    Gaspar—kings from Arabia, Persia, and India respectively—eastern Christians
                    identified twelve kings from “beyond the land of Nod.” One of the
                        “apocryphal”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">
                            While the utility of this term has been contested, it continues to be
                            used (albeit reluctantly) by various scholars as a way to demarcate an
                            important body of early Christian literature. For an extensive
                            discussion see <hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha: More Canonical
                                Scriptures, Volume I</hi>, ed. Tony Burke and Brent Landau (Grand
                            Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2016), xxii-xxiii.</p></note> texts that attests
                    to this eastern tradition is the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the
                        Magi</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Brent Landau has done a great service to the field of Early Christian
                            Studies by bringing increased attention to this hitherto practically
                            unknown Syriac text. Landau’s Harvard doctoral dissertation, under the
                            supervision of François Bovon, “The Sages and the Star-Child:An
                            Introduction to the Revelation of the Magi, An Ancient Christian
                            Apocryphon” (PhD diss., Harvard University, 2008) contains a re-edited
                            Syriac text along with English translation and contextual commentary. A
                            “popular” translation was published in 2010 by HarperCollins, <hi
                                rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi: The Lost Tale of the Wise
                                Men’s Journey to Bethlehem</hi>, while a summary of the text has
                            appeared in <hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha: More Canonical
                                Scriptures, Volume I</hi>, 19-38. </p></note> Although
                    conventionally dated to sometime between the late 2<hi rend="superscript"
                        >nd</hi> and early 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century CE<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> The text appears
                            to have undergone several redactional stages, such as the possible later
                            addition of the Judas Thomas epilogue (<hi rend="italic">New Testament
                                Apocrypha I</hi>, 20-23). A much shorter version of the story is
                            found in a 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century Latin commentary on
                            Matthew, known as the <hi rend="italic">Opus Imperfectum</hi>. While
                            some scholars, such as Duchesne-Guillemin, believed that both works drew
                            on a common source (<anchor xml:id="Hlk71635124"/><hi rend="italic"
                                >“</hi>Die Magier in Bethlehem und Mithras als Erlöser?”
                            <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morganländischen Gesellschaft </hi>111,
                            no. 2 (1961): 472), Landau has argued that the <hi rend="italic">Opus
                                Imperfectum</hi> is an abbreviation of a 4<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi>-century Greek version of the <hi rend="italic">Revelation
                                of the Magi</hi>, with the original Syriac version dated even
                            earlier to the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> or 2<hi
                                rend="superscript">nd</hi> century CE (<hi rend="italic">New
                                Testament Apocrypha I</hi>, 21-22). Moreover, thematic affinities
                            with other early Christian apocrypha texts also point to a 2<hi
                                rend="superscript">nd</hi>-3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> century
                            context
                            (<hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha I, </hi>22).
                        </p></note> and associated with the city of Edessa,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> Landau has asserted a partial
                            Edessene association for the text
                            (<hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha I, </hi>23),
                            but this is conjectural. It has become customary in scholarship to
                            highlight the role of Edessa in the emergence of Christianity in
                            Mesopotamia, largely due to the success of the Abgar legend, and to
                            associate early Syriac literary traditions with that locale. This view,
                            however, has been problematized by <anchor xml:id="Hlk71635234"/>David
                            Taylor (“The Coming of Christianity to Mesopotamia,” in
                            <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World, </hi>ed. Daniel
                            King [New York: Routledge, 2019], 68-87), who highlights the historical
                            unreliability of the traditional apostolic origin stories and advocates
                            for a more nuanced reconstruction of the origins of Syriac Christianity.
                            As for the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>, there is no
                            internal evidence that specifically links its origins to Edessa, other
                            than the emphasis on Thomas, which itself appears to be a later
                            addition. </p></note> the origins of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>remain
                    largely obscure. We find it preserved in the 8<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi>-century Syriac <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of Zuqnin</hi>,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> The text was
                            inserted into the world-chronicle by the author/compiler with no
                            commentary (Landau, <hi rend="italic">Sages and the Star-Child</hi>,
                            3-5). </p></note> as part of a world history. This text is remarkable in
                    several ways, not only does it offer an extensive and compelling amplification
                    of a key part of the Nativity story, but it also presents a decidedly
                    pluralistic concept of revelation, prophecy, and divine truth. </p>
                <p>According to the <hi rend="italic">Revelation</hi>’s account, the magi form part
                    of a long lineage of initiates from “land of Shir” (2.4) in the far east,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> For perceptions of
                            the far east in late antique literature, including the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Revelation of the Magi</hi>, see Annette Yoshiko Reed, “Beyond the
                            Land of Nod: Syriac Images of Asia and the Historiography of ‘The
                            West’,” <hi rend="italic">History of Religions</hi> 49, no. 1 (August
                            2009): 48-87.</p></note> who have preserved primordial revelations from
                    Adam and Seth in a remote mountain retreat. Praying in silence, they await the
                    appearance of a brilliant star that will outshine the heavens and lead them to
                    further divine knowledge. When the star finally appears after many generations,
                    it reveals itself as a polymorphic saviour and leads the magi on a fantastic
                    journey westward to Bethlehem just in time for the birth of Jesus.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> Early Christians
                            have put forward a variety of explanations for the appearance of a star
                            at the birth of Jesus (see Nicola Denzey, “A New Star on the Horizon:
                            Astral Christologies and Stellar Debates in Early Christian Discourse,”
                            in <hi rend="italic">Prayer, Magic, and the Stars in the Ancient and
                                Late Antique World,</hi> ed. Scott Noegel et al [Pennsylvania:
                            Pennsylvania State University Press, 2003], 207-221), although none are
                            as theologically developed as what is presented in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Revelation of the Magi</hi>. </p></note> After their return home,
                    the apostle Judas Thomas arrives and explains to them the true Christological
                    meaning of their experience. The magi are then baptized and given an apostolic
                    commission of their own.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See Landau’s full translation in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Revelation of the Magi</hi> and summary in
                            <hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha </hi>30-38.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>In-depth study of the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> has only just
                    begun and its relationship with other late antique religious traditions has yet
                    to be fully explored. Who wrote it and for what sort of audience or community
                    are questions that remain unanswered. As a starting point for further
                    contextualization, it should be noted that there are a number of passages in the
                    text that resonate with terminological and theological motifs found in the
                    surviving corpus of Manichaean literature. As such, this article will argue that
                    several key elements found in both the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the
                        Magi</hi> and Manichaean discourse are indicators of their emergence from a
                    shared historical and religious milieu within early Syriac Christianity. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>The Magi in Manichaean Literature</head>
                <p rend="H Normal First">Even though the figure of Zoroaster (Zarathustra) is
                    considered to be an important part of the Manichaean prophetic lineage—along
                    with the Buddha and Jesus—and Mani is sometimes presented as debating
                    Zoroastrian doctrines,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See Paul Dilley, “Also Schrieb Zarathustra? Mani
                            As Interpreter of the ‘Law of Zarades’” in Iain Gardner, Jason BeDuhn,
                            and Paul Dilley, <hi rend="italic">Mani at the Court of the Persian
                                Kings: Studies on the Chester Beatty "Kephalaia" Codex</hi> (Leiden:
                            Brill, 2015), 101-135.</p></note> the figure of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >magus</hi> is generally despised in early Manichaean texts due to the role
                    played by members of the Zoroastrian priesthood in the execution of Mani<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> See W. B.
                            Henning, “Mani’s Last Journey,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the School
                                of Oriental and African Studies</hi> 10, no.4 (1942): 941-953; see
                            also Iain Gardner, “Mani’s Last Days,” in Gardner, BeDuhn, and Dilley,
                                <hi rend="italic">Mani at the Court of the Persian Kings</hi>,
                            159-208.</p></note> and the persecution of his early movement. According
                    to the <hi rend="italic">Narrative of the Crucifixion</hi>, from the Manichaean
                        <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> codex:</p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block">When the Magi noticed how (people) asked: ‘Who, indeed, is
                    this person who has entered (the city)?,’ [(and how others) answered] them: ‘It
                    is Manichaios,”—when they heard [these (words), they shook] and were filled with
                    wrath. They went and accused [him] before Kardel (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲕⲁⲣⲇⲉⲗ</foreign>). Kardel himself told it to the
                    assessor (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲥⲩⲛⲕⲁⲑⲉⲇⲣⲟⲥ</foreign>). Then Kardel and
                    the assessor went [and proclaimed] the accusations to the counsellor (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲙⲁⲅⲓⲥⲧⲱⲣ</foreign>). The counsellor himself told it
                    to the king. When he heard these (words), … Then he sent and called for my lord.
                    On the lord’s day (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲕⲩⲣⲓⲁⲕⲏ</foreign>) he entered
                    Belapat (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲃⲏⲗⲁⲡⲁⲧ</foreign>)” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Homilies</hi> 45.11-20).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Nils Arne Pedersen, <hi rend="italic">Manichaean
                                Homilies</hi>, Corpus Fontium Manichae-orum, Series Coptica II
                            (Turnhout: Brepols, 2006).</p></note></p>
                <p>The “Kardel” mentioned in this Coptic text is none other than the (im)famous
                    Zoroastrian high priest Kartir, who boasted about his persecution of various
                    religious communities in the Sassanian Empire in Middle Persian inscriptions
                    from the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd </hi>century CE,
                    including the Manichaeans themselves.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> D. N. MacKenzie, “A Zoroastrian Master of
                            Ceremonies,” in <hi rend="italic">W.B. Henning Memorial Volume</hi>, ed.
                            Mary Boyce, and Ilya Gershevitch (London: Lund Humphries,
                        1970).</p></note></p>
                <p>As a result, the Zoroastrian priestly class is subsequently portrayed in an
                    extremely negative light by Manichaean authors, particularly those writing in
                    the late 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> and early 4<hi rend="superscript"
                        >th</hi> century CE Mesopotamian context, for whom the traumas of
                    persecution were still deeply felt. For instance, in the Manichaean <hi
                        rend="italic">Sermon on the Great War</hi>, also from the Coptic <hi
                        rend="italic">Homilies</hi> codex, the biblical figure of Babylon is
                    presented as the personification of Evil and as the enemy of righteousness in
                    the world. Specifically, we are told, she has “reigned in the fire [of the]
                    magi” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲁⲥⲣ̅ ⲣ̅ⲣⲟ ϩⲛ̅ ⲧⲥⲉⲧⲉ ϩⲛ [ⲛ̅ⲧⲉ
                        ⲙ̅]ⲙⲁⲅⲟⲩⲥⲁⲓⲟⲥ</foreign>)
                        (<hi rend="italic">Homilies </hi>11.17-18),<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> Pedersen, <hi
                                rend="italic">Manichaean Homilies</hi>. </p></note> who are also
                    referred to as “rulers in the world” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲛ̅ⲣ̅ⲣⲟ
                        ϩⲙ̅ ⲡⲕⲟⲥⲙⲟⲥ</foreign>) (<hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> 26.2) in the text’s
                    originally Sassanian context. Similarly, in the Coptic Manichaean <hi
                        rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi>, the magi (<foreign xml:lang="cop"
                            >ⲙ̅ⲙⲁⲅⲟⲩⲥⲁⲓⲟⲥ</foreign>) are classed among the “lawless sects” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲛ̅ⲇⲟⲅⲙⲁ ⲛ̅ⲁⲛⲟⲙⲟⲥ</foreign>) (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Psalm-Book</hi> 15.7) and are called “impious men, mad and godless” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲛ̅ⲁⲥⲉⲃⲏⲥ ⲉⲧⲗⲁⲃⲉ ⲛ̅ⲁⲧⲛⲟⲩⲧⲉ</foreign>)
                        (<hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>15.11).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> The
                            <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>further castes
                            them as “brothers of the Jews, the murderers of Christ” (<hi
                                rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi> 15.11-12) in an effort to make the
                            death of Mani more closely resemble that of Jesus. </p></note></p>
                <p>Moreover, on a more scriptural level, Manichaeans had little to no interest in
                    the Nativity story, since they generally denied the physical birth of Jesus. In
                    the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century CE anti-Manichaean disputation known
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Acts of Archelaus</hi>, Mani is presented as writing to
                    a pious Mesopotamian man named Marcellus in order to win him as a convert to his
                    new religion, saying: </p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block">I am completely amazed at how they can dare to call God the
                    maker and creator of Satan and his evil deeds. Would that their vacuity had
                    reached only this far and they did not say that the only-begotten Christ, ‘who
                    descended from the Father’s bosom,’ was the son of a woman called Mary, and was
                    born of flesh and blood and all the other pollutions of women” (<hi
                        rend="italic">Acts of Archelaus</hi> V).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Hegemonius, <hi rend="italic">Acta Archelai
                                (The Acts of Archelaus)</hi>, trans. Mark Vermes (Louvain: Brepols,
                            2001), 42; Hegemonius, <hi rend="italic">Acta Archelai</hi>, GCS 16
                            (Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs, 1906).</p></note></p>
                <p>This position is also affirmed by the “Psalms to Jesus” from the Manichaean <hi
                        rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi>, which state that Jesus “was not born in a
                    womb corrupted” (<hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi> 53.23).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> C.R.C. Allberry, <hi
                                rend="italic">A Manichaean Psalm-Book, Part II</hi> (Stuttgart:
                            Kohlhammer, 1938). </p></note> As such, in surviving sources, Manichaean
                    authors display no real interest in the magi as playing a role in the story of
                    birth of Jesus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">
                            On the origins of Jesus in the Manichaean myth see Majella Franzmann,
                            <hi rend="italic">Jesus in the Manichaean Writings </hi>(London:
                            T&amp;T Clark, 2003), 51-59.</p></note> other than for polemical
                    purposes. For them, Jesus has a much larger function in their cosmogonic myth as
                    an avatar of the ruler of the light realm and his chosen champion against the
                    powers of darkness. Augustine, in fact, in his dispute with the North African
                    Manichaean Bishop Faustus, referenced the Magi as he mocked this Manichaean
                    notion of the cosmic Christ:</p>
                <p rend="H Quote Block">You are not ashamed, however, to speak ill of the star by
                    which the Magi were led to adore the infant Christ. And yet you do not locate
                    your false Christ, the son of your false first man, under a star that bears
                    witness to him, but you say that he is imprisoned in all the stars. For you
                    believe that he was mingled with the princes of darkness in that war by which
                    that first man of yours fought against the nation of darkness, with the result
                    that the world was fashioned out of the very princes of darkness who were
                    captured in such a mingling. Hence, these sacrilegious ravings also force you to
                    say that Christ—no longer your savior but someone for you to save when you eat
                    those things and belch—is confined and imprisoned not only in heaven and in all
                    the stars but also in the earth and in all the things that are born from it (<hi
                        rend="italic">Contra Faustum</hi>, 2.5).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18"
                        n="18"><p rend="footnote text"> Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Answer to
                                Faustus, a Manichean</hi>, trans. Roland Teske, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Works of Saint Augustine: A Translation for the 21</hi><hi
                                rend="italic superscript"
                            >st</hi><hi rend="italic"> Century</hi> (NY: New
                            City Press, 2007), 73-74;
                            <hi rend="italic">Sancti Aureli Augustini, </hi>ed.
                            Zycha, CSEL 25.1 (Vienna, 1891), 258.</p></note></p>
                <p>Unbeknownst to Augustine, the astral messiah he ridicules here is not entirely
                    dissimilar to the saviour figure portrayed in the <hi rend="italic">Revelation
                        of the Magi</hi>. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>MANICHAEAN MOTIFS IN THE <hi rend="italic">REVELATION OF THE MAGI</hi></head>
                <p rend="H Normal First">Given the apparent lack of interest that Manichaeans would
                    have had in the Nativity story generally and the “magi” specifically, it seems
                    surprising that a text such as the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>which seeks
                    to amplify and expand upon their story should contain elements that appear to
                    resonate strongly with several important concepts<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> This comparative exercise is
                            based on the fact that both the
                            <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>and
                            early Manichaean texts derive from the same geographic and linguistic
                            milieu, as well as being more or less contemporaneous with each other.
                            As mentioned above, the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> is
                            thought to have been composed originally in Syriac sometime during the
                                3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>-4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                            centuries CE, whereas the earliest expressions of Manichaean theological
                            discourse would have been in Syriac (the language of Mani himself)
                            during that same period. Some of the earliest surviving Manichaean
                            literature in Greek and Coptic shows significant traces of this Syriac
                            substratum (particularly the “Psalms of Thomas” and the <hi
                                rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi>, see below). In fact, the
                            Manichaean material from Kellis contains multilingual texts including
                            Coptic-Syriac glossaries (Iain Gardner,
                            <hi rend="italic">Kellis Literary Texts, Vol. I </hi>[Oxford:
                            Oxbow, 1996], 101-131). For these reasons, as well as the limits of the
                            author’s linguistic abilities, this study is restricted primarily to
                            Manichaean texts in Coptic and Greek. Further work would be needed to
                            trance these elements further afield in Manichaean literature from
                            Central Asia. </p></note> from Manichaean tradition.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> It should be noted, also,
                            that this study seeks to compare a single text (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Revelation of the Magi</hi>) to a parallel religious “discourse”
                            attested by multiple (often fragmentary) sources. Even thought Mani went
                            to great lengths to record his teachings in writing, this “canonical”
                            tradition has been mostly lost. The theological framework articulated by
                            Mani must be pieced together from a variety of sources, some of which
                            show significant evidence of redaction and development by later
                            Manichaean interpreters (see Timothy Pettipiece, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Pentadic Redaction in the Manichaean Kephalaia</hi> [Leiden: Brill,
                            2009]), as well as a degree of regional variation (see Jason BeDuhn,
                            <hi rend="italic">The Manichaean Body in Discipline and Ritual </hi>[Baltimore:
                            John Hopkins University Press, 2000], 1-24). At most we can speak of
                            early Manichaean tradition(s), as opposed to what Mani himself may or
                            may not have specifically taught. Still the proximity of these sources
                            to one another warrants juxtaposition. </p></note>
                </p>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>1. Father of Greatness</head>
                    <p>The first element that stands out is the terminology used by the author of
                        the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> to describe God. According
                        to the text, as the magi reflected upon their ancient ritual tradition, they
                        knelt before the “Cave of Treasures of Hidden Mysteries” <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܥܪܬ ܓܙܐ ܕܐܪܙܐ
                            ܟܣܝܐ</foreign>) and “prayed and worshiped in silence, without a sound, to the <hi
                            rend="italic">Father of that heavenly majesty</hi> that is ineffable and
                        infinite forever” (<hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> 5.7).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Landau, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>, 43.</p></note> Aside
                        from the (likely incidental) fact that Mani is said to have composed
                        scriptural texts known as the
                        <hi rend="italic">Treasure of Life </hi>and the <hi
                            rend="italic">Mysteries</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> According to John C. Reeves, terms like
                                <hi rend="italic">treasury </hi>and
                                <hi rend="italic">treasure of life </hi>“pepper
                                the lexicon of Syro-Mesopotamian gnosis” (“Reconsidering the
                                ‘Prophecy of Zardūšt’,” in <hi rend="italic">A Multiform Heritage:
                                    Studies in Early Judaism and Christianity in Honor of Robert A.
                                    Kraft</hi>, ed. Benjamin G. Wright (Atlanta: Scholars Press,
                                1999), 167-182) as commonly shared motifs. </p></note> the Syriac
                        phrase translated by Landau as “Father of Heavenly Majesty”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text"> A slight
                                variant occurs at
                                <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>3.5:
                                “Greatness of the Father” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܒܘܬܗ ܕܐܒܐ</foreign>).</p></note> can also be
                        rendered as “Father of Greatness” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܒܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܐ</foreign>) (<hi rend="italic">Revelation
                            of the Magi</hi> 5.7). As it happens, the “Father of Greatness” is the
                        primary name for the ruler of the Manichaean light-realm used in Syriac,
                        Greek, and Coptic Manichaean texts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> Sebastian Brock has already signaled the
                                importance of this association in 2006 (“An Archaic Syriac Prayer
                                over Baptismal Oil,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica </hi>41
                                [2006]: 12), although without further comment. See Theodore bar
                                Khonai’s Syriac account of the Manichaean cosmogony in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Book of Scholia</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Liber scholiorum, </hi>ed.
                                Addai Scher; CSCO 69; [Louvain: Imprimerie orientaliste L. Durbecq,
                                1954], 313.15). Also attested in Greek as ὁ πατἠρ τοῦ μεγέθους in
                                the
                                <hi rend="italic">Seven Chapters Against Manichaeans </hi>3
                                (see Lieu, Fox, and Sheldon <hi rend="italic">Greek and Latin
                                    Sources on Manichaean Cosmogony and Ethics</hi>, Corpus Fontium
                                Manichaeorum, Series Subsidia VI [Turnhout: Brepols, 2010], 119),
                                and as
                                    <foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲡⲓⲱⲧ ⲛⲧⲉ ⲧⲙⲛⲧⲛⲁϩ </foreign>in
                                Coptic sources, including the (as yet) unpublished portions of
                                Mani’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Living Gospel </hi>from the
                                    <hi rend="italic">Synaxeis</hi> codex (Wolf-Peter Funk, <hi
                                    rend="italic">personal communication</hi>). See Aloïs van
                                Tongerloo, “The Father of Greatness,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">Gnosisforschung und Religionsgeschichte. Festschrift fūr Kurt Rudolph zum 65. Geburtstag, </hi>ed.
                                Holger Preißler und Hubert Seiwert (Marburg: diagonal-Verlag, 1994),
                                329-342 and Paul Van Lindt, <hi rend="italic">The Names of
                                    Manichaean Mythological Figures: A Comparative Study on
                                    Terminology in the Coptic Sources</hi> (Wiesbaden: Otto
                                Harrassowitz, 1992), 3-16.</p></note> A similar figure, the “Lord of
                        Greatness,” (<hi rend="italic">mara d-rabuta</hi>) is also mentioned in
                        Mandaean texts,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> See Mandaean <hi rend="italic">Book of
                                    John</hi> 66.13; 67.41 (Charles G. Häberl and James F. McGrath,
                                eds., <hi rend="italic">The Mandaean Book of John: Text and
                                    Translation</hi> [Berlin: De Gruyter, 2020]).</p></note> and as
                        there is a close relationship between Manichaean and Mandaean literature,
                        Geo Widengren suggested that there must be some link between the
                        <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>and those
                            traditions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                                rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Iranisch-semitische Kulturbegegnung in parthischer Zeit </hi>(Köln:
                                Westdeut-scher Verlag, 1960), 74.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>While the use of the title “Father of Greatness” is most often associated
                        with Manichaeism, it is not unthinkable that such an epithet formed part of
                        a shared Aramaic religious vocabulary in late antique Mesopotamia, as it is
                        also attested in a handful of post-Manichaean sectarian theologies.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text"> Theodore bar
                                Khonai describes the teaching of a certain John of Apamea (not the
                                influential monastic spiritual author), in which the sole God is
                                referred to as the “Father of Greatness” (<hi rend="italic">Book of
                                    Scholia</hi> 11.76)
                                (<hi rend="italic">Théodore bar Koni: Livre des scholies (recension de Séert) I. Mimrè I-V, </hi>trans.
                                Robert Hespel and René Draguet, CSCO, Scriptores syri 187 (Louvain:
                                Peeters, 1981), 248. He also presents the doctrine of the (5<hi
                                    rend="superscript">th</hi> cent CE?) sectarian leader Batai, who
                                promoted a kind of modified dualism whereby Good and Evil were
                                derived from the “Father of Greatness” (<hi rend="italic">Book of
                                    Scholia</hi> 11.85 (<hi rend="italic">Théodore bar Koni</hi>,
                                256-257).</p></note> Still, given the title’s close association with
                        Manichaean discourse it is difficult to imagine it being used by an author
                        who wasn’t sympathetic to Mani’s ideas or seeking to appeal to them in some
                        way. </p>
                    <p>Similarly, the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> also refers to
                        God as the “Lord of All” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܐ ܟܠ</foreign> )
                        (32.3), a title which is found is found in Manichaean sources (“Lord of All”
                        (<foreign xml:lang="cop">[ⲡϫⲁⲓ̈ⲥ] ⲙ̅ⲡⲧϩⲏⲣϥ) </foreign>as
                        an alternate name for the “Father of Greatness” (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Homilies</hi> 47.13-14; <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia</hi> 40.10; 156.6).
                        Once again, it is difficult to determine if this reflects a distinctively
                        Manichaean usage or is derived from a common theological lexicon.</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>2. Revealed Books and Primordial Prophets</head>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> also puts an important
                        emphasis on revealed knowledge being recorded in books. Seth, we are told,
                        set his wisdom “down in a book” and, in fact, “from him a book appeared in
                        the world for the first time” (3.2-3). Noah, in turn, preserved the “books
                        of Seth about the majesty (i.e. greatness) of the Father” (3.5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܒܐ ܕܪܒܘܬܐ</foreign>)
                        and took them into the Ark. These books were then subsequently preserved in
                        the ancient tradition of the magi (3.6). </p>
                    <p>With this idea, too, we find parallels in Manichaean tradition. Whereas Mani
                        is said to have included Buddha, Zoroaster, and Jesus in his list of
                        prophetic predecessors, some early Manichaean texts also insert a
                        pre-Noachid lineage going back to the biblical figure of Seth(el).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"> This sort of
                                biblical lineage is found in a wide array of Manichaean and
                                anti-Manichaean sources, see Michel Tardieu, <hi rend="italic">Le
                                    manichéisme</hi> (Paris: Presses universitaires de France,
                                1981), 20-22. Moreover, the idea of “Sethian” <hi rend="italic"
                                    >gnosis</hi> is a well-established trope in apocryphal
                                literature, see A. F. J. Klijn, <hi rend="italic">Seth in Jewish,
                                    Christian, and Gnostic Traditions</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1977). A
                                discussion of a so-called “Prayer of Sethel” forms the basis of
                                <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia </hi>chapter 10
                                (42.24-43.21). This connection to Seth is particularly notable in
                                light of the fact that the “abbreviated” version of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>story,
                                found in the <hi rend="italic">Opus Imperfectum</hi>, is said to be
                                derived from an “apocryphal book in the name of Seth” <anchor
                                    xml:id="Hlk71719073"/>(Alexander Toepel, “The Apocryphon of
                                Seth,” in <hi rend="italic">Old Testament Pseudepigrapha: More
                                    Noncanonical Scriptures</hi>, vol. 1, ed. Bauckham, Davila, and
                                Panayotov [Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 2013], 33-39).</p></note> For
                        example, in <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia</hi> Chapter 1 “On the Coming of the
                        Apostle” Mani is presented as articulating a sequence of apostolic
                        predecessors “from Sethel [the first] born son of Adam up to Enosh, along
                        with [Enoch]; [from] Enoch [up] to Sem [the] son of [Noah …” (<hi
                            rend="italic">Kephalaia</hi> 12.10-12).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29"
                            n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> Polotsky, H.-J. and A. Böhlig, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Kephalaia (I): 1. Hälfte [Lieferung 1-10]</hi>.
                                Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 1940. See also the litany from
                                <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>179.</p></note>
                        Seth is also listed in the Manichaean
                        <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>as part of a litany
                        of biblical and apostolic figures embodying the ideal of “endurance” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ϩⲩⲡⲟⲙⲟⲛⲏ</foreign>) (142.4), and there is even a
                        passage from a so-called Sethian book quoted in the hagiographical account
                        of Mani’s life preserved in the Greek <hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani
                            Codex</hi>, where Seth(el) recounts a vision of a luminous entity: “I
                        opened my eyes and I saw before my face an [angel] whose [brightness] I
                        could not describe [for he was] nothing other than lightning” (CMC 50).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text"> Iain Gardner
                                and Samuel Lieu, <hi rend="italic">Manichaean Texts from the Roman
                                    Empire</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004), 55;
                                Albert Henrichs and Ludwig Koenen,
                                <hi rend="italic">Der Kölner Mani-Kodex: Über das Werden seines Liebes </hi>(Opladen:
                                Westdeutscher Verlag, 1988), 32-33.</p></note> Earlier in the same
                        text Adam is quoted as receiving a command from “Balsamos, the greatest
                        Angel of Light” to “receive from me and write these things I reveal to you
                        on the purest papyrus which is not perishable or liable to worms” (CMC 49).
                        A similar episode occurs in the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the
                            Magi</hi>, where we are told:</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">Adam instructed Seth his son about … [and about the
                        revelation] of the light of the star and about its glory, because he [saw]
                        it in the Garden of Eden when it descended and came to rest over the Tree of
                        Life; and it illuminated the entire (garden) before Adam transgressed
                        against the commandment of the Father of heavenly majesty (i.e. greatness)
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܒܐ ܕܪܐܒܘܬܐ ܥܠܝܬܐ</foreign>)” (6.2). </p>
                    <p>As such, in both the <hi rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi> and the <hi
                            rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> we have accounts of revelatory
                        encounters with luminous beings in the Garden of Eden which are then
                        recorded in primordial holy books. In both contexts these episodes are used
                        as a means to establish their protagonists’ divine authority as part of a
                        chain of true prophecy traced back to the biblical forefathers Adam and
                            Seth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Nicholas Baker-Brian, <hi rend="italic">Manichaeism: An Ancient
                                    Faith Rediscovered</hi> (London: T&amp;T Clark, 2011),
                                50-51.</p></note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.3" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>3. Polymorph Messiah</head>
                    <p rend="H Normal First">Mani’s notion of prophetic succession was also linked
                        to the periodic appearance of an entity he called the “Light-Mind”
                        (essentially a sort of Manichaean Logos) via “apostles of light” in various
                        times and places. Most notably, Mani is quoted as stating in a discourse
                        given to Sassanian King Shapur I that “Apostles of God have constantly
                        brought wisdom and deeds in successive times.”<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> As quoted by 11<hi
                                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century Islamic scholar al-Biruni in
                                his <hi rend="italic">Chronology of Ancient Nations</hi> (see John
                                C. Reeves, <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena to a History of Islamicate
                                    Manichaeism</hi> (Sheffield: Equinox, 2011), 102.</p></note>
                        Similarly, the Manichaean <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia</hi> equates “all the
                        apostles who are on occasion sent to the world” to farmers” (9.24-25),
                        comparing their periodic appearance with the agricultural cycle of sowing
                        and reaping. According to John C. Reeves, Mani would have likely inherited
                        this idea of a cyclical apostolate from the Elchasaites, a Mesopotamian sect
                        among whom he is reported to have spent his early life.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"> Tardieu, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Le manichéisme</hi>, 9-12; Baker-Brian, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Manichaeism</hi>, 47-48; Samuel N. C. Lieu, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Manichaeism in the Later Roman Empire and Medieval
                                    China</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 1992), 35-50.</p></note>
                        According to the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>-century CE Christian
                        heresiological treatise attributed to Hippolytus,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> Hippolytus’ authorship is
                                disputed. See <hi rend="italic">Refutation of All Heresies</hi>,
                                trans. M. David Litwa, <hi rend="italic">Writings from the
                                    Greco-Roman World 40</hi> (Atlanta: SBL Press, 2016),
                                xxxiii-xlii.</p></note> certain devotees of a <hi rend="italic">Book
                            of Elchasai</hi>: </p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">do not confess one Christ. Rather, they believe in a
                        single Christ above who transmigrates numerous times into numerous bodies
                        and was recently incarnated in Jesus. Likewise, he is sometimes born from
                        God, while at other times he becomes spirit. Sometimes he is born from a
                        virgin, at other times not. Later on, he continues his never-ending
                        transmigration into bodies and is manifested in many different bodies at
                        various times. They also use incantations and baptisms in addition to their
                        confession by the elements. They plume themselves on their knowledge of
                        astronomy, astrology, and magic; and they call themselves “knowers of the
                        future” (<hi rend="italic">Refutation of All Heresies</hi> 10.29.2).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Refutation of All Heresies</hi>, 739. See John C.
                                Reeves,
                                <hi rend="italic">Heralds of That Good Realm: Syro-Mesopotamian Gnosis and Jewish Traditions </hi>(Leiden:
                                Brill, 1996), 8; A. F. J. Klijn and G. J. Reinink,
                                <hi rend="italic">Patristic Evidence for Jewish-Christian Sects </hi>(Leiden:
                                Brill, 1973), 122-123</p></note></p>
                    <p>In the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent. CE, Epiphanius similarly stated
                        that the Elchasaites believed Christ “was created and that he appears time
                        and again…he was formed for the first time in Adam and he puts off the body
                        of Adam and assumes it again whenever he wished” (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Panarion</hi> 53.1.8).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Reeves, <hi rend="italic">Heralds of That Good
                                    Realm</hi>, 8; Klijn and Reinink, <hi rend="italic">Patristic
                                    Evidence</hi>, 196-197.</p></note> The same idea is also found
                        in the Pseudo-Clementine <hi rend="italic">Homilies,</hi> which state that
                        Christ “changed his forms along with his names from age to age” (<foreign xml:lang="gr">ἀπ’ ἀρχῆς
                        αἰῶνος ἅμα τοῖς ὀνόμασιν μορφὰς ἀλλάσσων τὸν αἰῶνα</foreign>) (3.20),<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text"> Rehm,
                                    ed. <hi rend="italic">Die Pseudoklementinen I: Homilien</hi>
                                (Berlin: Akademie, 1992), 64. </p></note> and where the idea of the
                        polymorphic “True Prophet” is traced back to what some scholars have
                        described as a “Jewish-Christian” source document from the 3<hi
                            rend="superscript">rd</hi> century CE.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                            n="38"><p rend="footnote text"> See
                                <hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha, Vol. 2, </hi>ed.
                                Schneemelcher, (Louisville: WJK Press, 2003), 488-492, where the
                                resonances with Manichaean and Mandaean tradition are
                            noted.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The idea that the saviour has appeared periodically in many forms<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"> Landau
                                discusses the topic of the polymorphic Christ and universal
                                reve-lation in his dissertation on the <hi rend="italic">Revelation
                                    of the Magi</hi>, but only engages with a small sample of
                                possible cognate traditions (mostly biblical) (“Sages and the
                                Star-Child,” 249-255). A survey of (the fairly extensive) evidence
                                from both canonical and non-canonical sources is provided by Paul
                                Foster, “Polymorphic Christology: Its Origins and Development in
                                Early Christianity,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological
                                    Studies</hi> 58 (2007): 66-99. </p></note> also fits well with
                        what we find in the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>, which
                        states that Christ (the “star-child”) has appeared “in the world in a body,
                        and the forms with him are seen in every land, because he has been sent by
                        his majesty (i.e. greatness) (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܒܘܬܗ</foreign>) for the salvation and redemption of
                        every human being” (23.4). The “star-child” himself states “I am everywhere,
                        and there is no land in which I am not” (26.3). At the end of the text, when
                        Judas Thomas has brought the gospel back to the homeland of the magi,<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"> Thomas was
                                traditionally considered to have been an apostle to the east.
                                Eusebius mentions him going to Parthia in particular
                                (<hi rend="italic">History of the Church </hi>3.1).</p></note>
                        the apostle proclaims:</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">We glorify your sweet majesty (i.e greatness) (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܒܘܬܟ</foreign>),
                        your singularity in many personifications (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܨܘܦܐ</foreign>),<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="gr">πρόσωπον</foreign> in a
                                Christological sense, but also “<hi rend="italic">appearance,
                                    likeness</hi>” (R. Payne Smith, <hi rend="italic">A Compendious
                                    Syriac Dictionary</hi> [Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1903],
                                464a).</p></note> your glorious images (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܩܢܝܟ</foreign>)<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text"> From Greek εἰκών.
                            </p></note> that you have shown us, and the clothes that you have put on
                        for our sake, that we may be clothed in your powerful majesty. And by as
                        many names as you have been called, you are not in any one of them, for you
                        alone have known your great name and your majesty, and your exalted Father,
                        and no one else. And all these forms in which you were clothed and appeared
                        for our sake (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܠܝܢ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܐܣܟܝܡܐ ܕܠܒܫܬ ܘܐܬܚܙܝܬ ܡܛܠܬܢ</foreign>), that we might know
                        you, were because you loved us with your great mercy (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Revelation of the Magi</hi> 31.4-6). </p>
                    <p>This passage presents a remarkably open-ended Christology, even employing the
                        term πρόσωπον for the savior’s many manifestations and appearances. Such
                        radical inclusivism has startled modern readers and has been used to market
                        the text to the religiously interested reading public.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"> The back of the
                                dust-jacket to the mass-market edition published by HarperCollins
                                includes quotations from well-known scholars of early Christianity
                                such as Marvin Meyer and John Dominic Crossan about the
                                “astonishing,” “theologically sophisticated,” “unique,” and “radical
                                depth” of the text. The work no doubt appeals to those seeking
                                ancient precedent for an inclusivist and pluralist approach to
                                Christianity in a modern context. </p></note> Yet is such a
                        perspective really that unique or was it part of the text’s original
                        environment?</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.4" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>4. Thomas Twins </head>
                    <p rend="H Normal First">The apostle Thomas, it should be noted, is already
                        well-known for his many Manichaean associations,<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text"> Not only are there
                                “Thomas Psalms” in the Manichaean <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi>,
                                but strong associations with both the <hi rend="italic">Gospel of
                                    Thomas</hi> (Wolf-Peter Funk, “Einer aus Tausend, zwei aus
                                Zehntausend: Zitate aus dem Thomasevangelium in den koptischen
                                Manichaica,” in <hi rend="italic">For the Children, Perfect
                                    Instruction: Studies in Honor of Hans-Martin Schenke</hi>, ed.
                                Bethge et al. [Leiden: Brill, 2002], 67-94; J. Kevin Coyle, “The
                                Gospel of Thomas in Manichaeism?” in <hi rend="italic">Colloque
                                    international L’Évangile selon Thomas et les textes de Nag
                                    Hammadi, Québec, 29-31 mai 2003</hi>, ed. Louis Painchaud and
                                Paul-Hubert Poirier [Québec : Les Presses de l’Université Laval /
                                Louvain : Éditions Peeters, 2007], 75-91; Paul Allan Mirecki,
                                “Coptic Manichaean Psalm 278 and the Gospel of Thomas 37,” in <hi
                                    rend="italic">Manichaica selecta</hi>, ed. A. van Tongerloo and
                                S. Giversen [Louvain, 1991], 243-262) and the
                                <hi rend="italic">Acts of Thomas </hi>(A. F. J.
                                Klijn, “The So-Called Hymn of the Pearl [Acts of Thomas ch.
                                108-113],” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 14, no. 3
                                [1960]: 154-164).</p></note> and the polymorphic Christ<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> A list of
                                sources for the polymorphic Christ is provided by Henri-Charles
                                Puech, <hi rend="italic">EPHE Annuaire</hi> 73 (1964): 122-125. See
                                also Gedaliahu G. Stroumsa, “Polymorphie divine et transformations
                                d’un mythologème : L’Apocryphon de Jean et ses sources,” <hi
                                    rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 35, no. 4 (1981) :
                                412-434.</p></note> is explicitly attested in Manichaean tradition.
                        For example, the Manichaean <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi> states: “You
                        assumed different forms until you had visited all races” (42.31). In this
                        context, Mani himself is understood as being the last of those many forms,
                        since the psalmist refers to Christ as Mani’s “light-twin”
                        (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲡⲥⲁⲓ̈ϣ ⲛ̅ⲟⲩⲁⲓ̈ⲛⲉ) </foreign>(<hi
                            rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi> 42.22). The concept of the celestial
                        “twin” is central to Mani’s own prophetic and revelatory authority, as it is
                        for all of his alleged predecessors.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"
                                ><p rend="footnote text"> For a discussion of the widely attested
                                tradition of divine twinship in Late Antiquity see <anchor
                                    xml:id="Hlk72240148"/>Charles M. Stang,
                                <hi rend="italic">Our Divine Double </hi>(Cambridge,
                                MA: Harvard University Press, 2016).</p></note> Not surprisingly,
                        the notion of divine twinship is also invoked in the hymn at the end of the
                            <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>, where Judas Thomas
                        describes Christ as “twinned (ܡܬܐܡܬ) with the Spirit” (30.5) and as soaring
                        over the water “like your twin (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                            >ܒܪܬ ܙܘܓܗ</foreign> ) the Holy Spirit” (30.6).<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text"> Brock has pointed out the
                                early Syriac usage of the grammatical feminine for the Holy Spirit
                                (“An Archaic Syriac Prayer over Baptismal Oil,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica </hi>41
                                [2006]: 9). See also Susan Ashbrook Harvey, “Feminine Imagery for
                                the Divine: The Holy Spirit, the Odes of Solomon, and Early Syriac
                                Tradition,”
                                <hi rend="italic">St. Vladimir’s Theological Quarterly </hi>37
                                (2004): 1-29.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Paul-Hubert Poirier has argued that the “Thomas” to whom the “Psalms of
                        Thomas” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲛⲯⲁⲗⲙⲟⲥ ⲛⲑⲱⲙ</foreign>) are attributed
                        in the Manichaean
                        <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>could be based on a
                        word-play involving the Aramaic/Syriac term for twin (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܐܡܐ</foreign>),<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text"> Paul-Hubert
                                Poirier, “Une nouvelle hypothèse sur le titre des Psaumes manichéens
                                dits de Thomas”
                                <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha </hi>12 (2001) :
                                9-27. According to the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-century
                                Islamic scholar al-Nadim, when Mani was twenty-four years old, he
                                was visited by an angel named <hi rend="italic">“the Tawm</hi>,
                                which is a Nabatean word meaning ‘Companion’” (Bayard Dodge, ed.,
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Fihrist of al-Nadim</hi>, Vol 2 [New York:
                                Columbia University Press, 1970], 774).</p></note> which is cognate
                        with the verb “twinned” used in the final hymn from the
                        <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>(30.5).
                        Similarly, the Greek term σύζυγος, used as a loan-word in the same passage
                        (30.6), is used of Mani’s celestial twin throughout the Greek <hi
                            rend="italic">Cologne Mani Codex</hi>. Moreover, of all the liturgical
                        texts collected in the Manichaean <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi>, the
                        “Psalms of Thomas/Thōm” are the ones that most clearly reveal traces of an
                        Aramaic <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49"
                            n="49"><p rend="footnote text"> Peter Nagel,
                                <hi rend="italic">Die Thomaspsalmen des koptisch-manichäischen Psalmbuches </hi>(Berlin,
                                1980).</p></note> and display striking thematic and compositional
                        parallels with Mandaean liturgical texts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50"
                            n="50"><p rend="footnote text"> For example, “Psalm of Thomas 13” (T.
                                Säve-Söderbergh, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the Coptic Manichaean
                                    Psalm-Book</hi> [Uppsala, 1949] 119-120). The relationship
                                between Manichaean and Mandaean traditions is complex, as there are
                                multiple points of context between both textual corpora.
                                Säve-Söderbergh ultimately argued that the Manichaean “Psalms of
                                Thomas” were based on Mandaean prototypes (161). </p></note>
                        Therefore, it is not surprising that we might observe various points of
                        contact between the Manichaean Thomas-psalms and the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Revelation of the Magi</hi>. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>5. Little Child of Light</head>
                    <p rend="H Normal First">The <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> also
                        presents an episode that is strangely evocative of Steven Spielberg’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Close Encounters of the Third Kind</hi>. When the magi
                        have their epiphany in the Cave of Treasures, they see “(something) like the
                        hand of a small person draw near from the pillar and the star,” (12.3) and a
                        light-being “that appeared to us in the bodily form of a small and humble
                        human, and he said to us: ‘Peace to you’” (13.1). Surprised by this luminous
                        appearance, the light-being reassures the sages: “(do not doubt that)… it
                        appeared to you in the form of a small, humble, and unworthy human, because
                        indeed, the inhabitants of the world cannot bear to see the glory of the
                        only Son of the Father of majesty (i.e. greatness) (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܒܐ ܕܪܐܒܘܬܐ</foreign>)” (13.2). </p>
                    <p>Once again, the Manichaean “Psalms of Thomas” provide an important parallel.
                        There, the cosmic avatar of the heavenly father is described as the “the
                        Little One” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲡⲕⲟⲩⲓ</foreign>) who leaps into the
                        abyss to do battle with the powers of darkness (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Psalm-Book</hi> 204.22-27), and describe him as appearing as an “image
                        of light” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲁⲩϩⲓⲕⲱⲛ ⲛ̅ⲟⲩⲁⲓⲛⲉ</foreign>)<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"> See <hi
                                    rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> 31.4 mentioned above.
                            </p></note> to the powers of the world
                        (<hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>214.1-12) who are
                        driven mad by its brightness. In reverence, the powers then proclaim: “You
                        have come in peace, O Child of Brightness, that you shall be the illuminator
                        of our worlds” (<hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book</hi> 214.12-14). In fact,
                        “Jesus the Child” features prominently in the “Psalms of Thomas” as one
                        important aspect of the polymorphic Manichaean Christ.</p>
                    <p>As might be expected, a similar motif is also found in the Mandaean <hi
                            rend="italic">Book of John</hi>, although with a somewhat different
                        prophetological focus: </p>
                    <table rend="rules">
                        <row>
                            <cell style="text-align: left;"><p>A child was transplanted from on
                                    high</p><p>The priests had dreams.</p><p>An utter silence fell
                                    upon the Eulaeus,</p><p>He opened his mouth for evil,</p><p>He
                                    opened his mouth for evil, </p><p>“I saw in my night
                                    visions,</p><p><hi rend="italic">I didn’t sleep, rest or lie
                                        down,</hi>
                                </p><p><hi rend="italic">I didn’t sleep and I didn’t rest</hi>—
                                    </p><p>a fire rose, burning over elder</p><p>three lamps
                                    appeared, </p><p>… … …</p><p>A shooting star burst over
                                    Judaea,</p><p>The sun appeared at night,</p></cell>
                            <cell style="text-align: left;"><p>a secret was revealed in
                                    Jerusalem.</p><p>an utter silence fell upon Jerusalem.</p><p>and
                                    his lying lips.</p><p>saying to all the priests,</p><p>in my
                                    vision when I lay down—</p><p><hi rend="italic">and sleep did
                                        not overtake me in the night.</hi></p><p>that a star came to
                                    Elizabeth,</p><p>father Zechariah,</p><p>the sun set and the
                                    lamps shined forth.</p><p>a shooting star burst over
                                    Jerusalem.</p><p>and the moon shined forth during the day.”<note
                                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Book of John</hi>,
                                    18.1-15.</p></note></p></cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>In this passage a divine child is reveled from the heavenly realm, holy
                        silence is observed, just as the sages pray silently in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>, while a star appears, as well
                        as light in multiple forms. Even though the focus may be different, the
                        general contours remain the same.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Interestingly, the Mandaean <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Book of John</hi> presents Christ’s polymorphy as a sign of his
                                duplicity and untrustworthiness (Chapter 76) as one who “changes his
                                appearance.” See James McGrath, “Polemic, Redaction, and History in
                                the Mandaean Book of John: The Case of the Lightworld Visitors to
                                Jerusalem,” <hi rend="italic">Aram </hi>25
                                (2013): 378-379.</p></note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.6" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>6. Darkness and Error</head>
                    <p>The theological hallmark of Manichaeism is its dualistic cosmological
                        framework in which Light is radically opposed to Darkness as two
                        pre-existent cosmic principles. This doctrine, more than any other aspect of
                        Manichaean teaching, was the focus of fierce polemical backlash from a
                        variety of quarters. Although not nearly as pronounced, traces of this sort
                        of dualistic imagery can also be discerned in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Revelation of the Magi</hi>. For example, when the magi encounter Mary
                        and Joseph in Bethlehem, Mary is said to a have become “a gate for the great
                        light (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܘܗܪܐ</foreign>) that entered the world in grace to banish the darkness
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܫܘܟܐ</foreign>)” (22.2). Later, in the Thomas hymn, the apostle asks Christ to
                        “enlighten us and drive away darkness and error” (30.4 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܫܘܟܐ ܘܠܛܘܝܝ</foreign>).<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"> Sebastian
                                Brock has suggested that this may indicated the influence of
                                “Zoroastrian terminology” (“An Archaic Syriac Prayer over Baptismal
                                Oil,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica </hi>41
                                [2006]: 8), whereas Geo Widengren perceived an Iranian background
                                behind the text as a whole
                                (<hi rend="italic">Iranisch-semitische Kulturbegegnung in parthischer Zeit </hi>[Köln:
                                Westdeutscher Verlag, 1960], 71-72). Hultgård, however, acknowledged
                                criticisms of Widengren’s interpretation, but nonetheless asserts
                                that Iranian traditions were at play (Anders Hultgård, “The Magi and
                                the Star—the Persian Background in Text and Iconography,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">“Being Religious and Living Through the Eyes”: Studies in Religious Iconography </hi>[Uppsala,
                                1998], 223). </p></note> In Coptic Manichaean texts, “error” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲡⲗⲁⲛⲏ</foreign>) is practically synonymous with
                        the power of Darkness and evil in the world.<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"> See <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Kephalaia</hi> 21.18; 28.31; 31.30; 33.24,30; 48.34; 90.20,
                                etc.; <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>4.22;
                                8.8,24; 52.31, etc. </p></note> For instance, the Manichaean
                        <hi rend="italic">Psalm-Book </hi>states: “Let us bless
                        our Lord Jesus who has sent us the Spirit of Truth. He came and separated us
                        from the Error (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲧⲡⲗⲁⲛⲏ</foreign>)” (9.4-5). This
                        “Error” is most often associated with the various sects to which Manichaeans
                        were opposed, whereas the light-child in the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of
                            the Magi</hi> explains how “error has reigned in deceit over your
                        generations” (21.9) and that only those who possess true knowledge belong to
                        the “race of light” (21.9 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢ ܛܘܗܡܐ ܐܢܬܘܢ ܕܢܗܘܪܐ</foreign>). As we might expect, this
                        last motif (“race of light”) is also present in Manichaean <hi rend="italic"
                            >Psalm-Book</hi> in a passage denouncing the “sects of Error” (<foreign xml:lang="cop">ⲛ̅ⲇⲟⲅⲙⲁ ⲛ̅ⲧⲡⲗⲁⲛⲏ</foreign>) (86.14).</p>
                    <p>The use of imagery contrasting light and darkness is certainly not unique to
                        Manichaean discourse, as it appears to have been widespread in Mesopotamia.
                        Not only were dualistic concepts important to various forms of Zoroastrian
                        theology, but also to the teachings of Marcion and Bardaisan, each of whom
                        were closely associated with Mani in early Syriac tradition.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text"> François De
                                Blois, “Dualism in Iranian and Christian Traditions,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society </hi>10,
                                no. 1 (2000): 1-19.</p></note> Moreover, the Mandaeans too made
                        extensive use of it in their own literature, which as we have already seen
                        has some relationship with early Manichaean texts. It is not surprising,
                        then, that the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> should display
                        at least some dualistic tendencies. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.3.7" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>7. Final Fire</head>
                    <p rend="H Normal First">Fittingly, the final point that ought to be highlighted
                        in this study is how the
                        <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>imagines
                        the end of cosmic history. As much as the text is focused on the beginning
                        of the Christian narrative, by highlighting the birth of Jesus, it closes
                        with a (dualistic) vision of the end-time and an eschatological exhortation
                        from the magi:</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">Flee from the
                        <hi rend="italic">darkness </hi>(<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܫܘܟܐ</foreign>) and come to the
                            <hi rend="italic">light</hi> (ܢܘܗܪܐ) that does not pass away, so that
                        you may live and have refuge under the wings of our Lord Jesus, our saviour
                        and our great refuge on the last day, from the fearsome judgement of <hi
                            rend="italic">fire</hi> that will come suddenly to purify the entire
                        earth from <hi rend="italic">error</hi>, which has ruled over it in its
                        deceit. And you shall be delivered by faith from the heat of the fire and
                        shall enter that <hi rend="italic">rest</hi> that is prepared for all the
                            <hi rend="italic">chosen</hi> and the believers who have believed in the
                            <hi rend="italic">child of perfect light</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܠܕܗ ܕܢܘܗܪܐ ܓܡܝܪܐ</foreign>), and
                        in eternal life, in the kingdom of my Lord Jesus Christ, the Son of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Lord of all</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܐ ܟܠ</foreign>), in his heavenly <hi
                            rend="italic">majesty</hi> (i.e. greatness) (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܒܘܬܗ</foreign>), in his <hi
                            rend="italic">new world</hi> (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܠܡܗ ܚܕܬܐ</foreign>), and in his heavenly and great
                        and never-passing away light, and in his glorious rest (32.2-3 <hi
                            rend="italic">emphasis added</hi>). </p>
                    <p>Once again, we can observe numerous resemblances to Manichaean religious
                        discourse. For its part, the Manichaean vision of the end times foresees the
                        final appearance of Jesus the Splendor, avatar of the “Lord of All” (see
                        above) who will vanquish the powers of darkness and purify the world by
                        means of a “Great Fire.” The chosen “Elect” will then be rewarded in a “New
                        Aeon” of eternal light and rest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Baker-Brian, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Manichaeism</hi>, 116-118; Timothy Pettipiece, “Burn the World
                                Down: Manichaean Apocalyptic in Comparative Perspective,” in
                                <hi rend="italic">The Armenian Apocalyptic Tradition: A Comparative Perspective, </hi>ed.
                                Kevork Bardakjian and Sergio La Porta (Leiden: Brill, 2014),
                                657-666.</p></note> As one Middle Persian fragment from Mani’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Book of Giants</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58"
                            n="58"><p rend="footnote text"> Counted among Mani’s canonical
                                scriptures, this work contains many points of contact with other
                                apocryphal texts from an Aramaic background (see John C. Reeves,
                                <hi rend="italic">Jewish Lore in Manichaean Cosmogony: Studies in the </hi>Book
                                of
                                Giants<hi rend="italic"> Traditions </hi>[Cincinatti,
                                1992]).</p></note> suggests:</p>
                    <p rend="H Quote Block">…on brilliant wings they (the righteous ones) shall fly
                        and soar further beyond and above that Fire, and shall gaze into its depth
                        and height. And those righteous ones that will stand around it, outside and
                        above, they shall have power over the Great Fire, and over everything in it
                        … they are purer and stronger [than the] Great Fire of Ruin that sets the
                        worlds ablaze.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> T ii D ii 164 (trans. Hans-Joachim Klimkeit,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Gnosis on the Silk Road</hi> [San Francisco:
                                HarperCollins, 1993], 247); <anchor xml:id="Hlk61269759"/>W. B.
                                Henning, “The Book of Giants,” BSOAS 11 (1943): 68.</p></note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2pettipiece.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>CONCLUSIONS AND IMPLICATIONS</head>
                <p rend="H Normal First">What, then, are we to make of all the apparent similarities
                    between the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> and Manichaean
                    theological language? While some resemblances are perhaps more on the surface
                    level, such as imagining God and the divine realm in terms of
                    <hi rend="italic">life, light, treasure, splendor, </hi>and<hi rend="italic"> greatness—</hi>all
                    of which seem to have been part of a shared Aramaic religious vocabulary—others
                    emerge as more deeply rooted themes. Most notably:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">i) identifying God as the “Father of Greatness”</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ii) a chain of True Prophets traced back to Adam and
                    Seth</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">iii) a polymorphic messiah-figure who appears to all
                        humanity</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">iv) revelatory authority granted through divine
                    twinship</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">v) emphasis on Thomas traditions</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">vi) opposition between Light and Darkness / Truth and
                        Error</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">vii) eschatological fire and rest</hi></p>
                <p>As such, both the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> and Manichaean
                    literature construct the same basic soteriological storyline. Namely, that the
                        <hi rend="italic">Father of Greatness</hi> reveals himself through a chain
                    of <hi rend="italic">true prophets</hi> extending back to <hi rend="italic">Adam
                        and Seth</hi> that have appeared in many times and places as manifestations
                    of <hi rend="italic">divine twinship</hi>. The message that these prophets
                    deliver periodically to all humanity emphasizes the opposition between <hi
                        rend="italic">light and darkness</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">error </hi>manifest in sectarian
                    divisions. The forces of darkness and evil, however, will ultimately be defeated
                    when Jesus returns in glory to set
                    <hi rend="italic">fire </hi>to the world and grant eternal
                    <hi rend="italic">rest </hi>to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >children of light</hi>. </p>
                <p>Does this mean that the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>is a
                    Manichaean text? I am not ready to go that far. Notably absent are a
                    multiplicity of technical terms for the many well-defined figures from the
                    Manichaean cosmogonic myth, other than the “Father of Greatness.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> This in itself
                            does not necessarily discount the idea of the
                            <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>being
                            a Manichaean text, as the specific technical language of the cosmogony
                            appears to have been largely unknown to outsiders, with a few notable
                            exceptions such as Theodore bar Khonai. Most polemical descriptions of
                            the Manichaean myth make use of a generic template focused on its
                            dualistic basis rather than a detailed narrative. </p></note> Nor is
                    there any direct or implied references to Mani himself.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> There is a somewhat oblique
                            reference to the “Paraclete Spirit” (14.8) in the text, although this
                            does not appear to connect with the Manichaean notion of Mani as the
                            Paraclete promised by Jesus. </p></note> Even though Manichaean scribal
                    activity has been observed in other pieces of Christian apocryphal literature,
                    that does not appear to be happening here.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62"
                        n="62"><p rend="footnote text"> See Timothy Pettipiece, “Manichaean
                            Redaction of the <hi rend="italic">Secret Book of John</hi>,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Fakes, Forgeries, and Fictions: Writing Ancient and
                                Modern Christian Apocrypha: Proceedings from the 2015 York Christian
                                Apocrypha Symposium</hi>, ed. Tony Burke (Eugene, Oregon: Cascade
                            Books, 2017).</p></note> Moreover, as mentioned above, the magi and the
                    Nativity story were of little intrinsic interest to Manichaean authors, who
                    found the idea of an incarnated Jesus theologically offensive. It seems more
                    likely that the presence of common thematic elements points to a common milieu
                    out of which both the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>and
                    Manichaeism emerged. More specifically, I would argue that both are building on
                    a pre-existing soteriological narrative that appears to have been rooted in <hi
                        rend="italic">variant</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> By <hi rend="italic">variant</hi> I mean streams
                            of early Christian tradition that diverge considerably from emerging
                            orthodoxy. </p></note> forms of Christianity that developed in
                    Aramaic/Syriac speaking Mesopotamia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> This geographic area has been described as a
                            “crucible of cultural creativity for Jews no less than Platonists,
                            Christians, and Manichaeans in the first three centuries of the Common
                            Era” (Han and Reed, “Reorienting Ancient Judaism,” 148).</p></note> The
                    exact origins of this narrative, however, remain difficult to define, as they
                    appear tied to the notoriously complex and contested issue of “Jewish
                    Christianity.” <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">
                            The notoriously difficult puzzle of “Jewish Christianity” has been the
                            subject of much debate and controversy. See Annette Yoshiko Reed,
                            “Historicizing ‘Jewish-Christianity’,” in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Jewish-Christianity and the History of Judaism: Collected
                                Essays</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018), xv-xxx. Typically, this
                            hybrid term has been used to describe either an imagined segment of
                            Jesus’ earliest followers, or in reference to certain sectarian groups
                            identified by patristic heresiologists as outliers. In spite of the term
                            being “anachronistic, clumsy, fraught, and contested,” (as Reed admits),
                            it nonetheless points to a liminal historical, discursive, and even
                            geographical space in which certain discernable expressions of late
                            antique religious tradition and community connect themselves in
                            important ways to both
                            <hi rend="italic">Christianity </hi>and <hi
                                rend="italic">Judaism</hi> while at the same time resisting those
                            categorical constructs as they have come to be defined. As problematic
                            as the term is, it nonetheless points to something that needs to be
                            further explored and better understood.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>As mentioned earlier, the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> was
                    likely composed in Syriac, possibly near Edessa in the 3<hi rend="superscript"
                        >rd</hi> or 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century CE,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text"> See note 4.</p></note> which
                    was an important center of early Christian activity in Mesopotamia. We also know
                    that Mani and his early disciples wrote and preached in Syriac in the same
                    region around the same time. Mandaic, for its part, is an Aramaic dialect, and
                    communities of Mandaeans, or their predecessors, have in some form been (until
                    recently) historically present long the Tigris and Euphrates since at least the
                        3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> cent. CE.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67"
                        n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> The recent re-assessment by Kevin van Bladel
                            suggests that a distinctive “Mandaean” identity only emerged in the 5<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> century CE out of competition among other
                            “Syro-Mesopotamia” religious groups (<hi rend="italic">From Sasanian
                                Mandaeans to Ṣābians of the Marshes</hi> [Leiden: Brill,
                        2017]).</p></note> It is therefore not surprising that religious traditions
                    emanating from the same time-period and geographical area would demonstrate some
                    common characteristics and thematic concerns. In fact, as recent studies
                    continue to demonstrate, Jewish, Christian, Zoroastrian, and Manichaean
                    traditions regularly engaged one another in late antique Mesopotamia and display
                    significant degrees of overlap.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See, for example, Adam H. Becker, “The Comparative
                            Study of ‘Scholas-ticism’ in Late Antique Mesopotamia: Rabbis and East
                            Syrians,” <hi rend="italic">AJS Review </hi>34 no.
                            1 (2010): 91-113; Yishai Kiel, “Study Versus Sustenance: A Rabbinic
                            Dilemma in Its Zoroastrian and Manichaean Context,”
                            <hi rend="italic">AJS Review </hi>38 no. 2 (2014):
                            275-302; Yishai Kiel, “Reimagining Enoch in Sassanian Babylonia in Light
                            of Zoroastrian and Manichaean Traditions,” <hi rend="italic">AJS
                                Review</hi> 39 no.2 (2015): 407-432 to name but a few. </p></note>
                </p>
                <p>Unfortunately, the story of early Christianity beyond the eastern borders of the
                    Roman Empire is not one that is well-known or well-understood outside of
                    specialized circles.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> As Sebastian Brock has pointed out, the Eusebian
                            model of early Christian history has linked that narrative so closely
                            with the Roman Empire, that the development of Christianity in Persia is
                            either omitted from that story or minimized (see Sebastian Brock,
                            “Christians in the Sasanian Empire: A Case of Divided Loyalties,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Syriac Perspectives on Late Antiquity</hi>,
                        2-3).</p></note> Thus modern readers’ surprise at a text such as the <hi
                        rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>. While early missionaries would
                    have arrived by the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> century CE, there was also a
                    significant influx of Christians due to the forced deportation of hundreds of
                    thousands of captives from the Roman Empire by Persian King Shapur I in the 3<hi
                        rend="superscript">rd</hi> century CE.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70"
                        n="70"><p rend="footnote text"> Josef Wiesehöfer, <hi rend="italic">Ancient
                                Persia from 550 BC to 650 AD</hi> (New York: I. B. Tauris, 1998),
                            201.</p></note> Notably, an inscription by the Sasanian high-priest
                    Kartir (mentioned above) points to an official differentiation between two
                    groups known in Middle Persian as <hi rend="italic">nāsrāy</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">kristiyān</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> It is difficult to imagine that Kartir would use
                            these terms in an official inscription without understanding that they
                            implied some important distinction. </p></note> It has been suggested
                    that the former group, the “Nazoreans”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Based on what we know from early Christian
                            heresiological sources, the term “Nazorean” is used as a kind of
                            catch-all to connect a cluster of sectarian groups that were all thought
                            to derive from the so-called “Jewish-Christian” stream of early
                            Christianity, such as Cerninthians, Elchasaites, and Ebionites.
                            “Nazorean” is also attested as a term of self-designation found in
                            Mandaean writings, although in a somewhat ambivalent sense, and is
                            applied to Christians pejoratively in the Talmud (see François De Blois,
                            “Naṣrānī [Ναζωραȋος] and ḥanīf [ἐθνικός]: Studies on the Religious
                            Vocabulary of Christianity and of Islam”
                            <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies </hi>65,
                            no. 1 [2002]: 4).</p></note> represents local Aramaic-speaking
                    Christians, many of whom were still strongly connected to non-rabbinic Jewish
                    traditions, while the latter refers to relocated “western” Christians who had
                    more in common with the Roman church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Sebastian Brock, “Christians in the Sasanian Empire: A Case of Divided Loyalties,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Syriac Perspectives on Late Antiquity</hi>,
                        3-6.</p></note> Similarly, Persian authorities in Syriac martyr acts from
                    the Sasanian period seem to make the same terminological differentiation when
                    discussing interactions with Christian communities under their
                        jurisdiction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> De Blois, “Naṣrānī [<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ναζωραȋος</foreign>] and ḥanīf
                            [ἐθνικός], 8. </p></note></p>
                <p>While a more concrete history of the churches of Persia begins to take shape in
                    the 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century CE, prior to that, particularly in
                    the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> and 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>
                    centuries, Iranian territories appear to have been home to an eclectic mix of
                    doctrines and sects associated with early Christian teachers such as Marcion,
                    Bardaisan, and Elchasai,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Wiesehöfer, <hi rend="italic">Ancient Persia</hi>,
                            205. Later, Mani himself will be added to this list of founding figures.
                        </p></note> all of whom where later deemed “heretical” by proto-orthodox
                    authorities, but whose doctrines were considered authoritative and foundational
                    for the earliest forms of Aramaic/Syriac Christianity<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text"> The work of Stanley Jones has
                            helped further refine this understanding of early Christianity in
                            Syro-Mesopotamia (see F.S. Jones,
                            <hi rend="italic">Pseudoclementia Elchasaiticaque inter Judaeochristiana: Collected Studies </hi>[Leuven:
                            Peeters, 2012]).</p></note> in the region. As we saw above, several of
                    the central themes and motifs common to both the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of
                        the Magi</hi> and Manichaean discourse, such as the chain of True Prophets
                    and the polymorphic Christ, point back to such “Elchasaite” or “Nazorean”
                        prototypes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <anchor xml:id="Hlk62205521"/>Cirillo, Luigi, ''From the Elchasaite
                            Christology to the Manichaean Apostle of Light,” in <hi rend="italic">Il
                                Manicheismo: Nuove Prospettive della Richerca. Atti del Quinto
                                Congresso Internazionale di Studi sul Manicheismo (Dipartimento di
                                Studi Asiatici, Università degli Studi di Napoli “L’Orientale”;
                                Napoli, 2-8 Settembre 2001)</hi>, ed. van Tongerloo, Aloïs and
                            Cirillo, Luigi. Manichaean Studies 5. Turnhout: Brepols, 2005), 47-54.
                            Gerard P. Luttikhuizen has referred to this idea as a distinctly “Syrian
                            Christology” (see “The Baptists of Mani’s Youth and the Elchasaites,”
                                in <hi rend="italic">Gnostic Revisions of Genesis Stories and Early
                                Jesus Traditions</hi>, NHMS 58 [Leiden: Brill, 2006],
                        178-179).</p></note>
                </p>
                <p>The current model of the historical development of early Christianity has long
                    had its own version of a “dark matter” problem. There are strong indicators of
                    an important stream of early Christian tradition that exerted considerable
                    influence on other contemporary trajectories and against which proto-orthodoxy
                    defined itself, but whose exact nature remains obscure, since evidence of it has
                    been almost totally erased.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Nearly a century ago, Walter Bauer argued that the
                            prevailing forms of “orthodox” Christianity that developed during Late
                            Antiquity were often built against a pre-existing background of
                            traditions later deemed “heretical.” A key example of this phenomenon
                            relates to the story of King Abgar and the introduction of Christianity
                            to the city of Edessa (<hi rend="italic">Rechtgläubigkeit und Ketzerei
                                im ältesten Christentum</hi> [Tübingen: Mohr, 1934]).</p></note>
                    This tradition can only be vaguely decerned as a palimpsest read against the
                    background of preserved early Christian discourse and is partly visible through
                    heresiological labels such as Gnostic, Ebionite, Elchasaite, and Nazorean, as
                    well as surviving early Christian and Jewish apocrypha traditions.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"> Geo Widengren
                            identified this as a form of “jüdisch-iranischen Gnosis” in specific
                            reference to the
                            <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>(<hi rend="italic">Mani und der Manichäismus </hi>[Stuttgart:
                            Kohlhammer, 1961], 29).</p></note> This evidence suggests that a
                    well-developed and widespread <hi rend="italic">parallel</hi> Christian
                    tradition (or cluster of traditions) developed early on and largely
                    independently in Aramaic-speaking Mesopotamia that presented a much different
                    theological focus than what developed later into Nicene orthodoxy and therefore
                    looks alien to ancient and modern commentators for whom Christianity in the
                    Roman Empire is the primary point of reference. In particular, in these
                    alternate traditions, a much stronger emphasis is placed on Christ’s appearance
                    (or rather appearances) in the world and his role as a revealer rather than the
                    redemptive value of his embodiment, death, and resurrection, which were viewed
                    as illusory. It is also differentiated by its assertion of an alternative
                    Trinity emphasizing the femininity of the Spirit,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text"> This too was a reflection of
                            its Aramaic context, in which the word for “spirit” is grammatically
                            feminine. See Timothy Pettipiece, “Many Faced Gods: Triadic
                            (Proto-)Structure and Divine Androgyny in Early Manichaean Cosmogony,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Open Theology</hi> (2015) 1: 245–254, where it is
                            argued that the entirety of the early Manichaean cosmogonic myth is
                            rooted in this alternate trinitarian framework of Father-Mother-Child.
                            François De Blois has suggested that this type of trinity tradition was
                            “widespread” on the periphery of the late-antique world, and in fact
                            represents the form of Christianity likely engaged with by Muhammed and
                            the early Muslims, adding to its historical importance (“Naṣrānī
                            [Ναζωραȋος] and ḥanīf [ἐθνικός],” 27).</p></note> and a chain of “true
                    prophets” periodically sent to humanity. I am suggesting, here, that the <hi
                        rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> and the teaching of Mani represent
                    two closely related theological trajectories derived from this stream of early
                    Mesopotamian Christianity. </p>
                <p>What accounts for such theological differences? The fact that these alternate
                    Christian traditions developed in Iranian territory, during the late Parthian
                    and early Sassanian periods, is certainly key. Sebastian Brock has suggested
                    that the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi> may have, at least in
                    part, sought to provide “a foundation legend for the Iranian Christian
                        community.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Sebastian Brock, “An Archaic Syriac Prayer over Baptismal Oil,”
                        5.</p></note>Although, if we imagine the considerable religious diversity
                    <hi rend="italic">on the ground </hi>in the early Sasanian
                    Empire, as evidenced by the inscription of Kartir, which mentions Jews (<hi
                        rend="italic">yahūd</hi>), Buddhists (<hi rend="italic">šaman</hi>),
                    Brahmans (<hi rend="italic">brāman</hi>), and “baptisers” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >makdag</hi>) as objects of his derision,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82"
                        n="82"><p rend="footnote text"> Wiesehöfer, <hi rend="italic">Ancient
                                Persia</hi>, 199. </p></note> then it is possible that the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>(and the
                    teachings of Mani for that matter) could be viewed as an attempt to bridge the
                    gap between a diversity of communities and establish a unified soteriological
                    framework. It is worth noting, however, that the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of
                        the Magi</hi> contains almost no overtly polemical elements, and its author
                    does not seem interested in attacking other religious perspectives directly.
                    Instead, a story is told of a saviour from the light-realm that appears in
                    multiple forms throughout the ages to all people in an on-going effort to
                    achieve universal salvation. Tellingly, at the end of the star-child’s discourse
                    to the magi a voice is heard saying: “Amen! The will of complete salvation, joy
                    and peace to all the worlds!” (<hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi</hi>
                    21.12). One has to wonder if the very focus placed on the magi as bearing
                    witness to the appearance of Jesus is in some sense an attempt to appeal to the
                    imperial Zoroastrian tradition and to validate Christianity’s status as a
                    religious minority in the Sasanian Empire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83"
                        n="83"><p rend="footnote text"> See Hultgård, “The Magi and the Star—the
                            Persian Background in Text and Iconography,” 225. A similar point is
                            made by Sergey Minov in relation to representations of the magi in the
                            Syriac <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>, which are said to
                            “reflect the values and aspirations of a Christian minority group
                            seeking to engage actively the dominant culture of the Sassanian empire”
                            (“Dynamics of Christian Acculturation in the Sassanian Empire: Some
                            Iranian Motifs in the <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Jews, Christians and Zoroastrians: Religious Dynamics
                                in a Sasanian Context</hi>, ed. G. Herman, <hi rend="italic">Judaism
                                in Context 17</hi> (Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2014),
                            200). Even the names of the Magi, such as Hormizd, Atrahšišat, Merodak,
                            appear designed to make allusion to figures from prior Iranian and
                            Mesopotamian traditions
                            (<hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>2.3).</p></note>
                    Moreover, if indeed the author of the text was attempting to build a bridge
                    between various neighboring religious communities, then perhaps the use of the
                    title “Father of Greatness” itself could similarly be seen as a deliberate
                    theological overture to Manichaean sensibilities. </p>
                <p>As Sebastian Brock has also pointed out, the history of early Christianity is
                    often distorted by the overriding emphasis placed on the Roman context, which is
                    seen as somehow essential to its early development. From this perspective, the
                    experience of Christians has often been stereotyped as either persecuted
                    minority or supremacist majority.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Sebastian Brock, “Christians in the Sasanian
                            Empire: A Case of Divided Loyalties,” 1-2. A similar issue has affected
                            scholarly discussions of ancient Judaism, which until recently have
                            placed emphasis on Graeco-Roman contexts as opposed to Parthian and
                            Sassanian (see Jae Hee Han and Annette Yoshiko Reed, “Reorienting
                            Ancient Judaism: Syrian, Mesopotamian, and Persian Perspectives,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of Ancient Judaism</hi> 9 no. 2 (2018):
                            145-146).</p></note> Imperial Roman Christianity, as reflected by
                    post-Nicene orthodoxy, could afford to be supremacist and exclusive in
                    orientation, as it had the full-force of the emperors to assert its theological
                    and ideological agendas. But what about Christianity in other contexts? For the
                    most part, Christians in Persian territory were tolerated as a recognized
                    religious minority. Whereas Mani, in the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>
                    century, sought to replace all existing religious traditions with his own
                    universal church, his highly polemical efforts generated enormous hostility and
                    resulted in his execution by the state. The <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the
                        Magi</hi>, however, appears to take an equally inclusivist approach, but a
                    more conciliatory tone, in that it avoids overt attempts to antagonize other
                    religious communities, while seeking to integrate them into a discourse of
                    universal salvation. Such a universalizing soteriology might appear surprising
                    and appealing to modern readers, but when viewed in its historical context and
                    against a broader background of other related, early Christian traditions, it is
                    perhaps not all that original. It is simply unfamiliar. </p>
                <p>While enigmatic and exotic on the surface, the
                    <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi </hi>and its
                    Manichaean parallels appear to have inherited and integrated significant
                    elements from a pre-existing tradition we know largely from fragments and
                    hostile testimonies. Not only is it theologically compelling, but it also
                    provides another important piece to the still incomplete puzzle of “early
                        Christianities”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> I am not particularly fond of the plural coinage
                            “Christianities.” However, in the case of the earliest forms of the
                            Christian movement in Syriac-speaking Mesopotamia it does seem as though
                            we are faced with some fairly independent trajectories of development
                            with unique characteristics. </p></note> outside the Roman Empire. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Allberry, C.R.C., <hi
                        rend="italic">A Manichaean Psalm-Book, Part
                    II</hi> (Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 1938).</bibl>
                <bibl>Ashbrook Harvey, Susan, “Feminine Imagery for the Divine: The Holy Spirit, the Odes of Solomon, and Early Syriac Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">St. Vladimir’s Theological Quarterly </hi>37 (2004): 1-29.</bibl>
                <bibl>Augustine, <hi
                        rend="italic">Answer to Faustus, a
                        Manichean</hi>, trans. Roland Teske, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Works of Saint Augustine: A
                        Translation for the 21</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                       
                    >st</hi><hi rend="italic"> Century</hi> (NY: New City Press, 2007),</bibl>
                <bibl>Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Sancti Aureli Augustini, </hi>ed. Zycha, CSEL 25.1 (Vienna, 1891).</bibl>
                <bibl>Baker-Brian, Nicholas <hi
                        rend="italic">Manichaeism: An Ancient Faith
                        Rediscovered</hi> (London: T&amp;T Clark, 2011).</bibl>
                <bibl>Bauer, Walter, <hi
                        rend="italic">Rechtgläubigkeit und Ketzerei im
                        ältesten
                    Christentum</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr, 1934).</bibl>
                <bibl>Becker, Adam H., “The Comparative Study of ‘Scholasticism’ in Late Antique Mesopotamia: Rabbis and East Syrians,” <hi rend="italic">AJS Review </hi>
                       34 no. 1 (2010): 91-113</bibl>
                <bibl>BeDuhn, Jason, <hi rend="italic">The Manichaean Body in Discipline and Ritual </hi>(Baltimore: John Hopkins University Press,
                        2000).</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian, “An Archaic Syriac Prayer over Baptismal Oil,” <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica </hi>41 (2006): 2-12.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian, “Christians in the Sasanian Empire: A Case of Divided Loyalties,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Syriac Perspectives on Late
                        Antiquity</hi> (London: Variorum Reprints, 1984), IV.1-19.</bibl>
                <bibl>Coyle, J. Kevin, “The Gospel of Thomas in Manichaeism?” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Colloque international L’Évangile selon
                        Thomas et les textes de Nag Hammadi, Québec, 29-31 mai
                    2003</hi>, ed. Louis Painchaud and Paul-Hubert Poirier (Québec: Les Presses de l’Université Laval / Louvain: Éditions Peeters, 2007), 75-91. </bibl>
                <bibl>Cirillo, Luigi, ''From the
                        Elchasaite Christology to the Manichaean Apostle of Light,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Il Manicheismo: Nuove Prospettive della
                        Richerca. Atti del Quinto Congresso Internazionale di Studi sul Manicheismo
                        (Dipartimento di Studi Asiatici, Università degli Studi di Napoli
                        “L’Orientale”; Napoli, 2-8 Settembre 2001)</hi>,
                        ed. van Tongerloo, Aloïs and Cirillo, Luigi. Manichaean Studies 5. Turnhout:
                        Brepols, 2005), 47-54.</bibl>
                <bibl>De Blois, François, “Dualism in Iranian and Christian Traditions,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society </hi>10, no. 1 (2000): 1-19.</bibl>
                <bibl>De Blois, François, “Naṣrānī [Ναζωραȋος] and ḥanīf [ἐθνικός]: Studies on the Religious Vocabulary of Christianity and of Islam” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and African Studies </hi>65, no. 1 (2002): 4.</bibl>
                <bibl>Denzey, Nicola “A New Star on the Horizon: Astral Christologies and Stellar Debates in Early Christian Discourse,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Prayer, Magic, and the Stars in the
                        Ancient and Late Antique
                    World,</hi> ed. Scott Noegel et al. (Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania State University Press, 2003).</bibl>
                <bibl>Dilley, Paul, “Also Schrieb Zarathustra? Mani As Interpreter of the ‘Law of Zarades’” in Iain Gardner, Jason BeDuhn, and Paul Dilley, <hi rend="italic">Mani at the Court of the Persian Kings: Studies on the Chester Beatty "Kephalaia" Codex </hi>(Leiden: Brill, 2015), 101-135.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dodge, Bayard, ed., <hi
                        rend="italic">The Fihrist of al-Nadim</hi>, Vol 2 (New York: Columbia University Press,
                        1970).</bibl>
                <bibl>Duchesne-Guillemin, Jacques, <hi
                        rend="italic"
                        >“</hi>Die Magier in Bethlehem und Mithras als Erlöser?” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morganländischen Gesellschaft </hi>111, no. 2 (1961): 469-475.</bibl>
                <bibl>Foster, Paul, “Polymorphic Christology: Its Origins and Development in Early Christianity,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Theological
                    Studies</hi> 58 (2007): 66-99. </bibl>
                <bibl>Franzmann, Majella, <hi rend="italic">Jesus in the Manichaean Writings </hi>(London: T&amp;T Clark, 2003).</bibl>
                <bibl>Funk, Wolf-Peter, “Einer aus Tausend, zwei aus Zehntausend: Zitate aus dem Thomasevangelium in den koptischen Manichaica,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">For the Children, Perfect Instruction:
                        Studies in Honor of Hans-Martin Schenke</hi>, ed.
                        Bethge et al. (Leiden: Brill, 2002), 67-94.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gardner, Iain, “Mani’s Last Days,” in Gardner, BeDuhn, and Dilley, <hi rend="italic">Mani at the Court of the Persian Kings: Studies on the Chester Beatty "Kephalaia" Codex </hi>(Leiden: Brill, 2015), 159-208.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gardner, Iain and Samuel Lieu, <hi
                        rend="italic">Manichaean Texts from the Roman
                        Empire</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2004).</bibl>
                <bibl>Häberl, Charles G. and James F. McGrath, eds., <hi
                        rend="italic">The Mandaean Book of John: Text and
                        Translation</hi> (Berlin: De Gruyter, 2020).</bibl>
                <bibl>Han, Jae Hee and Annette Yoshiko Reed, “Reorienting Ancient Judaism: Syrian,
                    Mesopotamian, and Persian Perspectives,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Ancient
                        Judaism</hi> 9 no. 2 (2018): 144-154.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hegemonius, <hi
                        rend="italic">Acta Archelai (The Acts of
                        Archelaus)</hi>, trans. Mark Vermes (Louvain:
                        Brepols, 2001).</bibl>
                <bibl>Hegemonius, <hi
                        rend="italic">Acta Archelai</hi>, GCS 16 (Leipzig: J.C. Hinrichs, 1906).</bibl>
                <bibl>Henrichs, Albert and Ludwig Koenen, <hi rend="italic">Der Kölner Mani-Kodex: Über das Werden seines Liebes </hi>(Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag, 1988).</bibl>
                <bibl>Henning, W. B., “Mani’s Last Journey,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and
                        African
                    Studies</hi> 10, no.4 (1942): 941-953. </bibl>
                <bibl>Henning, W. B., “The Book of Giants,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin of the School of Oriental and
                        African
                    Studies</hi> 11 (1943): 52-74.</bibl>
                <bibl>(Hippolytus), <hi
                        rend="italic">Refutation of All
                        Heresies</hi>, trans. M. David Litwa, <hi
                        rend="italic">Writings from the Greco-Roman World
                        40</hi> (Atlanta: SBL Press, 2016),</bibl>
                <bibl>Hultgård, Anders, “The Magi and the Star—the Persian Background in Text and Iconography,” in <hi rend="italic">“Being Religious and Living Through the Eyes”: Studies in Religious Iconography </hi>(Uppsala, 1998), 215-225. </bibl>
                <bibl>Jones, F. S. <hi rend="italic">Pseudoclementia Elchasaiticaque inter Judaeo-christiana: Collected Studies </hi>(Leuven: Peeters, 2012).</bibl>
                <bibl>Kiel, Yishai, “Reimagining Enoch in Sassanian Babylonia in Light of Zoroastrian and Manichaean Traditions,” <hi
                        rend="italic">AJS
                    Review</hi> 39 no.2 (2015): 407-432.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kiel, Yishai, “Study Versus Sustenance: A Rabbinic Dilemma in Its Zoroastrian and Manichaean Context,” <hi rend="italic">AJS Review </hi>38 no. 2 (2014): 275-302.</bibl>
                <bibl>Klijn, A. F. J., <hi
                        rend="italic">Seth in Jewish, Christian, and Gnostic
                        Traditions</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1977). </bibl>
                <bibl>Klijn, A. F. J. “The So-Called Hymn of the Pearl (Acts of Thomas ch. 108-113),” <hi
                        rend="italic">Vigiliae
                    Christianae</hi> 14, no. 3 (1960): 154-164.</bibl>
                <bibl>Klijn, A. F. J., and G. J. Reinink, <hi rend="italic">Patristic Evidence for Jewish-Christian Sects </hi>(Leiden: Brill, 1973).</bibl>
                <bibl>Klimkeit, Hans-Joachim, <hi
                        rend="italic">Gnosis on the Silk
                    Road</hi> (San Francisco: HarperCollins, 1993).</bibl>
                <bibl>Lieu, Samuel N. C., <hi
                        rend="italic">Manichaeism in the Later Roman Empire
                        and Medieval
                    China</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>Lieu, Samuel N. C., Gregory Fox, and John Sheldon, <hi
                        rend="italic">Greek and Latin Sources on Manichaean
                        Cosmogony and Ethics</hi>, Corpus Fontium
                        Manichaeorum, Series Subsidia VI (Turnhout: Brepols, 2010).</bibl>
                <bibl>Landau, Brent, “The Sages and the Star-Child:An Introduction to the Revelation of the Magi, An Ancient Christian Apocryphon” (PhD diss., Harvard University, 2008). </bibl>
                <bibl>Landau, Brent, <hi rend="italic">Revelation of the Magi: The Lost Tale of the Wise Men’s Journey to Bethlehem </hi>(HarperCollins, 2010).</bibl>
                <bibl>Luttikhuizen, Gerard P., “The Baptists of Mani’s Youth and the Elchasaites,”
                        in <hi rend="italic">Gnostic Revisions of Genesis Stories and Early Jesus
                        Traditions,</hi> Nag Hammadi and Manichaean Studies 58 (Leiden: Brill,
                    2006), 170-184.</bibl>
                <bibl>MacKenzie, D. N., “A Zoroastrian Master of Ceremonies,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">W.B. Henning Memorial Volume</hi>, ed. Mary Boyce, and Ilya Gershevitch (London: Lund
                        Humphries, 1970), 264-71.</bibl>
                <bibl>McGrath, James, “Polemic, Redaction, and History in the Mandaean Book of John: The Case of the Lightworld Visitors to Jerusalem,” <hi rend="italic">Aram </hi>25 (2013): 375-382.</bibl>
                <bibl>Minov, Sergey, “Dynamics of Christian Acculturation in the Sassanian Empire: Some Iranian Motifs in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Cave of
                        Treasures</hi>,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Jews, Christians and Zoroastrians:
                        Religious Dynamics in a Sasanian
                        Context</hi>, ed. G. Herman, <hi
                        rend="italic">Judaism in Context
                    17</hi> (Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2014), 149-201.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mirecki, Paul Allan, “Coptic Manichaean Psalm 278 and the Gospel of Thomas 37,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Manichaica Selecta</hi>, ed. A. van Tongerloo and S. Giversen (Louvain,
                        1991), 243-262.</bibl>
                <bibl>Nagel, Peter, <hi rend="italic">Die Thomaspsalmen des koptisch-manichäischen Psalmbuches </hi>(Berlin, 1980).</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">New Testament Apocrypha, Vol. 2, </hi>ed. Schneemelcher, (Louisville: WJK Press,
                    2003)</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">New Testament
                        Apocrypha: More Canonical Scriptures, Volume I</hi>, ed. Tony Burke and Brent Landau (Grand Rapids, MI:
                        Eerdmans, 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl>Payne Smith, R., <hi
                        rend="italic">A Compendious Syriac
                    Dictionary</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1903).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pedersen, Nils Arne, <hi
                        rend="italic">Manichaean Homilies</hi>, Corpus Fontium Manichaeorum, Series Coptica II
                        (Turnhout: Brepols, 2006).</bibl>
                <bibl>Pettipiece, Timothy, “Burn the World Down: Manichaean Apocalyptic in Comparative Perspective,” in <hi rend="italic">The Armenian Apocalyptic Tradition: A Comparative Perspective, </hi>ed. Kevork Bardakjian and Sergio La Porta (Leiden:
                        Brill, 2014), 657-666.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pettipiece, Timothy, “Manichaean Redaction of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Secret Book of
                        John</hi>,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Fakes, Forgeries, and Fictions: Writing
                        Ancient and Modern Christian Apocrypha: Proceedings from the 2015 York
                        Christian Apocrypha Symposium</hi>, ed. Tony
                        Burke (Eugene, Oregon: Cascade Books, 2017), 194-206.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pettipiece, Timothy, “Many Faced Gods: Triadic (Proto-)Structure and Divine Androgyny in Early Manichaean Cosmogony,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Open
                    Theology</hi> (2015) 1: 245–254.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pettipiece, Timothy, <hi
                        rend="italic">Pentadic Redaction in the Manichaean
                        Kephalaia</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2009).</bibl>
                <bibl>Polotsky, H.-J. and A. Böhlig, <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia (I): 1. Hälfte
                        [Lieferung 1-10]</hi> (Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 1940).</bibl>
                <bibl>Poirier, Paul-Hubert, “Une nouvelle hypothèse sur le titre des Psaumes manichéens dits de Thomas” <hi rend="italic">Apocrypha </hi>12 (2001) : 9-27. </bibl>
                <bibl>Puech, Henri-Charles, <hi
                        rend="italic">EPHE
                    Annuaire</hi> 73 (1964): 122-125. </bibl>
                <bibl>Reed, Annette Yoshiko, “Beyond the Land of Nod: Syriac Images of Asia and the Historiography of ‘The West’,” <hi
                        rend="italic">History of
                    Religions</hi> 49, no. 1 (August 2009): 48-87.</bibl>
                <bibl>Reed, Annette Yoshiko, “Historicizing ‘Jewish-Christianity’,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Jewish-Christianity and the History of
                        Judaism: Collected
                    Essays</hi> (Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2018), xv-xxx. </bibl>
                <bibl>Reeves, John C., <hi rend="italic">Heralds of That Good Realm: Syro-Mesopotamian Gnosis and Jewish Traditions </hi>(Leiden: Brill, 1996).</bibl>
                <bibl>Reeves, John C., <hi rend="italic">Jewish Lore in Manichaean Cosmogony: Studies in the </hi>Book of
                        Giants<hi rend="italic"> Traditions </hi>(Cincinnati, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>Reeves, John C., <hi
                        rend="italic">Prolegomena to a History of Islamicate
                        Manichaeism</hi> (Sheffield: Equinox, 2011).</bibl>
                <bibl>Reeves, John C., “Reconsidering the ‘Prophecy of Zardūšt’,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">A Multiform Heritage: Studies in Early
                        Judaism and Christianity in Honor of Robert A. Kraft</hi>, ed. Benjamin G. Wright (Atlanta: Scholars Press,
                        1999), 167-182.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rehm, Bernhard, ed, <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Pseudoklementinen I:
                        Homilien</hi>, GCS 42 (Berlin: Akademie,
                        1992). </bibl>
                <bibl>Säve-Söderbergh, T. <hi
                        rend="italic">Studies in the Coptic Manichaean
                        Psalm-Book</hi> (Uppsala, 1949). </bibl>
                <bibl>Stang, Charles M., <hi rend="italic">Our Divine Double </hi>(Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
                    2016).</bibl>
                <bibl>Stroumsa, Gedaliahu G., “Polymorphie divine et transformations d’un mythologème : L’Apocryphon de Jean et ses sources,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Vigiliae
                    Christianae</hi> 35, no. 4 (1981) : 412-434.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tardieu, Michel, <hi
                        rend="italic">Le
                    manichéisme</hi> (Paris: Presses universitaires de France, 1981)</bibl>
                <bibl>Taylor, David, “The Coming of Christianity to Mesopotamia,” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World, </hi>ed. Daniel King (New York: Routledge, 2019),
                        68-87)</bibl>
                <bibl>Theodore bar Khonai, <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of
                    Scholia</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Liber scholiorum, </hi>ed. Addai Scher; CSCO 69; (Louvain: Imprimerie orientaliste L. Durbecq, 1954). </bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="italic">Théodore bar Koni: Livre des scholies (recension de Séert) I. Mimrè I-V, </hi>trans. Robert Hespel and René Draguet, CSCO,
                        Scriptores syri 187 (Louvain: Peeters, 1981).</bibl>
                <bibl>Toepel, Alexander, “The Apocryphon of Seth,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">Old Testament Pseudepigrapha: More
                        Noncanonical Scriptures</hi>, vol. 1, ed. Richard
                        Bauckham, James Davila, and Alexander Panayotov (Grand Rapids: Eerdmans,
                        2013), 33-39.</bibl>
                <bibl>van Bladel, Kevin, <hi
                        rend="italic">From Sasanian Mandaeans to Ṣābians of
                        the
                    Marshes</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Van Lindt, Paul, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Names of Manichaean Mythological
                        Figures: A Comparative Study on Terminology in the Coptic
                    Sources</hi> (Wiesbaden: Otto Harrassowitz, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>van Tongerloo, Aloïs, “The Father of Greatness,” in <hi rend="italic">Gnosisforschung und Religionsgeschichte. Festschrift fūr Kurt Rudolph zum 65. Geburtstag, </hi>ed. Holger Preißler und Hubert Seiwert (Marburg:
                        diagonal-Verlag, 1994), 329-342.</bibl>
                <bibl>Widengren, Geo <hi rend="italic">Iranisch-semitische Kulturbegegnung in parthischer Zeit </hi>(Köln: Westdeutscher Verlag, 1960).</bibl>
                <bibl>Widengren, Geo, <hi rend="italic">Mani und der Manichäismus </hi>(Stuttgart: Kohlhammer, 1961).</bibl>
                <bibl>Wiesehöfer, Josef, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ancient Persia from 550 BC to 650
                        AD</hi> (New York: I. B. Tauris, 1998).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
