<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Sami Aydin (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Sergius of Reshaina,
                    Introduction to Aristotle and his Categories, Addressed to Philotheos: Syriac
                    Text, with Introduction, Translation, and Commentary</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Yury</forename>
                        <surname>Arzhanov</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Austrian Academy of Sciences</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2prarzhanov2</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Yury Arzhanov</author>
                        <title level="a">Sami Aydin (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Sergius of Reshaina,
                            Introduction to Aristotle and his Categories, Addressed to Philotheos: Syriac
                            Text, with Introduction, Translation, and Commentary</hi></title>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2PRArzhanov2.pdf</idno>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="545" to="547">545-547</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="11"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <ab type="review-title">Sami Aydin (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Sergius of Reshaina,
                        Introduction to Aristotle and his Categories, Addressed to Philotheos: Syriac
                        Text, with Introduction, Translation, and Commentary</hi>, Aristoteles
                        Semitico-Latinus 24 (Leiden: Brill, 2016). Pp. xii + 328; €112.00.</ab>
                </div>
            <div>
                <p xml:lang="en">Sergius of Reshʿaina (<hi rend="italic">Sargis d-Reš
                    ʿAyna</hi>, d. 536) is a unique figure in the history of the Syriac reception of
                    Greek philosophy. His activity marks the beginning of the process of transition of
                    Greek scientific, medical, and scholarly literature, which after M. Meyerhof is
                    traditionally labelled as going “from Alexandria to Baghdad.” Sergius studied
                    philosophy in Alexandria with Ammonius Hermeiou, who greatly impacted the entire
                    philosophical tradition of the sixth century. Later, Sergius moved to the town of
                    Reshʿaina, where he became the chief physician (<hi rend="italic">archiatros</hi>)
                    and started to translate Greek works into Syriac and to compose original works.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Sergius wrote two treatises based on Ammonius’ lectures: an
                    extensive <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Aristotle’s Categories</hi>, addressed to
                    Theodore, and a short <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Aristotle</hi>, addressed to
                    Philotheos. While the Syriac text of the former work remains unpublished, the latter
                    is now available in this volume. This book is a slightly revised version of the
                    author’s doctoral thesis, defended in 2015 at the University of Uppsala. The book’s
                    fifteen chapters are divides into four parts: an introductory section, an edition of
                    the Syriac text of Sergius’ treatise with a facing English translation, a
                    commentary, and a number of glossaries and indexes.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The introductory part, comprising chapters one to six, provides
                    an overview of Sergius’ life and legacy. Aydin stresses Sergius’ role in
                    transmitting philosophical materials of the school of Ammonius, which are known to
                    us also from the writings of Philoponus, Olympiodorus, Elias, and others.
                    Additionally, Sergius’ medical treatises give evidence for the <hi rend="italic"
                        >cursus studiorum</hi> of the so-called <hi rend="italic">iatrosophists</hi>,
                    and for the development of a similar curriculum in the Christian schools of the late
                    antique and early medieval periods. Besides biographical information, the
                    introductory part provides an inventory of Sergius’ writings and an overview of
                    terminology characteristic of Sergius. The latter overview presents Sergius as a
                    creator and/or a promoter of a whole corpus of philosophical terms, which influenced
                    later generations of Syriac and Arabic scholars.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Aydin’s comparison of two of Sergius’ works, the long <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentary on the Categories</hi> and the short <hi rend="italic"
                        >Introduction to Aristotle</hi>, brings him to the conclusion that the latter
                    must have been written after the former, as an abridgement. This conclusion turns
                    the <hi rend="italic">Commentary</hi> into an additional witness to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Introduction</hi>. The text of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Introduction</hi> has come down to us in a single manuscript, Berlin Petermann
                    I 9 (Sachau 88), dating from the 13th century (its description is provided in
                    chapter five). The use of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary</hi> for establishing the
                    text of the <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi> might be limited by the absence of a
                    reliable critical edition of the <hi rend="italic">Commentary</hi>, so that Aydin
                    had to refer to the two oldest codices containing it. An extra difficulty arises
                    from the fact that Sergius composed both treatises, so that the discrepancies
                    between them may go back to his own editorial work. In the section on “Editorial
                    Principles” (chapter six), the editor admits both limitations.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Chapter seven contains an edition of the Syriac text with a
                    facing English translation. In spite of the fact that Aristotle and his <hi
                        rend="italic">Categories</hi> are mentioned in the title of the published text,
                    Sergius’ treatise constitutes a general introduction to philosophy, rather than a
                    commentary on the first part of the <hi rend="italic">Organon</hi>. As Aydin
                    assumes, the target audience of the <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi> were
                    teachers of philosophy. It focuses on two main topics, namely, logical categories
                    and natural philosophy, a combination which reflects not only Sergius’ education in
                    Alexandria, but most likely also the teaching practices in Syriac schools. Though
                    Sergius clearly stands in the tradition of Aristotelianism, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Introduction</hi> includes excurses into Platonic cosmology and the Stoic
                    notion of qualities, as well as a doxography on the views of “natural
                    philosophers.”</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Chapter eight provides a commentary on the published text,
                    drawing on a large number of sources that may be divided into two main groups: a
                    corpus of writings that stand in the tradition of Ammonius’ school, and Syriac
                    sources that either can be ascribed to Sergius himself or that were composed under
                    the influence of his writings. The first group of sources allows the editor to
                    highlight those elements in Sergius’ text that bring him close to contemporary
                    Alexandrian exegesis. The second group opens the inner-Syriac perspective on the
                    development of the philosophical lexicon, to whose creators Sergius certainly
                    belongs.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In his method of rendering Greek philosophical and scholarly
                    terminology into Syriac, Sergius aimed to find fitting Syriac equivalents that both
                    reflect the Greek words and make them comprehensible for Syriac readers. Such a
                    method differs from later attempts by Syriac translators—who in the seventh and
                    early eighth centuries were mostly connected with the monastery of Qenneshre—to
                    create some sort of mirror-translations that closely follow the Greek originals and
                    employ mechanical equivalents to Greek technical terms. The comparison between the
                    Greek and Syriac sources provided in chapter eight is summarized in the form of
                    Syriac-Greek and Greek-Syriac glossaries that appear at the end of the book as
                    chapters ten and eleven.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">To sum up, Aydin’s book not only makes available an important
                    source for the late ancient Alexandrian tradition, but also provides us with further
                    evidence for Sergius’ contribution to the history of Syriac philosophy.</p>
            </div>     
                
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
