<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Mathews Severios, <hi rend="italic">Word Became Flesh: The
                    Christology of Philoxenos of Mabbug</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Robert A.</forename>
                        <surname>Kitchen</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Regina, Saskatchewan, Canada</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
                <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
                <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by</resp>
                    <name type="person">James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2prkitchen</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Robert A. Kitchen</author>
                        <title level="a">Mathews Severios, <hi rend="italic">Word Became Flesh: The
                            Christology of Philoxenos of Mabbug</hi></title>
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2PRKitchen.pdf</idno><!-- Complete file name -->
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="554" to="557">554-557</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="13"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            
                <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                    <ab type="review-title">Mathews Severios, <hi rend="italic">Word Became Flesh: The
                        Christology of Philoxenos of Mabbug</hi>, Studien zur Orientalischen
                        Kirchen-geschichte 63 (Zurich: LIT Verlag, 2020). Pp. 304; €54.90.</ab>
                </div>
            <div xml:lang="en">
                
                <p xml:lang="en">Time is not always of the essence, especially for
                    scholarship of Syriac Late Antiquity. Mathews Mar Severios is the Metropolitan of
                    the Kandanad West Diocese of the Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church in Kerala, India.
                    Severios submitted his doctoral dissertation in 1984 to the Pontifical Oriental
                    Institute, Rome, on the christology of Philoxenos of Mabbug, under the guidance of
                    Ortiz de Urbina, Vincenzo Poggi, René Lavenant, and Pierre Yousif. As happens with
                    many dissertations, it was not immediately published, but with the encouragement of
                    Martin Tamcke, editor of the series <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Orientalischen
                        Kirchengeschichte</hi>, and with updates in research on Philoxenos, Severios
                    finally brought his labor to full light. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Mar Severios’ title, <hi rend="italic">Word Became Flesh</hi>,
                    targets a critical phrase of Philoxenos in his lengthy and intricate christological
                    debates with a monk Ḥabib. <hi rend="italic">The Ten Discourses against Ḥabib</hi>
                    are well known from the research of André de Halleux and Luise Abramowski, but
                    little studied. Severios’ most important contribution is his point-by-point
                    transcription of Ḥabib’s criticisms of Philoxenos’ miaphysite christology, and the
                    responses to Ḥabib by Philoxenos. The complex subtleties of these accusations and
                    retorts, with plenty of vitriol seasoning the dialogue, require a reader’s full
                    concentration. Severios produces an effective and insightful commentary on the
                    correspondence, conveying a positive picture of the miaphysite theological rationale
                    during its most vibrant and politically viable era.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Beginning with a thorough investigation of the name(s) of the
                    bishop of Mabbug, Severios settles on the ascetical “wandering” character of the
                    term <hi rend="italic">aksenōyō</hi>. The episcopal name of Philoxenos, Severios
                    suggests, was a Greek accommodation for a see in Roman territory. He continues with
                    a chronology of the life and works of Philoxenos, including a number of details
                    culled from Eli of Qartamin’s thirteenth-century <hi rend="italic">mīmrō</hi> on
                    Philoxenos.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The majority of Severios’ narrative is devoted to Ḥabib’s
                    reaction to Philoxenos’ “Letter to the Monks,” the text and French translation of
                    which were published in <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> (1982) by M.
                    Brière and F. Graffin. Ḥabib, otherwise unknown, was apparently a monk whom
                    Philoxenos knew previously. Ḥabib shows himself to be a dyophysite, but neither
                    defends nor opposes directly Chalcedon or the so-called Nestorian interpretation.
                    Philoxenos, in turn, saw Ḥabib’s arguments as conniving and deceitful, and, in fact,
                    veiled Nestorianism. Philoxenos bluntly painted all dyophysites, including the
                    signers of the Chalcedonian definition, as Nestorians. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severios helpfully summarizes and evaluates the principal
                    questions and objections of Ḥabib, discerned from Philoxenos’ letters. The bishop
                    does not systematically list these questions, so Severios organizes Ḥabib’s
                    doctrinal challenges according to topic. The author does acknowledge instances in
                    which Ḥabib was not incorrect in his criticism of the elder theologian. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severios proceeds to an even lengthier treatment of Philoxenos’
                    replies to Ḥabib, similarly arranging the topics systematically, assiduously
                    footnoting the origins of the terms and concepts Philoxenos is employing. These
                    summaries provide a significant research tool that should become an essential
                    departure point for anyone examining this debate and the basics of miaphysite
                    Christology.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ḥabib accuses Philoxenos of advocating notions of Bardaisan,
                    Mani, Marcion, and Eutyches, but the bishop retorts that all these promoted a
                    docetic christology, whereas he holds that Christ was fully human and his body was
                    real and true. As Ḥabib bitterly charges Philoxenos with erring on numerous aspects
                    of Christ, the two pivotal battlegrounds are, first, Philoxenos’ phrase “the
                    becoming of Christ without change,” which Ḥabib rejects as violating the divine
                    nature of Christ (how can the divinity change?), and, second, the suffering, death,
                    and resurrection of Christ—the theopaschite issue—which Ḥabib declares is
                    illogical.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A primary deficiency of Ḥabib’s arguments to which Severios
                    points, following Philoxenos’ hints, is that he was not familiar with the Church
                    Fathers. Ḥabib did not recognize, or was not aware, that several councils and
                    leading theologians had approved on multiple occasions the theological statements
                    asserted by Philoxenos, which Ḥabib attacked as heretical. This is particularly
                    shown in “becoming without change,” as Philoxenos demonstrates the phenomenon of how
                    things can “become” something they were previously not—writing letters, the mystery
                    of baptism, things appearing to the eye, and the creation of human beings—without
                    changing or losing what they were. Philoxenos observes that the Word “was incarnated
                    and became human” was declared in Nicaea, and later confirmed in Constantinople, of
                    which Ḥabib was apparently unaware.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As for God dying on the Cross, which Ḥabib rejects as logically
                    and linguistically impossible, Philoxenos counters that Ḥabib is thinking at too low
                    a level, since Christ transcends the <hi rend="italic">kyānā</hi> or nature of a
                    human being. The death of Christ is a matter to be perceived and comprehended by the
                    “faculty” of faith, which the bishop perceives as a sixth sense, rather than by pure
                    logic. If Christ were an ordinary human being, Philoxenos insists, the crucifixion
                    would not have had salvific power for humanity as a whole.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severios readily adopts the Philoxenian side, for after all,
                    these <hi rend="italic">Ten Letters</hi> were unapologetically intended to
                    demonstrate the miaphysite advantage in thinking and in faith. Yet the subtlety of
                    thought exchanged, in which both protagonists misunderstood each other to some
                    degree, is evidence of how close their ideas were to one another, and at times it is
                    difficult to distinguish how they were different. By his additions to this monograph
                    thirty-six years after submitting the dissertation, Severios seems to perceive in
                    their struggle a mirror of the frustrations of contemporary doctrinal debate,
                    although he does not explicitly say so.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Severios adds an intriguing set of appendices to this deeply
                    theological dissertation, namely, a collection of statements from four major
                    consultations: between Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox (twice); Roman
                    Catholic and Syrian Orthodox; and the Roman Catholic Church and the Malankara
                    Orthodox Syrian Church of India. These statements are carefully worded declarations
                    that say a lot more from their context than by their words. The very fact that these
                    statements are being written at all is the good news, and while the participants are
                    ecstatic, their words are carefully measured in full recognition of what unites and
                    divides their churches. They rejoice, nevertheless, in their continued conversation
                    with hope for an agreement, perhaps a union of the Body of Christ, still just out of
                    reach. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Metropolitan Severios’ Malankara Orthodox Syrian Church is part
                    of these conversations, not by coincidence, so that while Philoxenos and Ḥabib are
                    not as amicable correspondents as these ecumenical consultations, the author appears
                    to be connecting these 1500-year-old theological debates with the still difficult
                    reconciliations in progress today.</p> 
                
            </div>  
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

