<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">In Memoriam: Mary T. Hansbury</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Jeanne-Nicole</forename>
                        <surname>Mellon Saint-Laurent</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Marquette University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2obhansbury</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Jeanne-Nicole Mellon Saint-Laurent</author>
                        <title level="a">In Memoriam: Mary T. Hansbury</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2OBHansbury.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="375" to="376">375-376</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass/>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="obituary">
        <body>
            
            <p xml:lang="en">Syriac scholar Dr Mary Hansbury passed away on March 2, 2021,
                at 79. Hansbury earned a PhD from Temple University in 1987, and she wrote her
                dissertation on <hi rend="italic">Evidence of Jewish Influence in the Writings of
                    Isaac of Nineveh.</hi> Hansbury produced many translations of Syriac texts by
                Ephrem, Jacob of Serug, Simeon the Graceful, Isaac of Nineveh, and John of Dalyatha,
                and these books brought Syriac authors to wider audiences. She lived in China for a
                semester and was interested in interreligious dialogue and the Syriac Church in the
                Tang dynasty. Don Giuseppe Dossetti, to whom Hansbury dedicated her translation of
                Jacob of Serug’s homilies <hi rend="italic">On the Mother of God,</hi> had a lasting
                impact on her spirituality and approach toward scripture, as David Michelson
                recalls. Hansbury fostered a close relationship with the Sisters of the Love of God
                in Oxford, who also published her work. She taught at La Salle University, Bethlehem
                University in Palestine, and SEERI in Kerala. Hansbury was also known for being an
                excellent iconographer. She offered beautiful icons to her teachers, students, and
                friends, as Jason Scully and Sebastian Brock noted in their comments about Mary’s
                life.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Although she liked to refer to herself as “just an Irish peasant,” in truth, she was
                a dedicated scholar and theologian who deeply cared about making Syriac spiritual
                writings accessible to wider audiences. Her conviction that the wisdom of the Syriac
                monastics could nourish contemporary spiritual seekers shaped her work. Hansbury
                attended and presented at many international conferences and was a faithful
                supporter of the community of Syriac Studies in greater Philadelphia. When one would
                converse with Mary at a conference or event, one would note her straightforward way
                of getting to the heart of what mattered to her, and often, as Daniel Schwartz
                remembers, it came down to the worship of God. She had a gift for making people feel
                appreciated and seemed genuinely curious to learn about the scholarship and ideas of
                others. In the introduction to her dissertation, one hears her enthusiasm for Isaac
                of Nineveh as she showcases his understanding of mercy as the foundation of
                adoration and humility: “And what is a merciful heart? It is the heart’s burning for
                all of creation… It grows tender and cannot endure hearing or seeing any injury or
                slight sorrow to anything in creation.” I will miss conversing with Mary and am
                grateful for all she taught me through her work. In the words of Sebastian Brock,
                who taught Mary and assisted her in editing her work, may Mary’s soul find rest in
                the bridal chamber of joy: <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                    >ܬܬܢܝܚ ܢܦܫܗ̇ ܒܓܢܘܢܐ ܕܚܕ̄ܘܬܐ</foreign> . </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
