<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Considerations in Rendering <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign>
                    in a Church Bible</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Jerome A.</forename>
                        <surname>Lund</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Independent Scholar</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2021</date>
                <idno>Volume 24.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv24n2lund</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Jerome A. Lund</author>
                        <title level="a">Considerations in Rendering <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign>
                            in a Church Bible</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol24/HV24N2Lund.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="24">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="395" to="410">395-410</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="4"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>translation</term>
                    <term>interpretation</term>
                    <term>Exodus</term>
                    <term>Red Sea</term>
                    <term>Yom suf</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2021-09-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">

            <front>
                <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Abstract</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">During the revision of the Antioch Bible, the question of how 
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign>
                        should be translated arose. Currently, different translators have offered different
                        solutions. This essay will trace the history of the term from the original
                        translators of both the Old and New Testaments, through the commentators, and then
                        through the lexicographers. The essay will offer a solution to the problem going
                        forward.</p>
                </div>
            </front>
        
            <body>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.0" xml:lang="en">
                <head>0. Introduction </head>
                <p>In preparing a translation of the Syriac Bible to English for the modern church,
                    translation issues arise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> This study arose through reviewing the translation
                            of the book of Exodus for the Antioch Bible project and discussing the
                            issue with the larger review committee. In particular, I wish to thank
                            my co-reviewer Tarsee Li of Oakwood University, Huntsville, Alabama, for
                            his critique of an earlier draft of this essay. The original translation
                            of Exodus was done masterfully by Mark R. Meyer, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Exodus in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>,
                            eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel (Piscataway: Gorgias Press,
                            2017). </p></note> One such issue is how to render the expression <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the sea
                    of Suph,” found in both the Old and New Testaments.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> Exod 10:19; 13:18; 15:4, 22;
                            23:31; Num 14:25; 21:4; 33:10, 11; Deut 1:40; 2:1; 11:4; Josh 2:10;
                            4:23; 24:6; Judg 11:16; 1 Kgs 9:26; Ps 106:7, 9, 22; 136:13, 15; Jer
                            49:21; Judith 5:13; Neh 9:9; 2 Chron 2:15; 1 Chron 4:9; Acts 7:36; Heb
                            11:29. The cases in the New Testament render <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐρυθρὰ θάλασσα</foreign> “the Red
                            Sea,” the translation of the Hebrew <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם</foreign>־<foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> known from
                            the Old Greek of Exodus and elsewhere. At times in the Old Greek, the
                            adjective comes after the noun as <foreign xml:lang="gr">θάλασσα ἐρυθρὰ</foreign>.</p></note> In this
                    essay, I will examine the problem historically and then offer a solution. The
                    essay will move from the original translations through the native commentators
                    to the lexicographers. Roughly speaking, the Peshitta Old Testament was made in
                    the second century from the Hebrew.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> M. P. Weitzman, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                                Version of the Old Testament</hi>, University of Cambridge Oriental
                            Publications 56 (Cambridge: Faculty of Oriental Studies, University of
                            Cambridge, 1999), 258.</p></note> By contrast, the Peshitta New
                    Testament came into being about the fifth century.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> Sebastian P. Brock, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac Tradition</hi>, Second Revised
                            Edition, Gorgias Handbooks 7 (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2006),
                        17.</p></note> While there was undoubtedly an older Syriac translation of
                    the New Testament, it is not extant for the relevant books, namely Acts and
                        Hebrews.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac Tradition</hi>, 17 and
                            19.</p></note> So, how did native Syriac speakers understand the term at
                    the translation stage and did this understanding change over time?</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>1. The Original Translations</head>
                <p>The second century translators of the Old Testament did not fully understand the
                    meaning of <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם־סוּף</foreign>, the
                    Hebrew construction consisting of a noun in construct state followed by another
                    noun in the absolute state. In keeping with other such constructions, they
                    rendered it as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the sea of Suph,” understanding <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> to be a proper noun.
                    This is in agreement with the rendering of other geographic terms like <foreign xml:lang="heb">גַּן־עֵדֶן</foreign> “the garden of
                    Eden” rendered as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܕܝܣܐ
                        ܕܥܕܢ</foreign> “the paradise of Eden” (Gen 3:23), <foreign xml:lang="heb">אֶרֶץ־מִדְיָן</foreign> “the land of
                    Midian” translated as <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܐܪܥܐ ܕܡܕܝܢ</foreign> “the land of Midian” (Exod 2:15), <foreign xml:lang="heb">מִדְבַּר־סִין</foreign> “the
                    wilderness of Sin” expressed as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܒܪܐ ܕܣܝܢ</foreign> “the
                    wilderness of Sin” (Exod 17:1), <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >הַר סִינַי</foreign> “the mountain of Sinai” put as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܛܘܪܐ ܕܣܝܢܝ</foreign> “the
                    mountain of Sinai” (Exod 24:16), <foreign xml:lang="heb">נְהַר מִצְרַיִם</foreign> “the river
                    of Egypt” expressed by <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܢܗܪܐ ܕܡܨܪܝܢ</foreign> “the river of Egypt” (Gen 15:18), and <foreign xml:lang="heb">מְקוֹם שְׁכֶם</foreign> “the
                    vicinity of Shechem” phrased as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܪܐ ܕܫܟܝܡ</foreign> “the
                    vicinity of Shechem” (Gen 12:6).</p>
                <p>Furthermore, this is in harmony with the renderings of <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם־כִּנֶּרֶת</foreign> “the Sea of
                    Kinnereth” and <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם
                        כִּנְרוֹת</foreign> “the Sea of Kinneroth” as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܟܢܪܬ</foreign> “the Sea
                    of Kinnereth” (Num 34:11 and Josh 12:3 respectively), and <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם יַעְזֵר</foreign> “the Sea of
                    Jazer” as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܝܥܙܝܪ</foreign> “the Sea of Jazer” (Jer 48:32). Although in these cases the noun
                    <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם</foreign> is vocalized in
                    Hebrew with <hi rend="italic">qametz</hi>, allowing for the interpretation of
                    the collocation as an apposition, the grammarians Takamitsu Muraoka and Paul
                    Joüon consider the form <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >יָם</foreign> as being in the construct state, noting that the only time that
                    the form <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם</foreign> is used in
                    Hebrew is in the collocation <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >יַם־סוּף</foreign>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Paul Joüon, S. J., and Takamitsu Muraoka, <hi
                                rend="italic">A Grammar of Biblical Hebrew</hi> (Rome: Pontifical
                            Biblical Institute, 2006), § 13c and § 96An. Accordance module:
                            Jouon–Muraoka Hebrew Grammar, version 2.6.</p></note> Moreover, the
                    Syriac translator had no problem with the directional
                    <hi rend="italic">he </hi>intervening between <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם</foreign> and its
                    <hi rend="italic">nomen rectum </hi>in <foreign xml:lang="heb">וַיִּתְקָעֵהוּ יָםָּה
                        סּוּף</foreign> taken over as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܪܡܝܬܗ ܒܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign>
                    “and (the wind) cast it (the locust) into the sea of Suph” (Exod 10:19). Again,
                    when the <hi rend="italic">nomen rectum </hi>is a common
                    noun, it comes in the <hi rend="italic">status emphaticus</hi> as in <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם הַמֶּלַח</foreign> “the sea of
                    salt” rendered as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܡܠܚܐ</foreign> “the sea of salt” (Gen 14:3).</p>
                <p>As well, compare: <foreign xml:lang="heb">לְשׁוֹן
                    יָם־מִצְרַיִם</foreign> “the tongue of the sea of Egypt” encoded as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܫܢ ܝܡܐ ܕܒܡܨܪܝܢ</foreign>
                    “the tongue of the sea that is in Egypt” (Isa 11:15) and <foreign xml:lang="heb">אֶל־יָם יָפוֹא</foreign> “to the sea
                    of Joppa” realized as <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܠܝܡܐ ܠܝܘܦܐ</foreign> “to the sea, to Joppa” (Ezra 3:7). Here, the translators
                    demonstrate flexibility in conveying the meaning to the target audience. </p>
                <p>Apart from the collocation <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                    >יַם־סוּף</foreign>, the word <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >סוּף</foreign> appears by itself as a geographic designation once (Deut 1:1).
                    There, the Old Greek offers <foreign xml:lang="gr">πλησίον τῆς
                        ἐρυθρᾶς</foreign> “near the red” for the Hebrew <foreign xml:lang="heb">מוֹל סוּף</foreign>, apparently
                    understanding this <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> to
                    be a reference to the Red Sea. Thus, NETS translates the phrase as “near the Red
                    Sea.” Some Greek text witnesses in fact explicitly read <foreign xml:lang="gr">πλησίον τῆς ἐρυθρᾶς θαλάσσης</foreign> “near the
                    Red Sea.” Targum Onqelos agrees with this interpretation of <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign>, rendering it as <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם סוּף</foreign> “the Sea of
                    Suph.” Targum Neofiti, Cairo Geniza manuscript Br, and the Fragment Targums
                    concur with Targum Onqelos in identifying this <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> as the sea through
                    which the children of Israel passed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For the targums, I have used the following
                            Accordance modules: TARG-T for Onqelos, TARG2-T for Neofiti, TARGG-T for
                            the Cairo Geniza manuscript, and TARGF-T for the Fragment Targums.
                        </p></note></p>
                <p>Knowledge of the Greek rendering
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐρυθρὰ θάλασσα </foreign> “the
                    Red Sea” was not widely known among the Syrians<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8"
                        n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> Where it was known was in the translations of
                            church fathers such as in the Syriac translation of Basil of Caesarea’s
                            Hexaemeron (Robert W. Thomson, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Version of
                                the Hexaemeron by Basil of Caesarea</hi> [CSCO 550, SS 222; Louvain:
                            Peeters, 1995], 57, l. 12), which translation dates probably to the
                            fifth century (compare Thomson, <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Version of
                                the Hexaemeron by Basil of Caesarea</hi>, VI, and Sebastian P.
                            Brock, “Basil of Caesarea,” <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic
                                Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage</hi>, ed. Sebastian P. Brock et
                            al. [Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2011], 64). I owe this insight to an
                            unnamed reviewer.</p></note> until the translation of the Greek Old
                    Testament, known to us as the Syrohexpla. In that translation, made in 616-17 at
                    the Enaton monastery near Alexandria, Egypt, Paul of Tella used <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                    Sea” as the reflex of <foreign xml:lang="gr">θάλασσα ἐρυθρὰ</foreign> “the
                    Red Sea.” In Deut 1:1, Paul renders <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                        Sea,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Arthur
                            Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">The Pentateuch in the Version of the
                                Syro-Hexapla, A fac-simile Edition of a Midyat MS. discovered
                                1964</hi>, CSCO 369, Subsidia 45 (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO,
                            1975), fol. 152r.</p></note> supporting the Greek variant <foreign xml:lang="gr">τῆς ἐρυθρᾶς θαλάσσης</foreign> “(near) the Red
                    Sea.”</p>
                <p>Now, there are three or possible four places in the Old Testament where Hebrew
                    <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> indicates a water
                    plant. Richard D. Patterson has called attention to these passages, stating that
                    <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> is “a general
                    term for marshplants.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Richard D. Patterson, <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign>, entry 1479
                            in <hi rend="italic">Theological Wordbook of the Old Testament</hi>,
                            eds. R. Laird Harrison, Gleason L. Archer, and Bruce K. Waltke (Chicago:
                            Moody Bible Institute, 1980). Accordance module TWOT.</p></note> In Exod
                    2:3 and 5, Patterson glosses it as “marsh reeds,” in Isa 19:6 as “rushes,” and
                    in Jonah 2:6 as “seaweed.” He also renders the Hebrew collocation <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם סוּף</foreign> as “sea of
                    reeds.” What is interesting for this study is that the Peshitta finds
                    appropriate words to translate these passages, never using the word <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign>. In Exodus, the
                    Peshitta uses the word <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܪܩܩܐ</foreign> “a shallow,” in Isaiah the word <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܦܝܪܘܢ</foreign> “papyrus,”
                    and in Jonah the phrase <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܒܐܫܬܗ ܕܝܡܐ</foreign> “at the bottom of the sea.” There is, therefore, no
                    indication that the translator of Peshitta Exodus understood the <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַם־סוּף</foreign> as a water plant.
                    One could say the same for Onqelos and its twin Targum Jonathan to the Prophets.
                    In Exodus, Onqelos translates the <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> of Exodus 2 as <foreign xml:lang="heb">יַעְרָא</foreign> “rushes.” Jonathan
                    renders it as <foreign xml:lang="heb">גוֹמַא</foreign>
                        “papyrus reed” in Isaiah, but understands the <foreign xml:lang="heb">סוּף</foreign> of Jonah 2:6 to be a
                    reference to the Sea of Suph (<foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >יַמָא דְסוּף</foreign> ). Similarly, the Palestinian targums Neofiti and the
                    Fragment Targums rendered <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                        >סוּף</foreign> of Exodus 2 as <foreign xml:lang="heb"
                            >אפרה</foreign> “grassy area.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See the discussion of Jerome A. Lund, “2.4.5
                            Peshitta,” in The Hebrew Bible, Vol. 1B: Pentateuch, Former and Latter
                            Prophets, eds. Armin Lange and Emanuel Tov, in <hi rend="italic">Textual
                                History of the Hebrew Bible</hi>, ed. Armin Lange et al. (Leiden:
                            Brill, 2017), 178.</p></note></p>
                <p>The early fifth century translators of the Peshitta New Testament at Acts 7:36
                    and Heb 11:29 substituted the Old Testament expression <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the sea
                    of Suph” for the Greek
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐρυθρὰ θάλασσα </foreign> “the
                    Red Sea,” rather than translate it as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                    Sea.” The reference to the Exodus in both of these verses is patently clear.
                    Their translation strategy of substitution, that is, using the expression that
                    appears in their Old Testament, removed any apparent discrepancy with the
                    Peshitta Old Testament. It was not until the translation of Thomas of Harkl,
                    made at the same time and in the same place as the Old Testament translation of
                    Paul of Tella, that the reading <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                    Sea” entered the Syriac New Testament. Thomas rendered <foreign xml:lang="gr">ποιήσας τέρατα καὶ σημεῖα ἐν γῇ Αἰγύπτῳ καὶ ἐν
                        ἐρυθρᾷ θαλάσσῃ</foreign> “doing wonders and signs in the land of Egypt and at the
                    Red Sea” as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܥܒ̣ܕ
                        ܐܬܘ̈ܬܐ ܘܬܕܡܪ̈ܬܐ ܒܐܪܥܐ ܕܡܨܪܝܢ ܘܒܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “doing signs and wonders in
                    the land of Egypt and at the Red Sea” (Acts 7:36). From his translation, Thomas
                    could have had
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">σημεῖα καὶ τέρατα </foreign>“signs
                    and wonders” in his Vorlage rather than
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">τέρατα καὶ σημεῖα </foreign>“wonders
                    and signs.” His rendering <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ ܥܒܪܘ ܒܢܝ̈ܐ
                        ܕܐܝܣܪܐܝܠ ܠܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “By faith the children of Israel crossed the Red
                    Sea” (Heb 11:29) apparently goes back to the Greek
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">πίστει διέβησαν οἱ υἱοὶ Ισραηλ τὴν ἐρυθρὰν θάλασσαν </foreign>
                    “By faith the children of Israel crossed the Red Sea.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> I wish to thank Andreas
                            Juckel of the University of Muenster for providing me with these texts
                            from the Harklean version. As well, Dr. Juckel was kind enough to
                            critique a draft of this essay, offering concrete suggestions for its
                            improvement.</p></note> In his edition of the Greek New Testament,
                    Hermann Freiherr von Soden records this plus of the expressed subject <foreign xml:lang="gr">οἱ υἱοὶ Ισραηλ</foreign> as appearing in one
                    thirteenth century miniscule.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Hermann Freiherr von Soden, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Schriften des Neuen Testaments</hi>, vol. 2 (Göttingen: Vanderhoeck
                            und Ruprecht, 1913), 819.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>2. The Commentators</head>
                <p>The ninth century Ishodad of Merv dealt with the understanding of the term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> in his
                    commentary on Exod 15:4. It is clear that he had no straightforward answer to
                    what the word <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign>
                    meant. He states that the sea in question had two names, one <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                    Sea” ala the Greek and the other <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the sea
                    of Suph” as found in the Peshitta. Some, he says, do not give any special
                    meaning to the terms — the place was just called that. Others explain that the
                    sea was called <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܣܘܦ</foreign>
                    because Pharaoh and his forces came to an end (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܦܘ</foreign>) there, similar
                    to ‏<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܬܩܪܐ ܢܚܠܐ ܕܣܘܦܢܗ
                        ܕܓܘܓ</foreign> “It will be called the valley of the destruction of Gog” (Ezek
                    39:11). And these same exegetes would say that the sea was called <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “red” because
                    of the blood of those of the house of Pharaoh who perished in it. Their
                    interpretation of <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܣܘܦ</foreign> is rooted in etymology, deriving the term from <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> “come to an
                    end”; their interpretation of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “red” stems
                    from association with blood. Still others had another interpretation of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign>, also rooted in
                    etymology via the root <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܣܘܦ</foreign> “come to an end.” At that place, they say, the tongue of the sea
                    of the Indians comes to an end (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܿܠܡ ܘܣܿܐܦ</foreign>). Yet
                    others, using the same etymology, assert that nothing moves in it, but when they
                    come to that tongue they turn back, whether fish or anything else. In his
                    comments, Ishodad does not mention any connection with flora that grows in
                    wetlands.</p>
                <p>In his commentary on Deut 1:1, Ishodad brings the view of a certain Michael on
                    the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܩܒܠ
                        ܣܘܦ</foreign> “opposite Suph.” Michael explains that <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> means <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܡܠܚܐ</foreign> “the Salt
                    Sea.” In the margin of Ishodad’s commentary, someone added the following: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܢܝܐ ... ܚܠܦ ܟܠ ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܣܘܦ. ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ ܐܿܡܪ</foreign> “The Greek reads ‘the Red Sea’ in every instance
                    of ‘the Sea of Suph’.” In her translation of this verse, Carmel McCarthy renders
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܩܒܠ ܣܘܦ</foreign> as
                    “opposite Suph.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > Carmel McCarthy, <hi rend="italic">Deuteronomy in The Syriac Peshiṭta
                                Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                            Andreas Juckel (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2013). </p></note></p>
                <p>The thirteenth century polymath Barhebraeus discusses the term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> in his
                    commentary on Exod 15:4.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Martin Sprengling and William Creighton Graham,
                            eds., <hi rend="italic">Barhebraeus’ Scholia on the Old Testament, Part
                                I: Genesis–II Samuel</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                            1931), 120–21.</p></note> He comments as follows: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ ܝܘ̄ ܒܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ
                        ܗ̄ ܕܣܘܦ ܐܬܩܼܪܝ. ܒܕܣܘܦܐ ܗܘ ܕܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ ܕܒܬܝܡܢ ܥܡܪܬܐ. ܘܐܝܟ ܠܫܢܐ ܡܿܬܚ ܠܐܦ̈ܝ
                        ܡܨܪܝܢ ܘܡܣܬܝܟ ܟܪ ܕܥܒܪܘ ܥܒܪ̈ܝܐ. ܐܝܟܐ ܕܡ̈ܐܬܝܢ ܡ̈ܝܠܐ ܗܘ ܦܬܝܗ</foreign> “<hi
                        rend="italic">In the sea of Suph</hi>. The Greek: <hi rend="italic">In the
                        Red Sea</hi>. It was called Suph because it was the end of the Red Sea that
                    is in the south of the inhabited area, and like a tongue it stretches towards
                    Egypt and ends where the Hebrews crossed, where its breadth is two hundred
                    miles.” So, for Barhebraeus, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> was a
                    geographic term derived etymologically from the root “to end,” due to the fact
                    that it was the end of the sea as it jutted into Egypt. It coincided with what
                    the Greeks termed “the Red Sea.”</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>3. Lexicography</head>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.3.1" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>3.1 A Classical Lexicon</head>
                    <p>Writing in the tenth century, Hassan bar Bahlul states the following: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܣܘܦ ܕܝܢ ܐܬܩܼܪܝ. ܡܛܠ
                        ܕܒܗ ܣܦܘ ܡܨܪ̈ܝܐ. ܘܡܬܼܐܡܪ ܕܝܢ ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ ܡܛܠ ܕܒܗ ܐܬܛܠܩ ܕܡܗܘܢ</foreign> (The sea)
                        “was called” (the sea) “of Suph because the Egyptians came to an end in it,
                        and it is termed the Red Sea because their blood vanished in it.”<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> Rubens
                                Duval, ed., <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum Auctore Hassano bar
                                    Bahlule e Pluribus Codicibus Edidit et Notulis Instruxit</hi>
                                (Paris, 1901), col. 1319.</p></note> Bar Bahlul echoes the same
                        understandings recorded by Ishodad. </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.3.2" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>3.2 Modern Lexica</head>
                    <p>A survey of the modern lexica reveals two views of understanding the term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign>. On the one
                        hand, some explain the term as representing the Egyptian word for papyrus.
                        On the other hand, there are those who regard it as a proper noun.</p>
                    <p>Influenced by an essay of Frederic Charles Cook, Robert Payne Smith calls <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> an Egyptian
                        word meaning “papyrus.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Robert Payne Smith, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Thesaurus Syriacus</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1879-1901),
                                2577. Payne Smith based this on the essay of Frederic Charles Cook,
                                “On Egyptian Words in the Pentateuch,” pages 476-492 in <hi
                                    rend="italic">The Holy Bible according to the Authorized Version
                                    (A.D. 1611), with an Explanatory and Critical Commentary and A
                                    Division of the Translation by Bishops and Other Clergy of the
                                    Anglican Church, Vol. I – Part I: Genesis–Exodus</hi>, ed.
                                Frederic Charles Cook (New York: Scribner, Armstrong &amp; Co.,
                                1873), 484. The authoritative source standing behind the essay of
                                Cook was the Egyptologist Charles Wycliffe Goodwin.</p></note> It is
                        no wonder then that his daughter Jayne Payne Smith describes <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> as “from
                        the Egyptian word for papyrus,” glossing <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as
                        “<hi rend="italic">the reedy sea </hi>i.e. the Red
                            Sea.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Jayne Payne Smith, <hi rend="italic">A Compendious Syriac
                                    Dictionary</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1903), 369.</p></note>
                        Also within the British tradition, William Jennings in his New Testament
                        dictionary defines <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                            >ܣܘܦ</foreign> as “reeds,” connecting it to the Egyptian word <hi
                                rend="italic">twfi</hi> “reeds, papyrus,” and glosses the phrase <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as
                        “lit. <hi rend="italic">the reedy sea</hi>, <hi rend="italic">the Red
                            Sea</hi>.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> William Jennings, <hi rend="italic">Lexicon to
                                    the Syriac New Testament</hi>, revised Ulric Gantillon (Oxford:
                                Clarendon Press, 1926), 149.</p></note> This view found favor in the
                        eyes of the native lexicographers Toma Audo and Jacques-Eugene Manna. Audo
                        states the following: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ: ܒܪܬ ܩܠܐ ܗܝ
                            ܡܨܪܝܬܐ. ܗ̄. ܕ̄. ܦܦܪܘܢ . ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ . ܗ̄. ܕ̄. ܕܗܘܐ ܒܗ ܦܦܪܘܢ ܘܐܪܒܢܐ. ܡܢ ܕܝܠܢ
                            ܐܢܫܝ̈ܢ ܡܦܪܫܝܢ ܠܗܿ . ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “The term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> is an
                        Egyptian expression meaning ‘papyrus’; the sea of ‘suph’ means that there
                        were papyrus and rushes in it. Some of our people interpret the collocation
                        as ‘the Red Sea’.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Toma Audo, <hi rend="italic">Treasure of the
                                    Syriac Language (Simtā d-leššānā suryāyā)</hi>, 2 vols. (Mosul:
                                Dominican Press, 1897), 134. The second volume was published in 1901
                                but bears the date of the first, to wit, 1897. See George A. Kiraz,
                                “Introduction,” in Thomas Audo, Treasure of the Syriac Language,
                                vol. 1 (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2008), 3*.</p></note> Manna
                        defines <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> as
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܒܠܐ ܕܝܡܐ</foreign>
                        “sea squill” or “rush.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Jacques-Eugene Manna, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Chaldean – Arabic Dictionary</hi> (Mosul, 1900; reprinted
                                Beirut: Babel Center Publications, 1975), 486.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Carl Brockelmann, on the other hand, does not include it in his <hi
                            rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                            n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> Carl Brockelmann, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Lexicon Syriacum</hi>, Second Edition (Halle: Niemeyer,
                                1928).</p></note> He must have done so because he regarded <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> in this
                        collocation as a proper noun. In this, he was followed by Michael Sokoloff,
                        who likewise fails to record it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Michael Sokoloff,
                                <hi rend="italic">A Syriac Lexicon </hi>(Winona
                                Lake: Eisenbrauns and Piscataway: Gorgias Press,
                        2009).</p></note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>4. Antioch Bible Contributors’ Renderings of ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</head>
                <p>Translators of different books of the Bible handled the expression <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> in
                    different ways. For Exodus, Mark R. Meyer consistently renders the expression as
                    “the Sea of Suph” (Exod 10:19; 13:18; 15:4, 22; 23:31).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> Mark R. Meyer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Exodus</hi>.</p></note> By contrast, for Numbers,
                    Edward M. Cook translates <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as “the
                    Reed Sea” (Num 14:25) and “the Sea of Reeds” (Num 21:4; 33:10-11).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Edward M. Cook,
                                <hi rend="italic">Numbers in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                                Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015). </p></note> Similarly in Deuteronomy,
                    Carmel McCarthy phrases it as “the Sea of Reeds” (Deut 1:40; 2:1; 11:4).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> McCarthy, <hi
                                rend="italic">Deuteronomy</hi>.</p></note> Gillian Greenberg and
                    Donald M. Walter consistently render <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as “the
                    Sea of Suph” in Joshua (Josh 2:10; 4:23; 24:6),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                        n="27"><p rend="footnote text"> Gillian Greenberg and Donald M. Walter, <hi
                                rend="italic">Joshua in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                                Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015).</p></note> as “the sea of Suph” in
                    Judges (Jud 11:16)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Donald M. Walter and Gillian Greenberg, <hi
                                rend="italic">Judges in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                                Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015).</p></note>, and again as “the Sea of
                    Suph” in 1 Kings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Donald M. Walter and Gillian Greenberg, <hi
                                rend="italic">Kings in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                                Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2018).</p></note> For Psalms, Richard A.
                    Taylor uses “the Sea of Reeds” as his slot translation (Ps 106:7, 9, 22; 135[MT
                    136]:13, 15). In Jdt 5:13, Walter, Greenberg, and Eric Tully use “the Sea of
                    Suph” as their translation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Donald M. Walter, Gillian Greenberg, and Eric
                            Tully, <hi rend="italic">The Book of Women: Ruth, Susanna, Esther, and
                                Judith in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>,
                            eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel (Piscataway: Gorgias Press,
                            2020).</p></note> In sum, the most prominent translations in the Old
                    Testament are “the Sea of Suph” and “the Sea of Reeds.”</p>
                <p>While an early error entered the Syriac text tradition at 2 Chron 2:16 (MT 15) as
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the
                    Sea of Suph” as attested by the only reading found in the Leiden edition,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> R. P. Gordon in
                            collaboration with P. B. Dirksen (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Chronicles,
                                Part IV.2 of The Old Testament in Syriac according to the Peshiṭta
                                Version</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1998).</p></note> the Antioch Bible
                    correctly reads <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܝܘܦܐ</foreign> “the sea of Joppa,” a reading confirmed by the Hebrew <foreign xml:lang="heb">יָם יָפוֹ</foreign> “the sea of
                        Joppa.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Robert P. Gordon, <hi rend="italic">Chronicles in The Syriac Peshiṭta
                                Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                            Andreas Juckel (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2019). </p></note> The
                    translations of Neh 9:9 and 1 Macc 4:9 have yet to appear in print.</p>
                <p>Turning to the New Testament, Robert Kitchen offers the rendition “the Red Sea”
                    for <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> in the
                    text, but adds a footnote stating that it literally means “sea of reeds.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"> Robert Kitchen,
                                <hi rend="italic">Acts in The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                                Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel
                            (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2014), 47.</p></note> In Heb 11:29, Daniel
                    King and J. Edward Walters render <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as “the
                    Red Sea” without any footnote.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Daniel King and J. Edward Walters, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hebrews and the General Catholic Epistles in The
                                Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George
                            Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel (Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2016),
                            123.</p></note> These renderings ignore the Syriac and slot in a
                    contemporary traditional translation based on the Greek.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv24n2lund.5" xml:lang="en">
                <head>5. Conclusion</head>
                <p>Historically speaking, the translators of the Peshitta Bible understood the word
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> in the
                    collocation <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> to be a proper noun, that is, “The Sea of Suph.” The translators
                    of the New Testament borrowed the Old Testament term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> “the Sea
                    of Suph” to bring harmony to the text of Scripture, rather than translating the
                    Greek
                    <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐρυθρὰ θάλασσα </foreign> “the
                    Red Sea,” as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ
                        ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red Sea.” It was not until the translations of Paul of Tella
                    and Thomas of Harkl that the term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܣܘܡܩܐ</foreign> “the Red
                    Sea” entered Syriac literature. Later interpreters tried to add meaning to the
                    text by explaining the term <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> etymologically,
                    connecting it to the root <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> “come to an
                    end.” For some, it was where the Egyptian hordes came to an end. For others, it
                    was where the sea came to an end as its tongue extended into Egypt. No one
                    connected it to river fauna. Only in modern times have native speakers of Syriac
                    followed the view that <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܣܘܦ</foreign> is equivalent to an Egyptian word meaning “papyus,” a water plant.
                    While British scholars quickly embraced the suggestion, Carl Brockelmann did
                    not. But since both Toma Audo and Jacques-Eugene Manna accept the view that <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܦ</foreign> means
                    “papyrus,” it is permissible to translate <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as “the
                    Reed Sea” or the like in a modern church Bible, even though the ancient
                    translators and interpreters of the Bible did not recognize it as such. My
                    personal preference would be to render <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܡܐ ܕܣܘܦ</foreign> as “the
                    Sea of Suph” in the Antioch Bible, adding the modern understanding in a
                    footnote. For the New Testament, the note should read that the New Testament
                    translators substituted the Old Testament expression “the Sea of Suph” rather
                    than translated the Greek “the Red Sea.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Accordance Bible Software. Targumic modules: TARG-T for Onqelos, TARG2-T for
                    Neofiti, TARGG-T for the Cairo Geniza manuscript, and TARGF-T for the Fragment
                    Targums. </bibl>
                <bibl>Audo, Toma.
                        <hi rend="italic">Treasure of the Syriac Language </hi>(<hi
                        rend="italic">Simtā d-leššānā suryāyā</hi>), 2 vols. Mosul: Dominican Press,
                    1897.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock, Sebastian P. <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac Tradition</hi>.
                    Second Revised Edition. Gorgias Handbooks 7. Piscataway: Gorgias Press,
                    2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>Brockelmann, Carl. <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum</hi>. Second Edition.
                    Halle: Niemeyer, 1928.</bibl>
                <bibl>Cook, Edward M. <hi rend="italic">Numbers. The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                        Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel. Piscataway:
                    Gorgias Press, 2015. </bibl>
                <bibl>Cook, Frederic Charles. “<hi rend="italic">On Egyptian Words in the
                        Pentateuch</hi>.” Pages 476-492 in
                    <hi rend="italic">The Holy Bible according to the Authorized Version (A.D. 1611), with an Explanatory and Critical Commentary and A Division of the Translation by Bishops and Other Clergy of the Anglican Church, Vol. I – Part I: Genesis–Exodus, ed. </hi>Frederic
                    Charles Cook<hi rend="italic">. </hi>New York: Scribner,
                    Armstrong &amp; Co., 1873.</bibl>
                <bibl>Duval, Rubens, ed.
                    <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum Auctore Hassano bar Bahlule e Pluribus Codicibus Edidit et Notulis Instruxit. </hi>Paris,
                    1901.</bibl>
                <bibl>Greenberg, Gillian, and Donald M. Walter. <hi rend="italic">Kings. The Syriac
                        Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                    Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2018.</bibl>
                <bibl>Greenberg, Gillian, and Donald M. Walter. <hi rend="italic">Joshua. The Syriac
                        Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                    Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gordon, R. P., in collaboration with P. B. Dirksen (eds.). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chronicles</hi>. Part IV.2 of <hi rend="italic">The Old Testament in Syriac
                        according to the Peshiṭta Version</hi>. Leiden: Brill, 1998.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gordon, Robert P. <hi rend="italic">Chronicles</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                        Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                    Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2019.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jennings, William. <hi rend="italic">Lexicon to the Syriac New Testament</hi>.
                    Revised Ulric Gantillon. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1926.</bibl>
                <bibl>Joüon, Paul, S. J., and Takamitsu Muraoka,
                    <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of Biblical Hebrew. </hi>Rome:
                    Pontifical Biblical Institute, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl>King, Daniel, and J. Edward Walters. <hi rend="italic">Hebrews and the General
                        Catholic Epistles. The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>,
                    eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2016.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kiraz, George A. “Introduction.” In Thomas Audo, <hi rend="italic">Treasure of
                        the Syriac Language</hi>, vol. 1. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2008.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kitchen, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Acts. The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                        Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel. Piscataway:
                    Gorgias Press, 2014.</bibl>
                <bibl>Lund, Jerome A. “2.4.5 Peshitta.” Pages 173–80 in <hi rend="italic">The Hebrew
                        Bible</hi>, Vol. 1B: <hi rend="italic">Pentateuch, Former and Latter
                        Prophets</hi>, eds. Armin Lange and Emanuel Tov, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Textual History of the Hebrew Bible</hi>, ed. Armin Lange et al. Leiden:
                    Brill, 2017.</bibl>
                <bibl>Manna, Jacques-Eugene.
                    <hi rend="italic">Chaldean – Arabic Dictionary. </hi>Mosul,
                    1900; reprinted Beirut: Babel Center Publications, 1975. </bibl>
                <bibl>McCarthy, Carmel. <hi rend="italic">Deuteronomy. The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with
                        English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel.
                    Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl>Meyer, Mark R. <hi rend="italic">Exodus. The Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English
                        Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and Andreas Juckel. Piscataway:
                    Gorgias Press, 2017. </bibl>
                <bibl>Patterson, Richard D. סוּף. Entry 1479 in <hi rend="italic">Theological Wordbook
                        of the Old Testament</hi>, eds. R. Laird Harrison, Gleason L. Archer, and
                    Bruce K. Waltke. Chicago: Moody Bible Institute, 1980. Accordance module
                    TWOT.</bibl>
                <bibl>Payne Smith, Jayne.
                    <hi rend="italic">A Compendious Syriac Dictionary. </hi>Oxford:
                    Clarendon Press, 1903.</bibl>
                <bibl>Payne Smith, Robert.
                    <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus. </hi>Oxford:
                    Clarendon Press, 1879-1901). </bibl>
                <bibl>Sokoloff, Michael.
                    <hi rend="italic">A Syriac Lexicon. </hi>Winona Lake:
                    Eisenbrauns and Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2009.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sprengling, Martin, and William Creighton Graham, eds. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Barhebraeus’ Scholia on the Old Testament</hi>, Part I: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Genesis–II Samuel</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1931.</bibl>
                <bibl>Vööbus, Arthur.
                    <hi rend="italic">The Pentateuch in the Version of the Syro-Hexapla, A facsimile Edition of a Midyat MS. discovered 1964. </hi>CSCO
                    369, Subsidia 45. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1975.</bibl>
                <bibl>Walter, Donald M., and Gillian Greenberg. <hi rend="italic">Judges. The Syriac
                        Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz and
                    Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2015.</bibl>
                <bibl>Walter, Donald M., Gillian Greenberg, and Eric Tully. <hi rend="italic">The Book
                        of Women: Ruth, Susanna, Esther, and Judith</hi>. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Syriac Peshiṭta Bible with English Translation</hi>, eds. George Anton Kiraz
                    and Andreas Juckel. Piscataway: Gorgias Press, 2020.</bibl>
                <bibl>Weitzman, M. P. <hi rend="italic">The Syriac Version of the Old Testament</hi>.
                    University of Cambridge Oriental Publications 56. Cambridge: Faculty of Oriental
                    Studies, University of Cambridge, 1999.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
