<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Johannes Hahn and Volker Menze, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Wandering Holy Man: The Life of Barsauma,
                    Christian Asceticism, and Religious Conflict in Late Antique Palestine</hi> (Oakland:
                    University of California Press, 2020)</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Susan Ashbrook</forename>
                        <surname>Harvey</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Brown University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n1prharvey</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Susan Ashbrook Harvey</author>
                        <title level="a">Johannes Hahn and Volker Menze, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Wandering Holy Man: The Life of Barsauma,
                            Christian Asceticism, and Religious Conflict in Late Antique Palestine</hi> (Oakland:
                            University of California Press, 2020)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N1PRHarvey.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="296" to="299">296-299</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="9"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-03-04">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>

            
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                <ab type="review-title">Johannes Hahn and Volker Menze, eds., <hi rend="italic">The Wandering Holy Man: The Life of Barsauma,
                Christian Asceticism, and Religious Conflict in Late Antique Palestine</hi> (Oakland:
                University of California Press, 2020). Pp. x + 307; $95.00.
                </ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">

            <p xml:lang="en">This admirable book takes as its focus one of the most bewitching late antique
                hagiographies, the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Life of Barsauma</hi>. It offers a collection of essays by
                scholars of differing expertise, together with an appendix providing an English
                translation of the Syriac text by Andrew Palmer. The book represents the
                collaborative fruits of a project funded by the German Research Foundation (DFG)
                between 2010 and 2013, including the conference at which the majority of these
                essays were first presented. This same translation (the first in a modern language)
                has also been published separately in its own volume by the University of California
                Press (Andrew N. Palmer, <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Syrian Saint Barsauma: Eulogy of a Hero of
                the Resistance to the Council of Chalcedon</hi>, 2020).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Life of Barsauma</hi> has captivated scholars since François Nau published select
                portions of the text in the early twentieth century (“Deux episodes de l’histoire
                juive sous Théodose II (423 et 438) d’après <hi rend="italic">La Vie de Barsauma le Syrien</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des
                Études Juives</hi> 83 [1927]: 184–206). One of the longest surviving hagiographies of
                late antiquity, its subject is a monastic leader and wandering holy man notorious in
                his day (and subsequently, as seen in other primary sources) as an especially
                charismatic and violent opponent of the Council of Chalcedon (451).</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> itself is a gripping read. The hero’s eventful career began in childhood and
                played out across the eastern Roman provinces through a dramatic series of
                pilgrimages. Adept at miracles of healing, exorcism, and ecological
                disruption—summoned as blessing or curse—Barsauma was an aggressive apostle for the
                (non-Chalcedonian) faith, assaulting, harassing, and sometimes killing his
                opponents, whether pagans, Jews, Samaritans, or heretics (most often in this text,
                supporters of the Council of Chalcedon). Exceptional violence characterizes his own
                ascetic practice no less than his encounters with these “others.” Yet, the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>
                presents him further as the wise confidant and spiritual guide to emperors,
                empresses, bishops, clergy, laity, the poor and needy, as well as his own disciple
                monks. Bristling with references to historical persons, places, and events, the text
                is an irresistible window into the full volatility of late antique Christianity. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Or is it? That is the crux of this book. With close attention, the picture unravels.
                Simon Corcoran on Barsauma and the emperors, Günter Stemberger on Barsauma’s travels
                to the Holy Land and Jewish history, Jan Willem Drijvers on Barsauma’s dealings with
                the empress Eudocia, Reuven Kiperwasser and Serge Ruzer on the Holy Land and its
                inhabitants in the Barsauma narrative, Johannes Hahn on the presentation of
                Samaritans: each of these essays examines the alluring detail of the hagiographical
                text with scrupulous care and judicious rigor. Each time, we confront verisimilitude
                at its most compelling. The same episodes and encounters that have most excited
                scholars with the possibility of historical data are the ones least able to bear
                scrutiny.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Thankfully, the book does not stop there. Another way forward is evident in Cornelia
                Horn’s insightful study of the ascetic practice portrayed in the <hi rend="italic">Life of Barsauma</hi>.
                Her thorough treatment of the rhetoric—including nuanced descriptions of hair,
                garment, tears, and posture—establishes a concrete context of late antique Syriac
                monastic tradition, with devotional implications for pious laity. Her conclusion is
                one of the most important moments of the book: modern readers may find the use of
                tropes and conventions common to Syriac monastic and ascetic writings to be
                “indicators that weaken the claims to the historicity of the story, the person, and
                the ascetic profile presented in the text.” But for the ancient reader, precisely
                these same rhetorical patterns “demonstrated the historical authenticity of the
                story” (p. 72). </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">In a similar vein, Jan Willem Drijvers urges us to leave aside the historical
                “accuracy” of events portrayed and instead to set the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> into the context of other
                Syriac imaginative literature of the time, for example, other anti-Jewish texts such
                as the <hi rend="italic">Julian Romance</hi> or the Syriac legends on the finding of the True Cross (pp.
                99–103). Here is a fruitful approach to “this fascinating hagiographic report,”
                viewing it as “an excellent source for understanding the religious climate in the
                Syriac-speaking regions in the fifth and sixth centuries” (p. 103). Reuven
                Kiperwasser and Serge Ruzer turn attention to the narrative strategies of the text
                “as expressions of negotiating a Christian identity in a late antique
                Syriac-speaking realm” (p. 104). Not only do they offer intriguing readings of the
                Holy Land portions of the Barsauma <hi rend="italic">vita</hi>, but they further suggest parallel
                consideration with, e.g., Genesis Rabbah 64.10 on Jewish messianic activism (pp.
                116–118). The comparison points to a very real climate of anxiety in the fifth
                century eastern provinces regarding Jerusalem and the Temple Mount. Along with the
                essay by Johannes Hahn on the Samaritans, we have here interesting perspectives on
                the roles these imagined communities play in the Barsauma narrative. As Hahn
                astutely observes (p. 128), the <hi rend="italic">Life of Barsauma</hi> is filled with hostile religious
                diversity, all in siloed groups: pagans, Jews, Samaritans, “heretical” Christians,
                and “orthodox” Miaphysites, each strangely presented as a community wholly separate
                from the others. If this literary diversity represents the broad panoply of
                religious groups in the late antique eastern Roman provinces, the picture of
                separate homogenous communities makes no sense at all, historically speaking.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Daniel Caner takes on the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> as hagiography in its fullest literary sense, with a
                richly masterful analysis setting Barsauma (d. 456) together with his elder
                contemporary Alexander Akoimetes (d. 430/5). Both were controversial figures in
                their lifetimes, associated with violence and notoriety. Both were the subjects of
                exceptionally powerful hagiographies: literary interpretations of their careers
                that re-cast their leadership and models into timeless glory, Alexander for the
                apostolic ideal of ceaseless prayer, Barsauma for elevating the penitential life of
                the “mourner” to exalted efficacy. Together with the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Life of Simeon the
                    Stylite</hi>, as well as contrasting models in Theodoret of Cyrrhus’ <hi rend="italic">History of the Monks
                        of Syria</hi> or even the magnanimous <hi rend="italic">Life of Rabbula of Edessa</hi>, we are dealing here
                with literary masterpieces of an era. Matters of historicity can be handled
                expeditiously—as the essays in this volume show—but more profound issues of
                cultural, societal, political, and religious import are there for the taking, the
                more vividly displayed by the imaginative mode of hagiographical discourse at work.
                It is to such fruits that Johannes Hahn points in his thoughtful closing essay,
                “Barsauma between Hagiography and History.”</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The entire collection is ably framed by Volker Menze’s opening essay on Barsauma and
                the relevant historical issues, and Andrew Palmer’s vibrant translation in the
                Appendix from manuscript Damascus Syr. Patr. 12/17 (he is presently completing a
                critical edition and more literal translation). We are much in the debt of these
                colleagues for providing the eminently useful and usable treasure of this book! </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
