<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Schema of the Syriac Šḥimo</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>George A.</forename>
                        <surname>Kiraz</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton / Beth Mardutho: The Syriac
                            Institute</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2kiraz</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>George A. Kiraz</author>
                        <title level="a">Schema of the Syriac Šḥimo</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2Kiraz.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="455" to="483">455-483</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="4"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Liturgy</term>
                    <term>Prayers</term>
                    <term>Šḥimo</term>
                    <term>XML</term>
                    <term>TEI</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The current paper gives a schema of the liturgical book known as
                    the Book of Šḥimo with some historical remarks. It will be shown that the received
                    tradition goes back at least to the early modern period (ca. 1500s) and some
                    elements are attested in the literature in the Syriac renaissance period. At least
                    in one instance, it is argued that an element assigned to priests and bishops must
                    have originally been assigned to the deacon. Snippets from an XML-TEI encoding
                    demonstrate how digital humanities projects can encode liturgical texts.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.1" xml:lang="en">
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Book of Šḥimo</hi> [The Book of the
                Prayers of the Simple (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> Ordinary) Week] contains the
                Liturgy of the Hours according to the West Syriac rite: the Syriac Orthodox Church
                in the Patriarchate of Antioch and the <hi rend="Emphasis">Maphrianate</hi> of the
                East (Mosul, Malankara), the Syriac Catholic Church in the Patriarchate of Antioch,
                and the Syro-Malankara Catholic Church in India. It is closely related to the
                tradition of the Maronite Catholic Church in the Patriarchate of Antioch, and
                perhaps they share a common origin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> I presented an earlier version of this paper at The
                            V<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> (North American) Syriac Symposium at the
                        University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, June 25–27, 2007. Sebastian
                        P. Brock and Mor Severus R. Akhrass kindly read the penultimate draft and
                        gave valuable suggestions.</p></note> This study aims at providing a schema
                of this text, based on the modern editions of the various rites, with remarks on
                modern practices from the Syriac Orthodox rite. By schema, I mean an outline of the
                elements that constitute the liturgical texts, how these elements are organized
                sequentially, and the attributes (e.g., who is the speaker, what is the melody of a
                hymn) assigned to these elements.</p>
            <p>Our earliest manuscripts of the Šḥimo belong to the Early Modern period, but scholars
                have found a few liturgical fragments from earlier periods. Barsoum notes fragments
                preserved in the Damascus Museum dating from around the 8<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">
                        Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi> p. 73-75.</p></note> He
                claims that their text is similar to the received tradition. Barsoum informs us that
                some manuscripts credit Jacob of Edessa (d. 708) as the initial compiler. He also
                tells us that he examined some manuscripts according to the traditions of Edessa.
                While the literary content varies among manuscripts, the schematic structure remains
                the same.</p>
            <p> This study shows that all the main elements of the schema appear in various
                commentaries dating back to the early second millennium. We can be confident that
                the structure of the prayers found in the printed editions represents the schema of
                the text as it stood in the Early Modern period (ca. 15<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi> or 16<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century), if not earlier. Indeed,
                early fragments found in the Cairo Geniza contain texts that a young deacon today
                might select and chant, though they do not reveal much about structure.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"> G. Kiraz, “Learning
                        Syriac and Garshuni in Early Modern Egypt: Evidence from the Cairo Genizah”
                        in Geoffrey Khan, Sabine Schmitdke, and Sarah Stroumsa (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Studies in Literary Genizot</hi>
                        (=<hi rend="italic"> Intellectual History of the Islamicate World</hi>
                        8 (2020): 1–26; G. Kiraz, “A Young Syriac Pupil in the Cairo Genizah:
                        Or.1081 2.75.30.” <hi rend="italic">Fragment of the Month: Newsletter of the
                            Cambridge University Library Genizah Unit</hi>. August 2018. <ref
                            target="https://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/collections/departments/taylor-schechter-genizah-research-unit/fragment-month/fotm-2018/fragment-6"
                            >https://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/collections/departments/taylor-schechter-genizah-research-unit/fragment-month/fotm-2018/fragment-6</ref>.</p></note></p>
            <p>Scholars have not analyzed the structure of the Šḥimo in any detail. The late Robert
                Taft provides some brief observations on the present living tradition,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> R.
                        Taft,<hi rend="italic"> The Liturgy of the Hours in East and West</hi>
                        (1993) 239–247.</p></note> and Christine Chaillot outlines the main daily
                offices prepared by Sebastian P. Brock.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Christine Chaillot, The Syrian Orthodox Church of
                        Antioch and All the East, a brief introduction to its life and spirituality
                        (Geneva: Inter-Orthodox Dialogue, 1998), pp. 99, 156-157.</p></note> Eugene
                Aydin (aka Mor Poloycarpus) produced an essay in Syriac detailing the sources of the
                text with a discussion on the differences between the Orthodox, Catholic and
                Maronite printed editions,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Eugene Aydin, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܚܝܡܐ: ܟܬܒܐ ܕܨܠܘ̈ܬܐ ܕܫܒܬܐ ܫܚܝܡܬܐ</foreign> in <hi
                            rend="italic underline">H</hi><hi rend="italic">eto</hi> 3 (2001), no.
                        5: 46-35.</p></note> and I have relied upon his helpful lists of editions
                and translations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> See
                        also A. Baumstark, “syr-Antioch” in <hi rend="italic">Der Katholik</hi> 82
                        (401–427, 538–550) &amp; 83 (43–54); A. Baumstark, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Geschichte der syrischen Literatur</hi> 47, n.4; where he lists mss);
                        J. Tomajean, “La semaine liturgique dans le rite syrien” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Parole de l'Orient</hi> (1966) no. 1, 95–114. For the
                        Maronite Lilyo and Ṣafro, see J. Tabet, <hi rend="italic">L'Office commun
                            maronite</hi> (Kaslik, 1972).</p></note></p>
            <p>The text editors also provide us with further information. Barsoum, Konat, Griffith,
                and Mnayyer introduce the faithful to using the text, with Konat’s introduction
                being the most extensive. However, they all assume familiarity with the tradition.
                Having said that, such instructional material is no more valuable than New Jersey’s
                road signs which are helpful if you already know how to reach your destination. As
                such, only the trained clergy can perform the prayers. Numerous parts are absent
                from the printed texts (see, for example, the <hi rend="italic">Sedro</hi> schema
                below). </p>
            <p>As far as I know, this article is the first attempt to describe the schema of a west
                Syriac liturgical rite. Such an analysis is helpful for digital humanities projects
                seeking to represent or encode the text. I will provide a conceptualization of the
                main structures and their elements. I will begin with a description of the printed
                editions upon which the study is based (I), an outline of the canonical hours (II),
                a schema of the text (III-VI), observations on the thematic structure (VII), and
                finally concluding remarks (VIII). An appendix gives snippets from an XML-TEI schema
                for consideration in digital humanities projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Modern Editions and Translations</head>
                <p>The Syriac Orthodox editions bear the title
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܨܠܘ̈ܬܐ ܕܫܒܬܐ </foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܚܝܡܬܐ</foreign> “The Book
                    of the Prayers of the Simple (<hi rend="italic">or</hi> Ordinary) Week,” and the
                    Syriac Catholic editions bear the title
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܠܘ̈ܬܐ ܕܝܘܡ̈ܬܐ ܫܚܝ̈ܡܐ
                        ܕܫܒܬܐ</foreign> “The Prayers of the Simple Days of the Week.” One observes that
                    the adjective <foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܫܚܝܡܐ</foreign> “simple” is a modifier of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܬܐ</foreign> “week” and
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܡ̈ܬܐ</foreign>
                    “days,” not of the prayers themselves. In this terminology, a “simple” day is a
                    non-feast day and excludes Sundays. (The Konat edition is the exception giving
                    the title <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܨܠܘܬܐ ܫܚܝܡܬܐ</foreign> “The Book of the Simple Prayer.”) In his
                    introduction to an Arabic translation of the Šḥimo text, Yousef Mnayyer stresses
                    this referential property of the title.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Mnayyer, <hi rend="italic">al-ʾIšḥīm</hi>
                            (Damascus, 1994) p. 13.</p></note></p>
                <p>The Syriac Orthodox church produced its first edition at the Deir al-Zaʿfaran
                    press in 1890. A second edition by Barsoum was produced at the same press in
                    1913 based on nine MSS (seven according to his introduction!), one of which is
                    by a certain monk named David (fl. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        century).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Šḥimo (Mardin, 1913) p. 6.</p></note> A third edition was produced in
                    Jerusalem in 1934 and became standard. It has been used in subsequent editions
                    from Bar Hebraeus Verlag in Holland. The Barsoum text incorporates the western
                    tradition of the Patriarchate of Antioch and the eastern tradition of the
                    Maphrianate of Tikrit (now the Mosul and Nineveh Plains tradition).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi
                                rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi> p. 73-75.</p></note> The
                    Malankara tradition produced an edition by Matta Konat in 1915. While Konat’s
                    edition contains many differences in textual renderings, Konat’s structure is
                    identical to Barsoum’s.</p>
                <p>There are four Syriac Catholic editions: the 1696 edition produced by Athanasius
                    Safar ʿAṭṭār of Mardin; the 1787 edition by Elias Amirkhan, itself based on the
                    1696 edition; the 1835 edition by Patriarch Peter Shabadin through the
                    Propaganda Fide; the 1902 edition by Aphram Rahmani; and finally, the 1937
                    edition by Gabriel Tabbouni.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Aydin, p. 41-42.</p></note></p>
                <p>Although there are more Syriac Christians in the diaspora than in the homeland,
                    hardly any churches have produced translations of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Šḥimo</hi>. In parishes where the tradition is kept, mostly the Syriac
                    Orthodox of Europe, the Syriac text is used. While prose prayers appear in
                    translation here and there, poetry is far more difficult to translate for
                    liturgical purposes, and the musical component is not easy to bridge across
                    languages. However, a few translations exist. Mnayyer mentions an unpublished
                    French translation by “brother Kristian who belongs to the young brothers of
                        Jesus.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Mnayyer, p. 19.</p></note> Bede Griffiths produced an English
                    translation (n.d., reprinted by Gorgias Press in 2005), from which Madey
                    produced a German translation in 1995.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Johannes Madey, <hi rend="italic">S’himo Oder
                                Das Stundenlob der Syro-Antiochenischen Kirche an Wochentagen</hi>
                            (1995).</p></note> Acharya, produced another translation based in
                    Griffith, but this version contains numerous adaptations.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> F.
                            Acharya,<hi rend="italic"> Prayer with the Harp of the Spirit. I, A Weekly Celebration of the Economy of Salvation</hi>
                            (Kurisumala Ashram, Vagamon, 1983).</p></note> A few translations
                    appeared in Malayalam, in part or in full, between 1910 and 1998. Mnayyer
                    produced his Arabic translation in 1994. Finally, in 1969 Heinrich Husmann
                    produced an edition of musical notations of the main hymns based on recordings
                    by the late Qurillos Jacob Qas Girgis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Heinrich Husmann, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Melodien der Jakobitischen Kirche, Die Melodien des
                                Wochenbreviers</hi> (Wien: Hermann Böhlaus Nachf,
                    1969)</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>The Canonical Hours</head>
                <p>The west Syriac canonical hours follow Psalm 118 [MT
                    119]:164—<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܰܥ ܒܝܰܘܡܳܐ
                        ܫܰܒܰܚܬܳܟ</foreign> “Seven (times) a day I praised you” and are hence seven. The
                    ecclesiastical day begins at sunset, following the Jewish tradition. As such,
                    <hi rend="bold">(1)</hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܡܫܐ</foreign> (hereafter,
                    Ramšo) “evening” is the first of the prayers; it corresponds to Latin vespers.
                    Ramšo is usually indicated in liturgical texts with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܓܗ</foreign> “dawn”
                    followed by the day, e.g., <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܓܗ ܬܪܝܢ ܒܫܒܐ</foreign> “the
                    dawn of Monday,” Monday being the day to come. One performs this prayer today on
                    Sunday evening, i.e., the eve of Monday.</p>
                <p>The same applies to the next hour, <hi rend="bold">(2)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܬܪܐ</foreign> (Sutoro)
                    “covering, protection,” which corresponds to Latin Compline. Its name derives
                    from Ps 91:1 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܳܬܶܒ
                        ܒܣܶܬܳܪܶܗ ܕܰܡܪܰܝܡܳܐ</foreign> “He who sits in the protection of the Most High”).
                    This Psalm, recited during this hour, is what the faithful associate with this
                    hour. Yet, its text does not appear in most of the editions considered here and
                    in none of the manuscripts under consideration, demonstrating the
                    interconnection between the written modality and orality.</p>
                <p>The next hour is <hi rend="bold">(3)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܠܝܐ</foreign> (Lilyo)
                    “night,” corresponding to Latin nocturnes. It consists of three <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܘ̈ܡܐ</foreign> (<hi
                        rend="italic">qawme</hi>) or “watches” (literally “standings”); some
                    manuscripts (e.g., MS<hi rend="superscript">1624</hi> (should this be written MS
                    1624?) MS, for which see under III) use <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܡܫܬܐ</foreign>
                    (Teshmeshto) “service” instead of Qawmo. Then comes <hi rend="bold">(4)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܦܪܐ</foreign> (Ṣaphro)
                    “morning,” which is the apposition of Ramšo; it corresponds to Latin matins.</p>
                <p>Then, we have <hi rend="bold">(5)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܠܳܬܫ̈ܳܥܺܝܢ</foreign> or
                    the Third Hour, corresponding to Latin terce. The numbering of hours is offset
                    by sunrise. Hence, the Third Hour—depending on the season—is approximately
                    around 9:00 AM. Then, <hi rend="bold">(6)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܶܬܫ̈ܳܥܺܝܢ</foreign> or the
                    Sixth Hour, corresponding to Latin sext, approximates our noontime. Finally, <hi
                        rend="bold">(7)</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܰܥܫ̈ܳܥܺܝܢ</foreign> or
                    the Ninth Hour corresponds to Latin none, sometimes in the early afternoon. </p>
                <p>A few Syriac writers cite these hours from the thirteenth and fourteenth
                    centuries. Jacob of Bartelleh (d. 1241) gives a list of them with additional
                    commentary in his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Simotho</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub Albartali, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Treasures</hi>. Translated into Arabic by Behnam Daniel
                            al-Bartali (Aleppo: Dar Mardin, 2007). The translation is based on three
                            mss: the first is in the Syriac Orthodox Bishopric of Mosul dated 1718,
                            the second belongs to bishop Saliba Shimoun of Mosul dated 1889, and the
                            third belongs to the translator dated 1912.</p></note> Bar ʿEbroyo (d.
                    1287), in both his <hi rend="italic">Hudoye</hi> (V, 5) and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ethicon</hi> (I, 1, 8), states that the hours did not
                    initially include Sutoro; it was later added in order to comply with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܺܝܥܳܝܽܘܬܳܐ</foreign>
                    “sevenness.” Ignatius bar Wahib (d. 1333), in a brief unpublished treatise on
                    liturgical prayers,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Barsoum, <hi rend="italic">Al-lulu</hi> 545,
                            citing mss Homs (might be in Damascus now), Berlin Sachaw 151, Cambridge
                            2887, and Mosul.</p></note> counts the three <hi rend="italic"
                        >qawme</hi> of Lilyo as individual hours, giving a total of ten canonical
                    hours. We can be confident that the canonical hours of the Šḥimo go back to at
                    least the early second millennium.</p>
                <p>In earlier monastic settings, each hour was probably conducted independently at
                    its own time. The received tradition, however, groups them into two synaxes (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܽܘܢܰܟܣ̈ܺܝܣ</foreign>). The
                    first is the evening synaxis, sometimes recited between 3:00 PM and 6:00
                    PM—depending on local traditions—consists of the Ninth Hour (of the current day
                    in modern reckoning), followed by Ramšo and Sutoro (of the following day). For
                    instance, on a Sunday evening, one begins with the Sunday Ninth Hour (the last
                    hour of Sunday), then moves to the Ramšo and Sutoro of Monday. The second is a
                    morning synaxis that is sometimes recited between 5:00 AM and 7:00 AM, depending
                    on local traditions. It consists of Lilyo, Ṣaphro, the Third Hour, and the Sixth
                    Hour, all of the current day. The following diagram outlines the hours
                    corresponding to modern times. </p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">7</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">5</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">9<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi>
                            Hr</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi
                            >Ramšo</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi
                            >Sutoro</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi
                            >Lilyo</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi
                            >Ṣaphro</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">3<hi
                                rend="superscript">rd</hi>
                            Hr</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">6<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi>
                            Hr</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="3"><hi>Evening
                                Synaxis</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><hi>Morning
                                Synaxis</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Note that the break of a new ecclesiastical day occurs <hi rend="italic"
                        >during</hi> the evening synaxis. After the completion of the 9<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Hour, which follows the melody set of the current
                    day, the melody will switch for Ramšo of the newly issued day. This cannot be
                    more pronounced than on Palm Sunday, which is followed by Passion Week with its
                    specific prayers and melodies. The faithful gather again on Sunday evening,
                    after the completion of Palm Sunday festivities, for the service of Nahire that
                    commemorates the parable of the wise and foolish virgins (Matthew 25:1–13). They
                    begin with the 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Hour with the festive melodies of
                    Palm Sunday. Then, the entire atmosphere changes as Ramšo issues a new day,
                    Monday, the beginning of Passion Week. The melodies become somber. The Trisagion
                    is replaced by unique passion phraseology. The large Phenqitho volumes of the
                    Lent season—used for the Liturgy of the Hours instead of the Šḥimo—are put away
                    and replaced with the Passion Phenqitho.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Phenqithos have the text for the Lent cycle
                            and for passion week in different volumes. Some modern editions,
                            however, combine them in one volume.</p></note></p>
                <p>In some monastic settings, an additional noon synaxis is observed during which
                    the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi>, 6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, and 9<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Hours are recited. In such cases, it would be a
                    repetition of the same hours, albeit using a different text. The first edition
                    of a noon synaxis was published by Abraham Konat<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܨܠܘܬܐ
                                ܕܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܠܦܘܬ ܥܝܕܐ ܕܥܕܬܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܬܐ ܐܪܬܘܕܘܟܣܝܝܬܐ ܕܡܝܠܝܒܐܪ</foreign> (Mar
                            Julius Press, Pampakuda, n.d.).</p></note> (n.d.). Çiçek then produced a
                    newer edition in 1989.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܛܟܣܐ ܕܨܠܘ̈ܬܐ
                                ܘܒܥܘ̈ܬܐ ܕܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܠܝܘ̈ܡܝ ܫܒܘܥܐ ܕܡܬܐܡܪ̈ܢ ܒܥܕܢ ܛܗܪܐ ܕܟܠܝܘܡ ܐܝܟ ܛܟܣܐ
                                ܕܥܕܬܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܬܐ ܬܪܝܨܬ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܕܐܢܛܝܘܟܝܐ</foreign> (Holland, 1989). The same
                            book was published at the same time in two trim sizes, large and
                            medium.</p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Schema of the Hour</head>
                <p>The following discussion is based on the published texts
                    of the following editions:</p>
                <p><hi>C	= Syriac </hi><hi rend="bold"
                       >C</hi><hi>atholic ed.</hi></p>
                <p><hi>H	= Husmann, </hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Die Melodien der Jakobitischen Kirche,
                        Die Melodien des
                    Wochenbreviers</hi><hi> (1969)</hi></p>
                <p>O<hi rend="superscript"
                        >H</hi>
                    <hi> =</hi><anchor xml:id="OLE_LINK1"/><anchor
                        xml:id="OLE_LINK2"
                        /><hi> Syriac </hi><hi
                        rend="bold">O</hi><hi>rthodox
                        Holland ed. &lt; O</hi><hi rend="superscript"
                    >J</hi></p>
                <p>O<hi rend="superscript"
                        >J</hi>
                    <hi>	= Syriac </hi><hi rend="bold"
                       >O</hi><hi>rthodox Jerusalem ed.
                        &lt; O</hi><hi rend="superscript">Z</hi></p>
                <p>O<hi rend="superscript"
                        >K</hi>
                    <hi>	= Syriac </hi><hi rend="bold"
                       >O</hi><hi>rthodox Konat
                    ed.</hi></p>
                <p>O<hi rend="superscript"
                        >Z</hi>
                    <hi>	= Syriac </hi><hi rend="bold"
                       >O</hi><hi>rthodox Zaʿfaran
                        ed.</hi></p>
                <p>In addition, when discrepancies are found, the following
                    MSS were consulted:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> I did not have access to an important early
                            manuscript, Charfet 5/1. According to Armalet, it is a Beth Gazo from
                            the 11<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century. If true, this could be the
                            oldest existing Beth Gazo which contains the prayers of Šḥimo (item 9);
                            see Issac Armalet, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue des Manuscrits de
                                Charfet</hi> (1937) 85 ff.</p></note></p>
                <p>MS<hi rend="superscript"
                        >Osaka</hi><hi>	A Beth Gazo from the Osaka collection, C942369413. Though undated, the first fragmentary portion of the MS, containing the Šḥimo text, is probably one of the earliest surviving Beth Gazo manuscripts. The paleography is from the first half (if not the first quarter) of the second millennium, judging from the squarish </hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡ‍</foreign><hi>, the </hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬ</foreign><hi>, and a good number of Estrangela-like </hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕ</foreign><hi> and </hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ</foreign><hi
                       >. I am grateful to Hidemi Takahashi for sharing the
                        images of this manuscript with me.</hi></p>
                <p>MS<hi rend="superscript"
                        >1624</hi><hi> A Beth Gazo in Library of the Syriac
                        Orthodox Archdiocese of the Eastern United States, Paramus, NJ, originally
                        from St. Mark’s library, Jerusalem. The scribe began in 1624 and came back
                        to complete the MS in 1651 (the Šḥimo portion is at the beginning of the
                        MS).</hi>
                </p>
                <p>MS<hi rend="superscript"
                        >Kiraz</hi><hi> A Šḥimo scribed by Giragos, son of
                        Daoud (Kiraz), 1900, in the G. A. Kiraz private collection.</hi></p>
                <p>Two of the canonical hours, Ramšo and Ṣaphro, are set apart by their length, not
                    only by the textual length of hymns but rather their inclusion of elements
                    absent in the other hours. I dub Ramšo and Ṣaphro as Major Hours, while all the
                    others as Minor Hours. The following table gives the elements found in each
                    type.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><hi rend="bold">I. Major
                                Hours<lb/>(Ramšo &amp; Ṣaphro)</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><hi rend="bold">II. Minor
                                Hours<lb/>(Sutoro, Lilyo, 3</hi><hi rend="bold superscript"
                                >rd</hi><hi rend="bold">, 6</hi><hi rend="bold superscript"
                                >th</hi><hi rend="bold">, &amp; 9</hi><hi rend="bold superscript"
                                >th</hi>
                            <hi rend="bold">Hrs)</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Opening Prayer</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Psalms</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.3 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Shubḥo in ʿEqbo</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">II.1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">ʿEqbo (Lilyo <hi rend="italic">qawme</hi>
                            only)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥusoyo I</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Qolo of Incense (odd number of
                            stanzas)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.6</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Prayer of Incense</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.7 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Qolo after Incense (odd)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.8 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Quqalion (even)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.9 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Shubḥo in ʿEqbo</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.9</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥusoyo II</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">II.2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥusoyo</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.10 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Qolo of Ramšo/Ṣaphro (even)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">II.3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Qolo (even)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">I.11 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Boʿutho (even)</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">II.4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Boʿutho (even)</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>As can be seen above, the schema of the Minor Hours is basically the tail of the
                    Major Hours. The relevance of odd/even stanzas and the sigla <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ</foreign> are discussed
                    in the appendix. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.1</hi> A Major Hour service, i.e., Ramšo or Ṣaphro, commences
                    with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܠܘܬܐ ܕܫܘܪܝܐ</foreign>
                    or an opening prayer. The texts of this prayer—or even any indication of its
                    existence—are absent in O<hi rend="superscript">ZJH</hi>. This is indeed one of
                    the difficulties of determining the schemas of liturgical prayers without
                    knowing the practice itself. Texts typically do not indicate fixed aspects of
                    the liturgy. But we can be sure that the opening prayer is not a Malankara
                    characteristic (O<hi rend="superscript">K</hi>) or a Catholic addition (C). It
                    is indeed mentioned by Jacob of Bartelleh (d. 1241) concerning the Ramšo, Lilyo,
                    and Ṣaphro hours.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub Albartali, p.
                        108-110.</p></note></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.2</hi> Then follows a recitation of a psalm. It should be
                    stressed that “a Psalm” does not correspond to our modern Psalm divisions. An
                    ecclesiastical Psalm usually corresponds to one or more Psalms of the modern
                    divisions, and not always contiguously.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Ramšo Ps. 140/141, 141/142, 118/119:105–112,
                            116/117 (simple); Ṣaphro Ps. 51 (simple), 63 (in ʿEnyoyo), and 113/158
                            (simple).</p></note> A psalm may be recited in two different manners: 1)
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܫܺܝܛܳܐܺܝܬ</foreign>
                    “simply” where the psalm is recited continuously by one or more deacons, one
                    “verse” after the next (again, “verse” does not correspond to modern divisions),
                    or 2) <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܥܶܢܝܳܢܳܐ</foreign>
                    “in response” where a response follows each “verse” of the psalm in the form of
                    a hymn stanza. There is disagreement with regards to the Ramšo psalm: O<hi
                        rend="superscript">ZJH</hi> prefixes the actual psalm text with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܶܢܝܳܢܳܐ ܕܪܰܡܫܳܐ</foreign>
                    , but provides no hymn for the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܶܢܝܳܢܳܐ</foreign>, while C
                    explicitly states that the psalm is recited <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܫܺܝܛܳܐܺܝܬ</foreign>
                    “simply,” and hence does not require a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܶܢܝܳܢܳܐ</foreign> hymn.
                        MS<hi rend="superscript">1624</hi> and MS<hi rend="superscript">Kiraz</hi>
                    agree with O<hi rend="superscript">ZJH</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.3</hi> Then follows a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܶܩܒܳܐ</foreign> (ʿEqbo),
                    literally “footstep, heel,” metaphorically meaning “to follow.” The ʿEqbo is
                    always prefixed with a Gloria, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܰܐܒܳܐ ܘܠܰܒܪܳܐ
                        ܘܰܠܪܽܘܚܳܐ ܩܰܕܺܝܫܳܐ</foreign> “praise to the Father, the Son, and the Holy
                    Spirit,” recited by the most senior priest present. Elsewhere, the Mosul
                    Phenqitho dubs this formula with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܒܳܚܳܐ</foreign> “i.e.
                    saying the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ</foreign>.” The Šuboḥo is followed by <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܶܢ ܥܳܠܰܡ ܘܰܥܕܰܡܳܐ
                        ܠܥܳܠܰܡ ܥܠܳܡܺܝܢ ܐܰܡܺܝܢ</foreign> “from now and forever, and ever, Amen,” recited
                    by the <hi rend="italic">gudo</hi>. The rubric <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܒ ܘܥܩܒܐ</foreign> denotes
                    this entire exchange in O<hi rend="superscript">ZJH,</hi> and the rubric <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܒ ܘܡܢ ܒܥܩܒܐ</foreign> in
                    C. The three <hi rend="italic">qawme</hi> of Lilyo also begin with a ʿEqbo
                    (II.1).</p>
                <p>Parenthetically, we know of (a now humorous) squabble over the Šuboḥo. It took
                    place in 1771 at the beginning of the Orthodox-Catholic split within the Syriac
                    Orthodox Church. The Syriac Orthodox Patriarch George IV entered the church in
                    Aleppo while a local priest, Joseph Hajjār, was already celebrating the liturgy.
                    It seems that Joseph had just joined the Catholic party. At the time of the
                    Šuboḥo, Joseph chanted the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܒܚܳܐ ܠܰܐܒܳܐ</foreign>
                    phrase even though the Patriarch—the highest-ranking priest—was present. The
                    Patriarch was quite annoyed and shouted at the priest in Arabic, <foreign xml:lang="ar">ورك انت تعطي
                        شبح وما تعرف من في واقف</foreign> “Hey! You say the Šuboḥo? Don’t you know who is
                    standing here?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">
                            MS Sbath 131, f. 48r; I am grateful to Feraz Krimsti for pointing out
                            this document.</p></note></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.4</hi> Then follows the first Sedro, whose schema is best
                    described separately as this genre occurs in other liturgical texts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.5</hi> The Sedro is followed by the First Qolo, or Qolo before
                    Incense. In MS<hi rend="superscript">1624</hi> and MS<hi rend="superscript"
                        >Kiraz</hi>, it is called the First Qawmo. The Qolo for the Ramšo of Monday
                    in the modern editions begins with four introductory stanzas, followed by four
                    stanzas for the Mother of God, another four for the saints, another four for
                    repentance, and one (four in O<hi rend="superscript">K</hi>) for the departed.
                    Other days may have different themes (to be discussed below), but all begin,
                    after the introductory stanzas, with the Mother of God and end with the
                    departed. Some stanzas are prefixed with a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܶܬܓܳܡܳܐ</foreign>
                    (Phethghomo), a portion of a verse from the Psalms. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.6</hi> Then follows the Prayer of Incense. This prayer may go
                    back to the seventh century or even earlier. Bar ʿEbroyo quotes Jacob of Edessa
                    (d. 708), saying, “even if the time of the morning or evening prayer comes and
                    there is no incense, perform, O priest, the prayers without incense.” It is
                    mentioned more explicitly by Jacob of Bartilleh.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub
                            Albartali, p. 108.</p></note> Prior to this prayer, the deacon chants
                    the phrase <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܳܪܝܳܐ
                        ܡܪܰܚܡܳܢܳܐ ܪܰܚܶܡ ܥܠܰܝܢ ܘܥܰܕܰܪܰܝܢ</foreign> “Merciful Lord, have mercy upon and us
                    and help us,” which is only preserved in the oral tradition.</p>
                <p>As far as I can tell, the entire Prayer of Incense is omitted in all the received
                    traditions. There is an implicit mention of it in O<hi rend="superscript">K</hi>
                    as the previous Qolo (I.5) is called the Qolo of Incense, and the following Qolo
                    (I.7) is called the Qolo after Incense; additionally, the two Qole are separated
                    by the word <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܳܪܝܳܐ</foreign> which starts the oral phrase mentioned above. There is no
                    indication of the Prayer of Incense in O<hi rend="superscript">ZJH</hi>; the
                    preceding Qolo is simply called the First Qolo, and the following is the Second
                    Qolo. MS<hi rend="superscript">Osaka</hi> supports O<hi rend="superscript"
                        >K</hi>; Both MS<hi rend="superscript">1624</hi> and MS<hi
                        rend="superscript">Kiraz</hi> are silent on the matter. This prayer is
                    explicitly mentioned in C, giving the full text of the prayer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.7</hi> Then comes the Second Qolo, or Qolo after Incense. It
                    has a similar structure as I.5. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">1.8</hi> Then follows the Quqalion. It consists of short Psalm
                    verses interspersed with Hallelujah. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">1.9</hi> Next comes a second ʿEqbo.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">1.10</hi> A Second Sedro follows. But it is almost always omitted
                    in the received tradition.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">1.11</hi> Then follows a third Qolo. Depending on the service, it
                    is called the Qolo of Ramšo or Ṣaphro. It consists in the modern editions of
                    four stanzas only.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">1.12</hi> The service ends with a Boʿutho. It is always a <hi
                        rend="italic">mimro</hi> (metrical poem) composed either in the meter of St.
                    Jacob of Sarug (12 syllables per strophe), St. Ephrem (7 syllables per strophe),
                    or St. Balai (5-syllables per strophe). The Mimro begins with a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܪܳܝܳܐ</foreign>
                    consisting of two strophes, each sung by a <hi rend="italic">gudo</hi>, and ends
                    in a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܠܳܡܳܐ</foreign> or
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܒܳܪ̈ܳܬܳܐ</foreign>
                    which, like the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܪܳܝܳܐ</foreign>, are two strophes. The main body consists of an even number
                    of stanzas. A multi-theme Boʿutho is marked as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܰܘܳܢܳܝܳܐ</foreign>
                    “general” and covers four themes: Mary, the saints, repentance, and the
                    departed; in such a case, it is chanted in its entirety (i.e., stanzas cannot be
                    skipped in order not to skip a theme).</p>
                <p style="text-align: center;">܀</p>
                <p>Akhrass<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Personal
                            communication, 5/19/2022.</p></note> observed that the schema of the
                    Major hours could be roughly divided into two <hi rend="italic">qawme</hi>,
                    duplicating an almost exact structure: the first qawmo consisting of I.2–I.7 and
                    the second qawmo consisting of I.8–I.11. This point becomes apparent when one
                    considers that the Quqalion (I.8) consists of Psalm verses (cf. I.2). The ʿEṭro
                    (I.6) becomes the only element found in the first <hi rend="italic">qawmo</hi>,
                    but not in the second. Only the first qawmo has an Opening Prayer (I.1). This
                    general schema of a service (Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܶܫܡܶܫܬܳܐ</foreign>) is
                    prevalent in all church rites.</p>
                <p>The Minor Hours simply consist of a Sedro, Qolo, and Boʿutho. C begins the Sutoro
                    with Ps 4, followed by a fixed ʿEqbo. These are absent in O<hi
                        rend="superscript">ZJH</hi>, MS<hi rend="superscript">1624,</hi> and MS<hi
                        rend="superscript">Kiraz</hi>.</p>
                <p>Before leaving this section, one needs to mention the schema of the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܥܺܝܪܳܢܳܐ</foreign>
                    (Mʿirono), which precedes the first Qawmo of Lilyo. It begins with the Prayer of
                    Mʿirono, sometimes called the Opening Prayer, followed by Ps. 133/134,
                    118/9:169-176, 116/7 recited in ʿEnyono. Then follows the Prayer after Mʿirono,
                    itself prefixed with Kyrie-eleison three times. Both prayers are attested in
                        MS<hi rend="superscript">1624</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.5" xml:lang="en">
                <head>IV. Ḥusoyo Schema</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">I.4</hi> The prayer of Ḥusoyo is
                    mentioned by Jacob of Barelleh as one of the elements in the Liturgy of the
                        Hours.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text"> Mar
                            Severios Yacoub Albartali, p. 108.</p></note> The Ḥusoyo is a prose text
                    that consists of two main parts, a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܪܽܘܡܝܽܘܢ</foreign>
                    (Promion), a Greek loanword meaning “preface,” and a longer <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܶܕܪܳܐ</foreign> (Sedro)
                    “list, array, items in a specific order.” While manuscripts—and printed
                    texts—typically give just these two elements, the entire Ḥusoyo consists of more
                    elements preserved only orally. These are outlined in the schema below.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">Part</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="bold">Speaker</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">Proclamation</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ1a</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Deacon:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Stomen Kalos (Let us stand well)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ1b</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">People:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Kyrie eleison</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Šuroyo:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ2a</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Priest:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܠܐ ܟܠܢ</foreign> ...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ2b</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">People:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܝܐ ܡܪܚܡܢܐ</foreign> ...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ2c</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Priest:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܒܘܚܬܐ ܘܬܘܕܝܬܐ</foreign> ...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Promion</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Priest:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="italic">text</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Mḥasyono</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="italic">Ḥ4a</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Bishop (if present):</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܥܛܪܐ ܕܒܣ̈ܡܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="italic">Ḥ4b</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Priest</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܚܣܝܢܐ ܗܟܝܠ ܡܕܟܝܢܐ</foreign> ...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="italic">Ḥ4c</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">People:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܝܢ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ5</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Sedro</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Deacon:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="italic">text</hi> (prefixed with
                                <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܟܡܪܝ</foreign>)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ḥ6</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Qubolo</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Priest:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: right;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢ ܐܠܗܐ ܢܩܒܠ</foreign> ...</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">People:</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܝܢ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ1</hi> The entire thing commences with
                    the deacon proclaiming a Greek loan phrase, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܛܰܘܡܶܢ ܩܰܐܠܳܘܣ</foreign>
                        (<hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>1a), which corresponds to the Syriac
                    liturgical phrase <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܩܽܘܡ ܫܰܦܺܝܪ</foreign> “let us stand well.” The people are to respond with the
                    Greek loan <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܽܘܪܝܶܠܰܝܣܳܘܢ</foreign>
                    <hi rend="italic">keyrieleson</hi>
                    <hi style="font-size:10pt">(Ḥ</hi>1b), which also corresponds to a Syriac
                    liturgical phrase, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܳܪܰܢ ܐܶܬܪܰܚܰܡ ܥܠܰܝܢ</foreign> . These could have entered Syriac from Greek
                    during the Byzantine reconquest of Asia Minor in the tenth century. Apart from
                    the Malankara tradition, <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>1a and <hi
                        style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>1b are collapsed. A single deacon chants them
                    as one unit. It is not clear when this occurred. M<hi rend="superscript"
                        >1624</hi> already gives the entire thing without space, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣ‍ܛܽܘܡܝܢܩܲܠܘܿܣܩܘܪܝܠܠܝ܏ܣ</foreign>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For further discussion on this phrase, see G.
                            Kiraz, “A Proclamation Out of Place, ‘Stomen Kalos, Kyrie-Eleison’ and
                            the Nicene Creed.” In <hi rend="italic">Ktheeboth hago</hi>: <hi
                                rend="italic">Festschrift in Honour of His Holiness Ignatius Zakka I
                                Iwas</hi>, ed. Roy Thomas, 417–31. Chicago: St. George Syrian
                            Orthodox Church of Malankara, 2005.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ2</hi> The oral portions continue with
                    the Šuroyo (I borrow the term from Mushe of Mardin, see below). The priest
                    proclaims <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܰܠܶܐ ܟܽܠܰܢ
                        ܘܪ̈ܰܚܡܶܐ ܘܰܚܢܳܢܳܐ ܡܶܢ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܢܶܒܥܶܐ</foreign> “let us all pray and beseech the
                    Lord for mercy and compassion” (<hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2a) to which
                    the faithful respond with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܡܪܰܚܡܳܢܳܐ ܪܰܚܶܡ
                        ܥܠܰܝܢ ܘܥܰܕܰܪܰܝܢ</foreign> “Merciful Lord, have mercy upon us and help us” (<hi
                        style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2b). The priest then recites (<hi
                        style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2c),</p>
                
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <p xml:lang="syr"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܶܫܒܽܘܚܬܳܐ ܘܬܰܘܕܺܝܬܳܐ ܘܗܶܕܪܳܐ ܘܩܽܘܠܳܣܳܐ
                        ܘܪܽܘܡܪܳܡܳܐ ܛܳܒܳܐ ܕܠܳܐ ܒܳܛܶܠ ܐܰܡܺܝܢܳܐܺܝܬ ܒܟܽܠܙܒܰܢ ܘܰܒܟܽܠܥܶܕܳܢ ܢܶܫܬܘܶܐ
                        ܕܢܰܣܶܩ.</foreign></p>
                <p>May we be worthy to
                        offer up continually, at all the time and in all seasons, praise,
                        thanksgiving, glory, adoration, and never-ceasing exaltation.</p>
                </quote>
                </cit>
                
                <p>In the received tradition, apart from Malankara, the
                    entirety of <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2 is collapsed into one element and
                    is chanted by the priest alone. If a bishop is present, he recites the entire
                    thing.</p>
                <p>But one must pause here and question if the received tradition is a corruption of
                    an earlier tradition. Is it possible that <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ3</hi> was
                    initially assigned to the deacon? The use of the jussive, expressed in the
                    prefixed (imperfect) form <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܰܠܶܐ</foreign> is typical
                    in proclamations made by the deacon. It is ubiquitous in the Qurobo, or
                    Eucharistic, liturgy. Before the reading of the Gospel, the deacon proclaims, in
                    the jussive, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܽܘܬ
                        ܘܢܶܫܡܰܥ ܠܰܣܒܰܪܬܳܐ ܕܡ̈ܶܠܶܐ ܚܰܝ̈ܳܬܳܐ</foreign> “let us give heed and listen to the
                    Gospel full of life.” His subsequent proclamation in the pre-Anaphora is the
                    exact words of <hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2a, just after he declares to
                    the faithful that the celebrating priest is placing incense “before the merciful
                    Lord” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܳܡ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ
                        ܡܪܰܚܡܳܢܳܐ</foreign> ). Here too, the faithful respond with the exact words of <hi
                        style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>2b. The deacon’s subsequent proclamation is
                    just before the recitation of the creed, again with a jussive, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܩܽܘܡ ܫܰܦܺܝܪ ܟܽܠܰܢ
                        ܒܰܨܠܽܘܬܳܐ</foreign> “let us all stand well in prayer.” At the beginning of the
                    Anaphora proper, the deacon instructs the faithful, again in the jussive, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܶܬܶܠ ܫܠܳܡܳܐ
                        ܠܰܚ̈ܕܳܕܶܐ</foreign> “let us give peace to one another” and right after the giving
                    of the peace, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܳܡ
                        ܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܡܪܰܚܡܳܢܳܐ ܪ̈ܺܝܫܰܝܢ ܢܰܪܟܶܢ</foreign> “let us bow down our head in front of
                    the merciful Lord.” The thurifer also uses the jussive when calling upon the
                    people, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܩܽܘܡ
                        ܫܰܦܺܝܪ</foreign> “let us stand well.” During the diptychs, deacons instruct the
                    faithful, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܰܠܶܐ
                        ܘܢܶܬܟܰܫܰܦ</foreign> “let us pray and beseech” and later <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܡܳܪܝܳܐ ܢܶܬܟܰܫܰܦ</foreign>
                    “let us beseech the Lord.” With almost every proclamation, there is a response
                    by the people. H2a must have once belonged to the deacon rather than the priest,
                    let alone the bishop.</p>
                <p>While the Šuroyo never appears in manuscripts or printed editions, we know about
                    it—and indeed its text—from Mushe of Mardin, the monk who traveled to Europe to
                    print the New Testament in 1555. After collaborating with Johann Albrecht
                    Widmanstad (1506–1557) to produce the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of
                    the NT, the two men put together a primer for the Syriac language.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> Widmanstad [and
                            Mushe of Mardin], <hi rend="italic">Primo Elementa</hi>
                        (1555).</p></note> After introducing the alphabet with some exercises, they
                    published a few prayers for which Mushe must have been the source. A Ḥusoyo is
                    given with the full text of the Šuroyo. It is most likely that Mushe included
                    the text of the Šuroyo explicitly, as Europeans would not be familiar with the
                    oral elements of the liturgy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi><hi rend="bold">3,5</hi> The Promion
                        (<hi style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>3) and the Sedro (<hi
                        style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi>5) are the only elements known from the written
                    text. The two elements form a set, the former recited by the priest and the
                    latter by the deacon. In the case of the Šḥimo, an appendix contains all the
                    Ḥusoyo texts in the form of Promion-Sedro pairs. One cannot read a Promion of
                    one Ḥusoyo and follow it with the Sedro of another.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ</hi><hi rend="bold">4</hi> The <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܚܰܣܝܳܢܳܐ</foreign>
                    (Mḥasyono) is interspersed between the Promion and the Sedro only if the deacon
                    offers incense and is usually omitted in the daily offices. This text is long
                    and survives orally. Here too, Mushe of Mardin gives us a version of the
                    text.</p>
                <p>The Mḥasyono is prefixed with the phrase <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܰܠ ܥܶܛܪܳܐ
                        ܕܒܶܣ̈ܡܶܐ</foreign> “by the fragrance of incense” (<hi style="font-size:10pt"
                        >Ḥ</hi>4a), chanted by the bishop if present. It is more likely that this
                    phrase is associated with the action of placing incense in the censor by the
                    highest-ranking priest, which would explain why the bishop would say this phrase
                    if present.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold" style="font-size:10pt">Ḥ6</hi> After the recitation of the Sedro,
                    the highest-ranking priest recites the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܽܘܒܳܠܳܐ</foreign>
                    (Qubolo), the formula being <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܶܢ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ ܢܩܰܒܶܠ
                        ܚܽܘܣܳܝܳܐ ܕܚܰܘܒ̈ܶܐ ܘܫܽܘܒܩܳܢܳܐ ܕܰܚܛܳܗ̈ܶܐ ܒܰܬܪ̈ܰܝܗܽܘܢ ܥܳܠ̈ܡܶܐ ܠܥܰܠܰܡ
                        ܥܳܠܡܺܝܢ</foreign> “May we receive from God remission of debts and forgiveness of
                    sings in both worlds, forever and ever.” Jacob of Bartilleh mentions the Qubolo
                    when he refers to the Sedro of the Lilyo hour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30"
                        n="30"><p rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub Albartali, p.
                        110.</p></note></p>
                <p>The entirety of the Ḥusoyo is delivered today in three different methods. At Mor
                    Gabriel Monastery, southeast Turkey, the entire thing is recited <hi
                        rend="italic">explicitly</hi> in some hours, especially those of Lilyo. In
                    many of the Tur Abdin parishes, and those in the Diaspora that originate from
                    Tur Abdin, the Ḥusoyo (Šuroyo + Promion + Sedro) is recited in <hi rend="italic"
                        >silence</hi> by a priest while the <hi rend="italic">gudo</hi> goes on with
                    what follows. In most parishes, the entire Sedro is <hi rend="italic"
                        >omitted</hi>, but the proclamation Ḥ1 is retained as part of chanting the
                    adjacent hymns.</p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.6" xml:lang="en">
                <head>V. Qolo Schema</head>
                <p>It is worth providing some comments on the structure of the
                    Qolo. A Qolo is basically a stanzaic poem (kind of a Madrosho) with a specific
                    metrical structure. The basic unit is the syllable or vowel count, called in
                    Syriac <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܶܓܝܳܢܳܐ</foreign>.
                    Stress does not play any role in Syriac poetry because Syriac syllables are all
                    of the same weight (bimoraic) as unstressed short vowels in open syllables
                    (which would be monomoraic) are absent.</p>
                <p>The next unit is the poetic phrase denoted by an unmarked caesura, a break or a
                    pause in a line of verse. The poetic phrase is bound because it cannot stand
                    alone in a line. Typically, long lines of seven or more syllables have such
                    caesurae. Syriac does not have a technical term for the poetic phrase, and some
                    poets are unaware of it. For example, it is commonly known that the <hi
                        rend="italic">qolo</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܰܡܳܐ ܘܥܰܡ̱̈ܡܶܐ</foreign>
                    —used often in dialog poems—consists of lines with seven syllables each. It is
                    less known that each line consists of two poetic phrases, 4+3 syllables, for the
                    melody to work smoothly. There is sometimes an intended discourse between the
                    poetic phrases. The next unit after the line is the stanza itself. This point is
                    illustrated with the qolo named <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܽܘܩܳܝܳܐ</foreign> whose
                    meter, given from right to left, is:</p>
                
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <p>5+4 5+7 5+7 5+4 5+4 5+7 4+7</p>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                
                <p>Here is an actual stanza. I use the punctuation ‘<foreign xml:lang="syr">܇</foreign>’ to denote a
                    caesura break. A colon denotes a line break. A period denotes the end of a
                    melodic section (to be discussed next). </p>
                
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <p rend="Quote"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܪܳܝܳܐ</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">: ܟܽܠܳܗ̇ ܐܰܪܥܳܐ
                        ܕܶܐܦܶܣܳܘܣ܇ ܛܰܠܳܐ ܪܶܣܡܰܬ݂:</foreign> 4+7</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"
                    ><foreign xml:lang="syr">	ܟܰܕ݂ ܐܰܝܬܺܝ ܡܳܪܝ̱ ܝܽܘܚܰܢܳܢ܇ ܟܬ݂ܳܒ̈ܶܐ ܕܰܒܬ݂ܽܘܠܬܳܐ. </foreign>
                    5+7</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܶܨܥܳܝܳܐ</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">: ܕܰܪܫܺܝܡ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ ܒܗܽܘܢ܇
                        ܕܢܶܗܘܶܐ ܕܽܘܟ݂ܪܳܢܳܐ:</foreign> 5+4</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><foreign xml:lang="syr">
                        ܕܰܡܒܰܪܰܟ݂ܬܳܐ܇ ܬܠܳܬ݂ ܙܰܒ̈ܢܺܝܢ ܒܫܰܢ̱ܬܳܐ.</foreign> 5+4</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܠܳܡܳܐ</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">: ܒܟܳܢܽܘܢ ܢܶܗܘܶܐ ܥܰܠ
                        ܙܰܪ̈ܥܶܐ܇ ܘܒܺܐܝܳܪ ܥܰܠ ܫܶܒ̈ܠܶܐ:</foreign> 5+7</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܘܒܳܐܒ
                        ܝܰܪܚܳܐ ܡܶܛܽܠ ܓܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ܇ ܕܐ̱ܪܳܙ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܨܺܝܪ ܒܗܶܝܢ:</foreign> 5+7</p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> ܗܰܠܶܠܽܘܝܰܗ܇ ܨܠܽܘܬ݂ܳܗ̇ ܬܥܰܕܰܪܝ̱ ܠܰܢ. 5+4</p>
                    </quote>
                </cit>                
                <p>The musical layer adds another complication. Each stanza consists of a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܪܳܝܳܐ</foreign>
                    “beginning,” an optional <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܶܨܥܳܝܳܐ</foreign>
                    “middle,” and a <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܠܳܡܳܐ</foreign> “end.” Typically, the poetic (and melodic in the case of
                    chanting) structure of the <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܪܳܝܳܐ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܽܘܠܳܡܳܐ</foreign> is
                    either exact or very similar. Notice that each poetic phrase corresponds to a
                    grammatical phrase in terms of discourse. It is seldom that a grammatical phrase
                    crosses over poetic phrases. A further melodic subdivision, not shown above,
                    could split words. For instance, all 7-syllable caesurae are divided <hi
                        rend="italic">melodically</hi> into 2+5 syllables. The boundary in line 2
                    occurs in the middle of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܰܝܬܺܝ</foreign><hi
                        style="font-size:2pt"> </hi>:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <p><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܰܕ݂ ܐܰܝـ  ـܬܺܝ ܡܳܪܝ̱ ܝܽܘܚܰܢܳܢ܇ ܟܬ݂ܳܒ̈ܶܐ ܕܰܒܬ݂ܽܘܠܬܳܐ. </foreign>
                    5+(7 = 5 + 2)</p>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p>The same occurs with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܰܪܚܳܐ</foreign> in line 6:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <p><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܒܳܐܒ ܝܰܪ
                        ܚܳܐ ܡܶܛܽܠ ܓܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ܇ ܕܐ̱ܪܳܙ ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܨܺܝܪ ܒܗܶܝܢ:</foreign> 5+(7 = 5 + 2)</p>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p>Such subdivisions could vary across regional musical traditions, a topic that is
                    beyond the scope of the current paper. </p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.7" xml:lang="en">
                <head>VI. Hour Delimiters</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">As a syntaxis consists of more than one hour, how
                    does one determine where one hour ends and where the next begins?</p>
                <p>Thus far, we have encountered elements known from two modalities: written and
                    oral. A third modality, usually ignored in multimodal frameworks, is at play
                    here: silence. Long pauses of silence—or what seems to be silence—mark the end
                    of an hour and the beginning of the next.</p>
                <p>But here, silence is associated with actions. In silence, the recitation of a
                    Qawmo is associated with making the sign of the cross a few times. Until quite
                    recently—around the end of the twentieth century—the silence was sometimes a
                    form of incoherent mumbling. In the last decade or two, especially during events
                    when many of the faithful are present, the mumbling turns into full-fledged oral
                    action.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">qawmo</hi> consists of the Trisagion (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܰܕܺܝܫܳܬ ܐܰܠܗܳܐ</foreign>
                    ...) followed by the Lord’s prayer (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܰܒܽܘܢ ܕܒܰܫܡܰܝܳܐ</foreign>
                    ...). The Trisagion is audible with specific melodies in some hours, but the
                    Lord’s Prayer is silent. The only exception is the <hi rend="italic">qawme</hi>
                    of Lilyo where the entire thing is replaced with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܝܟ ܗܘ ܐܝܩܪܗ</foreign>
                     ...
                    which is mentioned by Jacob of Bartelleh.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                        n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub Albartali, p.
                        110.</p></note> The full texts of these delimiter prayers are given in
                    Barsoum’s <hi rend="italic">al-Tuḥfa al-Rūḥiyya</hi>, a guide to the faithful in
                    Arabic that has been translated into many languages.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> A. Barsoum, <hi rend="italic"
                                >al-Tuḥfa al-Rūḥiyya</hi> (Aleppo, 1956, 5<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> ed.), with many editions and translations.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.8" xml:lang="en">
                <head>VII. Themes</head>
                <p>Before closing, it is worth noting the thematic
                    organization of the Šḥimo. Each day/hour has a theme. These themes range from
                    glorifying Mary (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܳܠܕܰܬ ܐܰܠܳܗܳܐ</foreign> ), calling upon the apostles (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܺܝܚ̈ܶܐ</foreign>), and
                    sometimes the evangelists (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܶܘܰܢܓܶܠܺܣ̈ܛܶܐ</foreign>),
                    remembering the saints (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign>)—or one
                    particular saint (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܰܕ
                        ܩܢܽܘܡܳܐ</foreign> ), or remembering the martyrs (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܳܗ̈ܕܶܐ</foreign>) and the
                    departed (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܰܢܺܝ̈ܕܶܐ</foreign>). Another theme is commemorating the cross (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܠܺܝܒܳܐ</foreign>) during
                    the resurrection season. Repentance (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܳܒܽܘܬܳܐ</foreign>) is
                    another central theme. A multi-theme hymn is called <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܰܘܳܢܳܝܬܳܐ</foreign>
                    “general, common.” The table in Appendix 1 gives the days of the week, the
                    hours, and the themes assigned to each hour.</p>
                <p>In order to remember this complex arrangement, the Malphone came up with a poem,
                    cited by Konat, that spells out the various themes,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"> Konat ed., intro p.
                        II.</p></note></p>
                <cit>
                    <quote xml:lang="syr">
                        <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܽܘܡ ܚܰܕ ܒܫܰܒܳܐ ܕܰܩܝܳܡܬܳܐ܆ ܬܪܶܝܢ ܒܫܰܒܳܐ ܕܰܬܝܳܒܽܘܬܳܐ܆</foreign></l>
                <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܳܟܘܳܬ ܒܰܬܠܳܬܳܐ ܒܫܰܒܳܐ܆ ܐܰܪܒܥܳܐ ܒܫܰܒܳܐ ܕܰܒܬܽܘܠܬܳܐ܀</foreign></l>
                <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܰܡܫܳܐ ܒܫܰܒܳܐ ܕܰܫܠܺܝܚ̈ܶܐ܆ ܘܡܰܠ̈ܦܳܢܶܐ ܕܥܺܕܰܬ ܩܽܘܕܫܳܐ܆</foreign></l>
                <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܪܽܘܒܬܳܐ ܕܰܨܠܺܝܒܳܐ ܚܰܝܳܐ܆ ܘܣܳܗ̈ܕܶܐ ܓܒ̈ܰܝܳܐ ܘܩܰܕܺܝ̈ܫܶܐ܀</foreign></l>
                <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܽܘܡ ܫܰܒܬܳܐ ܕܶܐܬܬܢܺܝܚ ܡܳܪܝܳܐ܆ ܡܶܢ ܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܥܒܳܕܰܘ̈ܗ̱ܝ ܕܰܥܒܰܕ܆</foreign></l>
                <l><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܟܳܗ̈ܢܶܐ ܙܗ̈ܰܝܳܐ ܘܩܰܕܺܝ̈ܫܶܐ܆ ܘܟܽܠܗܘܢ ܥܰܢܺܝ̈ܕܶܐ ܡܗܰܝ̈ܡܢܳܐ܀</foreign></l>
                </quote>
                </cit>
                <cit>
                    <quote xml:lang="en">
                        <l>Sunday is for the Resurrection; Monday is for
                        repentance;</l>
                <l>Likewise on Tuesday (i.e., repentance); Wednesday for
                        the Virgin.
                </l>
                <l>Thursday for the Apostles and the Doctors of the Holy
                        Church;</l>
                <l>Friday for the Living Cross and the chosen martyrs and
                        the saints.</l>
                <l>Saturday, during which the Lord rested from all the
                        deeds that he accomplished, is for the reverend priests and the saints; and
                        all the faithful departed.
                </l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p>This thematic structure also goes back to at least the beginning of the second
                    millennium. Jacob of Bartelleh mentions that the Qolo of Sutoro is for
                    repentance, agreeing with the above table.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                        n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> Mar Severios Yacoub Albartali, p.
                        108</p></note> The themes of the Ramšo <hi rend="italic">Quqalion</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Boʿutho</hi> seem to represent an earlier thematic
                    arrangement known from Bar Salibi’s treatise against the Melkites,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"> A. Mingana, <hi
                                rend="italic">Woodbrook I</hi>, p. 33.</p></note></p>
                <p rend="Quote"><hi style="font-size:10pt">Sundays are consecrated to the festival
                        of the Resurrection; Mondays and Tuesdays are devoted to prayers and
                        repentance; Wednesdays are to the Mother of God, to the martyrs, and the
                        dead; Thursdays to the Apostles and Doctors, to the Mother of God, to the
                        martyrs, and to the dead; Fridays to the Cross; and Saturdays to the Mother
                        of God, to the martyrs, and the dead.</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.9" xml:lang="en">
                <head>VIII. Concluding Remarks</head>
                <p>This paper argues that the schema of the Šḥimo goes back to
                    at least the early modern period (ca. 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century)
                    if not to the first quarter of the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> millennium,
                    as many of its elements are mentioned by writers of the Syriac renaissance
                    period. It has also been shown that a complete understanding of the liturgical
                    genre requires a close familiarity with the received tradition, where the
                    written text engages quite intimately with orality, not to mention silence.
                    Indeed, the written-oral-silence interface has not been addressed by scholarship
                    to the best of my knowledge.</p>
                <p>Another remark also argues that “corruption” is part of a living tradition. It
                    has been proposed, for example, that the Šuroyo of the Ḥusoyo prayer (viz., <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܠܐ
                        ܟܠܢ</foreign>) must have belonged once to the deacon on the bases of philological
                    analogy with the Qurobo liturgy.</p>
                <p>Digital Humanities projects may find this study helpful in representing
                    liturgical texts. Some snippets appear below.</p>
            </div>
            <div  xml:id="h25n2kiraz.10" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Appendix: TEI-XML Schema</head>
                <p>The following are TEI-XML snippets for encoding the text
                    of Šḥimo. The main <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >TEI</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> section includes one <hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">text</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> element (lines 2–12) and another <hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">body</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> element (lines 3–11). The main division
                    element (<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>, line 4) under the body has two attributes.
                    The first, <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi>, states that the content is a
                    book. The second, <hi rend="color(FF0000)">subtype</hi>, defines the genre as
                        <hi rend="color(0000FF)">šximo</hi>. It is proposed that the rest of the
                    schema is dependent on this value, <hi rend="color(0000FF)">šximo</hi>. It
                    determines the schema of the rest of the XML. Other liturgical books would have
                    other values for <hi rend="color(FF0000)">subtype;</hi> the rest of the XML will
                    look differently. </p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 1 <anchor xml:id="Hlk103648794"/><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">TEI</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 2 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">text</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">xml:lang</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">syr</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 3 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">body</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 4 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">book</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">subtype</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<anchor xml:id="Hlk103345792"/><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">šximo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 5 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">day</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">n</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">xad bšabo</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 6 <hi rend="color(0000FF)"> &lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">hour</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">n</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"7<hi rend="color(0000FF)">"&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 7 <hi rend="color(0000FF)"
                        >&lt;!--</hi><hi rend="color(008000)"> Liturgical elements here </hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">--&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 8 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 9 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 10 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 11 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">body</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 12 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">text</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; "> 13 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">TEI</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p>A Qolo, such as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܽܘܩܳܝܳܐ</foreign> mentioned above, can be encoded with the following snippet.
                    The entire thing is a division of <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)">qolo</hi> (line 1 below). Again, this type determines
                    the schema that follows. The <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">sp</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> element (line
                    2) designates the speaker, which <hi rend="italic">gudo</hi> is to chant the <hi
                        rend="italic">qolo</hi>. The two <hi rend="italic">gude</hi> are designated
                    by <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ</foreign>. The odd number
                    of stanzas in a <hi rend="italic">qolo</hi> ensures that the <hi rend="italic"
                        >gude</hi> alternate in starting the hymns.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">rubric</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> element (lines 3–7) gives the qolo name with
                    a link to a bethgazo encoding (line 4) and also designates the tune number (line
                    5).</p>
                <p>The actual stanza is encoded as a line group (<hi rend="color(0000FF)"
                        >&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)"
                    >&gt;</hi>, lines 8–22) of <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)">stanza</hi>. Again, the type determines the schema that
                    follows. The three subdivisions of the stanza (<hi rend="italic">šuroyo</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">meṣʿoyo</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">šulomo</hi>) are each
                    encoding with a line group as well. Then each line of the stanza is encoded with
                    a line element (<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>).</p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">1 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">qolo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">2 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">sp</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">speaker</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>ܓܘܕܐ ܐ<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">speaker</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">sp</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">3 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">rubric</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">4 <hi style="font-size:11ptdirection:rtl;"
                        >ܥܠ ܩܠܐ ܕ</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">ref</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">bethgazo</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">target</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">...</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi><hi style="font-size:11ptdirection:rtl;"
                        >ܩܽܘܩܳܝܳܐ</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">5 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">num</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">tune</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">value</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">1</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi><hi style="font-size:11ptdirection:rtl;"
                        >ܩܕܡܝܐ</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >num</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">6 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">ref</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">7 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">rubric</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">8 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">stanza</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">9 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">šuroyo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">10 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܟܽܠܳܗ̇ ܐܰܪܥܳܐ ܕܶܐܦܶܣܳܘܣ܇ ܛܰܠܳܐ ܪܶܣܡܰܬ݂:</foreign><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">11 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܟܰܕ݂ ܐܰܝܬܺܝ ܡܳܪܝ̱ ܝܽܘܚܰܢܳܢ܇ ܟܬ݂ܳܒ̈ܶܐ ܕܰܒܬ݂ܽܘܠܬܳܐ.</foreign><hi rend="color(0000FF)"> &lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">12 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">13 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">meṣʿoyo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">14 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܕܰܪܫܺܝܡ ܗ̱ܘܳܐ ܒܗܽܘܢ܇ ܕܢܶܗܘܶܐ ܕܽܘܟ݂ܪܳܢܳܐ:</foreign><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">15 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܰܡܒܰܪܰܟ݂ܬܳܐ܇ ܬܠܳܬ݂ ܙܰܒ̈ܢܺܝܢ
                        ܒܫܰܢ̱ܬܳܐ.</foreign><hi rend="color(0000FF)"> &lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">16 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">17 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">šulomo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">18 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܟܳܢܽܘܢ ܢܶܗܘܶܐ ܥܰܠ ܙܰܪ̈ܥܶܐ܇ ܘܒܺܐܝܳܪ ܥܰܠ
                        ܫܶܒ̈ܠܶܐ:</foreign><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">29 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܒܳܐܒ ܝܰܪܚܳܐ ܡܶܛܽܠ ܓܽܘ̈ܦܢܶܐ܇ ܕܐ̱ܪܳܙ
                        ܚܰܝ̈ܶܐ ܨܺܝܪ ܒܗܶܝܢ:</foreign><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">20 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܰܠܶܠܽܘܝܰܗ܇ ܨܠܽܘܬ݂ܳܗ̇ ܬܥܰܕܰܪܝ̱ ܠܰܢ</foreign>
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)">l</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">21 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">22 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">lg</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">23 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p>One can, of course, choose to fine-tune this encoding further to encode the
                    caesura breaks or even the melodic breaks within words that were mentioned
                    above.</p>
                <p>Texts that appear elsewhere, or the oral liturgical elements described above, can
                    be encoded once and referred to with the <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">ref</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi> element.
                    Here is an example for linking to a <hi rend="italic">ḥusoyo</hi> text.</p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">1 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">ḥusoyo</hi>"<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">2 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">p</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">ref</hi>
                    <hi rend="color(FF0000)">type</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"<hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">ḥusoyo</hi>" <hi rend="color(FF0000)">target</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)">=</hi>"..."<hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܕܪܐ
                        ܕܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</foreign><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >ref</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)"
                        >p</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p rend="XML" style="text-align: left; ">3 <hi rend="color(0000FF)">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)">div</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p>One can explicitly states all of the oral aspects of the liturgy in the XML
                    encoding.</p>
                <p style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt"
                        >&lt;</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)" style="font-size:9.5pt">colophon</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p style="text-align: left;">
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt">&lt;</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)" style="font-size:9.5pt">p</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)"
                        style="font-size:9.5pt">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܟܕܘ ܗܠܝܢ
                        ܠܦܪ̈ܘܫܐ</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                <p style="text-align: left;">
                    <hi rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt">&lt;/</hi><hi
                        rend="color(A31515)" style="font-size:9.5pt">p</hi><hi rend="color(0000FF)"
                        style="font-size:9.5pt">&gt;</hi></p>
                <p style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt"
                        >&lt;/</hi><hi rend="color(A31515)" style="font-size:9.5pt">colophon</hi><hi
                        rend="color(0000FF)" style="font-size:9.5pt">&gt;</hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <p>Acharya, F. <hi rend="italic">Prayer with the Harp of the Spirit. I, A Weekly
                        Celebration of the Economy of Salvation</hi> (Kurisumala Ashram, Vagamon,
                    1983).</p>
                <p>Armalet, I. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue des Manuscrits de Charfet</hi>
                    (1937).</p>
                <p rend="footnote text"
                        ><hi style="font-size:12pt">Aydin, E. </hi><hi
                        style="font-size:12ptdirection:rtl;">ܫܚܝܡܐ: ܟܬܒܐ ܕܨܠܘ̈ܬܐ ܕܫܒܬܐ
                        ܫܚܝܡܬܐ</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> in </hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline" style="font-size:12pt">H</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        style="font-size:12pt"
                    >eto</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> 3 (2001), no. 5: 46-35.</hi></p>
                <p>Barsoum, A. <hi rend="italic">al-Luʾluʾ al-Manthūr</hi> (Aleppo, 1956 2<hi
                        rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed.).</p>
                <p>Barsoum, A. <hi rend="italic">al-Tuḥfa al-Rūḥiyya</hi> (Aleppo, 1956, 5<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> ed.), with many editions and translations.</p>
                <p>Baumstark, A. “syr-Antioch” in <hi rend="italic">Der Katholik</hi> 82 (401–427,
                    538–550) &amp; 83 (43–54).</p>
                <p>Baumstark, A. <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der syrischen Literatur</hi>
                    (1922).</p>
                <p rend="footnote text"
                        ><hi style="font-size:12pt">Chaillot, C. </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Syrian Orthodox Church of Antioch
                        and All the East, a brief introduction to its life and
                    spirituality</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> (Geneva: Inter-Orthodox Dialogue, 1998).</hi></p>
                <p>Kiraz, G. “A Proclamation Out of Place, ‘Stomen Kalos, Kyrie-Eleison’ and the
                    Nicene Creed.” In <hi rend="italic">Ktheeboth hago</hi>: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Festschrift in Honour of His Holiness Ignatius Zakka I Iwas</hi>, ed. Roy
                    Thomas, 417–31. Chicago: St. George Syrian Orthodox Church of Malankarra,
                    2005.</p>
                <p rend="footnote text"
                        ><hi style="font-size:12pt">Kiraz, G. “A Young Syriac Pupil in the Cairo Genizah: Or.1081 2.75.30.” </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Fragment of the Month: Newsletter of
                        the Cambridge University Library Genizah
                        Unit</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt">. August 2018. </hi><ref
                        target="https://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/collections/departments/taylor-schechter-genizah-research-unit/fragment-month/fotm-2018/fragment-6"
                            ><hi style="font-size:12pt"
                            >https://www.lib.cam.ac.uk/collections/departments/taylor-schechter-genizah-research-unit/fragment-month/fotm-2018/fragment-6</hi></ref><hi
                        style="font-size:12pt">.</hi></p>
                <p rend="footnote text"
                        ><hi style="font-size:12pt">Kiraz, G. “Learning Syriac and Garshuni in Early Modern Egypt: Evidence from the Cairo Genizah” in Geoffrey Khan, Sabine Schmitdke, and Sarah Stroumsa (eds.), </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">Studies in Literary
                    Genizot</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> (=</hi><hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"> Intellectual History of the Islamicate World</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> 8 (2020): 1–26.</hi></p>
                <p rend="footnote text"
                        ><hi style="font-size:12pt">Mnayyer, Y. </hi><hi
                        rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt"
                    >al-ʾIšḥīm</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> (Damascus, 1994).</hi></p>
                <p>Severios Yacoub Albartali. <hi rend="italic">The Treasures</hi>. Translated into
                    Arabic by Behnam Daniel al-Bartali (Aleppo: Dar Mardin, 2007).</p>
                <p>Tabet, J. <hi rend="italic">L'Office commun maronite</hi> (Kaslik, 1972).</p>
                <p rend="footnote text"><hi style="font-size:12pt">Taft, R. </hi>
                    <hi rend="italic" style="font-size:12pt">The Liturgy of the Hours in East and
                        West</hi><hi style="font-size:12pt"> (1993).</hi></p>
                <p>Tomajean, J. “La semaine liturgique dans le rite syrien” in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Parole de l'Orient</hi> (1966) no. 1, 95–114.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Appendix 1: Table of Daily Prayers</head>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Su</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Mo</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Tu</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ramšo</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><seg>  </seg><hi
                                rend="italic">Quqalyon</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܪܡܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܪܡܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">
                            <hi rend="italic">Bo</hi>ʿ<hi rend="italic">utho</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Sutoro</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lilyo, Q I</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lilyo Q II</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lilyo Q III</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Lilyo Q IV</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ ܘܟܢ ܚܕ ܩܢܘܡܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><seg>   </seg><hi
                                rend="italic">Boʿutho</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">Ṣaphro</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><seg>   </seg><hi
                                rend="italic">Quqalyon</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܨܦܪܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܨܦܪܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><seg>   </seg><hi
                                rend="italic">Boʿutho</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Hr</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">6<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Hr</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Hr</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"/>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p style="text-align: left;"><pb/></p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:lang="en">
                <p>Appendix 1 : Table of Daily Prayers (cont.)</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">We</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Th</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Fr</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;"><hi rend="smallcaps">Sa</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܪܡܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܗ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="2">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ ܐܘ ܨܠܝܒܐ*</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܝ̈ܚܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܗ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ/ ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ ܘܟܢ ܚܕ ܩܢܘܡܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܝ̈ܚܐ ܘܐܘܢܓܠܣ̈ܛܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܘ ܨܦܪܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܠܝܒܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܗ̈ܢܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;">"</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܠܕܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܝܒܘܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܠܝܒܐ</foreign></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܗ̈ܢܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܘܢܝܬܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: center;" cols="4"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܝ̈ܕܐ</foreign></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
