<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Arman Akopian, <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac</hi>
                    (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2019)</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Emmanuel</forename>
                        <surname>Aïm</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Tel Aviv</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2praim</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Emmanuel Aïm</author>
                        <title level="a">Arman Akopian, <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac</hi>
                            (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2019)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2PRAim.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="485" to="489">485-489</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="5"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                <ab type="review-title">Arman Akopian, <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac</hi>
                    (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2019). Pp. xiv + 384; $98.00.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="author" xml:lang="en">
                <ab type="review-author">Emmanuel Aïm, Tel Aviv</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">In addition to Robinson’s standard work (6th edition by
                Coakley, 2013), other valuable Classical Syriac course books for English-speaking
                learners are available, viz. Thackston (1999), Healey (2005), Kiraz (2013), Hallam
                (2016), and Younansardaroud (2019). Gorgias Press recently added to this series the
                book under review, whose Armenian original version was published by Yerevan State
                University in 2005.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Akopian’s work follows the classical format already used in
                most of these textbooks. Following an introductory course of eight lessons on Syriac
                script and phonology, it provides a basic course of 40 lessons, each introducing
                some elements of grammar followed by reading and translation exercises along with a
                vocabulary list. Serto is used throughout, while Estrangelo and East Syriac script
                are introduced later. The manual ends with useful appendices (on scripts, grammar,
                the names of the biblical books in Syriac), paradigms, and keys to exercises. Its
                comfortable trim size (7 x 10 inches), substantial length (399 pages), and clear and
                beautiful typesetting (font size, Syriac characters, layout) are conducive to study
                and can only make the student want to immerse himself in the study of Syriac.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The book opens with an overview of the history of the Syriac
                language that the author calls ‘brief’. This is in fact a relatively long (28 pages)
                and very well documented introduction to the history of the Aramaic language and its
                dialects with, of course, a special emphasis on Syriac. Worth noting is the mention
                of the Syriac Melkites (pp. 14–15, 20), who are too often disregarded in
                introductions to Syriac (as in the aforementioned textbooks, but also in reference
                grammars such as Costaz 1955 and Muraoka 1997). On page 5, Akopian states that
                Hebrew ceased to be spoken in Palestine after the return of the exiles from Babylon
                and was replaced by Aramaic. Yet, modern scholarship has almost unanimously
                abandoned this view and agrees that Hebrew continued to be spoken, side by side with
                Aramaic, until the end of the Mishnaic period approximately (see Bar-Asher 1999, pp.
                29ff.). Also, on page 7, the author rightly states that the Arabic script is
                believed to stem from the Nabatean Aramaic script. However, he should have added
                that some scholars are, interestingly, of the opinion that it originates from the
                Syriac script (see Briquel-Chatonnet 1997 and the references therein). Finally,
                while it is not customary to present a bibliography in textbooks, some basic
                references would have been welcome due to the rich content of the introduction.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The manual then provides a series of lessons that the author
                designed so as to cover one academic year, or to be used for self-study. The main
                strength of these lessons is their very progressive aspect. Contrary to Coakley
                (2013), Hallam (2016), and Younansardaroud (2019) who present first the nominal
                system and then the verbal system, Akopian gradually introduces – like Thackston
                (1999) – aspects of both systems. This order seems more useful, allowing the student
                to use and read sentences from the very beginning. Other notable instances of this
                pedagogy are the progressive presentation of the genitive constructions, pronominal
                suffixes attached to the verbs, numerals, and the Estrangelo and East Syriac
                scripts. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The exercises are well conceived. They consist of readings and
                translations both from and into Syriac. The author does not limit them to sentences
                drawn or adapted from the classical Syriac literature. He also composed texts and
                dialogues and added texts from Qarabashi (1986) to introduce the student to the
                modern usage of Syriac (<hi rend="italic">kthobonoyo</hi>). This allows the student
                to practice on a wider range of vocabulary, content, and style. In addition, the
                texts include many footnotes that refer to sections containing the relevant
                grammatical material. If learners encounter some difficulties, they can quickly and
                easily find the corresponding paragraphs within the book.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Besides, a significant merit of the textbook is the clarity
                with which the author presents grammatical concepts and rules without going into
                overly technical details. For example, during the introduction of the absolute state
                (p. 85), he does not discuss the reasons why the vocalization of a noun may vary.
                Rather than overload the description with a phonological rule (viz. the
                retrogressive syncope of short vowels in open syllable) that may appear complex or
                unnecessary at that point, the author simply refers the student to the glossaries
                and the online dictionary in order to learn the possible various forms of a noun. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Finally, another virtue of Akopian’s work is the supplementary
                documents available online at the Gorgias Press site
                (https://www.gorgiaspress.com/arman-akopian-classical-syriac-download). The
                Syriac–English and English–Syriac dictionaries will be particularly useful,
                especially for doing the exercises. The downloadable reader contains various texts
                in the three Syriac scripts, with or without vocalization. It allows the student to
                progress significantly after completing the textbook. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Some minor aspects are nevertheless not completely
                satisfactory. First, Akopian uses the Greek/West Syriac vowels with the Serto
                script, but in a way that reflects the East Syriac vocalization (the real West
                Syriac vocalization is given when relevant). In the case of <hi rend="italic"
                    >o/u</hi>, the ambiguity is removed by the additional use of East Syriac <hi
                    style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bibledirection:rtl;">ܘܿ</hi> and <hi
                    style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bibledirection:rtl;">ܘܼ</hi>. However, in the
                case of <hi rend="italic">i/e</hi>, opacity remains in the verbal forms where West
                Syriac <hi style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bibledirection:rtl;">ܺ</hi> corresponds
                to East Syriac <hi style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bibledirection:rtl;">ܹ</hi>.
                Here, the author employs <hi style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bibledirection:rtl;"
                    >ܶ</hi>, as for example in <hi
                    style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bible;font-size:14ptdirection:rtl;">ܢܶܐܠܰܕ</hi>
                and <hi style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bible;font-size:14ptdirection:rtl;"
                    >ܢܶܐܬܶܐ</hi>, which appear in West Syriac as <hi
                    style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bible;font-size:14ptdirection:rtl;">ܢܺܐܠܰܕ</hi>
                and <hi style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bible;font-size:14ptdirection:rtl;"
                    >ܢܺܐܬܶܐ</hi>, respectively. As a result, students learn and read spellings that
                do not really exist and that they will never find in vocalized texts. My only
                concern is that this artificial combination of the two vowel-systems may be
                confusing for some. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Second, <hi rend="italic">quššāyā</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >rukkā</hi><hi rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic">ā</hi> are marked
                inconsistently throughout the book. As for the combination of the two vowel-systems
                mentioned above, this is not a major obstacle to learning. Yet, regular marking
                would have been more suitable, especially to learn a correct pronunciation.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Third, the keys to exercises cover only the eight introductory
                chapters and the first ten lessons, which means that the use of the manual for
                self-study is limited since students cannot check themselves with certainty. Note
                that minor errors appear at times in the keys to exercises. For instance, on page
                370, the adjective ‘big’ is rendered as <hi
                    style="font-family:Serto Antioch Bible;font-size:14ptdirection:rtl;"
                    >ܐܘܽܟܳܡܳܬܳܐ</hi> (sentence 10, key to exercise 5 on p. 79), and the adjective
                ‘great’ is not translated (sentence 13, key to exercise 5 on p. 79).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Finally, I found some typos among which are the recurrent
                transliteration of spirantized <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟ</foreign> as
                    <hi rend="italic">ḥ</hi> (instead of <hi rend="italic underline">k</hi>), e.g.,
                    <hi rend="italic">arriḥe</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">arri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic">e </hi>(p.
                76, §2.8.1), <hi rend="italic">arriḥā</hi><hi rend="italic underline">t</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ā</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">arri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic">ā</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">t</hi><hi rend="italic">ā </hi>(p.
                76, §2.8.2), <hi rend="italic">arriḥā</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">arri</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic">ā </hi>(p.
                80), <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >riḥā</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                    >ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ri</hi><hi rend="italic underline"
                >k</hi><hi rend="italic">ā </hi>(p. 123), <hi rend="italic"
                    >g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥaḥ/g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥeḥ</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">g</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >ḥa</hi><hi rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic">/g</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ḥe</hi><hi
                        rend="italic underline">k</hi> (p. 158). In the same vein, we also find <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܰܪܺܝܚܶܐ</foreign> instead of 
                <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܰܪܺܝܟܶܐ</foreign> (p. 368, lesson 2, exercise 1). Some confusion occurs at time
                between <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ā</hi>. Thus, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܳ</foreign> is occasionally
                transliterated as <hi rend="italic">a</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">ā</hi>, for
                instance <hi rend="italic">harkā</hi> instead of
                <hi rend="italic">hārkā </hi>(p. 74), <hi rend="italic"
                    >ʾakelqarṣā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hayden</hi>, <hi rend="italic">m</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ṣi</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic">ta</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >na</hi><hi rend="italic underline">g</hi><hi rend="italic">ū</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi> instead of <hi
                    rend="italic">ʾā</hi><hi rend="italic underline">k</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >elqarṣā</hi>, <hi rend="italic">hāyden</hi>, <hi rend="italic">m</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">ə</hi><hi rend="italic">ṣi</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic">tā</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >nā</hi><hi rend="italic underline">g</hi><hi rend="italic">ū</hi><hi
                    rend="italic underline">d</hi><hi rend="italic">ā</hi>, respectively (p. 202).
                On page 191, §4.4,<hi rend="italic"> [ā]</hi> should be read as
                    <hi rend="italic">[a]</hi> since it transcribes <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܱ</foreign>. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">These minor problems do not undermine the value of Arman
                Akopian’s work. Overall, the author wrote a highly valuable textbook. He has well
                designed the sequence of lessons and the progression in grammar and vocabulary. With
                its length of 399 pages, the book is the longest manual for English-speaking
                learners. Moreover, the online additional reader (68 pages) significantly expands
                the course. No doubt, students who go through the entire manual and online reader
                will attain a respectable level that they cannot reach by using the other available
                course books. Therefore, this textbook is highly recommended for learners who intend
                to invest earnestly in the study of Syriac.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
            <listBibl>
                <bibl>Bibliography</bibl>
            <bibl>Bar-Asher, M. <hi rend="italic">L’hébreu mishnique: études
                    linguistiques</hi>. Louvain: Peeters, 1999. </bibl>
            <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F. “De
                l’araméen à l’arabe: quelques réflexions sur la genèse de l’écriture arabe.<hi
                    rend="color(333333)">” In </hi><hi rend="italic">Scribes et manuscrits du
                    Moyen-Orient</hi>, ed. F. Déroche and F. Richard. Paris: Bibliothèque nationale
                de France, 1997, 135–149.</bibl>
            <bibl>Coakley, J. F. <hi rend="italic">Robinson’s Paradigms and
                    Exercises in Syriac Grammar</hi> (6th ed.). Oxford: University Press, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl>Costaz, L. <hi rend="italic">Grammaire syriaque</hi>. Beyrouth: Librairie Orientale, 1955.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hallam, S. C. <hi
                    rend="italic">Basics of Classical Syriac: Complete Grammar, Workbook, and
                    Lexicon</hi>. Grand Rapids, MI:
                        Zondervan, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl>Healey, J. F. <hi rend="italic">Leshono Suryoyo: First Studies
                    in Syriac</hi>. Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl>Kiraz, G. A. <hi rend="italic">The New Syriac Primer</hi> (2nd
                ed.). Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2013.</bibl>
            <bibl>Muraoka, T. <hi rend="italic">Classical Syriac: A Basic Grammar
                    with a Chrestomathy</hi>. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl>Qarabashi, A.-M. <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܪܓܐ
                    ܕܩܪܝܢܐ</foreign>. 6 vols. Losser: Bar-Hebraeus Verlag, 1985–1986.</bibl>
            <bibl>Thackston, W. M. <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Syriac: An
                    Elementary Grammar with Readings from Syriac Literature</hi>. Bethesda,
                Maryland: IBEX, 1999.</bibl>
                <bibl>Younansardaroud, H. <hi rend="italic">Classical
                Syriac Course Book.</hi> Translated by
                G. Wetherall (2nd ed.). Berlin: Universitätsbibliothek der Freien Universität,
                2019.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
