<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">A Preliminary Survey on Isaac of Nineveh’s
                    Arabic Collection in the MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Ar. 151</hi>)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Vasiliki</forename>
                        <surname>Chamourgiotaki</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Freie Universität Berlin</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Emanuele</forename>
                        <surname>Zimbardi</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Ca’ Foscari Università di Venezia</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Vasiliki Chamourgiotaki</author>
                        <author>Emanuele Zimbardi</author>
                        <title level="a">A Preliminary Survey on Isaac of Nineveh’s
                            Arabic Collection in the MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi> (<hi
                                rend="italic">Ar. 151</hi>)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2Chamourgiotaki-Zimbardi.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="365" to="416">365-416</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="2"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Isaac of Nineveh</term>
                    <term>John of Dalyatha</term>
                    <term>MS Strasbourg 4226</term>
                    <term>Isaac Arabus</term>
                    <term>Arabic translation</term>
                    <term>Sinai</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The MS Strasbourg 4226 was produced by the Melchite community of
                    Mar Saba under the commission of Saint Catherine’s monastery on Sinai. Dating as
                    early as the latter part of the ninth century (885/886), it is a very important
                    witness to Isaac Arabus. The aim of this paper is to give an exact overview of the
                    homilies transmitted under the name of Isaac of Nineveh in this manuscript (ff.
                    81v-148v). Each homily is presented with the following information: title (both in
                    the general index and in the body of the text), incipit and desinit, and their
                    textual correspondences with the printed editions of Isaac Syrus by Paul Bedjan and
                    Isaac Graecus by Marcel Pirard. Moreover, the textual correspondences with extracts
                    of three homilies of John of Dalyatha, falsely attributed to Isaac of Nineveh, are
                    indicated with references to the edition of Nadira Khayyat. At the end of the paper
                    a table of correspondences between the Arabic homilies and the Syriac and Greek
                    editions is provided.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Introduction</head><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> We
                            would like to thank Sabino Chialà, for his useful insights in the
                            complex tradition of Isaac and his advice for the structuring of the
                            central part of this paper, and Professor Arianna D’Ottone Rambach, for
                            her useful remarks in Arabic palaeography and her kindness in sharing
                            with us her expertise with Arabic manuscripts. We would also like to
                            thank the anonymous reviewers for their suggestions and comments.
                        </p></note>
                
                <p xml:lang="en">The Arabic transmission of Isaac of Nineveh’s ascetical
                    discourses is largely unexplored by scholarship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2"
                        n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> General accounts on the Isaac Arabus and its
                            textual transmission can be found in G. Assemani, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Bibliotheca Orientalis Clementino-Vaticana</hi>, Vol. 1, <hi
                                rend="italic">De scriptoribus Syris orthodoxis</hi> (Roma: Sacra
                            Congregatio de Propaganda Fide, 1719), 446-459; G. Assemani and S.
                            Assemani, <hi rend="italic">Bibliothecae apostolicae Vaticanae codicum
                                manuscriptorum catalogus</hi>, Vol. 1,3, <hi rend="italic">Reliqui
                                codices Chaldaici sive Syriaci</hi> (Roma: Ex typographia linguarum
                            orientalium, 1759), 427-441; J. Chabot, <hi rend="italic">De S. Isaaci
                                Ninivitae vita, scriptis et doctrina</hi> (Louvain: Lefever F. &amp;
                            S., 1892), 54-60; G. Graf, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der christlichen
                                arabischen Literatur</hi>, Vol. 1, <hi rend="italic">Die
                                Übersetzungen</hi> (Città del Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica
                            Vaticana, 1944), 436-442; id., <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                                christlichen arabischen Literatur</hi>, Vol.
                            2<hi rend="italic">, Die Schriftsteller bis zur Mitte des 15. Jahrhunderts </hi>(Città
                            del Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1947), 58; 397; id., <hi
                                rend="italic">Geschichte der christlichen arabischen Literatur</hi>,
                            Vol. 5<hi rend="italic">, Register </hi>(Città del
                            Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1953), 75, s.v. <hi
                                rend="italic">Isaak der Syrer</hi>; E. Khalifé-Hachem, "Isaac de
                            Ninive," in <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de Spiritualité, ascétique et
                                mystique, doctrine et histoire</hi>, eds. M. Viller et alii, Vol.
                            7.2 (Paris: Beauchesne, 1971), 2052; id., "Les versions arabes d’Isaac
                            de Ninive," in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 28th International
                                Congress of Orientalists (Canberra, 6-12 January 1971)</hi>, ed. A.
                            Davis (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1976), 36–7, M. Pirard (ed.), <hi
                                rend="italic">Ἀββᾶ Ἰσαὰκ τοῦ Σύρου. Λόγοι ἀσκητικοί. Κριτικὴ
                                ἔκδοσι</hi> (Ἅγιον Ὄρος: Ἱερὰ Μονὴ Ἰβήρων, 2012), 65-67. For a brief
                            but comprehensive account of the state of the art on this topic, see S.
                            Chialà, <hi rend="italic">Dall’ascesi eremitica alla misericordia
                                infinita. Ricerche su Isacco di Ninive e la sua fortuna</hi>
                            (Firenze: Leo S. Olschki, 2002), 334-338, with further relevant
                            bibliography. For the first part of the four-part collection of Isaac
                            Arabus transmitted by the MS <hi rend="italic">Vat. syr 198</hi> (once
                                <hi rend="italic">Nitrensis 20</hi>, beginning of the 16<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> c.), see id., "The Arabic Version of
                            Saint Isaac the Syrian. A Channel of Transmission of Syriac Literature,"
                            in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Patristics
                                Conference ‘Saint Isaac the Syrian and His Spiritual Legacy’ Held at
                                the Sts Cyril and Methodius Institute for Postgraduate Studies
                                (Moscow, October 10-11, 2013)</hi>, ed. H. Alfeyev (Yonkers [NY]: St
                            Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2015), 59–67.</p></note> This makes the
                    recognition of the single texts that are transmitted in the so far identified
                    manuscripts of Isaac Arabus urgent. This article aims to make a first step
                    towards this direction: the identification of the single homilies or pieces of
                    homilies transmitted under the name of Isaac of Nineveh in the MS <hi
                        rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The manuscript is available at <ref
                                target="https://www.numistral.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b102352175"
                                >https://www.numistral.fr/ark:/12148/btv1b102352175</ref>.</p></note>
                    and the creation of a table of correspondences between this (unedited) Arabic
                    collection, the edited Syriac source text, and the edited Greek version of
                        Isaac.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Pataridze extended the list with correspondences, which reportedly has
                            been made by Géhin and Pirard: T. Pataridze, "Les discours ascétiques
                            d’Isaac de Ninive. Étude de la tradition géorgienne et de ses rapports
                            avec les autres versions" (<hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 124:1&amp;2
                            [2011]), 29, n. 8. Her compilation, though, does not recognize that some
                            Arabic homilies are in fact the fusion of more than one homily of Isaac
                            – as the survey in this article aims at showing – and identifies only
                            one out of three homilies of John of Dalyatha. Based on Pataridze’s
                            list, Alexander Treiger, when providing the table of contents of the MS
                                <hi rend="italic">Sinai ar. 549</hi> (10<hi rend="superscript"
                                >th</hi> c.), in which homilies of Isaac of Nineveh are included,
                            gives the correspondences between these homilies (or extracts of
                            homilies) and the MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi>: A. Treiger, "Syro-Arabic Translations in
                            Abbasid Palestine: The Case of John of Apamea’s Letter of Stillness
                            (Sinai Ar. 549)," in
                            (<hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient </hi>39
                            [2014]), 111; 113-22.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The Strasbourg manuscript is a very important witness to the Arabic transmission
                    of Isaac, for it is the earliest known manuscript that bears Isaac’s homilies in
                    Arabic (dated to 885/886, s. <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"> Another ancient witness of
                            Isaac Arabus is a collection of maxims chosen and translated by Ibn
                            aṣ-Ṣalt (end of 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-beginning of 10<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> c.). For relevant bibliography see
                            Chialà,
                            <hi rend="italic">Dall’ascesi eremitica, </hi>334-35.</p></note>
                    For this reason and in order to have a solid ground to start off with collations
                    of the Syriac, Arabic and Greek manuscripts, it is important to know which texts
                    of Isaac are transmitted in this very ancient witness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> The aim of the present article
                            is not to ascertain whether the Arabic translation was made on the basis
                            of a Syriac or a Greek <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>. For the last
                            hypothesis see S. Brock, "Syriac into Greek at Mar Saba: The Translation
                            of St. Isaac the Syrian," in <hi rend="italic">Sabaite Ηeritage in the
                                Orthodox Church from the Fifth Century to the Present</hi>, ed. J.
                            Patrich (Leuven: Peeters, 2001), 207. According to the soundings of
                            Pataridze, the Arabic translation of the Strasbourg manuscript was made
                            undoubtedly from a Syriac prototype belonging to the West Syriac
                            tradition of Isaac: see her remarks, substantiated by many examples, in
                            T. Pataridze, "Les discours ascétiques," 32-54; ead., "Isaac from the
                            Monastery of Mar Saba. The History of the Origin of the Multiple
                            Translations of St Isaac the Syrian’s Work and Their Distribution in the
                            Holy Lavra," in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International
                                Patristics Conference ‘Saint Isaac the Syrian and His Spiritual
                                Legacy’ Held at the Sts Cyril and Methodius Institute for
                                Postgraduate Studies (Moscow, October 10-11, 2013)</hi>, ed. H.
                            Alfeyev (Yonkers [NY]: St Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2015),
                        42-50.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The homilies of Isaac in this manuscript are still unedited. The manuscript
                    became well known as a witness to Isaac Arabus after its first description by
                    Oestrup in 1897.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Oestrup mentions that the collection of Isaac in this manuscript has
                            “eine Reihe von grösseren und kleineren Abschnitten, von welchen die
                            meisten sich in dem von Chabot…gegebenen Verzeichnis der Werke Isaacs
                            wiederfinden”: J. Oestrup, "Über zwei arabische Codices Sinaitici der
                            Straßburger Universitäts- und Landesbibliothek" (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 51:3
                            [1897]), 457. The catalogue of the Strasbourg manuscript essentially
                            relies on Oestrup: E. Wickersheimer, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue général
                                des manuscrits des bibliothèques publiques de France</hi>, Vol. 47,
                                <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg</hi> (Paris: Librairie Plon, 1923),
                            747-8.</p></note> Afterwards, it attracted the attention of several
                    scholars (s. <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>) but nobody described precisely the
                    content of Isaac’s works.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The collection of Isaac’s homilies in the manuscript occupies ff. 81v-148v. The
                    origin of the Arabic translation could be traced back to the Melchite monastery
                    of Mar Saba, where the manuscript was copied and where a fervid multilingual
                    interchange and translation movement took place, permitted by the presence of
                    speakers of Syriac, Greek, Arabic, and Georgian, and by the wide circulation of
                    manuscripts in these languages.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For an instructive account on this <hi
                                rend="italic">milieu</hi>, see T. Pataridze, "Christian Literature
                            in Arabic in the Early Islamic Period (8th-10th c.): The Circulation of
                            Texts and Ideas between the Greek, Syriac, Arabic, and Georgian
                            Communities," (<hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 132, 1&amp;2 [2019]),
                            especially 200-8, with further relevant bibliography. </p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>The Manuscript: Its Provenance, Its Palaeographical Description, and Its
                    Copyist</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">According to the MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg
                        4226</hi>’s colophon<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Pet. Ar. N.S. 263</hi>, fol. 5v. </p></note> (s. <hi
                        rend="italic">infra</hi>), the manuscript was copied in 885/886 in the
                    well-known monastery of Mar Saba in Southern Palestine under the commission of
                    anbā Isḥāq of the monastery of Saint Catherine in Sinai.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">
                            I. Kračkovskij, "Novozavjetnyj apokrif v
                            arabskoj rukopisi 885-886 goda po R. Hr." (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Vizantijskij Vremennik</hi> 14 [1909]), 248. The manuscript can be
                            traced back to Sinai also due to an indication of its ancient Sinaitic
                            signature 'βιβλίον λθ' (fol. 2v), and a note of possession by Germanos,
                            a Sinai’s bishop in the 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> cent. (fol.
                            7v-8v): see A. Binggeli, "Les trois David, copistes arabes de
                            Palestine," in <hi rend="italic">Manuscripta Graeca et Orientalia.
                                Mélanges monastiques et patristiques en l'honneur de Paul
                            Géhin</hi>, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 243, eds. A. Binggeli, A.
                            Boud'hors and M. Cassin (Leuven: Peeters, 2016), 82.</p></note> The
                    Strasbourg’s <hi rend="italic">codex</hi> bears the distinctive codicological
                    and paleographical characteristics which were developed from the 8<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> c. onwards in the Arabic Christian production
                    from Palestine to Sinai.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See A. D’Ottone, "Arabic Palaeography,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Comparative Oriental Manuscript Studies. An
                                Introduction</hi> (s.l.: s.e., 2015), 271 (with relevant
                            bibliography).</p></note> Fleischer described its script as totally
                    corresponding with that of another Christian Arabic manuscript, a palimpsest
                    formerly written in Greek, the MS <hi rend="italic">Leipzig gr. 2</hi> (once <hi
                        rend="italic">Codex Rescriptus Tischendorf 2</hi>).<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> H. Fleischer, "Beschreibung
                            der von Prof. Tischendorf im Jahre 1853 aus dem Morgenlange
                            zurückgebrachten christlich-arabischen Handschriften" (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 8
                            [1854]), 587. The catalogue reference for this MS is in V. Gardthausen,
                                <hi rend="italic">Katalog der Handschriften der
                                Universitäts-Bibliothek zu Leipzig</hi>, Vol. 3, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Die griechischen Handschriften</hi> (Leipzig: Harrassowitz 1898),
                            4. On this manuscript see also M. van Esbroeck, "Le codex rescriptus
                            Tischendorf 2 à Leipzig et Cyrille de Scythopolis en version arabe," in
                                <hi rend="italic">Actes du deuxième Congrès international d’études
                                arabes chrétiennes</hi>, ed. S. Khalil Samir (Rome: Pontificium
                            Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1986), 81-91.</p></note> According to
                    the German scholar, the script is a Naskh with ancient characteristics, very
                    similar to Kufic, regarding the shape of the individual letters, but also
                    divergent from it, in regard to the distance between certain letters within the
                    same word.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> H.
                            Fleischer, "Über einen griechisch-arabischen Codex rescriptus der
                            Leipziger Universitäts-Bibliothek" (<hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der
                                Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 1 [1847]), 159-160.
                            This assertion corresponds with the short one in Oestrup, "Über zwei
                            arabische Codices", 454: "ein altertümliches, noch sehr steifes, aber
                            ganz reines Neschi".</p></note> A very accurate description of the form
                    of single letters is given by Heffening,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> W. Heffening, "Die griechische
                            Ephraem-Paraenesis gegen das Lachen in arabischer Übersetzung" (<hi
                                rend="italic">Oriens christianus</hi> 3:2 [1927]), 97-9. Concerning
                            the writing, the usage of small diacritical signs underneath the letters
                            ح, ص, ع is peculiar. According to I. Kračkovskij, "Novozavjetnyj apokrif
                            v arabskoj rukopisi 885-886 goda po R. Hr." (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Vizantijskij Vremennik</hi> 14 [1909]), 249 and Heffening, "Die
                            griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis," 99, they could be small versions of the
                            same letters, a practice which is confirmed by the comparison with the
                            Arabic tradition: cf. W. Wright, <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of the
                                Arabic Language</hi>, Vol. 1 (Beirut: Librairie du Liban, 1974<hi
                                rend="superscript">3</hi>), 4. In contrast to this, Oestrup observed
                            that only under ص there is such a small diacritical sign, which he
                            interpreted as the initial م of the word مهمل: Oestrup, "Über zwei
                            arabische Codices," 454.</p></note> who avoids systematically the terms
                        <hi rend="italic">nasḫī</hi> or <hi rend="italic">kūfī</hi>, umbrella terms
                    which in Arabic paleography does not allow an effective description of
                        scripts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">
                            For a brief but useful discussion of this issue, see D’Ottone, "Arabic
                            Palaeography," 273-6. However, in the field of Christian Arabic the
                            terms 'Naskh' and 'Kufic' (with their sub-variants such as 'pre-' or
                            'old') have become widespread: see for example A. Atiya, "The monastery
                            of St. Catherine and the Mount Sinai expedition" (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Proceedings of the American Philosophy Society</hi> 96 [1952]),
                            578-586; id., "Codex Arabicus (Sinai Arabic Ms. No. 514)," in <hi
                                rend="italic">Homage to a Bookman: Essays on Manuscripts, Books and
                                Printing Written for Hans P. Kraus on his 60th Birthday</hi>, ed. H.
                            Lehmann-Haupt (Gebr. Mann Verlag: Berlin, 1967), 75-87.</p></note>
                    Nowadays, the hand of the copyist of the Strasbourg manuscript is well known: it
                    belongs to a <hi rend="italic">warrāq</hi> of the monastery of Mar Saba, David
                    Antony of Baghdad.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> On this copyist and the other known manuscripts
                            copied by him, see Kračkovskij, "Novozavjetnyj apokrif,", 247, n. 5,
                            with further reference to A. Mai; Heffening, "Die griechische
                            Ephraem-Paraenesis," 99-103; S. Griffith, <hi rend="italic">Arabic
                                Christianity in the Monasteries of Ninth-Century Palestine</hi>
                            (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1992).</p></note> Recently, Hjälm has described
                    very carefully the main features of Antony’s script and has proposed the label
                    'New Style script', a precursor of the cursive script that developed especially
                    in the 10<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17"
                        n="17"><p rend="footnote text"> M. Hjälm, "A Paleographical Study of Early
                            Christian Arabic Manuscripts" (<hi rend="italic">Collectanea Christiana
                                Orientalia</hi> 17 [2020]), 64-8. A. D’Ottone kindly informed us
                            that she will publish in 2021 an article on the special features of
                            Antony’s hand, see A. D’Ottone Rambach, "Sharing the written space:
                            Contact and Interaction Between Arabic and Other Scripts," in <hi
                                rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Symposium: Navigating
                                Language in the Early Islamic World (The Marco Institute for
                                Medieval and Renaissance Studies, The University of Tennessee,
                                Knoxville, 6-7 April 2018)</hi>, eds. A. Borrut and A.V. Vacca
                            (Brepols: Turnhout 2021 [forthcoming]).</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>The MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi> and Its <hi rend="italic"
                        >Disiecta Membra</hi>: The Story of a Reconstructed Arabic Manuscript</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi> is
                    mutilated in its initial and final parts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18"
                        n="18"><p rend="footnote text"> For the story of its arrival at Strasbourg
                            in 1895, see Oestrup, "Über zwei arabische Codices," 453, n.
                        4.</p></note> The first quire, apparently starting at f. 3r, has only 7
                    leaves - almost all the other quires of the manuscript have 8 - being thus
                    deprived of the first folio, given that the actual f. 3r clearly does not
                    present the beginning of a text. As already suggested by Heffening, ff. 1-2 have
                    been added at the beginning of the manuscript.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19"
                        n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> Heffening, "Die griechische
                            Ephraem-Paraenesis," 95-6, n. 2.</p></note> The manuscript stops
                    abruptly at f. 215v. Therefore, in its present form it preserves neither the end
                    of the last text(s) copied nor a colophon. The first and last leaves pertaining
                    to this manuscript and completing it have been identified by scholars in the
                    last century.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"> A
                            short account of the story of the reconstitution of the manuscript is
                            given in M. van Esbroeck, "Un feuillet oublié du codex arabe Or. 4226 à
                            Strasbourg" (<hi rend="italic">Analecta Bollandiana</hi> 96 [1978]), on
                            whom we rely for some information punctually signalled in the text. Our
                            intent is to give a comprehensive account of the scholarly efforts that
                            finally brought to the finding of all the parts of the MS <hi
                                rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In 1927 Heffening, following a suggestion of Baumstark,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Baumstark suggested to
                            Heffening that eight folios found in Hiersemann’s collection should
                            immediately follow f. 215v, where the manuscript currently ends, see
                            Heffening, "Die griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis," 94-5.</p></note>
                    discovered a parchment fragment in the catalogue of Hiersemann,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> In Hiersemann’s
                            catalogue nr. 565 (1926), the manuscript is described under the number
                            411. For further references on this fragment, see Heffening, "Die
                            griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis," 94, n. 1.</p></note> now preserved in
                        Birmingham,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Van Esbroeck cites the references for this fragment (Birmingham,
                            University’s Cadbury Research Library, Mingana collection, MS <hi
                                rend="italic">Arabicus Christianus 93</hi>: Esbroeck, "Un feuillet
                            oublié," 383; the Mingana collection has been now relocated from the
                            Selly Oak College, where it was preserved until 2010, to the University
                            campus. Van Esbroeck gives also the reference for the catalogue: ibid.,
                            383, n. 7. Garitte mentioned that Heffening announced in 1936 the
                            passage of the fragment to the Mingana collection: G. Garitte, "Homélie
                            d'Ephrem "Sur la Mort et le Diable". Version géorgienne et version
                            arabe" (<hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 82 [1969]), 125, n.
                        6.</p></note> which corresponded to the immediate continuation of the MS <hi
                        rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi>. He demonstrated with solid
                    paleographical, codicological and textual arguments that the fragment
                    constituted the 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> quire of the manuscript;
                    moreover, he recognized that this 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> quire was not
                    the concluding one, which should contain the final part of the text and the
                        colophon.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Heffening, "Die griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis," 94-5. One of the
                            arguments is that the number of leaves in the manuscript’s quires is
                            eight. This is actually true for all the 27 quires of the actual
                            manuscript (including also the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> one),
                            except for the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> and the 6<hi
                                rend="superscript">th</hi> one, which count 7 leaves, and not 8. The
                            absence of the last leaf in each quire is indeed strange, also given
                            that there is apparently no textual caesura between these two quires and
                            those which immediately precede and follow. For a more precise
                            codicological description of the whole manuscript, alongside its <hi
                                rend="italic">disiecta membra</hi>, s. Binggeli, "Les trois David,"
                            80-1, and n. 6.</p></note> Heffening supposed that this last quire would
                    be probably less than 8 leaves and assumed that its discovery would have been
                    very unlikely.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Heffening, "Die griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis," 95, n. 1.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In 1853 Tischendorf had brought six parchment leaves from the Orient to Leipzig
                    with other three manuscripts; the leaves were then bought by the British
                        Library.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Fleischer, "Beschreibung," 585, n. 1.</p></note> At the beginning of the
                    following century they ended up, under unknown circumstances, in the National
                    Library of Saint Petersburg, where they were examined and edited by
                        Kračkovskij.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > An extensive study of the fragments is in Kračkovskij, "Novozavjetnyj
                            apokrif".</p></note> Ff. 1r–5v, which are still preserved in Saint
                        Petersburg,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Van Esbroeck cites the references for this fragment (Saint Petersburg,
                            National Library of Russia,
                            MS<hi rend="italic"> Arabicus N.S. 263</hi>; the
                            library was known as “Saltykov-Ščedrin Library” at the time of van
                            Esbroeck’s writing: Esbroeck, "Un feuillet oublié," 383). Van Esbroeck
                            does not give any reference for the catalogue.</p></note> contain the
                    missing final part of the last text of manuscript of Strasbourg and the
                    colophon. It was only to Garitte’s discovery that this textual portion was
                    recognized as pertaining to an Ephremian work and was thus connected to the
                    Hiersemann fragment that Heffening had recognized as containing also an
                    Ephremian text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Garitte, "Homélie d'Ephrem," 126-8. Fleischer identified the fragments
                            as “Schluss einer Legende vom Siege Christi über Tod und Teufel”, some
                            details of which were strictly connected with the apocryphal <hi
                                rend="italic">Gospel of Nicodemus</hi>: Fleischer, "Beschreibung,"
                            587.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The sixth folio of the set of leaves which appeared in Saint Petersburg in the
                    first decades of the 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c. is now preserved in
                        Birmingham.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Van Esbroeck cites the references for this
                            fragment (Birmingham, University’s Cadbury
                            Research Library, Mingana collection, MS <hi rend="italic">Arabicus
                                Christianus Additional 136</hi>): Esbroeck, "Un feuillet oublié,"
                            384. He also gives the reference for the catalogue (ibid., n.
                        2).</p></note> It is written by the same hand as the other five folios but
                    presents the beginning of a text about the struggle of some Christians of
                    Sebaste (in Cilicia) against their bishop Peter in the time of Basil the
                        Great.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Fleischer, "Beschreibung," 587.</p></note> The text, which has a rubric
                    at the top consisting of 11 widely damaged lines, is published in Kračkovskij
                        1913.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"> I.
                            Kračkovskij, "K istorii sevastijskoj eparhii v IV veke" (<hi
                                rend="italic">Hristianskij Vostok</hi> 2 [1913]),
                        154-155.</p></note> This textual portion was recognized also by Garitte as
                    pertaining to the <hi rend="italic">MS Strasbourg 4226</hi>, representing the
                    first lost folio of the first quire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Garitte, "Homélie d'Ephrem," 126-8.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Thus, the once complete manuscript is constituted with the following order by: </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic">Ming. Ar. Chr. Add. 136</hi> (1 folio) +
                    <hi rend="italic">Stras. 4226 </hi>(215 folios) + <hi
                        rend="italic">Ming. Ar. Chr. 93</hi> (8 folios) + <hi rend="italic">Pet. Ar.
                        N.S. 263</hi> (5 folios). </p>
                <p rend="New Normal">Before connecting the Saint Petersburg leaves to the Strasbourg
                    manuscript, scholars, influenced by a note in f. 1r, dated the manuscript to
                        950.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Oestrup, "Über zwei arabische Codices," 453-4; Wickersheimer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Catalogue général</hi>, 747-8.</p></note> This note,
                    though, was written by a different hand than the rest of the manuscript and
                    Heffening rightly argued that it was a later forgery.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"> Heffening, "Die griechische
                            Ephraem-Paraenesis," 96-7.</p></note> The manuscript, according to its
                    colophon (now preserved in Saint Petersburg, f. 5v), is well dated to
                    885/886.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>General Remarks</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">This paper presents the following parts of the Arabic
                    collection of Isaac in the MS <hi rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi>: 1) the
                    initial index of the manuscript where all the titles of Isaac’s homilies are
                    indicated; 2) a description for each homily, encompassing the following pieces
                    of information: title of the homily in the index, title of the homily in the
                    text, incipit and desinit with the relevant correspondences to the Syriac text
                    of Isaac edited by Bedjan (indicated as B) and the Greek version of Isaac edited
                    by Pirard (indicated as P), as well as to Khayyat’s edition (indicated as K) for
                    the pieces of homilies written by John of Dalyatha but falsely attributed to
                    Isaac of Nineveh.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> P. Bedjan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Mar Isaacus
                                Ninivita. De perfectione religiosa</hi> (Leipzig: Otto Harrassowitz
                            1909); Pirard, <hi rend="italic">Ἀββᾶ Ἰσαὰκ τοῦ Σύρου</hi>; N. Khayyat
                            (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Jean de Dalyatha. Les homélies I-XV</hi>
                            (Antélias: Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches Orientales; Hadath:
                            Université Antonine, 2007).</p></note> Moreover, at the end of the
                    paper, there is a table of correspondences between the Arabic homilies and the
                    Syriac and the Greek editions. Some homilies (nr. 7, 13, 14, 15, 17, 19, 22) are
                    composed of more than one single homily, and their sub-divisions are precisely
                    indicated.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A few remarks about the conventions adopted here. The rubrication of the titles
                    and the first word(s) of each homily is not indicated. Every homily is counted
                    according to our own system of computing (there is no numbering system in the
                    manuscript), based on the mere succession of the homilies, each of which has a
                    distinctive title. Regarding the orthography, we have decided to always indicate
                    the diacritical dots above <hi rend="italic">tāʾ marbūṭa</hi>, even if they are
                    never noted in the manuscript. As in the
                    manuscript,<hi rend="italic"> hamza</hi> is never noted,
                    and the preposition <hi rend="italic">ʿalā</hi> is written always with final <hi
                        rend="italic">yāʾ</hi>. Whenever <hi rend="italic">ḍamma</hi> is noted in
                    the manuscript, this is also reproduced in our edition. The diacritical signs
                    underneath the letters <hi rend="italic">ʿayn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ḥāʾ</hi>,
                    and <hi rend="italic">ṣād</hi> are never reproduced.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text"> See n. 14.</p></note> The
                    orthographic variations of the name of Isaac, some of which could be a result of
                    orthographic Syriac influence as well as of phonetic realisation, have been
                    reproduced as they appear. The only form attested in the index is <foreign xml:lang="ar">مار سحق</foreign>, whereas in
                    the titles of the homilies in the text we find the following forms: <foreign xml:lang="ar">مار اسحق</foreign> (nine times
                    in hom. 4, 6, 7, 14, 15, 18, 21, 22, 26), <foreign xml:lang="ar">ماري سحق</foreign> (three
                    times in hom. 1, 3, 16), <foreign xml:lang="ar">مار سحق</foreign> (two times in hom. 12, 13), and <foreign xml:lang="ar">ماري اسحق</foreign> (once in
                    hom. 18). </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Regarding the punctuation, we have decided not to reproduce in every detail the
                    usage of points and rosettes which distinguish respectively one sentence from
                    the other, and the titles from the texts. In the description for each homily,
                    rosettes are never written, while points are present only occasionally.
                    Corrections of the transmitted text are directly written in the main text, and a
                    footnote signals the form attested in the manuscript. Regarding the titles in
                    the index, conjectures of words in a now cut off part of the manuscript’s folio
                    are indicated with &lt; &gt;, while illegible text is written in [ ]. These
                    conjectures are made on the basis of the titles in the main text. Some
                    linguistic observations on specific morpho-syntactical phaenomena are indicated
                    in the footnotes.</p>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.5" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Index (ff. 1v,14–2r,11)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">من قول مار سحق القديس من الميمرالاول علي الابتعاد<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ايضا من الميمر الثاني كلام مختار<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر الثالث &gt;علي&lt; الحب<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر الرابع<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر [الخامس]<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا [من] &gt;الميمر&lt; السادس<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا كلام ملتقط من قول مار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">[وايضا من قول مار سحق امور نافعة]<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وراس ايضا لمار سحق يعلم فيه بماذا ينتفع الانسان في قلبه بتقربه الي الله<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر يعلم فيه بماذا تحفظ جمال ]الرهبانية[<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق علي انه لا ينبغي لعبد الله الذي قد تمسكن من الدنيا
                        وخرج في طلبه<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ومسايل له ايضا وجواباتها<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا لمار سحق كلام مختار<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">راس اخر<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ورسالة له لمار سحق الي اخ كان يحب السُكوت<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وراس لمار سحق يعلم فيه ان التجربة تعلم كل<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وراس اخر ايضا لمار سحق علي الحب<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وراس اخر لمار سحق مختار من قوله<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق القديس<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق<foreign xml:lang="syr">>܀</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وايضاو من قول مار سحق القديس علي الجهتين التي بمعرفة اتعلمت تحقيق الذي ينبغا
                        لها ان تقرا كل ايام حياتك فيها<foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.6" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Basmala (f. 81v,4)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">بسم المسيح منير<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">متير</foreign> ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">انفسنا ومهدي عقولنا</foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">܀</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.7" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 1 (ff.
                            81v,4–83r,11)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with
                        the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 1:1–10)
                        and in Pirard’s edition (P 1:213–224). The Arabic title is more elaborated
                        than the Syriac one (B 1:1:7). The beginning of the Arabic text corresponds
                        with the very beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the
                        Arabic text does not correspond with the end of the Syriac and the Greek
                        texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">من قول مار سحق القديس من
                        الميمر الاول علي الابتعاد</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 81v,4–6):<foreign xml:lang="ar"> هذا قول ماري
                        سحق القديس قاله علي تدبير الرهبانية والابتعاد من العالم كلام مختار من الميمر
                        الاول</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 81v,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">مخافة الله هي راس الصلاح</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 1:1:8 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܚܠܬ ܐܠܗܐ: ܪܫܐ ܗܝ
                            ܕܡܝܬܪܘܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 1:213:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὁ φόβος τοῦ Θεοῦ, ἀρχὴ τῆς ἀρετῆς</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 83r,10–11): <foreign xml:lang="ar">هولا الذي بهم دُعيت ليسوع المسيح منجل الاعمال الصالحة</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 1:10:17
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܢܝܢ ܕܒܗܝܢ ܐܬܩܪܝܬ ܒܝܫܘܥܡܫܝܚܐ </foreign>[sic]<foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܥܒܕ̈ܐ ܛܒ̈ܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 1:224:228 <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐν αἷς ἐκλήθης ὑπὸ τοῦ Κυρίου ἡμῶν Ἰησοῦ Χριστοῦ εἰς τὰ ἀγαθὰ
                        ἔργα</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.8" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 2 (ff. 83r,11–84v,11)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with
                        the 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 2:11–20)
                        and in Pirard’s edition (P 2:225–236). The Arabic title corresponds with the
                        Syriac one (B 2:11:1). The beginning of the Arabic text corresponds with the
                        very beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text
                        does not correspond with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: ايضا من الميمر الثاني كلام
                        مختار </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 83r,11): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الميمر الثاني</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 83r,12): <foreign xml:lang="ar">شكر الذي ياخذ يحرك للذي يُعطي</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 2:11:1 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܘܒܠܛܝܒܘܬܐ ܕܢܣܘܒܐ ܡܓܪܓ
                        ܠܝܗܘܒܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 2:225:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἡ εὐχαριστία τοῦ λαμβάνοντος, ἐρεθίζει τὸν διδόντα</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 84v,10–11): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ان كان هادي ·· وهذا مُلتقط من كُتُب كثيرة</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 2:20:6
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܫܠܐ ܘܦܪܘܫ: ܚܠܦ ܟܬܒ̈ܐ ܣܓܝ̈ܐܐ </foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 2:236:231 <foreign xml:lang="gr">ἐὰν ἡσυχάζῃ καὶ ἔστιν ἀφωρισμένος, ἀντὶ πολλῶν βιβλίων</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.9" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 3 (ff. 84v,11–87r,2)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with
                        the 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 3:20–40)
                        and in Pirard’s edition (P 3:237–259). The Arabic title almost corresponds
                        with the Syriac one (B 3:20:12). The beginning of the Arabic text does not
                        correspond with the very beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The
                        end of the Arabic text does not correspond with the end of the Syriac and
                        the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر الثالث &lt;علي&gt; [الحب]</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 84v,11): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الميمر الثالث لماري سحق</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 84v,12): <foreign xml:lang="ar">لا تبدل حب قريبك بحب الاشيا</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 3:30:21 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܬܚܠܦ ܚܘܒܐ ܕܩܪܝܒܟ ܒܚܘܒܐ
                        ܕܨܒ̈ܘܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 3:249:246-247 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Μὴ ἀλλάξῃς τὴν ἀγάπην τοῦ ἀδελφοῦ σου ἀγάπῃ τινὸς τῶν
                        πραγμάτων</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 87r,2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ومنجل ذلك اساميهم مكتوبة في سفر الحياة الي مجي ربنا يسوع
                        المسيح</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 3:39:3-4 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܐ ܩܠܝܠ ܡܢ ܣܓܝ ܪܫܝܡܝܢ
                        ܫܡܗܝ̈ܗܘܢ ܒܣܦܪܐ ܕܚܝ̈ܐ: ܥܕܡܐ ܠܡܐܬܝܬܗ ܕܡܪܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 3:258:445-446 <foreign xml:lang="gr">ὧν τὰ ὀνόματα γέγραπται ἐν βίβλῳ ζωῆς μέχρι τῆς παρουσίας τοῦ
                        Κυρίου</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.10" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 4 (ff. 87r,3–90v,6-7)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 4<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 4:40–60) and in Pirard’s edition
                        (P 3: 260–281). The Arabic title almost corresponds with the Syriac one (B
                        4:40:11). The beginning of the Arabic text corresponds with the very
                        beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text
                        almost corresponds with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر الرابع</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 87r,3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الميمر الرابع لمار اسحق </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 87r,4): <foreign xml:lang="ar">النفس التي تحب الله في الله هو نياحها وحده فقط</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 4:40:12 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܦܫܐ ܕܠܐܠܗܐ ܡܚܒܐ: ܒܐܠܗܐ ܗܘ
                        ܒܠܚܘܕ ܢܘܚܗ̇</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 4:260:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἡ ψυχὴ ἡ τὸν Θεὸν ἀγαπῶσα, ἐν τῷ Θεῷ καὶ μόνῳ τὴν ἀνάπαυσιν
                        κέκτηται</foreign></p>
                    <p style="text-align: left;">Desinit (f. 90v,6-7):
                        وينال خير كثير من الله الذي له السُبح والكرامة <lb/>B 4:60:5-7 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܕܪܟ
                            ܠܗܘ ܡܕܡ ܕܡܛܠܬܗ ܐܕܪܟܢ ܡܫܝܚܐ</foreign>
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">. </foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܠܗ
                            ܘܠܐܒܘܗܝ ܘܠܪܘܚܐ ܕܩܘܕܫܐ</foreign>
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">: </foreign><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܒܚܐ
                            ܘܩܘܠܣܐ</foreign>
                        <lb/>P 4:281:449-451 <foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ καταλαβόντος ἐκεῖνο τὸ πρᾶγμα δι’ ὃ ἐπεδήμησεν ὁ
                        Χριστός, ᾧ ἡ δόξα σὺν τῷ Πατρὶ καὶ τῷ ἁγίῳ Πνεύματι</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.11" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 5 (ff. 90v,7–92v,14)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 5<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 5:60–80) and in Pirard’s edition
                        (P 5:282–306). The Arabic title corresponds with the Syriac one (B 5
                        :60:10). The beginning of the Arabic text corresponds with the very
                        beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text does
                        not correspond with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من الميمر [الخامس]</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 90v,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الميمر الخامس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 90v,8): <foreign xml:lang="ar">قد اكثر الله الكرامة للانسان بالتعليم المُضعف الذي اعطاه</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 5:60:11-12 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܣܓܝ ܐܠܗܐ ܐܝܩܪܐ ܠܒܪܢܫܐ:
                        ܒܝܘܠܦܢܐ ܥܦܝܦܐ ܕܝܗܒ ܠܗ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 5:282:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Πολλὴν ὁ Θεὸς δέδωκε τοῖς ἀνθρώποις τὴν τιμὴν τῇ διπλῇ
                        μαθήσει</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 92v,13-14): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وكم تُرا اقدر ان اصف او احصي او اخبر عن حب</foreign><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"> Without
                                diacritical point under <hi rend="italic">bāʾ</hi>.</p></note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar">الملايكة لنا </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 5:67:6-7 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܟܡܐ ܐܝܬ ܠܝ ܠܡܡܢܐ: ܥܠ
                        ܚܘܒܗܘܢ ܕܡܠܐܟ̈ܐ ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ ܕܠܘܬ ܓܢܣܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 5:290:153-154 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Καὶ τί δεῖ τὰ πολλὰ καταριθμεῖν τὴν πρὸς ἡμᾶς τῶν ἁγίων
                        ἀγγέλων ἀγάπησιν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.12" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 6 (ff. 92v,15–96r,18)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 6<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition (B 6:81–99) and in Pirard’s edition
                        (P 6:307–326). The Arabic title almost corresponds with the Syriac one (B
                        6:81:1). The beginning of the Arabic text does not correspond with the very
                        beginning of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text
                        corresponds with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا [من] &lt;الميمر&gt; السادس </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 92v,15): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الميمر السادس لمار اسحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 92v,16-17): <foreign xml:lang="ar">في ثلثة</foreign> [sic] <foreign xml:lang="ar">اشكال التي بها تتقرب كل نفس ناطقة الي
                        الله</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 6:81:7-8 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܠܬܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܐܣܟܡ̈ܐ: ܕܒܗܘܢ
                        ܡܬܩܪܒܐ ܟܠ ܢܦܫܐ ܡܠܝܠܬܐ ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 6:307:8-9 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Τρεῖς τρόποι εἰσὶ δι’ ὧν πᾶσα λογικὴ ψυχὴ τῷ Θεῷ προσεγγίσαι
                        δύναται</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 96r,17-18): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الذي له القوة والقدرة</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"> Written without the two
                                diacritical points on <hi rend="italic">qāf</hi> and with a point on
                                <hi rend="italic">dāl</hi>.</p></note><foreign xml:lang="ar"> والملك والسُبح والكرامة
                        الي الابد امين</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 6:99:1-3 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܠܗ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܘܐܘܚܕܢܐ ܘܣܓܕܬܐ
                        ܘܪܘܡܪܡܐ: ܠܥܠܡ ܥܠܡܝܢ. ܐܡܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 6:326:403 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Αὐτῷ ἡ δόξα καὶ τὸ κράτος εἰς τοὺς αἰῶνας, ἀμήν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.13" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7 (ff. 96v-102v)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The Arabic title is not present in the Syriac
                        original. It hints at a collection of mixed homilies, the most of which are
                        composed by pieces of several different Syriac sermons by Isaac and John of
                        Dalyatha. In the Arabic manuscript there is a system of distinction between
                        different homilies through the usage of separating flowers and of
                        rubrication of the first word(s) of each homily. We have indicated each
                        homily of this collection with a letter of the Latin alphabet after the
                        number 7.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا كلام ملتقط من قول مار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 96v,1): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا كلام ملتقط من قول مار اسحق</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.14" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7a (ff. 96v,2-97v,9)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">7a contains small passages from five different
                        homilies, which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s
                        edition: B 16:130-133 ▬ P 16:365-368; B 17:34-139 ▬ P 17:369-375; B
                        23:175-177; B 24:177-182; B 53:379-390 ▬ P 44:619-633. Homilies 23 and 24 of
                        Bedjan are not included in the Greek collection published by Pirard. More
                        specifically: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 96v,2-7: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) lines 2-3 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">في السكوت…ينبغي للراهب</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 16:130:15-17 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܙܗܝܪܘܬܐ…
                        ܙܕܩ ܠܗ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 16:365:5-7 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Δεῖ…τὸν νοῦν αὐτοῦ</foreign>); </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">b) lines 3-7 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">الصلاح…كما ان</foreign>) correspond (with omissions) with<lb/>B
                        16:132:2-11 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܡܝܬܖ̈ܬܐ…ܫܪܝܪܐܝܬ ܐܚܝ̈</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 16:366:31—16:367:42 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐν ἀληθείᾳ, ἀδελφοί…τῇ τῶν ἀρετῶν χλόῃ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. f. 96v,7-8 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">سكوت...الاشيا</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 17:139:1-2 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܝܐ...
                            ܨܒ̈ܘܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 17:374:117-17:375:119 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἡ διηνεκὴς ἡσυχία… πραγμάτων</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iii. f. 96v,8-12 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ليس صلاة...انت قايم</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 23:177:2-7 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܝܬ ܨܠܘܬܐ...
                            ܩܐܡ ܐܢܬ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iv. f. 96v,12-f. 97r,3 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">فطوبا...علي الرجا</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 24:179:15—24:182:14 (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                            >ܛܘܒܘܗܝ...ܥܠ
                        ܣܒܪܐ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> v. f. 97r,3-f. 97v,9 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">اذا ما رجعت... اي راحة ولذة لا توصف ولد لي من
                        الصبر</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 53:385:4—53:388:20 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܬܝ
                            ܕܬܦܢܐ...ܐܝܢܐ ܢܝܚܐ ܕܠܐ ܣܟܐ
                            ܐܘܠܕ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 44:626:150—44:631:2 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὅταν στραφῇς…ποίαν ἀνάπαυσιν ἀπλήρωτον ἐγέννησεν</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.15" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7b (ff. 97v,10-98r,7)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 53<hi rend="superscript"
                            >rd</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 44<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 53:379-390 ▬ P 44:619-633). The
                        beginning of the Arabic text does not correspond with the beginning of the
                        Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text corresponds with the
                        end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 97v,10): <foreign xml:lang="ar">كان بعض الابهات ياكُل مرتين في الجمعة</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 53:388:21 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬ ܗܘܐ ܚܕ ܡܢ ܐܒܗ̈ܬܐ:
                        ܕܐܟܠ ܗܘܐ ܬܪܬܝܢ ܙܒܢ̈ܝܢ ܒܫܒܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 44:631:237 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἦν τίς τῶν πατέρων, καὶ ἦν ἐσθίων δεύτερον τῆς ἑβδομάδος</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 98r,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">فشكرت الله علي كثرة نعمته عند الناس والي اي شرف يساوي
                        للذين يطلبونه </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 53:390:2 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܘܕܝܬ ܠܐܠܗܐ: ܕܟܡܐ ܫܦܝܥܐ
                        ܛܝܒܘܬܗ ܠܘܬ ܒܢܝ̈ܢܫܐ: ܘܠܐܝܕܐ ܪܒܘܬܐ ܡܫܘܐ ܠܕܒܥܝܢ ܠܗ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 44:633:264 <foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ ηὐχαρίστησα τῷ Θεῷ ὅτι πόσον ἡ χάρις αὐτοῦ ὑπερεκχεῖται ἐπὶ
                        τὸν ἄνθρωπον καὶ εἰς ποίαν μεγαλωσύνην ἀξιοῖ τοὺς καταδιώκοντας αὐτόν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.16" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7c (ff. 98r,7-99r,11)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 17<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s edition (B 17:134-139 ▬ P
                        17:369:375). The beginning of the Arabic text corresponds with the beginning
                        of the Syriac and the Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text does not
                        correspond with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 98r,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">لا تظن ايه</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> See J. Blau, <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of
                                    Christian Arabic. Based mainly on South-Palestinian texts from
                                    the first millennium</hi>, Vol. 1, Corpus Scriptorum
                                Christianorum Orientalium 267, Subsidia 27, (Louvain: Secrétariat du
                                CorpusSCO, 1966), 78.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الانسان ان في جميع الاعمال عمل ادفع
                        وافضل من عمل السهر</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 17:134:4 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܬܣܒܪ ܠܟ ܐܘ̇ ܒܪܢܫܐ:
                        ܕܐܝܬ ܒܟܠܗܘܢ ܥܡܠ̈ܐ ܕܥܢܘܝ̈ܐ ܕܘܒܪܐ ܕܪܒ ܘܡܝܬܪ ܡܢ ܥܡܠܐ ܕܫܗܪܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 17:369:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Μὴ νομίσῃς, ὦ ἄνθρωπε, ὅτι ἐν πάσῃ τῇ ἐργασίᾳ τῶν μοναχῶν ἔστι
                        διαγωγὴ μείζων τῆς ἀγρυπνίας τῆς νυκτός</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f.99r,12): فان حرك الانسان نفسه بالسخونة وطرح عنه هولا وكلف نفسه
                        قليل حينيذ تقترب اليه النعمة وتحل به قوة اخرا </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 17:138:10 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܕܝܢ ܐܙܝܥ ܐܢܫ ܝܬܗ
                            ܚܡܝܡܐܝܬ ܘܢܦܨ ܫܕܐ ܡܢܗ: ܘܥܨܐ ܩܠܝܠ ܢܦܫܗ: ܡܚܕܐ ܩܪܒܐ ܛܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܝܟ ܕܒܙܒܢ. ܘܐܬܐ
                            ܠܗ ܚܝܠܐ ܐܚܪܢܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 17:374:102 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Καὶ ἐὰν διεγείρῃ ἑαυτὸν μετὰ θερμότητος καὶ ἐκτινάξῃ ἀφ’ ἑαυτοῦ
                        ταῦτα καὶ ἀναγκάσῃ ἑαυτὸν μικρόν, τηνικαῦτα πλησιάζει αὐτῷ ἡ χάρις ὥσπερ ἦν.
                        Καὶ ἔρχεται αὐτῷ ἄλλη δύναμις</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.17" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7d (ff. 99r,12-99v,4)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The extract contained in homily 7d has been
                        identified with a part of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> homily of John
                        of Dalyatha. This extract is not present in Bedjan’s edition but it is
                        attested in the MS Sinai, <hi rend="italic">Syr. 24</hi>, which circulated
                        in the Melchite <hi rend="italic">milieu</hi> of the monastery of Mar Saba,
                        and could have possibly similarities with the Arabic tradition attested in
                        the Strasbourg manuscript.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> On this manuscript, s. G. Kessel, "Sinai syr.
                                24 as an Important Witness to the Reception History of Some Syriac
                                Ascetic Texts," in <hi rend="italic">Sur les pas des Araméens
                                    chrétiens. Mélanges offerts à Alain Desreumaux</hi>, Cahiers
                                d’études syriaques 1, eds. F. Briquel-Chatonnet and M. Debié (Paris:
                                Geuthner, 2010), 207-18.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 99r,12): <foreign xml:lang="ar">قال لي انسان انه جرب انه في ايام تخالط الناس انه ياكُل
                        في اليوم ثلث</foreign> [sic] <foreign xml:lang="ar">خبزات</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">حبزات</foreign> ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">واربعة</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P Index 1:812:241 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Διηγήσατό μοι τίς ἐξ ὧν ἐδοκίμασεν, ὅτι ἐν αἷς ἡμέραις
                        συναναστρέφομαι τισίν, ἐσθίω τρία παξαμάτια ἢ τέσσαρα </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">K 1:112:7 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܪ ܠܝ ܐܢܫ ܡܢ ܢܣܝܢܐ
                            ܕܒܩܢܘܡܗ ܗܟܢܐ. ܕܒܝܘ̈ܡܬܐ ܕܗܘܝܐ ܠܝ ܚܠܝܛܘܬܐ ܥܡ ܐܚܖ̈ܢܐ ܐܟܠ ܐܢܐ ܬܠܬܐ ܘܐܪ̈ܒܥܐ
                            ܩܠܘܖ̈ܐ ܒܝܘܡܐ</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> The passage corresponds with that attested in
                                MS <hi rend="italic">Sinai
                                Syr</hi>.<hi rend="italic"> 24</hi>, f.
                                168vb,25.</p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 99v,4): <foreign xml:lang="ar">واكل خُبزه وحده ويكون خلطته</foreign><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">حلطته</foreign> ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">مع
                        الله وحده في كل ساعة </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P Index 1:812:259 <foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ ἐσθίων μόνος τὸν ἑαυτοῦ ἄρτον, ὅτι διαπαντὸς μετὰ τοῦ
                        Θεοῦ διαλέγεται</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">K 1:112:21 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܟܠ ܠܚܡܗ ܒܠܚܘܕܘܗܝ. ܕܥܡ
                        ܚܕ ܟܠܫܥ ܡܬܥܢܐ</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> The passage corresponds with that attested in
                                MS <hi rend="italic">Sinai Syr. 24</hi>, f. 169rb,14.</p></note></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.18" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7e (ff. 99v,4-100v,18)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">7e contains small passages from five different
                        homilies, which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s
                        editions: B 24:177-182; B 38:177-182 ▬ P 30:508-514; B 39:182-187 ▬ P
                        31:515-524; B 46:330-335 ▬ P 38:561-565; B 50:343-359 ▬ P 41:574-594. Homily
                        24 of Bedjan’s edition is not included in the Greek collection published by
                        Pirard. More specifically:</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. ff. 99v,4-100r,17: It corresponds to the 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>
                        homily of Bedjan’s edition. Although the beginning of the Arabic text
                        corresponds with the beginning of the Syriac text, the last four Arabic
                        words may be a paraphrase of the whole or part of the last section of the
                        Syriac sermon. The textual part from <foreign xml:lang="ar">بشي</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="ar">المسيح</foreign> does not seem to
                        correspond exactly to a specific textual string of the Syriac text but the
                        expression<foreign xml:lang="ar">بشي غريب</foreign> may be a paraphrase of <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܕܕܠܐ ܗܘܠ̈ܐ ܗܘ ܥܢܝܢܟ</foreign> at
                        line 8 and the word <foreign xml:lang="ar">بعون</foreign> may correspond to the word <foreign  xml:lang="syr">ܡܥܕܪܢܐ</foreign> at line 12.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 99v,4): <foreign xml:lang="ar">قال مار اسحق عن شيخ من القديسين قال ربما مرار كثيرة في
                        اعراض النهار لو اُعطي الراهب جميع ملك الارض لم يحب ان يخرج من قليته ولا يكلم
                        احد</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 24:177:12 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܙܒ̈ܢܝܢ ܣܓܝ̈ܐܢ ܓܕܫ ܡܨܥܬ
                            ܫܥ̈ܐ ܕܐܝܡܡܐ: ܕܐܢ ܡܠܟܘܬܐ ܕܐܪܥܐ ܬܬܠ ܠܐܚܐ: ܠܐ ܡܬܛܦܝܣ ܒܫܥܬܐ ܗܝ ܕܢܦܘܩ ܡܢ
                            ܩܠܝܬܗ: ܘܠܐ ܕܢܩܘܫ ܠܗ ܐܢܫ</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 100r,17): <foreign xml:lang="ar">فانه لا يستطيع العدوا</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                            n="47"><p rend="footnote text"> The word must be in plural, but this
                                form does not correspond to the attested forms for the plural of <hi
                                    rend="italic">ʿadūw</hi> in vocabularies.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">يدنوا الي
                        قلبك بشي غريب بعون المسيح</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 24:182:8: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܡܕܡ ܚܘܫܒܐ ܡܫܟܪܐ: ܠܠܒܟ
                        ܠܐ ܩܪܒ</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 100r,18-100v,1 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">صغر النفس...وقلة الامانة</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 38:291:2-5 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܙܥܘܪܘܬ
                        ܢܦܫܐ</foreign>...<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܠܐ ܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 30:508:1-5 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Σημεῖον ἐστὶ…τῆς ἀπιστίας</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iii. f. 100v,1-3 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">كل ما اديت...القديسين بالتعب</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 39:298:1-3 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܐܘܪܚܐ
                        ܕܡܪܕܝܬܟ</foreign>...<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܕܘܖ̈ܟܬܐ ܠܐܝ̈ܬܐ
                            ܕܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign> ) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 31:517:45-47 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὃταν γὰρ εὕρῃς…ὑπὸ τῶν μοχθηρῶν ποδῶν τῶν ἁγίων</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iv. f. 100v,3-4 <foreign xml:lang="ar">فان كان احد تقرب الي الله بلا بلايا·· اتشبه به انت</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 38:291:7-8 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܐܝܬ ܕܒܠܥܕ ܐܘ̈ܠܨܢܐ
                        ܐܬܩܪܒ ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ: ܐܦ ܐܢܬ ܐܬܕܡܐ ܒܗ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 30:508:7-8 <foreign xml:lang="ar">Ἐάν τις ἐκτὸς ἀγώνων καὶ κινδύνων καὶ πειρασμῶν τῷ Θεῷ
                        προσήγγισε, καὶ σὺ αὐτὸν μίμησαι</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> v. f. 100v,4-10: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) lines 4-6 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">اعلم انك كل ما تقدمت...كُثرت عليك</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 39:298:3-6 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܡܐ ܓܝܪ
                        ܕܬܫܬܘܫܛ...ܝܬܝܪ ܬܥܘܠ ܠܢܣ̈ܝܘܢܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 31:517:47-50 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὅσον γὰρ διαβαίνεις…πληθύνονται κατὰ σοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> b) lines 6-10 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">لا تطلب...من الوقعة</foreign>) correspond (with omissions) with</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 39:297:8-21 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܬܒܥܐ...ܡܢ
                        ܓܘ̈ܢܝܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 31:516:26—31:517:44 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Μὴ ζητήσῃς…καὶ τὰς κατηγορίας</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> vi. f. 100v,10-12 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">الذي هو مريضا...الطريق</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 50:344:21—50:345:1 (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܕܟܪܝܗ...ܐܘܪܚܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 41:576:43-45 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">Ὁ τῇ ψυχῇ ἀσθενῶν…τὴν ὁδόν</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> vii. f. 100v,12-14: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) lines 12-13 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">اذا كثر... في السر</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 46:332:11-12 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܬܝ
                        ܕܬܣܓܐ...ܒܟܣܝܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 38:563:52-53 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὅταν πληθυνθῇ…τὴν χάριν τῆς παρακλήσεως</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> b) lines 13-14 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ان حفظت لسانك ياخي تُعطا من الله موهبة</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 46:334:6 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܠܫܢܟ ܬܛܪ ܐܚܝ: ܡܬܝܗܒܐ
                        ܠܟ ܡܢ ܐܠܗܐ ܡܘܗܒܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 38:564:86-87 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐὰν φυλάξῃς τὴν γλῶσσαν σου, ὦ ἀδελφέ, δίδοταί σοι παρὰ τοῦ
                        Θεοῦ ἡ χάρις τῆς κατανύξεως τῆς καρδίας</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.19" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7f (ff. 100v,14-102v,14)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Unlike the previous homilies, 7f is not separated
                        from the preceding homily by means of rubrication. Instead only separating
                        flowers are used. It contains small passages from five different homilies,
                        which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions:
                        B 46:330-335 ▬ P 38:561-565; B 50:343-359 ▬ P 41:574-594; B 64:441-442 ▬ P
                        46:639-641; B 74:507-518 ▬ P 62:735-748. The extracts i and iii actually
                        belong to parts of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> and 6<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> homilies of John of Dalyatha, the first of
                        which has found its way also into the Greek Isaac (see Pirard, p. 801f.).
                        The Syriac text is edited by Khayyat 2007. In ii and v, the same text is
                        translated but with different wording.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 100v,14-16: <foreign xml:lang="ar">قال لي بعض الاخوة اذا ما قابلوا</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Without diacritical point under <hi
                                    rend="italic">bāʾ</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الشياطين انسان يحركوا عليه
                        الاخوة الذين يطاوعوهم لكيما يكونوا لهم اعوان في القتال</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> K 6:184:4-5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܡܪ ܗܘܐ ܬܘܒ. ܕܡܐ
                            ܕܥܒܕܝܢ ܫ̈ܐܕܐ ܥܡ ܐܢܫ ܐܓܘܢܐ܆ ܡܙܝܥܝܢ ܠܐܚ̈ܐ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܡܫܬܡܥܝܢ ܠܗܘܢ ܕܢܗܘܘܢ ܠܗܘܢ
                            ܥܕܪܐ ܒܬܟܬܘܫܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 100v,16-101v,1 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">امشي الي اصدقاك...احتفظ من الشبع</foreign>) corresponds (with
                        omissions) with</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 50:346:18—50:351:1 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘܬ ܖ̈ܚܡܝܟ:
                        ܒܐܣܟܡܐ ܗܠܟ...ܛܪ ܐܦܢ ܡܢ ܣܒܥܘܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 41:578:97—41:584:223 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Πρὸς τοὺς φίλους σου ἐν εὐλαβείᾳ πορεύθητι…κἂν
                        φύλαξον τοῦ μὴ χορτασθῆναι</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iii. f. 101v,1-3: <foreign xml:lang="ar">شاب يصاحب شاب يبكوا عليه الصالحين ·· وشيخ يحب يصاحب الشباب
                        يقتني في نفسه اوجاع نجسة افضل من الشباب النجسين</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> K 1:106:12-14 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܛܠܝܐ ܕܢܩܝܦ ܠܛܠܝܐ܆
                            ܢܕܡܥܘܢ ܥܠܝܗܘܢ ܦܖ̈ܘܫܐ. ܘܐܦ ܣܒܐ ܕܪܚܡ ܢܩܦܐ ܕܛ̈ܠܝܐ܆ ܕܥ ܠܟ ܕܢܕܝܕܝܢ ܚܫ̈ܘܗܝ ܡܢ
                            ܕܛܠ̈ܝܐ ܛܡ̈ܐܐ</foreign>)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> The passage corresponds with that attested in
                                MS <hi rend="italic">Sinai Syr. 24</hi>, f. 167va,17-21.</p></note>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P Index 1:808:152-154 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Νέος νεωτέρῳ ἀκολουθῶν, ποιεῖ τοὺς διακριτικοὺς ἐπ’
                        αὐτοὺς πενθεῖν καὶ κλαίειν. Γέρων δέ, ἀκολουθῶν νεωτέρῳ, δυσωδέστερον τοῦ
                        τῶν νεωτέρων κέκτηται πάθος</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iv. f. 101v,3-14: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) lines 3-10 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ما احسن وافضل حُب القريب...في النفس التي تسكن فيه كل الشرور</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 46:331:3—46:333:20 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܒܝܚ ܘܡܝܬܪ
                        ܚܘܒܐ ܕܩܪܝܒܐ...ܟܠ ܒܝ̈ܫܢ ܡܫܡܠܐ ܒܢܦܫܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 38:561:13-14—38:564:77 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τί ὡραία καὶ ἐπαινετὴ ἡ ἀγάπη τοῦ πλησίον…πᾶσα
                        κακία τελειοῦται ἐν τῇ ψυχῇ τῇ οἰκούσῃ ἐν αὐτῷ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> b) lines 10-14 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">انا اقول ان العالم...بلا خلطة الاوجاع</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 46:332:6-11 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܠܡܐ ܩܪܐ ܐܢܐ...ܒܠܥܕ
                        ܥܢܝܢ ܚܫ̈ܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 38:563:46-51 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τὸν κόσμον καλῶ…χωρὶς τῆς ὁμιλίας τῶν παθῶν</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> v. ff. 101v,14-102r,13 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">كُل عمل تعمله... ابكي عليه</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 50:348:21—50:356:15 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܠ ܥܒܕ ܕܕܠܐ
                        ܚܘܫܒ ܬܥܒܕ...ܒܟܝ ܥܠܘܗܝ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 41:581:158—41:590:369 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἕκαστον ἔργον, ὅ, τι ποιεῖς…κλαῦσον ὑπὲρ αὐτοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> vi. ff. 102r,13-102v,5 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ليس كُل شهوة حسنة...ان اهوا·· وان افعل</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 64:441:15—B 64:442:13 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܘ ܟܠ ܪܓܬܐ
                        ܕܫܦܝܪܬܐ...ܐܦ ܠܡܨܒܐ: ܐܦ ܠܡܣܥܪ</foreign> ) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 46:639:7—46:640:26 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">οὐχὶ γὰρ πᾶσα ἐπιθυμία καλὴ…τὸ θέλειν καὶ τὸ
                        ἐνεργεῖν</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> vii. f. 102v,5-14 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">غاية جميع السعي...وعلي الكُل يريث</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 74:507:5-16 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܟܐ ܕܟܠܗ ܪܗܛܐ...ܘܟܠ
                        ܕܐܝܬ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 62:735:1—62:736:15 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τελειότης παντὸς δρόμου…καὶ ὑπὲρ παντὸς κτίσματος</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.20" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 7g (ff. 102v,14-103r,4)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">7g contains small passages from two different
                        homilies, which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s
                        editions: B 74:507-518 ▬ P 62:735-748; B 77:524-536 ▬ P 63:749-762.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 102v,14-17 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">مسلة</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Read مسألة.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">كيف يقتنا الاتضاع...الي
                        عمل متضع حقير</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 74:508:8-11 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܟܢ ܡܬܩܢܝܐ
                        ܡܟܝܟܘܬܐ...ܠܥܒܕܐ ܨܥܝܪܐ ܘܡܟܐ ܢܪܗܛ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 62:736:32—P 62:737:36 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Καὶ ἠρωτήθη· Πῶς τις δύναται κτήσασθαι τὴν
                        ταπείνωσιν…τοῖς ἔργοις τοῖς ἐλαχίστοις καὶ καθυβρισμένοις</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. f. 102v,17-103r,4 (ايه<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> See n. 41.</p></note><foreign xml:lang="ar"> الانسان الضعيف...
                            والاعتجاب</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> The word is unknown to standard lexica in this
                                form.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">يلحقه الابتعاد من الله</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 77:524:6-13 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܘ̇ ܒܪܢܫܐ
                        ܚܠܫܐ...ܠܡܣܒܖ̈ܢܘܬܐ ܕܝܢ: ܪܚܝܩܘܬܐ ܕܡܢ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 63:749:1-10 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὦ ἄνθρωπε ἐλάχιστε…τῇ οἰήσει δὲ ἀκολουθεῖ τὸ ἀπέχεσθαι ἀπὸ
                        τοῦ Θεοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.21" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 8 (ff. 103r,5—104v,3)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the following homilies in
                        Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions: B 43:315-318 ▬ P 35:540-544. The Arabic
                        title corresponds with the Syriac one. Both the beginning and the end of the
                        Arabic text correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق امور نافعة</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 103r,5): <foreign xml:lang="ar">امور نافعة ممتلية حكمة روح القدس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 103r,6): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الامانة هي باب السراير</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 43:315:2 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ ܐܝܬܝܗ̇: ܬܪܥܐ
                        ܕܐܖ̈ܙܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 35:540:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἡ πίστις ἐστὶν ἡ θύρα τῶν μυστηρίων</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (ff. 104r,18-104v,3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">فاذا نحن بلغنا الي الحب وصلنا الي الله وتمت
                        طريقنا وجزنا الي الجزيرة التي خارج من العالم حيث الاب والابن وروح القدس</foreign>
                            اله<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text"> The
                                word is to be read either <foreign xml:lang="ar">اليه</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="ar">له</foreign>, both of them having the same
                                meaning.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">المجد والقوة ولنا يُساوي لمخافته وحُبه امين</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 43:318:3-7 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܐ ܕܝܢ ܕܡܢܥܢܢ ܠܚܘܒܐ:
                            ܡܢܥܢ ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ. ܘܫܠܡܬ ܐܘܪܚܢ: ܘܥܒܪܢܢ ܠܓܙܪܬܐ ܕܠܗܠ ܡܢ ܥܠܡܐ: ܠܐܝܟܐ ܕܐܝܬܘܗܝ
                            ܐܒܐ ܘܒܪܐ ܘܪܘܚܐ ܕܩܘܕܫܐ. ܕܠܗ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܘܐܘܚܕܢܐ: ܘܠܢ ܢܫܘܐ ܠܕܚܠܬܗ ܘܠܚܘܒܗ.
                            ܐܡܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 43:544:85-90 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Καὶ ὅτε φθάσομεν τὴν ἀγάπην, ἐφθάσαμεν πρὸς τὸν Θεόν, καὶ ἡ
                        ὁδὸς ἡμῶν ἐτελειώθη, καὶ διέβημεν πρὸς τὴν νῆσον τὴν ἐκεῖθεν τοῦ κόσμου
                        οὖσαν, ὅπου ὁ Πατὴρ καὶ ὁ Υἱὸς καὶ τὸ Πνεῦμα τὸ ἅγιον· αὐτῷ ἡ δόξα καὶ τὸ
                        κράτος, καὶ ἡμᾶς ἀξίους ποιῆσαι τοῦ φόβου αὐτοῦ καὶ τῆς ἀγάπης αὐτοῦ,
                        ἀμήν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.22" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 9 (ff. 104v,4-106v,17)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the following homilies in
                        Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions: B 8:104-110 ▬ P 7:327-333. <anchor
                            xml:id="Hlk61944026"/>The Arabic title is shorter than the Syriac one.
                        Both the beginning and the end of the Arabic text correspond with those of
                        the Syriac and Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وراس ايضا لمار سحق يعلم فيه بماذا ينتفع الانسان في قلبه
                        بتقربه الي الله</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 104v,4-6): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس يعلم فيه بماذا ينتفع الانسان في قلبه
                        بتقربه الي الله وما السبب الذي بالحقيقة يقرب اليه المعونة في السر وايهما
                        المعنا الذي به يتقرب الانسان الي الاتضاع</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 104v,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">طوبا للانسان الذي يعرف ضعفه</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 8:104:10 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܛܘܒܘܗܝ ܠܒܪܢܫܐ ܕܝܕܥ
                        ܡܚܝܠܘܬܗ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 7:327:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Μακάριος ἄνθρωπος ὁ γινώσκων τὴν ἑαυτοῦ ἀσθένειαν</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 106v,16-17): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ليس عند الله منبوع العدل جور حاشا</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 8:110:4-5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܝܬ ܓܝܪ ܥܘܠܐ ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ:
                        ܚܣ: ܗܘ̇ ܡܒܘܥܐ ܕܙܕܝܩܘܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 7:333:134-135 <foreign xml:lang="gr">διότι οὐκ ἔστι παρὰ τῷ βρύοντι Θεῷ τὴν δικαιοσύνην ἀδικία· μὴ
                        γένοιτο</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.23" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 10 (ff. 106v,17-107v,16)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the following homilies in
                        Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions: B 11:119-121 ▬ P 10:345-347. The Arabic
                        title in the index is shorter, but the one at the beginning of the homily
                        corresponds with the Syriac title. Both the beginning and the end of the
                        Arabic text correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر يعلم فيه بماذا تحفظ جمال الرهبانية</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 106v,17-18): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر يعلم فيه بماذا تُحفظ جمال
                        الرهبانية وكيف يكون سبب تسبحة الله</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 107r,1): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ينبغي للراهب ان يكون في جميع ما حاط به منظر منفعة
                        للناظرين اليه لكيما منجل حسناته الكثيرة التي تحيط به وتبرق منه بمنزلة شعاع
                        الشمس</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 11:119:7-9 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܙܕܩ ܠܗ ܠܝܚܝܕܝܐ: ܕܡܢ
                            ܟܠܗܘܢ ܚܘܕܖ̈ܘܗܝ: ܚܙܬܐ ܕܓܘܪܓܐ ܢܗܘܐ ܠܚܙܝܘ̈ܗܝ. ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܡܢ ܫܘܦܖ̈ܘܗܝ ܣܓܝ̈ܐܐ:
                            ܕܐܝܟ ܙܠܝ̈ܩܝ ܫܡܫܐ ܡܒܪܩܝܢ ܡܢ ܟܠ ܚܘܕܖ̈ܘܗܝ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 10:345:1-3 <foreign xml:lang="ar">Δεῖ τὸν μοναχὸν εἶναι ἐν πᾶσι τοῖς ἑαυτοῦ πράγμασι τύπον
                        ὠφελείας τοῖς ὁρῶσιν αὐτὸν, ὅπως ἐκ τῶν πολλῶν ἀρετῶν αὐτοῦ, τῶν
                        διαλαμπόντων ἀκτινοειδῶς</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 107v,15-16): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ومن هاهنا يهيي</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54"
                            n="54"><p rend="footnote text">
                                Without
                                diacritical point under the second <hi rend="italic">yāʾ</hi> as in
                                Classical Arabic. For the metaplasm, cf. Blau, <hi rend="italic">A
                                    Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, Vol. 1, 177-80.</p></note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="ar">لنفسه موضع للنياحة من قبل خروجه من هذا العالم</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 11:121:11-12 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܡܢ ܗܪܟܐ ܡܛܝܒ ܠܗ̇
                        ܠܢܦܫܗ ܐܬܪܐ ܕܢܝܚܬܐ: ܡܢ ܩܕܡ ܡܦܩܢܗ ܕܡܢ ܗܢܐ ܥܠܡܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 10:347:44-45 <foreign xml:lang="gr">κἀντεῦθεν ἑτοιμάσει τῇ ψυχῇ αὐτοῦ τόπον ἀνέσεως, πρὸ τοῦ
                        ἐξελθεῖν αὐτὸν ἐκ τοῦδε τοῦ βίου</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.24" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 11 (ff. 107v,17-109r,1)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the following homilies in
                        Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions: B 12:121-123 ▬ P 13:353-355. The Arabic
                        title almost corresponds to the title of the Syriac and Greek texts. Both
                        the beginning and the end of the Arabic text correspond with those of the
                        Syriac and Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق علي انه لا ينبغي لعبد الله الذي قد
                        تمسكن من الدنيا وخرج في طلبه</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (ff. 107v,17-108r,2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر علي انه لا ينبغي لعبد الله
                        الذي قد تمسكن من الدنيا وخرج في طلبه ومنجل انه لم يبلغ</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">يبلع</foreign> ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">ادراك
                        الحق وفزع من ذلك يدع طلب الحق ويبقا من حمية الحرارة التي تولد من شوق
                        اللاهيات ومنجل هذا السبب يبقا العقل بطياشة السو وذكر الوجع</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 108r,3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ثلثة</foreign> [sic] <foreign xml:lang="ar">اشكال الذي فيها يتقلب جميع جري الانسان</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 12:121:19-20 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܠܬܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܛܟܣ̈ܐ:
                        ܕܒܗܘܢ ܡܬܕܪܓ ܟܠܗ ܪܗܛܐ ܕܒܪܢܫܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 13:353:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Τρεῖς εἰσι τάξεις ἐν αἷς προκόπτει ὁ ἄνθρωπος</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 108v,16-109r, 1): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وتحفظ الفكرة بتذكرة المواعيد العتيدة لكي لا
                        يسترخى العقل الي تذكرة الاشيا ومنجل ذلك تبرد حرارة الحركات ويقع في الشهوة
                        باسهل ذلك</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 12:123:16-19 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܢܛܪܝܢ ܠܪܥܝܢܐ
                            ܒܥܘ̈ܗܕܢܐ ܚܡܝ̈ܡܐ ܕܥܬܝ̈ܕܬܐ: ܕܠܐ ܢܬܐܫܕ ܒܝܕ ܒܛܠܢܐ ܠܥܘ̈ܗܕܢܐ ܕܨܒ̈ܘܬܐ: ܘܡܢ ܗܠܝܢ
                            ܬܫܬܗܐ ܚܡܝܡܘܬܐ ܕܙܘܥܗ: ܘܢܦܠ ܒܖ̈ܓܝܓܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 13:355:47-51 <foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ τηρεῖ τὴν διάνοιαν ἐν τῇ μνήμῃ τῶν μελλόντων ἀγαθῶν, ἵνα
                        μὴ χαυνωθῇ ὁ νοῦς ἐν τῇ ἀμελείᾳ αὐτοῦ εἰς τὴν μνήμην τῶν κοσμικῶν πραγμάτων,
                        διότι ἐκ τούτων ψυχραίνονται αἱ θερμότητες τῶν κινήσεων αὐτοῦ καὶ ἐμπίπτει
                        εἰς ἐπιθυμίας</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.25" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 12 (ff. 109r,2-121v,1)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the following homilies in
                        Bedjan’s and Pirard’s editions: B 35:224-269 ▬ P 27:438-480. The words <foreign xml:lang="ar">مسلة</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="ar">جواب</foreign> are
                        rubricated. The beginning corresponds with that of the Syriac and Greek
                        texts. The desinit of the Arabic homily (although it does not correspond
                        with those of the Syriac and Greek texts) agrees with the wording of the
                        corresponding Greek part.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">ومسايل له ايضا وجواباتها</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 109r,2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">من قول مار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 109r,2-3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">مسلة ܀ باي رباط يضبط القلب لكي</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text"> Without diacritical
                                points under <hi rend="italic">yāʾ</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">لا يجري الي الشر</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 35:224:15-16 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢܐ ܐܢܘܢ ܐܣܘܖ̈ܐ
                        ܠܒܘܟ̈ܐ ܕܪܥܝܢܐ: ܡܢ ܪܗܛܐ ܕܨܝܕ ܒܝ̈ܫܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 27:438:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐρώτησις. Ποίῳ δεσμῷ συνέχεται ἡ καρδία τοῦ μὴ τρέχειν εἰς τὰ
                        κακά;</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (ff. 121r,18-121v,1): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ولنا يحفظ بالنقاوة ويقدسنا بروح القدس ويهب لنا
                        ان نمجد اسمه بالنقاوة والذكاوة الي الابد امين </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 35:267:14-15 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܠܢ ܢܛܪ ܒܚܣܝܘܬܗ
                            ܘܢܩܕܫܢ ܒܪܘܚܗ ܠܐܝܩܪܐ ܕܫܡܗ: ܕܢܫܒܚܝܘܗܝ ܙܗܝܐܝܬ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܝܘ̈ܡܬܐ ܕܚܝܝ̈ܢ.
                            ܐܡܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 27:478:842-845 <foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ αὐτὸς ἡμᾶς φυλάξαι ἐν τῇ καθαρότητι αὐτοῦ καὶ ἁγιάσαι
                        ἡμᾶς τῷ ἁγιασμῷ τοῦ ἁγίου αὐτοῦ Πνεύματος εἰς τιμὴν τοῦ ὀνόματος αὐτοῦ, τοῦ
                        δοξάσαι τὸ ὄνομα αὐτοῦ ἐν καθαρότητι εἰς τοὺς αἰῶνας τῶν αἰώνων, ἀμήν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.26" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 13 (ff. 121v,2-123r,15)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains small passages from three different
                        homilies, which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s
                        edition: B 32:216-218 ▬ P 24:429-431; B 53:379-390 ▬ P 44:619-633; B
                        57:399-406 ▬ P 47:642-646.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا لمار سحق كلام مختار</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 121v,2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">من قول مار سحق ايضا كلام مختار</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 121v,3 – f. 122v,5: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) 121v, lines 3-11 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">الدموع التي تكون في الصلاة...ومن هذا الدموع تُكثر ··
                            وبالزيادة</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> Without diacritical point on <hi rend="italic"
                                    >zāʾ</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">تتربا</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 53:384:14-53:385:4 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܡ̈ܥܐ ܐܡܝ̈ܢܬܐ
                        ܕܒܨܠܘܬܐ...ܘܡܢ ܗܪܟܐ ܬܟ̈ܒܢ ܕܡ̈ܥܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 44:626:136-149 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τὰ δάκρυα τὰ ἐν τῇ εὐχῇ…καὶ ἐκ τούτων τὰ δάκρυα
                        πληθύνονται καὶ ἐπὶ πλέον αὐξάνονται</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> b) f. 121v,11 – 122v,5 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ان انت استاهلت الجلوس في الوحدة...وحينيذ يسلطهم علي
                        كنوزه الحفية</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 53:385:19-53:387:20 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܡܡܬܘܡ
                        ܬܫܬܘܐ ܠܝܚܝܕܝܘܬܐ...ܘܗܝܕܝܢ ܡܫܠܛ ܠܗܘܢ ܥܠ ܣܬܝܖ̈ܬܐ ܕܓܙܘ̈ܗܝ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 44:627:167-44:630:213 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐάν ποτε εὑρεθῇς ἄξιος τῆς ἀναχωρήσεως…Καὶ τότε
                        ἐξουσιάσαι αὐτοὺς ποιεῖ τῶν κρυπτῶν θησαυρῶν αὐτοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. f. 122v,5-9: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">لانه كما يتهاون الانسان بهذا العالم... وبمحبة للناس مثل
                            الاهوته</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">
                                For this variant form of <hi rend="italic">lāhūt</hi>, see G. Graf,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Verzeichnis arabischer kirchlicher
                                    Termini</hi> (Louvain: Imprimerie orientaliste L. Durbecq 1954),
                                13.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">يحمله ويخلصه</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 57:399:11-16 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܡܐ ܕܒܣܐ ܒܪܢܫܐ ܒܗܢܐ
                        ܥܠܡܐ...ܘܛܥܢܐ ܠܗ ܡܪܚܡܢܘܬܐ ܐܠܗܝܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 47:642:1-7 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">Ὅσον καταφρονήσει ἄνθρωπος τοῦ κόσμου τούτου…καὶ βαστάζει
                        αὐτὸν ἡ φιλανθρωπία τοῦ Θεοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iii. ff. 122v,9-123r,15: (اتحفظ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> For the prothesis of <hi rend="italic"
                                    >ʾalif</hi> in this verbal form, see Blau, <hi rend="italic">A
                                        Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, Vol. 1, 163-4.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">من
                        الاشيا البرانية... الا ان تطرحهم منها مستعجل</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 32:216:12-32:218:13 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪܚܝܩܘܬܐ ܕܡܢ
                        ܨܒ̈ܘܬܐ ܡܙܝܥܢ̈ܝܬܐ...ܐܢ ܠܝܓ ܠܝܓ ܡܢܗܘܢ ܠܐ ܢܫܕܘܢܗ̇</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 24:429:8-24:431:44 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">καὶ παραφυλάττου ἐκ τῶν πραγμάτων τῶν ἔξωθεν…ἐὰν μὴ
                        ῥίψῃς αὐτὰς ἐξ ἑαυτοῦ ταχέως</foreign>) </p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.27" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 14 (ff. 123r,15-124v,9)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains small passages from three different
                        homilies, which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s
                        edition: B 38:177-182 ▬ P 30:508-514; B 45:321-330 ▬ P 37:550-560; B
                        50:343-359 ▬ P 41:574-594.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign  xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 123r,15): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار اسحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. ff. 123r,16-123v,16: ((<foreign xml:lang="ar">اناس اشتهوا ان يريحوا الجسد...فهو من التدبير
                        المرتفع مويس كل ايام حياته</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 50:353:14—50:355:4 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܫܐ: ܐܚܝ̈:
                            ܕܐܝܟ ܕܠܣܘܡܟܐ ܒܠܚܘܕ ܨܒܝܢ ܕܢܢܝܚܘܢ ܠܦܓܪܐ...ܡܢ ܪܘܡܐ ܕܕܘܒܖ̈ܐ ܠܘܬ ܫܪܝܘܬܐ ܕܚܝ̈ܐ
                            ܐܫܬܒܝܘ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 41:587:295—41:588:331 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Εἰσί τινες οἱ ἐρειδόντες τὸ σῶμα καὶ ἐπιθυμοῦντες
                        ἀναπαῦσαι αὐτὸ…ἐκ τῆς ὑψηλῆς πολιτείας πρὸς λύσιν τῆς ζωῆς
                        ᾐχμαλωτίσθησαν</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 123v,16-124v,4: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">اما القتال الذي يكون من علل تخلية الكبرية...كرامته
                        من الله</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 38:294:20—38:296:4 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܪܒܐ ܕܡܢ
                        ܡܫܬܒܩܢܘܬܐ ܕܡܢ ܥܠܬ ܡܣܒܪܢܘܬܐ ܗܘܐ...ܐܝܩܖ̈ܘܗܝ ܡܢ ܐܠܗܐ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 30:512:96—30:514:129 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τὸν δὲ πόλεμον τὸν ἐκ παραχωρήσεως, τὸν ἐξ αἰτίας
                        τῆς οἰήσεως ἡμῶν γινόμενον….ἐκ τοῦ Θεοῦ ἡ τιμὴ αὐτοῦ</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> iii. f. 124v,4-9: </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> a) f. 124v,4-5 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">كذلك يمضي خلفه··وكما يكمل الانسان بالله</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> Without diacritical point
                                under <hi rend="italic">bāʾ</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">ويتم</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 45:324:14-15 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܡܐ ܐܢ ܢܬܓܡܪ ܒܪܢܫܐ
                        ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ: ܡܐܙܠ ܗܘ ܐܙܠ ܒܬܪܗ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 37:553:67-68 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὅσον γὰρ τελειοῦται ἄνθρωπος πρὸς τὸν Θεὸν, τοσοῦτον ὀπίσω
                        αὐτοῦ πορεύεται</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> b) f. 124v,5-9: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">فاذا ما اردت ان تدنوا</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61"
                            n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> For the paragoge of <hi rend="italic"
                                    >ʾalif</hi> in this verbal form, see Blau, <hi rend="italic">A
                                        Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, Vol. 1, 194-5.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الي
                        الله بقلبك... ومن هاهنا الرب يعمل اساس للتمام)</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 45:329:10-14 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܡܬܝ ܕܨܒܐ ܐܢܬ
                        ܕܬܬܩܪܒ ܒܠܒܟ ܠܘܬ ܐܠܗܐ...ܐܦ ܡܪܢ: ܡܢ ܗܪܟܐ ܥܒܕ ܫܬܐܣܬܐ ܠܓܡܝܪܘܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 37:559:183-189 (<foreign xml:lang="ar">Ὅταν θελήσῃς προσεγγίσαι τῷ Θεῷ τῇ καρδίᾳ σου…Καὶ ὁ Κύριος
                        ἐκτούτου ἐποίησε τὸν θεμέλιον τῆς τελειώσεως</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.28" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 15 (ff. 124v,10-125r,8)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains small passages from two different
                        homilies, which correspond to the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> and 16<hi
                            rend="superscript">th</hi> homily of Bedjan’s and Pirard’s edition: B
                        15:127-130 ▬ P 15:362-364; B 16:130-133 ▬ P 16:365-368.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 124v,10): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار اسحق القديس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 124v,11-18: <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> The last four words seem to be an addition of
                        the Arabic.</p></note>(<foreign xml:lang="ar">من الاعمال...من امور العالم تدنوا</foreign><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text"> See n.
                                63.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">النفس الي الله</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 15:127:20-15:128:19 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢ
                        ܥܡ̈ܠܐ...ܕܡܢ ܥܠܡܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 15:362:1-15:363:22 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐκ τῆς ἐργασίας...τοῦ μακρυσμοῦ τῶν βιωτικῶν</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. f. 124v,18-125r,8: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">انسان كثير الاهتمام... ليس تقدر</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 16:130:11-16:131:7 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܢܫܐ ܣܓܝ
                        ܨܦܬܐ...ܠܐ ܡܨܝܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 16:365:1-16:366:18 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἄνθρωπος πολυμέριμνος…οὐ δύνασαι</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.29" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 16 (ff. 125r,8-125v,5)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 13<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 11<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 13: 124-125 ▬ P 11:348-349). Both the
                        beginning and the end of the Arabic text correspond with those of the Syriac
                        and the Greek texts. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 125r,8): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا قول ماري سحق القديس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 125r,9-11): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الذي قدم في عقله ان يلزم طريق السكوت بطقس مذهبه</foreign><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">مدهبه</foreign>
                                ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">واعماله وفي طقس انواع</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> Without diacritical point
                                on <hi rend="italic">nūn</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">السكوت يجيز</foreign><note
                                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">يحيز</foreign>
                                        ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">ايام حياته مثل عادة السكوت الذي اخذ من النعمة الالهية</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 13:124:6-9 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܢܐ ܕܝܢ ܕܦܣܩ ܒܪܥܝܢܗ
                            ܕܒܕܘܝܪܐ ܠܚܘܕܝܐ ܕܥܡ ܢܦܫܗ ܢܛܟܣ ܝܬܗ: ܘܒܦܘܠܚܢܐ ܘܛܘܟܣܐ ܕܙܢܝ̈ ܫܠܝܐ ܢܦܩ ܫܪܟܢܐ
                            ܕܚܝܘ̈ܗܝ. ܐܡܬܝ ܕܐܝܟ ܥܝܕܐ ܕܒܫܠܝܐ: ܗܘ ܕܡܬܚܡ ܦܩܚܐܝܬ ܠܛܝܒܘܬܐ ܐܠܗܝܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 11:348:1-4 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὁ συνελθὼν τῷ νοῒ αὐτοῦ ἐν τῇ ἡσυχίᾳ πολιτεύσασθαι, ῥυθμιζέτω
                        ἑαυτόν, καὶ ἐν τῇ γεωργίᾳ καὶ τῇ τάξει τῆς ἡσυχίας διεξαγαγέτω τὸ ἐπίλοιπον
                        τῶν ἡμερῶν αὐτοῦ. Ὅταν συμβῇ σοι, ὡς ἔστι σύνηθες τῇ τάξει τῆς ἡσυχίας, τῇ
                        ὡρισμένῃ ὑπὸ τῆς θείας χάριτος</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 125v,4-5): <foreign xml:lang="ar">لان القراة في كُتب القديسين بالدوام تجدد النفس وتملاها
                        عجب لا يُدرك وفرح بالله</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 13:125:4-5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܪܓܐ ܐܡܝܢܐ ܕܒܟܬܒ̈ܐ
                        ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ: ܒܐܡܝܢܘ ܬܗܪܐ ܠܐ ܡܬܕܪܟܢܐ ܘܚܕܘܬܐ ܕܒܐܠܗܐ ܡܠ̈ܐ ܠܗ̇ ܠܢܦܫܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 11:349:21-23 <foreign xml:lang="ar">ἡ γὰρ διηνεκὴς μελέτη ἐν ταῖς γραφαῖς τῶν ἁγίων, θαύματος
                        ἀκαταλήπτου καὶ θείας εὐφροσύνης τὴν ψυχὴν ἐμπίπλησιν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.30" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 17 (ff. 125v,5-127r,4)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains passages from two different homilies,
                        which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s edition:
                        B 22:163-175 ▬ P 19:390-401; B 34:221-224 ▬ P 26:434-437.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 125v,5): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. f. 125v,6-16: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">السُبح لذلك الذي يفيض بعطاياه ... وتمنع من الشفتين الصلاة</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 22:163:18—22:164:15 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܗܘ
                        ܕܫܦܝܥܐ ܡܘܗܒܬܗ...ܘܐܦ ܠܗ̇ ܠܨܠܘܬܐ ܦܣܩܐ ܡܢ ܣܦ̈ܘܬܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 19:390:1-19:391:20 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Δόξα τῷ ἐκχέαντι πλουσίως τὰς ἑαυτοῦ δωρεὰς…καὶ τὴν
                        προσευχὴν τῶν χειλέων ἐκκόπτει</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 125v,16-127r,4: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا الامساك والجهاد هي ام القدوسية... والمعرفة
                        المُستقيمة تلد من البلايا)</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 34:221:4—34:224:10 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܢܘܝܘܬܐ: ܐܡܐ
                        ܗܝ ܕܩܕܝܫܘܬܐ...ܘܝܕܥܬܐ ܬܪܝܨܬܐ: ܝܠܕܐ ܕܢܣܝ̈ܘܢܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 26:434:1—26:437:68 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἡ ἄσκησις, μήτηρ τοῦ ἁγιασμοῦ…καὶ ἡ γνῶσις ἡ ἀληθινὴ
                        γέννημα τῶν πειρασμῶν</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.31" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 18 (ff. 127r,5-129v,2)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 41<hi rend="superscript"
                            >st</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 33<hi rend="superscript"
                            >rd</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 41:307-313 ▬ P 33:531-537). The Arabic
                        title is shorter than the Syriac one. The beginning corresponds with the
                        beginning of the Syriac and Greek texts. The end of the Arabic text almost
                        corresponds with the end of the Syriac and the Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">ورسالة له لمار سحق الي اخ كان يحب السُكوت</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 127r,5): <foreign xml:lang="ar">الي اخ كان يحب السكوت هذه رسالة لماري
                        اسحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 127r,6-8): <foreign xml:lang="ar">منجل اني اعرفك تحب السكوت وباسباب كثيرة يعقلك الشيطان
                        علي وجة الخير لانه يعرف مذهب غرض فكرك لكيما يسجسك من هذه الفضيلة الجامعة
                        الكثيرة الاجزا يا ايه</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See n. 41.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الاخ الفاضل·· </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 41:307:12-15 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܕܝܕܥܢܐ ܠܟ ܕܪܚܡ
                            ܫܠܝܐ ܐܢܬ: ܘܒܣܓܝ̈ܐܬܐ ܡܥܪܩܠ ܠܟ ܣܛܢܐ ܒܦܪܨܘܦܐ ܕܡܝܬܪܘܬܐ: ܒܗܝ ܕܝܕܥ ܠܢܝܫܗ
                            ܕܪܥܝܢܟ: ܐܝܟ ܕܢܦܠܗܕܟ ܡܢ ܡܝܬܪܘܬܐ ܗܕܐ ܚܒܘܫܬܐ ܘܣܓܝܐܬ ܡܢܘ̈ܬܐ: ܐܘ̇ ܐܚܘܢ
                            ܡܝܬܪܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 33:531:1-5 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Διότι γνωρίζω σε ἀγαπῶντα τὴν ἡσυχίαν, καὶ συμπλέκει σε ὁ
                        διάβολος ἐν πολλοῖς προφάσει τοῦ ἀγαθοῦ, διότι γνωρίζει τὸ θέλημα τὴς
                        διανοίας σου, ἕως ἂν διασκεδάσῃ σε καὶ ἐμποδίσῃ ἐκ τῆς ἀρετῆς τῆς
                        περιεκτικῆς τῶν πολλῶν τρόπων τῶν ἀγαθῶν, ὦ ἀδελφὲ ἀγαθέ</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 129v,1-2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">في ايام محدودة تكون تنظر الي وجوههم </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 41:313:7-8 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܬܚܘܡ ܝܘ̈ܡܬܐ ܬܚܙܐ
                        ܦܖ̈ܨܘܦܝܗܘܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 41:537:141 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ὡρισμέναις ἡμέραις θέασαι τὰς ὄψεις αὐτῶν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.32" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 19 (ff. 129v,3-135r,13)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains passages from two different homilies,
                        which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s edition:
                        B 63:437-441 ▬ P 53:673-677; B 65:443-464 ▬ P 54:678-691.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وراس لمار سحق يعلم فيه ان التجربة تعلم كل</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 129v,3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس يعلم فيه ان التجربة تعلم كُل</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. ff. 129v,4—131r,3: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">الرب المُبارك وقاره يفتح باب بين يدينا...ومصيرها تنحل
                        وتتلف</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 63:437:18-63:441:7 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪܝܟ ܐܝܩܪܗ:
                        ܗܘ ܢܦܬܚ ܬܪܥܐ ܩܕܡܝܢ...ܘܡܬܚܙܐ ܕܟܠܗܘܢ ܡܫܬܪܝܢ: ܘܐܒܕܝܢ ܠܗܘܢ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 53:673:1-53:677:90 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Εὐλογημένη ἡ τιμὴ τοῦ Κυρίου τοῦ ἀνοίγοντος θύραν
                        ἔμπροσθεν ἡμῶν…καὶ ὁρᾶται ὅτι πάντα λύονται καὶ ἀπόλλυνται</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 131r,3—135r,13: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">اكثر من هولا</foreign><note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text"> These first
                                three words do not correspond to any textual material in Bedjan’s
                                text. Nonetheless, they partially correspond with the last words of
                                the 53<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> Greek homily: P 53:677:90-91
                                (τὸ δὲ πλέον τούτων, μέτρον ἐστὶ τῶν λόγων). Interestingly, the
                                Arabic words which follow immediately after <foreign xml:lang="ar">هولا</foreign> correspond with the
                                beginning (except from the short title) of the 54<hi
                                    rend="superscript">th</hi> Greek homily, but not with the
                                beginning of the 65<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Syriac homily.
                                Following Pirard’ s table of correspondences (Pirard, <hi
                                    rend="italic"><foreign xml:lang="ar">Ἀββᾶ Ἰσαὰκ τοῦ Σύρου</foreign></hi>, 883), in this specific
                                case the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Vorlage</hi> of both the Arabic
                                and the Greek texts apparently presented the order of the Syriac
                                Western tradition.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الدوام في الصلاة الذي بلا طياشة·· لا
                        تحسبها بُطلان منجل تركك المزامير... الي الابد امين</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 65:446:11—65:464:18 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܬܚܫܘܒ
                        ܒܛܠܢܐ ܐܘܪܟܐ ܕܨܠܘܬܐ ܟܢܝܫܬܐ: ܡܛܠ ܦܘܫܐ ܕܡܙܡܘܖ̈ܐ...ܠܥܠܡ ܥܠܡܝܢ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 54:678:1—54:691:288 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Μὴ ψηφίσῃς ἀργίαν τὴν ἔκτασιν τῆς εὐχῆς τῆς
                        ἀμετεωρίστου καὶ συνηγμένης καὶ μακρᾶς, διὰ τὸ ἀφῆσαι τοὺς ψαλμούς…εἰς τοὺς
                        αἰῶνας τῶν αἰώνων, ἀμήν</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.33" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 20 (ff. 135r,14-136v,2)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 61<hi rend="superscript"
                            >st</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 51<hi rend="superscript"
                            >st</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 61:427-429 ▬ P 51:661-664). Both the
                        beginning and the end correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek
                        texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وراس اخر ايضا لمار سحق علي الحب</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 135r,14): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر ايضا لمار اسحق القديس علي الحُب</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 135r,15): <foreign xml:lang="ar">من الحُب الذي يورون</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69"
                            n="69"><p rend="footnote text"> For this form, see Blau, <hi
                                    rend="italic">A Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, Vol. 1,
                                175-6.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">القديسين لله</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 61:427:5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢ ܚܘܒܐ ܕܡܚܘܝܢ ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ
                        ܠܐܠܗܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 51:661:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐκ τῆς ἀγάπης, ἧς ἔδειξαν οἱ ἅγιοι πρὸς τὸν Θεόν</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 136v,1-2): <foreign xml:lang="ar">ان نحن انحنينا وطلبنا باتضاع وشوق وبدوام لا يبطل كُل
                        شي ناخذ في كُل حين </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 61:429:13-14 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܢܬܪܟܢ ܠܡܫܐܠ
                        ܒܡܟܝܟܘܬܐ ܟܕ ܝܐܝܒܝܢܢ ܒܐܟܝܦܘܬܐ ܡܚܡܣܢܢܐܝܬ: ܟܠܡܕܡ ܢܣܒܝܢ ܚܢܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 51:664:63-64 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐὰν ὑποταγῶμεν αἰτούμενοι ἐν ταπεινώσει μετ’ ἐφέσεως
                        ἀδιαλείπτου ἐν καρτερίᾳ, πάντα λαμβάνομεν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.34" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 21 (ff. 136v,3-137v,9)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 60<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 50<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 60:419-427 ▬ P 50:656-660). Both the
                        beginning and the end correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek
                        texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وراس اخر لمار سحق مختار من قوله</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 136v,3): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر لمار اسحق القديس مُختار من قوله</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 136v,4): <foreign xml:lang="ar">في كُل حين قريب هو الرب بمعونته للقديسين</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 60:419:9-10 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܒܟܠܙܒܢ ܩܪܝܒܘ ܡܪܝܐ
                        ܒܝܕ ܥܘܕܖ̈ܢܘܗܝ ܠܘܬ ܩܕܝ̈ܫܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 50:656:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐν παντὶ καιρῷ ἐν ᾧ ὁ Κύριος ἐγγὺς εἰς ἀντίληψιν τῶν ἁγίων
                        αὐτοῦ</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 137v,9): <foreign xml:lang="ar">هو يظهر فينا قوة حُبه امين</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 60:427:2 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܘ ܢܓܠܐ ܒܢ ܚܝܠܐ ܕܚܘܒܗ.
                        ܐܡܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 50:660:101-102 <foreign xml:lang="gr">αὐτὸς φανερώσοι ἡμῖν τὴν ἰσχὺν τῆς ἀγάπης αὐτοῦ, ἀμήν</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.35" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 22 (ff. 137v,10-139v,6)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It contains passages from two different homilies,
                        which correspond to the following numbers in Bedjan’s and Pirard’s edition:
                        B 58:407-414 ▬ P 48:647:650; B 77:524-536 ▬ P 63:749-762.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار سحق القديس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 137v,10): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار اسحق القديس</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> i. ff. 137v,11—138v,4: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ماذا تقول ايه</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70"
                        n="70"><p rend="footnote text"> See n. 41.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الانسان...ويصيروا
                            الانسان</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">
                                For the <hi rend="italic">constructio ad sensum</hi> of a verb in
                                plural referred to a subject in singular denoting a collective
                                entity, see J. Blau, <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of Christian
                                    Arabic. Based mainly on South-Palestinian texts from the first
                                    millennium</hi>, Vol. 2, Corpus Scriptorum Christianorum
                                Orientalium 268, Subsidia 28, (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO,
                                1967), 278.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">بلا حزن ولا وجع في شدة العذاب</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 77:534:14—77:536:11 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܢܐ ܐܡܪ ܐܢܬ:
                        ܐܘ̇ ܓܒܪܐ...ܗܘܝܢ ܠܐ ܚܫܘܫ̈ܐ ܒܥܘܙܐ ܕܚܫܐ ܕܬܫ̈ܢܝܕܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 63:760:259—63:762:304 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Τί λέγεις, ὦ ἄνθρωπε…γίνονται ἀπαθεῖς ἐν τῇ σφοδρᾷ
                        λύπῃ τῶν βασάνων</foreign>)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ii. ff. 138v,4—139v,6: (<foreign xml:lang="ar">ان انت عملت فضيلة... فليس يعرف</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> ندامة ) <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">
                                After this word there is a reference sign that points to a <hi
                                    rend="italic">marginalium</hi> written by a posterior hand. It
                                is a doxology, which does not correspond to any textual material in
                                Syriac or in Greek: <foreign xml:lang="ar">والله اب كل رحمة يوفقنا للاتضاع المرضي له برحمته
                                ورافته امين.</foreign></p></note></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> B 58:408:16—B 58:412:3 (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ ܦܠܚܬ
                        ܡܝܬܪܘܬܐ...ܠܐ ܝܕܥ ܕܢܬܬܘܐ</foreign>) </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"> P 48:647:12-48:650:81 (<foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐὰν ποιήσῃς ἀρετὴν…οὐκ οἶδε κατάνυξιν</foreign>)</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.36" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 23 (ff. 139v,7-142r,9)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 36<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 28<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 36:269-281 ▬ P 28:481-494). The
                        beginning corresponds with that of the Syriac and Greek texts. The end does
                        not correspond with the end of the Syriac and Greek texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 139v,7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 139v,8): <foreign xml:lang="ar">لعدونا الشيطان عادات اُخر للذين يدخلون في هذا الجهاد</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 36:269:12-13 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬ ܠܗ ܬܘܒ ܐܦ ܥܝܕ̈ܐ
                        ܐܚܖ̈ܢܐ ܠܒܥܠܕܪܢ ܣܛܢܐ: ܕܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܠܐܓܘܢܐ ܗܢܐ ܢܚܬܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 28:481:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἔχει ἔθος πάλιν ὁ διάβολος, ὁ ἀντίπαλος ἡμῶν, τοῖς ἐν τῷ ἀγῶνι
                        τούτῳ κατιοῦσι</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 142r,8-9): <foreign xml:lang="ar">هولا كلا المذهبين</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73"
                        n="73"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">المدهبين</foreign> ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">الذي لقتال
                        الشيطان </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 36:275:5-6 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܠܝܢ ܬܪܝܢ ܙܢܝ̈ܐ ܕܬܟܬܘܫܐ
                        ܕܥܕܡܐ ܠܗܪܟܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 28:487:147-148 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Οὗτοι οἱ δύο τρόποι τῆς πάλης τοῦ διαβόλου ἕως ὧδε</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.37" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 24 (ff. 142r,9-143v,7)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 47<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 39<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 47:335-338 ▬ P 39:566-570). Both the
                        beginning and the end correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek
                        texts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 142r,9): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 142r,10): <foreign xml:lang="ar">النفس الي الحياة الحركة الاولة التي من رحمة الاله
                        تقع</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text"> <foreign xml:lang="ar">نقع</foreign>
                            ms.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">في الانسان الذي تقود</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 47:335:19-20 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܙܘܥܐ ܩܕܡܝܐ ܕܡܢ ܖ̈ܚܡܐ
                        ܐܠܗܝ̈ܐ ܢܦܠ ܒܒܪܢܫܐ: ܕܠܘܬ ܚܝ̈ܐ ܢܓܕ ܠܗ̇ ܠܢܦܫܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 39:566:1-2 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Πρώτη ἔννοια, ἡ ἐκ τῆς φιλανθρωπίας τοῦ Θεοῦ ἐμπίπτουσα ἐν τῷ
                        ἀνθρώπῳ, ἡ ὁδηγοῦσα τὴν ψυχὴν εἰς τὴν ζωήν</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 143v,6-7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">طوبا لمن حفظ لهذه الحركة الفاضلة اذا ما وقعت في نفسه
                        ورباها ولم يبذرها منه بباطل وطياشة الارضيات</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 47:338:15-17 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܛܘܒܘܗܝ ܠܡܢ ܕܢܛܪܗ ܠܗܢܐ
                            ܙܪܥܐ ܛܒܐ ܡܐ ܕܢܦܠ ܒܢܦܫܗ: ܘܪܒܝܗ: ܘܠܐ ܦܠܗܕ ܡܢܗ ܒܣܖ̈ܝܩܬܐ ܘܦܗܝܐ
                            ܕܥܒܘܖ̈ܝܬܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 39:570:83-86 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Μακάριος ὃς ἐφύλαξε τοῦτον τὸν σπόρον τὸν ἀγαθόν, ὅταν πέσῃ ἐν
                        τῇ ψυχῇ αὐτοῦ, καὶ ηὔξησεν αὐτὸν καὶ οὐκ ἐσκόρπισεν αὐτὸν ἐξ αὐτοῦ ἐν τοῖς
                        ματαίοις καὶ ἐν τῷ μετεωρισμῷ τῶν παρερχομένων</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.38" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 25 (ff. 143v,8-144v,6)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 48<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 40<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 48:339-341 ▬ P 40:571-573). Both the
                        beginning and the end correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek texts.
                        In the Arabic text, the title of the homily, in contrast to the Syriac and
                        Greek texts, is incorporated in the main text of the homily.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا راس اخر لمار سحق</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 143v,8): <foreign xml:lang="ar">راس اخر</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Incipit (f. 143v,9): وايضا علي الابتدال الذي تقبل النفس في كُل حين </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 48:339:1 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܫܘ̈ܚܠܦܐ ܕܡܩܒܠܐ ܢܦܫܐ
                        ܒܟܠܥܕܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 40:571:Title <foreign xml:lang="gr">Περὶ τῆς ἀλλοιώσεως τῆς ἐν τῇ ψυχῇ γινομένης ἐν παντὶ
                        καιρῷ</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 144v,5-6): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وهذه الاشيا للذين يريدون يسلكوا في هذه الطريق</foreign> </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 48:341:4 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܠܝܢ: ܠܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܒܐܘܪܚܐ
                        ܪܕܝܢ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 40:573:56 <foreign xml:lang="ar">καὶ ἐν τούτοις εἶναι τοὺς πορευομένους ἐν τῇ ὁδῷ</foreign></p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.39" xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Homily 26 (ff. 144v,7-148v,7)</head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It corresponds with the 37<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> homily in Bedjan’s edition and the 29<hi rend="superscript"
                            >th</hi> in Pirard’s edition (B 37:281-290 ▬ P 29:495-507). Both the
                        beginning and the end correspond with those of the Syriac and Greek texts.
                        The title corresponds only partially with the Syriac and the Greek
                        title.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title in the index: <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضاو من قول مار سحق القديس علي الجهتين التي بمعرفة
                        اتعلمت تحقيق الذي ينبغا لها ان تقرا كل ايام حياتك فيها</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Title of the homily (f. 144v,7-9): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا من قول مار اسحق القديس علي الجهتين
                        التي بمعرفة اتعلمت</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> For the prothesis of <hi rend="italic"
                                    >ʾalif</hi> in this verbal form, see Blau, <hi rend="italic">A
                                        Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, vol. 1, 163.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">تحقيق
                        الذي ينبغي لها ان تقرا</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                                rend="footnote text"> With only one diacritical point on the <hi
                                    rend="italic">tāʾ</hi>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">كُل ايام حياتك فيها</foreign></p>
                    <p style="text-align: right;">Incipit (f. 144v,10): <foreign xml:lang="ar">مرار كثيرة حُربت بامور
                        اليمين والشمال </foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 37:281:5 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܓܝܪ ܙܒ̈ܢܬܐ ܣܓܝ̈ܐܬܐ
                        ܐܬܢܣܝܬ ܒܕܝܡܝܢܐ ܘܒܕܣܡܠܐ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 29:495:1 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἐν πολλῷ καιρῷ πειραζόμενος ἐν τοῖς δεξιοῖς καὶ ἀριστεροῖς</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Desinit (f. 148v,6-7): <foreign xml:lang="ar">وايضا يقول الذي منجلهم تريد ان تعيش منجلهم لا تكسل</foreign>
                        وتضجر ان تموت </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">B 37:290:17-18 <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܡܛܠܬܗܝܢ ܨܒܐ
                        ܐܢܬ ܕܬܚܐ: ܡܛܠܬܗܝܢ ܕܗܠܝܢ ܠܡܡܬ ܠܐ ܬܬܩܛܥ ܠܟ</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">P 29:507:233-234 <foreign xml:lang="gr">Ἅπερ δι’ αὐτῶν θέλεις ζῆσαι, μὴ ἀκηδιάσῃς ὑπὲρ αὐτῶν
                        ἀποθανεῖν</foreign></p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Explicit (f. 148v,8-9)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en"><foreign xml:lang="ar">تم قول مار اسحق القديس وللمسيح الشكر والسُبح ولابوه</foreign><note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"> For this form, see Blau,
                                    <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of Christian Arabic</hi>, vol. 2,
                                319.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="ar">وروح قدسه معه من الان والي الابد امين</foreign></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.40" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Table of Correspondences</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The following chart gives the corresponding homilies
                    between the Arabic Isaac of the <hi rend="italic">Ms Strasbourg 4226</hi> and
                    the editions of the Syriac and Greek Isaac<hi rend="italic">.</hi> For all the
                    details about the precise pericopes of each Arabic homily and their
                    correspondences to the Syriac and the Greek editions, see the description of
                    each one above. For the comparison of the Greek Isaac with the West and East
                    Syriac traditions of Isaac Syrus see the table of correspondences provided by
                    Pirard (2012: 881-883).</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="bold">Arabic Isaac (</hi><hi
                                rend="italic bold">Strasbourg 4226</hi><hi rend="bold">)</hi></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="bold">Syriac Isaac
                                (Bedjan)</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"> The passages which are actually from the
                                    Syriac John of Dalyatha will be signalised with the reference to
                                    the edition of Khayyat, <hi rend="italic">Jean de
                                    Dalyatha</hi>.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><hi rend="bold">Greek Isaac
                            (Pirard)</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">4</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">5</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">5</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">6</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">6</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">7</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"
                                ><p xml:lang="en">16</p><p xml:lang="en">17</p><p xml:lang="en">23</p><p xml:lang="en">24</p><p xml:lang="en">38</p><p xml:lang="en">39</p><p xml:lang="en">46</p><p xml:lang="en">50</p><p xml:lang="en">53</p><p xml:lang="en">64</p><p xml:lang="en">74</p><p xml:lang="en">77</p><p xml:lang="en">Khayyat
                                1</p><p xml:lang="en">Khayyat 6</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"
                                ><p xml:lang="en">16</p><p xml:lang="en">17</p><p xml:lang="en">-</p><p xml:lang="en">-</p><p xml:lang="en">30</p><p xml:lang="en">31</p><p xml:lang="en">38</p><p xml:lang="en">41</p><p xml:lang="en">44</p><p xml:lang="en">46</p><p xml:lang="en">62</p><p xml:lang="en">63</p><p xml:lang="en">Index
                                1</p><p xml:lang="en">-</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">8</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">43</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">35</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">9</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">8</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">7</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">10</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">11</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">10</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">11</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">12</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">12</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">35</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">27</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">13</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">32</p><p xml:lang="en">53</p><p xml:lang="en">57</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">24</p><p xml:lang="en">44</p><p xml:lang="en">47</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">14</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">38</p><p xml:lang="en">45</p><p xml:lang="en">50</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">30</p><p xml:lang="en">37</p><p xml:lang="en">41</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">15</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">15</p><p xml:lang="en">16</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">15</p><p xml:lang="en">16</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">16</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">13</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">11</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">17</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">22</p><p xml:lang="en">34</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">19</p><p xml:lang="en">26</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">18</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">41</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">33</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">19</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">63</p><p xml:lang="en">65</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">53</p><p xml:lang="en">54</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">20</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">61</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">51</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">21</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">60</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">50</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">22</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">58</p><p xml:lang="en">77</p></cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;"><p xml:lang="en">48</p><p xml:lang="en">63</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">23</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">36</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">28</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">24</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">47</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">39</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">25</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">48</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">40</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">26</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">37</cell>
                        <cell style="text-align: left;">29</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2chamourgiotaki-zimbardi.41" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Final remarks</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The results of this first survey of the texts
                    transmitted under the name of Isaac the Syrian in the Arabic MS <hi
                        rend="italic">Strasbourg 4226</hi> are the following:</p>
                <list rend="numbered">
                    <item>The texts gathered in this manuscript form a collection of selected works
                        transmitted under the name of Isaac the Syrian. It is hard to determine
                        whether this collection was based on a pre-existing, possibly more expanded,
                        Arabic translation or if it derived directly from a Syriac prototype already
                        formed as a collection of selected texts of the Isaac Syrus.</item>
                    <item>The collection presents both single sermons of Isaac (homilies 1-6, 8-12,
                        16, 18, 20-21, 23-26) and pieces of different homilies put together in one
                        single unit (homilies 7 [which has moreover englobed pieces from John of
                        Dalyatha], 13-15, 17, 19, 22).</item>
                    <item>The information that we gain from the titles (either in the index of the
                        ms. or at the beginning of the homily, or in both) include mostly the name
                        of Mār Isḥaq, the topic, and an identification tag. These tags, present in
                        all homilies, transmit to us the type of text which is to follow. Thus, we
                        have: a) <hi rend="italic">mīmar</hi> 'sermon' (homilies 1-6), b) <hi
                            rend="italic">qaul</hi> 'saying', almost always preceded by the
                        preposition <hi rend="italic">min</hi> (homilies 1, 7-8, 12-16, 22, 26), c)
                            <hi rend="italic">masāʾil wa-ǧawābāt</hi> 'erotapokriseis' (homily 12),
                        d) <hi rend="italic">risāla</hi> 'letter' (homily 18), and e) <hi
                            rend="italic">raʾs</hi> 'chapter' (homilies 9, 10-11, 17, 19, 20, 21,
                            23-25).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p xml:lang="en">
                                <hi>Two homilies preserve more than one identification tags, i.e. homily 1 is characterized both as </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >mīmar</hi><hi> and </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >qaul</hi><hi>, and homily 12 is characterized as </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                    >qaul</hi><hi> at the beginning of the homily and as </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic">masāʾil
                                    wa-ǧawābāt</hi><hi> in the index. The identification tag of homily 8 is given only in the index. These discrepancies could be the result of a copyist’s inaccuracy in case the titles already existed and are not the product of the copyist of MS </hi><hi
                                    rend="italic"
                                >Strasbourg</hi><hi> 4226.</hi></p></note>
                        In some cases, it is explicitly mentioned in the title (either in the index
                        or in the homily or in both) that the text is <hi rend="italic">muḫtār</hi>
                        'selected' (homilies 1, 2, 13, 21) or <hi rend="italic">multaqat</hi>
                        'gathered' (homily 7). In some cases, the topic of the homily is explicitly
                        mentioned, namely in the homilies 1, 3 (only in the index), 8-11, 18-20 and
                        26. All the titles of these homilies correspond partially or completely to
                        the titles of the Syriac and/or Greek edited texts, except for one, which
                        does not correspond at all (homily 19). In both the Arabic and edited Syriac
                        and Greek texts, the titles of the homilies 2 and 4-6 do not present the
                        topic but only the number of the homily (second, fourth, etc.).</item>
                </list>
                <p xml:lang="en">Any further consideration about the textual transmission concerning both the
                    titles and the texts must be done only after the collation with other manuscript
                    witnesses which bear the translation(s) of Isaac collections into Arabic before
                    Ibn al-Faḍl. This paper aimed at presenting an exact overview of the
                    correspondences between the textual portions transmitted in the Strasbourg
                    manuscript and the available printed editions of the Syriac and Greek Isaac,
                    with the intent to facilitate every future inspection of the Arabic tradition of
                    Isaac.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Works cited</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>Assemani G.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Orientalis Clementino-Vaticana, </hi>Vol.
                    1, <hi rend="italic">De scriptoribus Syris orthodoxis</hi> (Roma: Sacra
                    Congregatio de Propaganda Fide, 1719).</bibl>
                <bibl>Assemani G. and Assemani S., <hi rend="italic">Bibliothecae apostolicae Vaticanae
                        codicum manuscriptorum catalogus</hi>, Vol. 1,3, <hi rend="italic">Reliqui
                        codices Chaldaici sive Syriaci</hi> (Roma: Ex typographia linguarum
                    orientalium, 1759).</bibl>
                <bibl>Atiya A., "The monastery of St. Catherine and the Mount Sinai expedition" (<hi
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the American Philosophy Society</hi> 96
                    [1952]), 578-86.</bibl>
                <bibl>Atiya A., "Codex Arabicus (Sinai Arabic Ms. No.
                    514)," in <hi rend="italic">Homage to a Bookman: Essays on Manuscripts, Books
                        and Printing Written for Hans P. Kraus on his 60th Birthday</hi>, ed. H.
                    Lehmann-Haupt (Gebr. Mann Verlag: Berlin, 1967), 75-87.</bibl>
                <bibl>Bedjan P. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Mar Isaacus Ninivita. De perfectione
                        religiosa</hi> (Leipzig: Otto Harrassowitz 1909).</bibl>
                <bibl>Binggeli A., "Les trois David, copistes arabes de
                    Palestine," in <hi rend="italic">Manuscripta Graeca et Orientalia. Mélanges
                        monastiques et patristiques en l'honneur de Paul Géhin</hi>, Orientalia
                    Lovaniensia Analecta 243, eds. A. Binggeli, A. Boud'hors and M. Cassin (Leuven:
                    Peeters, 2016), 79-117.</bibl>
                <bibl>Blau J., <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of Christian Arabic. Based mainly on
                        South-Palestinian texts from the first millennium</hi>, Vol. 1, Corpus
                    Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 267, Subsidia 27, (Louvain: Secrétariat du
                    CorpusSCO, 1966).</bibl>
                <bibl>Blau J., <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of Christian Arabic. Based mainly on
                        South-Palestinian texts from the first millennium</hi>, Vol. 2, Corpus
                    Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium 268, Subsidia 28, (Louvain: Secrétariat du
                    CorpusSCO, 1967).</bibl>
                <bibl>Brock S., "Syriac into Greek at Mar Saba: The Translation of St. Isaac the
                    Syrian," in <hi rend="italic">Sabaite Ηeritage in the Orthodox Church from the
                        Fifth Century to the Present</hi>, ed. J. Patrich (Leuven: Peeters, 2001),
                    201-8.</bibl>
                <bibl>Chabot J., <hi rend="italic">De S. Isaaci Ninivitae vita, scriptis et
                        doctrina</hi> (Louvain: Lefever F. &amp; S., 1892).</bibl>
                <bibl>Chialà S., <hi rend="italic">Dall’ascesi eremitica alla misericordia infinita.
                        Ricerche su Isacco di Ninive e la sua fortuna</hi> (Firenze: Leo S. Olschki,
                    2002).</bibl>
                <bibl>Chialà S., "The Arabic Version of Saint Isaac the Syrian. A Channel of
                    Transmission of Syriac Literature," in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        International Patristics Conference ‘Saint Isaac the Syrian and His
                        Spiritual Legacy’ Held at the Sts Cyril and Methodius Institute for
                        Postgraduate Studies (Moscow, October 10-11, 2013)</hi>, ed. H. Alfeyev
                    (Yonkers [NY]: St Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 2015), 59-67.</bibl>
                <bibl>D’Ottone A., "Arabic Palaeography," in <hi rend="italic">Comparative Oriental
                        Manuscript Studies. An Introduction</hi> (s.l.: s.e., 2015), 271-6.</bibl>
                <bibl>D’Ottone Rambach A., "Sharing the written space: Contact and Interaction Between
                    Arabic and Other Scripts," in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International
                        Symposium: Navigating Language in the Early Islamic World (The Marco
                        Institute for Medieval and Renaissance Studies, The University of Tennessee,
                        Knoxville, 6-7 April 2018)</hi>, eds. A. Borrut and A.V. Vacca (Brepols:
                    Turnhout 2021 [forthcoming]).</bibl>
                <bibl>Esbroeck M. van, "Un feuillet oublié du codex arabe Or. 4226 à Strasbourg" (<hi
                        rend="italic">Analecta Bollandiana</hi> 96 [1978]) p. 383-4.</bibl>
                <bibl>Esbroeck M. van, "Le codex rescriptus Tischendorf 2 à Leipzig et Cyrille de
                    Scythopolis en version arabe," in <hi rend="italic">Actes du deuxième Congrès
                        international d’études arabes chrétiennes</hi>, ed. S. Khalil Samir (Rome:
                    Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1986) 81-91.</bibl>
                <bibl>Fleischer H., "<hi rend="Emphasis">Über einen
                        griechisch-arabischen Codex rescriptus der Leipziger
                        Universitäts-Bibliothek</hi>" (<hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen
                        Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 1 [1847]), 148-60.</bibl>
                <bibl><hi rend="Strong"><seg rend="normalweight">Fleischer</seg></hi> H., "<hi
                        rend="Emphasis">Beschreibung der von Prof. Tischendorf im Jahre 1853 aus dem
                        Morgenlange zurückgebrachten christlich-arabischen Handschriften</hi>" (<hi
                        rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 8
                    [1854]), 584-7.</bibl>
                <bibl>Gardthausen V., <hi rend="italic">Katalog der Handschriften der
                        Universitäts-Bibliothek zu Leipzig</hi>, Vol. 3, <hi rend="italic">Die
                        griechischen Handschriften</hi> (Leipzig: Harrassowitz 1898).</bibl>
                <bibl>Garitte G., "Homélie d'Ephrem "Sur la Mort et le Diable". Version géorgienne et
                    version arabe" (<hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 82 [1969]), 123-63.</bibl>
                <bibl>Graf G., <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der christlichen arabischen Literatur</hi>,
                    Vol. 1,<hi rend="italic"> Die Übersetzungen </hi>(Città del
                    Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1944).</bibl>
                <bibl>Graf G., <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der
                        christlichen arabischen Literatur</hi>, Vol.
                    2<hi rend="italic">, Die Schriftsteller bis zur Mitte des 15. Jahrhunderts </hi>(Città
                    del Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1947).</bibl>
                <bibl>Graf G., <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der christlichen arabischen Literatur</hi>,
                    Vol. 5<hi rend="italic">, Register </hi>(Città del
                    Vaticano: Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana, 1953).</bibl>
                <bibl>G. Graf, <hi rend="italic">Verzeichnis arabischer kirchlicher Termini</hi>
                    (Louvain: Imprimerie orientaliste L. Durbecq 1954).</bibl>
                <bibl>Griffith S., <hi rend="italic">Arabic Christianity in the Monasteries of
                        Ninth-Century Palestine</hi> (Aldershot: Ashgate, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>Heffening W., "Die griechische Ephraem-Paraenesis
                    gegen das Lachen in arabischer Übersetzung" (<hi rend="italic">Oriens
                        christianus</hi> 3:2 [1927]), 94-119.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hjälm M., "A Paleographical Study of Early Christian Arabic Manuscripts" (<hi
                        rend="italic">Collectanea Christiana Orientalia</hi> 17 [2020]), 37-77.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kessel G., "Sinai syr. 24 as an Important Witness to the Reception History of
                    Some Syriac Ascetic Texts," in <hi rend="italic">Sur les pas des Araméens
                        chrétiens. Mélanges offerts à Alain Desreumaux</hi>, Cahiers d’études
                    syriaques 1, eds. F. Briquel-Chatonnet and M. Debié (Paris: Geuthner, 2010),
                    207-18.</bibl>
                <bibl>Khalifé-Hachem E., "Isaac de Ninive," in <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de
                        Spiritualité</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ascétique et mystique, doctrine et
                        histoire</hi>, eds. M. Viller <hi rend="italic">et alii</hi>, Vol. 7.2
                    (Paris: Beauchesne, 1971), 2041-54.</bibl>
                <bibl>Khalifé-Hachem E., "Les versions arabes d’Isaac de Ninive," in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the 28th International Congress of Orientalists (Canberra,
                        6-12 January 1971)</hi>, ed. A. Davis (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1976),
                    36-7.</bibl>
                <bibl>Khayyat N. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Jean de Dalyatha. Les homélies I-XV</hi>
                    (Antélias: Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches Orientales; Hadath: Université
                    Antonine, 2007).</bibl>
                <bibl>Kračkovskij I., "Novozavjetnyj apokrif v arabskoj
                    rukopisi 885-886 goda po R. Hr." (<hi rend="italic">Vizantijskij Vremennik</hi>
                    14 [1909]), 246-75.</bibl>
                <bibl>Kračkovskij I., "K istorii sevastijskoj eparhii v IV veke" (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Hristianskij Vostok</hi> 2 [1913]), 154-5.</bibl>
                <bibl>Oestrup J., "Über zwei arabische Codices Sinaitici der Straßburger Universitäts-
                    und Landesbibliothek" (<hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift der Deutschen
                        Morgenländischen Gesellschaft</hi> 51:3 [1897]), 453-71.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pataridze T., "Les discours ascétiques d’Isaac de Ninive. Étude de la tradition
                    géorgienne et de ses rapports avec les autres versions" (<hi rend="italic">Le
                        Muséon</hi> 124:1&amp;2 [2011]), 27-58.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pataridze T., "Isaac from the Monastery of Mar Saba. The History of the Origin of
                    the Multiple Translations of St Isaac the Syrian’s Work and Their Distribution
                    in the Holy Lavra," in <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International
                        Patristics Conference ‘Saint Isaac the Syrian and His Spiritual Legacy’ Held
                        at the Sts Cyril and Methodius Institute for Postgraduate Studies (Moscow,
                        October 10-11, 2013)</hi>, ed. H. Alfeyev (Yonkers [NY]: St Vladimir’s
                    Seminary Press, 2015), 39-50. </bibl>
                <bibl>Pataridze T., "Christian Literature in Arabic in
                    the Early Islamic Period (8th-10th c.): The Circulation of Texts and Ideas
                    between the Greek, Syriac, Arabic, and Georgian Communities," (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Le Muséon</hi> 132, 1&amp;2 [2019]), 199-222.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pirard M. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Ἀββᾶ Ἰσαὰκ τοῦ Σύρου. Λόγοι ἀσκητικοί. Κριτικὴ
                        ἔκδοσι</hi> (Ἅγιον Ὄρος: Ἱερὰ Μονὴ Ἰβήρων, 2012).</bibl>
                <bibl>Treiger A., "Syro-Arabic Translations in Abbasid Palestine: The Case of John of
                    Apamea’s Letter of Stillness (Sinai Ar. 549)," (<hi rend="italic">Parole de
                        l’Orient</hi> 39 [2014]), 79-131.</bibl>
                <bibl>Wickersheimer E., <hi rend="italic">Catalogue général des manuscrits des
                        bibliothèques publiques de France</hi>, Vol. 47, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Strasbourg</hi> (Paris: Librairie Plon, 1923).</bibl>
                <bibl>Wright W., <hi rend="italic">A Grammar of the Arabic Language</hi>, Vol. 1
                    (Beirut: Librairie du Liban, 1974<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
