<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">The Body and Its Senses in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Madrashe
                        contra haereses</hi> and<hi rend="italic"> Madrashe de fide</hi>: Polemics
                    and Epistemology</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Michelle</forename>
                        <surname>Freeman</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2freeman</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Michelle Freeman</author>
                        <title level="a">The Body and Its Senses in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Madrashe contra haereses</hi> and<hi rend="italic"> Madrashe de
                                fide</hi>: Polemics and Epistemology</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2Freeman.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="417" to="453">417-453</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="3"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>Ephrem</term>
                    <term>Madrashe</term>
                    <term>Epistemology</term>
                    <term>Body</term>
                    <term>Senses</term>
                    <term>Perception</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">In his vast corpus of madrashe, Ephrem sometimes makes seemingly
                    inconsistent valuations of the body and its senses, praising them as vehicles
                    for experiencing God on the one hand and degrading them as foul, lowly, and
                    incapable of understanding God on the other. This article compares Ephrem’s
                    different assessments of the body and senses in his <hi rend="italic">Madrashe
                        contra haereses</hi> 42-44 and <hi rend="italic">Madrashe de fide</hi> 27,
                    41, 70, and 75. It will offer a twofold solution to understanding their
                    conflicting views of human corporeality by attending to Ephrem’s polemical
                    rhetoric and epistemological underpinnings. I argue that, while Ephrem shifts
                    his valuation of the body and its senses in accordance with his polemical
                    agenda, his recognition of the body’s centrality in acquiring knowledge remains
                    consistent. This argument advances our understanding of the perception-centered
                    epistemologies of many late ancient Christians, who drew from broader Greek and
                    Syrian philosophical contexts.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>

            <cit xml:lang="en">
                <quote>
                    <l>He divided up and gave. He gave to us the earth</l>
                    <l>For the feet; he gave to us light</l>
                    <l>For the eyes; and for the ears</l>
                    <l>He gave sounds and words. In these things which he gave </l>
                    <l>He is found trustworthy in everything that he promised. </l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Madrasha contra haereses</hi> 43.24</l>
                    <l>Look: the senses of the sons of the High One,</l>
                    <l>Though subtle and spiritual,</l>
                    <l>Are yet insufficient.</l>
                    <l>Therefore, cease from discussion,</l>
                    <l>O dense senses of the fat body,</l>
                    <l>Causing pus to flow!</l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Madrasha de fide </hi>75.26-27</l>
                </quote>
            </cit>

            <div xml:id="h25n2freeman.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem wrote amid intense competition for an orthodox
                    Christian identity in fourth-century Syria. In over four hundred extant <hi
                        rend="italic">madrashe</hi> or hymns, he frequently engages in polemics
                    centered around the human capacity to know God, responding to various
                    theological opponents: Marcionites, Manichaeans, Bardaisanites, and a slew of
                    neo-Arian groups. As the above stanzas demonstrate, sometimes Ephrem presents
                    seemingly contradictory views in his mass of hymnography. In the first, <hi
                        rend="italic">Madrasha contra haereses</hi> 43, he lauds the human body as a
                    vehicle for experiencing God’s creation. He claims that humans come to trust in
                    God’s promises through their senses and the material world perceived through
                    them. In the second, <hi rend="italic">Madrasha de fide</hi> 75, Ephrem takes a
                    different tack: he deprecates the body and its senses, which are too limited to
                    understand God. He associates the body with density, fatness, and pus, conjuring
                    negative and abject imagery to emphasize its distance from the divine. These
                    inconsistent perspectives on the body raise questions about Ephrem’s
                    epistemology: what role does the human body play in knowing God? What are the
                    body’s limits in understanding the divine? What is God’s relationship to His
                    material creation, including human corporeality?</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This article will compare Ephrem’s assessments of the body and senses in several
                    madrashe from these two cycles of hymns—the <hi rend="italic">Madrashe contra
                        haereses</hi> (<hi rend="italic">McH</hi>) and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Madrashe de fide</hi> (<hi rend="italic">MdF</hi>). It will offer a twofold
                    solution to understanding their different attitudes toward human corporeality by
                    attending to Ephrem’s polemical rhetoric and epistemological underpinnings. I
                    argue that, while Ephrem shifts his valuation of the body and its senses in
                    accordance with his polemical agenda, his recognition of the body’s centrality
                    in acquiring knowledge remains consistent. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem’s ostensibly divergent views of the body have caused scholars to produce
                    two different assessments of his epistemology. On the one hand, many readers
                    have highlighted Ephrem’s emphasis on the limited human capacity for knowing
                    God, who is separated from creation by a chasm that can only partially be
                        breached.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"> For
                            the chasm and partial breaching of it, see Ute Possekel, “Ephrem’s
                            Doctrine of God,” in <hi rend="italic">God in Early Christian Thought:
                                Essays in Memory of Lloyd G. Patterson</hi>, Supplements to Vigiliae
                            Christianae 94, ed. Andrew McGowan (Leiden: Brill, 2009), 202–6; Mark J.
                            Mourachian, "Human Freedom in the Context of the Theological
                            Anthropology of St. Ephrem the Syrian," (PhD diss., Catholic University
                            of America, 2012), 106–23; Thomas Kathanar Koonammakkal, "The
                            Self-Revealing God and Man in Ephrem" (<hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 6
                            [1993]), 233–43; Paul S. Russell, “Ephraem the Syrian on the Utility of
                            Language and the Place of Silence'' (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Early
                                Christian Studies</hi> 8 [2000]), 30–37; Sebastian Brock, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision of Saint
                                Ephrem</hi>, Cistercian Studies 124 (Spencer, MS: Cistercian
                            Publications, 1992; orig. published Rome: Center for Indian and
                            Inter-Religious Studies, 1985), 26–9; Jeffrey Wickes, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Bible and Poetry in Late Antique Mesopotamia: Ephrem’s Hymns on
                                Faith, </hi>Christianity in Late Antiquity 4 (Berkeley: University
                            of California Press, 2019), 11–42. For Ephrem’s reference to the chasm,
                            see <hi rend="italic">MdF </hi>69.11 and <hi rend="italic">MdF
                            </hi>15.5. English translation of <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> in Jeffrey
                            Wickes, trans., <hi rend="italic">St. Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns on
                                Faith</hi>, Fathers of the Church 130 (Washington, D.C.: Catholic
                            University of America Press, 2015), and Syriac text in E. Beck, ed and
                            trans., <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de
                                Fide</hi>, CSCO 73 (Louvain: CSCO, 1955). I draw all English
                            translations of the <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> from Wickes. </p></note>
                    According to Ephrem, humans can know God only to the extent that He has revealed
                    himself through symbols in nature, liturgy, and Scripture,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> On Ephrem’s notion of symbols
                            and their partial revelation in Scripture, nature, sacraments, and
                            Christ, see Predrag Bukovec, “Gotteserkenntnis in Ephraems des Syrers
                            Hymn de fide” (<hi rend="italic">Saeculum</hi> 60 [2010]), 17–40;
                            Georges Saber, "La typologie sacramentaire et baptismale de Saint
                            Ephrem" (<hi rend="italic">ParOr</hi> 4 [1973]), 73–91; Sidney H.
                            Griffith, “The Image of the Image Maker in the Poetry of Ephrem the
                            Syrian” (<hi rend="italic">StPatr</hi> 25 [1993]), 258-69; Edmund Beck,
                                <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie des heiligen Ephrem in seinen Hymnen
                                über den Glauben</hi>, Studia Anselmiana 21 (Rome: Pontificium
                            Institutum S. Anselmi, 1949), 23–34; Seeley Joseph Beggiana, “The
                            Typological Approach of Syriac Sacramental Theology” (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Theological Studies</hi> 64 [2003]), 543–57; Mourachian, “Human
                            Freedom,” 108–29; and Koonammakkal, “The Self-Revealing God”; and Brock,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye</hi>, 53–84. The classic study of
                            symbols in early Syriac literature, particularly that of Ephrem and
                            Aphrahat, is Robert Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and
                                Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac Tradition</hi> (Cambridge:
                            Cambridge University Press, 1975).</p></note> which humans can observe
                    through faith, love, and madrashic paradoxes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                        n="3"><p rend="footnote text">For emphases on faith and love in Ephrem, see
                            Sidney Griffith, “Faith Seeking Understanding in the Thought of St.
                            Ephrem,” in <hi rend="italic">Faith Seeking Understanding: Learning and
                                the Catholic Tradition: Selected Paper from the Symposium and
                                Convocation Celebrating the Saint Anselm College Centennial</hi>,
                            ed. George Charles Berthold (Manchester, NH: Saint Anselm College Press,
                            1991); Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye</hi>, 43–6 and 67–84;
                            Charis Vleugels, “The Response to Chasm and Bridge: The Wings of Truth
                            and Attitude in Ephrem the Syrian’s Hymns on Faith” (<hi rend="italic"
                                >The Harp</hi> 22 [2007]), 183–92; Mourachian, “Human Freedom,”
                            129–69. For a classic explanation of Ephrem’s paradoxical approach to
                            theology, see Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Luminous Eye</hi>, 24–5.
                        </p></note> These symbols give knowledge of God’s existence but not of the
                    mode or character of his being. As Jeffrey Wickes states regarding Ephrem’s <hi
                        rend="italic">MdF</hi>, Ephrem does not take issue with specific theological
                    doctrines <hi rend="italic">per se</hi> but rather with their mode of inquiry.
                    To proceed with logical and grammatical methods instead of Scripture and symbols
                    is to arrogate an intimate knowledge of God’s hidden nature.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> Wickes, <hi rend="italic">St.
                                Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, 43–6; David Bundy, “Language and the
                            Knowledge of God in Ephrem Syrus” (<hi rend="italic">The Patristic and
                                Byzantine Review</hi> 5 [1986]), 9–103. </p></note> Thus, most
                    scholars claim that Ephrem thought the limited nature of human knowledge
                    circumscribes human understanding of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> See especially E. Beck, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie und Erkenntnislehre</hi> (Louvain:
                            CSCO, 1980), 135-47. </p></note> This line of interpretation, however,
                    tends to focus heavily on knowledge as a cognitive, abstract experience. These
                    scholars refer to limited knowledge, knowledge merely of God’s existence,
                    faith-based inquiry, and revealed knowledge. They largely fail to engage
                    Ephrem’s frequent discussion of the body and perception as instruments—albeit
                    limited ones—of experiencing God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Beck, <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie</hi>, 23–34
                            attends briefly to Ephrem’s sensory language in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >MdF</hi>, although with little focus on the importance of
                            perception in knowledge. </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">On the other hand, Susan Ashbrook Harvey highlights Ephrem’s attention to
                    corporeality and the senses. Harvey proposes that, “Rather than seeing Creator
                    and creation separated by an unbreachable chasm, Ephrem delights in exploring
                    the created universe for its endless capacity to reveal its Maker” and that
                    “Ephrem is concerned with knowledge that is non-cognitive yet genuinely
                    revelatory of divine being, truth, and action.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7"
                        n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> Susan Ashbrook Harvey, “St. Ephrem on the
                            Scent of Salvation” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological
                                Studies</hi> 49 [1998]), 109–28.</p></note> In her view, Ephrem,
                    along with other late ancient Christians, conceives of sensory experience as a
                    means of directly encountering divine revelation in nature and liturgy.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> In addition to n.
                            6, see Susan Ashbrook Harvey, <hi rend="italic">Scenting Salvation:
                                Ancient Christianity and the Olfactory Imagination</hi>, The
                            Transformation of the Classical heritage 42 (Berkeley: University of
                            California Press, 2006). </p></note> Harvey’s work is part of a more
                    significant scholarly attempt to understand the perceptually based
                    epistemologies of late ancient Christians. After Christianity was legalized and
                    adopted by Roman imperial officials, Christians increasingly engaged the
                    potential of the material world as a point of interaction with the divine. In
                    particular, scholars have pointed to the body’s senses – sight, touch, smell,
                    sound, and taste – as mechanisms for knowing and experiencing God.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Major analyses
                            include Patricia Cox Miller, <hi rend="italic">The Corporeal
                                Imagination: Signifying the Holy in Late Antiquity</hi>,
                            Divinations: Rereading Late Ancient Religion (Philadelphia: University
                            of Pennsylvania Press, 2009), which labels this change in late ancient
                            Christian epistemology the “material turn”; Susan Ashbrook Harvey,
                            “Locating the Sensing Body: Perception and Religious Identity in Late
                            Antiquity,” in <hi rend="italic">Religion and the Self in Antiquity,
                            </hi>ed. David Brakke, Michael L. Satlow, and Steven Weitzman
                            (Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2005), 140–62; and Georgia
                            Frank, <hi rend="italic">The Memory of the Eyes: Pilgrims to Living
                                Saints in Late Antiquity</hi>, The Transformation of the Classical
                            Heritage 30 (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000). For essays
                            on the various late ancient Christian conceptions of the “spiritual
                            senses,” which in some cases were transformed or well-trained physical
                            senses, see Paul L. Gavrilyuk and Sarah Coakley, eds., <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Spiritual Senses: Perceiving God in Western Christianity</hi>
                            (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012).</p></note> Such work is
                    aided by studies that highlight the physiological basis of ancient perceptual
                    and cognitive theories.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For example, the materialist analysis of
                            Aristotelian perceptual theory in Deborah K. Modrak, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aristotle: The Power of Perception</hi> (Chicago: University of
                            Chicago Press, 1987); the psycho-somatic emphases in Philip J. Van der
                            Eijk, <hi rend="italic">Medicine and Philosophy in Classical Antiquity:
                                Doctors and Philosophers on Nature, Soul, Health, and Disease</hi>
                            (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005); the examination of the
                            materiality of ancient and medieval conceptions of memory in Mary
                            Carruthers, <hi rend="italic">The Book of Memory: A Study of Memory in
                                Medieval Culture</hi>, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> ed.
                            (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008); and the analysis of
                            ancient psycho-somatic dynamics of vision in A. Mark Smith, <hi
                                rend="italic">From Sight to Light: The Passage from Ancient to
                                Modern Optics</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                        2015).</p></note> This line of thinking proposes that many ancient
                    Christians had epistemologies firmly grounded in perception and corporeality. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Both of these interpretations of Ephrem’s conception of knowing God—limited
                    cognitive knowledge, yet rich sensory experience of his creation and
                    revelation—are well-founded, based on the hymns I analyze in this paper. The
                    varying polemical contexts of Ephrem’s madrashe generate his shifting
                    epistemological emphases, sometimes making his statements appear discordant. I
                    will address both his rhetorical situation and epistemological commitments to
                    analyze Ephrem’s seemingly disparate evaluations of the body introduced above.
                    As Ute Possekel notes, “Ephrem formulated his doctrine of God to a significant
                    extent with apologetic purposes in mind.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11"
                        n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> Possekel, “Ephrem’s Doctrine of God,” 198.
                        </p></note> Not only apologetic but blatantly polemical are many of his
                    madrashe, meant to sway listeners toward his brand of Christianity.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> On Ephrem’s
                            madrashe as a means of setting the boundaries of Orthodoxy, gaining
                            adherents for it, and polemicizing heretical doctrines, see Sidney
                            Griffith, “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint Ephrem’s Hymns
                            against Heresies,” in <hi rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient
                                Chrsitianity: Essays on Late Antique Thought and Culture in Honor of
                                R. A. Markus</hi>, ed. William E. Klingshirn and Mark Vessey (Ann
                            Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1999), 97–114; "The Marks of the
                            True Church According to Ephrem's Hymns Against Heresies,” in <hi
                                rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on Continuity and Change in
                                Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professir Han J. W. Drijvers</hi>,
                            eds. G. J. Reinink and Alexander Cornelis Klugkist (Louven: Peeters,
                            1999), 125–40; and Flavia Ruani, ed. and trans., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Éphrem de Nisibe: Hymnes contre les hérésies</hi>, Bibliotèque de
                            L’Orient Chrétien (Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2018), IX–LVI. For these
                            hymns as a means of instruction, see Jeffrey Wickes, “Between Liturgy
                            and School: Reassessing the Performative Context of Ephrem’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Madrashe</hi>” (<hi rend="italic">Journal of Early
                                Christian Studies</hi> 26 [2018], 25-51.</p></note> In the <hi
                        rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44, the focus of the first part of my analysis,
                    his adversaries are Marcionites, who disparage the human body as a wicked
                        vessel;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> It
                            should be noted that the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> is a group of hymns
                            that attacks a wide range of theological opponents: Marcionites,
                            Bardaisanites, Manichaeans, Arians, and even Jews. In <hi rend="italic"
                                >McH</hi> 42–44, however, Ephrem directs most of his attention
                            against Marcionite ideas. </p></note> and in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >MdF</hi> 27, 41, 70, 75, which I examine in the second part of my analysis,
                    he attacks theological “investigators,” who try to discern God’s nature. I have
                    chosen these particular madrashe for their focus on the body (<foreign
                        xml:lang="syr">ܦܓܪܐ</foreign>) and the senses (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܪ̈ܓܫܐ</foreign>), as well as for their aforementioned contrasting
                    perspectives on the body.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Notably, the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> have
                            received meager scholarly attention to date, and <hi rend="italic"
                                >McH</hi> 42–44 virtually none. Sustained analyses of the <hi
                                rend="italic">McH</hi> are Phil J. Botha, "The Poetic Face of
                            Rhetoric: Ephrem's Polemics against the Jews and Heretics in Contra
                            Haereses 25" (<hi rend="italic">Acta Patristica et Byzantina</hi> 2
                            [1991]), 16–36; idem, "The Textual Strategy of Ephrem the Syrian's Hymn
                            Contra Haereses I" (<hi rend="italic">Acta Patristica et Byzantina</hi>
                            15 [2004]), 57–75; Griffith, “Setting Right the Church”; idem, “Marks of
                            the True Church”; idem, "St. Ephrem, Bar Daysan, and the Clash of
                            Madrashe in Aram: readings in St. Ephrem's Hymni contra Haereses" (<hi
                                rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 21 [2006]), 447–72; idem,
                            "'Denominationalism' in Fourth-Century Syria: Readings in Saint
                            Ephraem's Hymns against Heresies,” in <hi rend="italic">The Garb of
                                Being: Embodiment and the Pursuit of Holiness in Late Ancient
                                Christianity, </hi>Orthodox Christianity and Contemporary Thought,
                            eds. Georgia Frank, Susan Holman, and Andrew S. Jacobs (New York:
                            Fordham University Press, 2020), 79–100; Christine Shepardson, <hi
                                rend="italic">Anti-Judaism and Christian Orthodoxy: Ephrem’s Hymns
                                in Fourth-Century Syria</hi> (Washington, D. C.: Catholic University
                            of America Press, 2008); and Ruani, <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de
                                Nisibe</hi>, 2018. </p></note> I will consider the rhetorical
                    situatedness of each set of hymns, allowing that Ephrem’s emphases may vary in
                    order to meet the practical needs of his listeners. Nevertheless, I will show
                    that there is an underlying epistemological assumption in these hymns that gives
                    their different approaches coherence: Ephrem conceives of all knowledge as
                    ultimately grounded in the body and perception.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15"
                        n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> In addition to Harvey’s work cited above,
                            other serious treatments of perception in Ephrem are E. Beck, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie, 135-47, </hi>which
                            discusses Ephrem’s references to corporeal eyes and the eyes of the soul
                            and his superficial familiarity with Stoic theories of perception and
                            cognition; Phil J. Botha, “The Significance of the Senses in St.
                            Ephrem’s Description of Paradise” (<hi rend="italic">Acta Patristica et
                                Byzantina</hi> 5 [1994]), 28–37, which argues for a metaphorical
                            interpretation of Ephrem’s sensory language; Ute Possekel, <hi
                                rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts in the
                                Writings of Ephrem the Syrian </hi>(Louvain: Peeters, 1999),
                            187–229, which convincingly demonstrates Ephrem’s familiarity with Greek
                            medico-philosophical theories of perception, particularly that of the
                            Stoics; and Wickes, <hi rend="italic">Bible and Poetry</hi>, 84-103,
                            which demonstrates Ephrem’s use of visual imagery and language of sight
                            to instruct his audiences, rather than relying on education for
                            theological understanding. </p></note> In his view, which conceives of a
                    tight unity between body and soul (or mind),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> For Ephrem’s conception of the tight unity
                            between body and soul (or mind), see Sebastian P. Brock, “The Dispute
                            between Body and Soul: An Example of a Long-Lived Mesopotamian Literary
                            Genre” (<hi rend="italic">ARAM</hi> 1 [1989]), 53–64 and <hi
                                rend="italic">The Luminous Eye</hi>, 36–8; Susan Ashbrook Harvey,
                                <hi rend="italic">Asceticism and Society in Crisis: John of Ephesus
                                and the Lives of the Eastern Saints</hi>, The Transformation of the
                            Classical Heritage 18 (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1990),
                            4–13; Jaehyun Kim, “Body and Soul in Ephrem the Syrian” (<hi
                                rend="italic">Syriac Studies</hi> [2002]), 79–117; and Thomas
                            Koonammakkal, “Ephrem’s Polemics on the Human Body” (<hi rend="italic"
                                >StPatr</hi> 35 [2001]), 428–32. </p></note> it is imprudent to
                    denigrate the body, which is humanity’s means of experiencing God’s activity. It
                    is also improper, however, to pursue theology to understand the nuances of God’s
                    being because all knowledge is derived from the body, which is limited in its
                    capacity to know God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> In a recent article, Blake Hartung (“The
                            Authorship and Dating of the Syriac Corpus of Ephrem of Nisibis: A
                            Reassessment” [<hi rend="italic color(0A0A0C)">Zeitschrift für Antikes
                                Christentum</hi> 22 (2018)], 296–321) has described the lack of
                            consensus regarding the authorship of all the hymns attributed to
                            Ephrem. Collected in thematic cycles by later editors, scholars
                            acknowledge that individual hymns and stanzas that Ephrem did not author
                            were included in these collections. This leaves us to wonder if the
                            contrasting perspectives of different hymns, such as those I examine
                            here, indicate multiple authors. This conclusion, I believe, is
                            unnecessary with regard to the two sets of hymns I analyze, as this
                            paper will demonstrate. </p></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2freeman.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Perceiving God: The Healed Human Body in <hi rend="italic">MCH</hi>
                    42-44</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">In Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44, praise for the body and its senses
                    is inseparably intertwined with clever and sarcastic arguments against
                    Marcionite dualism.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Syriac text in E. Beck, ed. and trans, <hi
                                rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra
                                Haereses</hi>, CSCO 77 (Louven: Peeters, 1957). Syriac text and
                            French translation, whose numbering I follow here, in Domonique
                            Cerbelaud, trans., <hi rend="italic">Ephrem de Nisibe: Hymnes contre les
                                heresies; Hymnes contra Julien</hi>, vol. 2 (Paris: Les editions du
                            Cerf, 2017). English translations of the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> have
                            been produced by myself and two of my colleagues, Nathan Tilley and
                            Maroun El Houkayem, both of Duke University. While Cerbelaud claims
                            Ephrem produced these hymns in Nisibis, Blake Hartung, “The Authorship
                            and Dating” demonstrates that our meager knowledge of the fourth-century
                            Syrian Christian context does not allow for precise claims about
                            provenance for most of Ephrem’s hymns. Ruani, <hi rend="italic">Éphrem
                                de Nisibe</hi>, XXVI–XXVII argues that some of the hymns were
                            composed in Nisibis and others in Edessa. </p></note> According to
                    Ephrem, Marcion preached that the god of the Old Testament was the creator of
                    the physical universe, who fashioned everything out of wicked matter (<hi
                        style="font-size:14pt">ܗܘܠܐ</hi>, Greek: ὕλη) and who “loves” the material
                    body; the “Stranger” God, who was present in Christ and who “hates the body,” on
                    the other hand, came to save humanity from the evil and sin inherent in its
                        corporeality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For Ephrem’s conception of the Marcionite view,
                            see Cerbelaud, <hi rend="italic">Ephrem de Nisibe</hi>, 11–3;
                            Koonammakkal, “Ephrem’s Polemics on the Human Body”; Botha, “The Textual
                            Strategy”; and David Kiger, “Fire in the Bread, Life in the Body: The
                            Pneumatology of Ephrem the Syrian,” (PhD diss., Marquette University,
                            2009), 106–12. Cf. <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 34.15-16. </p></note> For
                    Marcion, Christ came to heal the body of its innate lameness; Ephrem agrees that
                    Christ healed the body, but not, as I will show, because he thinks it was
                    created wicked, but because it was subsequently wounded by sin. Marcionites, he
                    claims, disparaged the body to such an extent that they considered it to be of
                    one nature with demons.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.4,17.
                        </p></note> They denigrate the material body as a wicked and depraved vessel
                    as opposed to the immaterial soul, which the Stranger loves.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> See <hi rend="italic"
                                >McH</hi> 42.3–4; This is not necessarily an accurate representation
                            of Marcionite views, but rather Ephrem’s rhetorical stereotype. My study
                            is not concerned with historical Marcionites’ beliefs but with how
                            Ephrem represents them. The extent of the threat that Marcionism posed
                            in Ephrem’s communities, or in the fourth century in general, is
                            unclear. </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">For Ephrem, Christ healed the body through his Incarnation, but not because he
                    thought it was created evil and sinful. How can Christ hate the body “even
                    though he dwells in it?” asks Ephrem.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42.3. For a comprehensive study of Ephrem’s
                            perspective on the role of healing in salvation history, see Aho
                            Shemunkasho, <hi rend="italic">Healing in the Theology of Saint
                                Ephrem</hi>, Gorgias Dissertations: Near Eastern Studies 1
                            (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2002).</p></note> Indeed, Christ “has as
                    a temple the body, which he loves” and “desires that it be his habitation.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42.2, 4.</p></note> Ephrem argues that Christ
                    would not have chosen to become incarnate in a human body if it were created
                    wicked and he hated it. Furthermore, he says that “With the body he would not
                    mingle his mysteries, if it were from the Wicked One.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.3. </p></note> While he does not conceive
                    of corporeality as wicked in its origins, he does admit that Christ came to heal
                    the body and its senses because they were worn out by past generations of humans
                    and thus in need of restoration to their earlier health:</p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>If it is the case that the body is a detestable instrument</l>
                        <l>Of the detestable Wicked One: its flutes grew old,</l>
                        <l>the body’s sense organs (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܓܫܝ ܓܘܫܡܐ</foreign> ),
                            and our Lord came </l>
                        <l>setting them straight. He made firm his harp, </l>
                        <l>Which he healed; he gave health to the body.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.19. </p></note>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem thus vindicates human corporeality, which was not created wicked and
                    decrepit by God but is merely wounded and erring.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Ruani, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Éphrem de Nisibe</hi>, LII–LIV also reaches this conclusion.
                        </p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem also proves the body’s intrinsic goodness by demonstrating that the
                    creator God of the Old Testament is the same God that sent Christ to heal human
                    corporeality; they are not distinct entities with opposing views of the body as
                    the Marcionites claim, but rather they both love the body. He shows this by
                    paralleling instances of positive, salvific activity toward the body by both the
                    Old Testament God and Christ. In the Old Testament, God cleanses Miryam and
                    Nahamon, just as Christ cleanses the ten lepers in the gospel.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.16.</p></note> God created people with
                    eyes and hands to do good, just as Christ healed them to do good in
                        redemption.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42.1, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>.
                        </p></note> Moreover, just as God had Moses destroy the eyes and ears of the
                    golden calf to guide Israel away from idolatry, Christ heals the eyes and
                        ears.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.11. </p></note> Because both God and
                    Christ positively value the body and its health, Ephrem considers<anchor
                        xml:id="Hlk94549785"/> it “wicked impiety” if “the Physician is more beloved
                    / Than the Fashioner, / And the Surgeon more beloved / Than the Creator.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.7. </p></note> Rather, these two are the
                    same God doing the same work: </p>
                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>That is to say, the body is between the Healer</l>
                        <l>And the Fashioner. The one they have blamed, </l>
                        <l>And the other they have praised. Their works are one . . . </l>
                        <l>The work of the carpenter, the carpenter then </l>
                        <l>Is able to repair. A blacksmith, too, </l>
                        <l>Can repair the work of a blacksmith. And the Son of the Creator, </l>
                        <l>can repair the work of the Creator. Because healing, too, </l>
                        <l>Is a second creation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.8–9. </p></note>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>

                <p xml:lang="en">The body is thus innately good, for God both made and continually guides it in
                    goodness. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In these three hymns, Christ directs his healing power primarily toward the sense
                    organs—the eyes, mouth, and ears—thus reorienting the human sensorium so humans
                    can experience and know God. Although they were worn out, “Our Lord came /
                    setting them straight. / He made firm his harp, / which he healed; he gave /
                    health to the body.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.19. </p></note> When Christ “found the
                    body blind” he “gave it light.” He “opened the eyes of the body, and its ears he
                        restored.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.10–11. </p></note> Taunting his opponents,
                    Ephrem sarcastically claims that “the Stranger / who hates the body, countless
                    deaf and tongue-tied / he healed.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.15. </p></note> It makes no sense to
                    Ephrem that Christ could heal the body, as he does in the gospel, if he hated
                    it. This positive restoration of the senses is the same as that performed by God
                    in the Old Testament, for </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>They do not indeed put new wine</l>
                        <l>In old wineskins. But he gave the senses (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                                >ܪ̈ܓܫܐ</foreign>), </l>
                        <l>According to the commandments: a new ear</l>
                        <l>According to the commandment. For by the ear that has grown old</l>
                        <l>New melodies are not heard. </l>
                        <l>This is a marvel, that he gave commandments</l>
                        <l>That are not the old ones, and he gave members (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                                >ܗܕ̈ܡܐ</foreign>)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">Possekel, <hi rend="italic">Evidence of
                                        Greek Philosophical Concepts</hi>, 188 notes that Ephrem
                                    often uses “senses (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܓܫܐ</foreign>)”
                                    and “limbs (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܕ̈ܡܐ</foreign>)
                                    synonymously. </p></note></l>
                        <l>That are not foreign! The senses, which he healed, </l>
                        <l>Proclaim him. For even if the sounds that he gave</l>
                        <l>Are new, they are not foreign!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                                    rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 44.6–7.
                                </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>

                <p xml:lang="en">In Ephrem’s view, God gave new commandments when Moses destroyed the tablets
                    inscribed with the Law.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For this theme more broadly in Ephrem, see
                            Shemunkasho, <hi rend="italic">Healing in the Theology of Saint
                                Ephrem</hi>, 109 and 181.</p></note> Along with these new
                    commandments, he renewed the senses so that humans might improve their
                    relationship with God and become more familiar with him through their bodies,
                    which are not “foreign” to him.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">That the body is not of the same nature as the demons and Satan—and therefore not
                    created wicked—Ephrem also demonstrates through Christ’s healing of human bodies
                    but not demonic ones. His account of Christ’s exorcising of the Gerasene
                    demoniac reduces the Marcionite argument to absurdity. Recalling how Christ sent
                    the demons into pigs, he says that Satan “asked for things contrary to himself,”
                    namely, he asked for a body with legs instead of his “lame” serpentine body.
                    Christ acquiesced so that the demons “might be disgraced”—sent into swine to
                    drown—and not, Ephrem mocks, because “Our Lord / who healed the lame, to the
                    serpent who is lame / in a lame body / he gave feet . . .” That is, if
                    Marcionites claim that demons and the human body are of the same nature, they
                    would be forced to give the ridiculous interpretation that Jesus was healing the
                    demons’ bodies by sending them into pigs. Rather, just as God “crippled the
                    serpent,” so Christ “drowned in the lake” the pigs possessed by the
                        demons.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic">
                                McH</hi> 43.1–6.</p></note> Their work is the same, directed not
                    toward transforming innately wicked bodies, whether human or demonic, but toward
                    healing the wounded human sensorium alone. Ephrem further highlights the illogic
                    of the Marcionites’ claim by reasoning, </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>And if, as they have determined, one is the nature </l>
                        <l>Of the body and the demons, and our Lord healed </l>
                        <l>Its (the body’s) feet and its hands, its eyes and its ears, </l>
                        <l>And the rest of its sense organs (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                                >ܪ̈ܓܫܘܗܝ</foreign>), then the whole demon</l>
                        <l>He has put in good order and made it to stand up and act impiously!<note
                                place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.17. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Again, Ephrem finds it ridiculous to conclude that Christ healed demons alongside
                    human bodies due to the supposed likeness between the human body and demons. The
                    absurdity of this conclusion, he feels, demonstrates the ontological distinction
                    between the two. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">According to these hymns, the body and senses play an instrumental role in God’s
                    salvific plan. They are the chief means of experiencing and communicating with
                    God through the sacraments and Scripture. Whereas Christ gave pigs to the
                    demons, “His bread and blood / he gave to the body. With the body he would not
                    mingle / his mysteries, if they were from the Wicked One.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.3. </p></note> The Eucharistic elements
                    are consumed by the body, tasted by the mouth, creating a relationship between
                    Christ and the human recipient. He exclaims, since Jesus did not hate the body
                    but came to heal it, “Blessed is the one who gave / the hands with which we may
                    receive his body!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.22. </p></note> The salvific power of
                    Christ’s body and the bodily mechanism, the hands, which God fashioned for
                    humans to receive it in the Eucharist, exhibit the value of corporeality for
                    salvation. The ear, too, is “necessary,” and Christ “opened it for his words” so
                    that people might hear Scripture, the main source of revelation from God in
                    Ephrem’s view.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.20. </p></note> God fashioned and healed
                    the human sensorium specifically in order to perceive and experience his
                    salvific power: </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>The mouth that he gave is for his bread </l>
                        <l>And for his cup; the eyes that he created </l>
                        <l>Are for his books; and for his church </l>
                        <l>He also gave the feet. And if to the Stranger</l>
                        <l>These things are useful, unbelievers are vanquished!<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.25. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">By God’s design and Christ’s healing, humans have a mouth and taste to partake of
                    the Eucharistic body and blood; they have eyes so they can see the words written
                    in Scripture, and they have feet to assemble at church and worship. In sum, the
                    body is how humans experience God’s activity in the world and attain
                    salvation.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Just as God modeled the body around the salvific plan, so also he constructed the
                    world around the human body so that the body and sense perception are, in their
                    very essence, beneficial for encountering God and his creation. By harmonizing
                    the world to human corporeality, God demonstrates the love that he and his Son
                    have for the body: </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>He divided up and gave. He gave to us the earth </l>
                        <l>For the feet; he gave to us light</l>
                        <l>For the eyes; for the ears</l>
                        <l>He gave sounds and words. In these things which he gave </l>
                        <l>He is found trustworthy in everything that he promised.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 43.24. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>

                <p xml:lang="en">Here, Ephrem notably ascribes the source of belief to the body and creation.
                    Humans come to believe in God's promises by the material world and its objects
                    of perception—earth, light, and sound—and by the limbs and organs he gave to
                    experience them. He berates his opponents because, “As much as they alienate
                    [Him], they come to encounter / our Creator, against whom they have blasphemed,
                    / although they do not perceive (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܪ̈ܓܝܫܝܢ</foreign>
                        ).”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 44.11. </p></note> In other words, he attacks
                    Marcionites not for failing to understand some abstract doctrine about God, but
                    specifically for not correctly interpreting sensory input that demonstrates
                    God’s beneficent disposition toward human corporeality. Ephrem thus grants an
                    inescapably positive valuation to the body and senses as a means of experiencing
                    God’s activity. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is noteworthy that in <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44, Ephrem never mentions
                    abstract, disembodied cognition as a means of knowing God. In one instance, he
                    derides his opponents for trying to “represent within their minds another light”
                    that is not the true God, but even this statement relies on ancient theories of
                    perception in which physical, sensory impressions are transformed into mental
                        representations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 44. 9. I assume throughout this paper, based
                            on the evidence provided by previous scholars, that Ephrem is familiar
                            with certain Greek philosophical theories of perception and cognition.
                            For the most comprehensive analysis, see Ute Possekel, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts</hi>, along with Beck, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie</hi>; Wickes, <hi
                                rend="italic">Bible and Poetry</hi>, 12–14; and Griffith, “Setting
                            Right the Church of Syria.” </p></note> Otherwise, Ephrem consistently
                    describes all encounters with God as corporeal, sensory experiences: Christ
                    inhabits the body, brings light to the eyes, and is consumed in the Eucharistic
                    elements. That is, embodied humans are capable of experiencing God’s revelation
                    and activity, but Ephrem does not propose that they can gain a cognitive
                    understanding of the divine nature. In these hymns, Ephrem’s attack on Marcion’s
                    disparagement of the body is founded on the notion that bodily perception is the
                    foremost means of encountering God. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2freeman.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Limited Knowledge of God: The Lowly Body in <hi rend="italic">MDF</hi> 27, 41,
                    70, and 75</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The body and senses also play a central role in <hi rend="italic">Madrashe de
                        fide 27, 41, 70, and 75</hi>, an aspect to which interpreters have paid
                    little attention. In the <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi>, Ephrem frequently and
                    consistently denounces those who “investigate (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܒܨܐ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܥܐ</foreign>)” and “debate
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܪܫ</foreign>)” about God’s nature. Based on
                    certain theological positions that Ephrem disputes in these hymns, most scholars
                    have determined that Ephrem likely aims his polemic at Arians, semi-Arians, or
                        Aetians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Griffith, “Faith Seeking Understanding,” 39–41; Possekel, “Ephrem’s
                            Doctrine of God,” 198–202; Wickes, <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
                            Faith</hi>, 19–48. While it is often stated that Ephrem likely wrote
                            these hymns when he came to Edessa and encountered Greek trinitarian
                            controversies, Hartung, “The Authorship and Dating” has demonstrated
                            that we cannot be certain.</p></note> But besides their varied attempts
                    to determine which trinitarian doctrine he attacks, scholars are more united in
                    their claim that Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> deride “a <hi rend="italic"
                        >way</hi> of doing theology.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Quotation in Wickes, <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
                                Faith</hi>, 46. See also Paul S. Russel, “A Note on Ephraem the
                            Syrian and ‘The Poison of the Greeks’ in Hymns on Faith 2” (<hi
                                rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 10 [1997]), 45–54; Vleugels, “Response
                            to Chasm and Bridge”; Possekel, “Ephrem’s Doctrine of God”; Francoise
                            Cassingena-Trevedy, "Le Rationalisme Theologique Comme Mal Radical a
                            travers Les Hymnes sur La Foi d'Ephrem de Nisibe," in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Les forces du bien et du mal dans les premiers siecles de l'eglide:
                                actes du colloque de Tours</hi>, ed. Yves-Marie Blanchard, Berbard
                            Pouderon, and Madeleine Scopello (Paris: Beauchesne, 2010), 65–75.
                        </p></note> Wickes argues that, much as Athanasius constructed the category
                    of “Arian,” Ephrem constructed the category of “investigation,” as opposed to
                    his own theological position, which argues for humans’ limited capacity to know
                        God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Wickes, <hi rend="italic">St. Ephrem the Syrian</hi>, 46. </p></note>
                    That is, Ephrem appears to reject, at least to a certain extent, the theological
                    debate about God’s nature undertaken by fourth-century Greek Christian thinkers. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Unlike in <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44, these four hymns from the <hi
                        rend="italic">MdF</hi> refer to the mind and its feeble attempts at
                    understanding, demonstrating that the target of Ephrem’s invective is abstract
                    theological pursuit. He complains that the soul “cannot be seen by the mind
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܪܥܝܬܐ</foreign>)”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50"
                        n="50"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 70.2. </p></note> and that although “minds
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܥܝܢܐ</foreign>) gaze” they “see themselves
                    instead of Him!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.1. </p></note> The nature of the soul and
                    God were typical objects of investigation in trinitarian and soteriological
                    discussions of the fourth century, but Ephrem does not think the human mind can
                    come to accurate conclusions about them. Indeed, he asserts that “it is
                    impossible to depict in our heart / the ‘how’ of [God’s] nature that
                        exists.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.3. See Beck, <hi rend="italic">Ephräms des
                                Syrers Psychologie</hi>, 147-59.</p></note> Whereas in his <hi
                        rend="italic">McH</hi> Ephrem lauded the ability of the body to experience
                    God’s creation and activity, here he takes issue with theologians’ attempts to
                    reason about the finer details of God’s being. He explains, “‘Where’ should not
                    be sought out, ‘how’ not debated, / ‘why’ not mentioned, and ‘when’ not
                        investigated.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.4.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">That Ephrem is talking about theology becomes most evident in the two biblical
                    analogies he provides. In one case, he refers to the account of Balaam and the
                    talking donkey in Numbers 22, focusing on Balaam’s reaction. He explains that
                    just like the “investigators” he loathes, “When that donkey unexpectedly spoke,
                    / Balaam saw the miracle, but completely failed to marvel. / Yet as the donkey’s
                    mouth was rational (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܠܠܐ</foreign>), / [Balaam] forgot
                    about himself and was persuaded by his Donkey.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54"
                        n="54"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.7. </p></note> Balaam did not wonder at
                    the miracle God placed right before his eyes—a talking donkey!—but was more
                    concerned with the logic of the donkey’s words, just as the “debaters” of his
                    day miss the mystery of the Trinity for their disputes over its nature.
                    Likewise, he compares these theologians to the scribes in the Gospels, who
                    “forsook the marvel [of] the blind [whose eyes] were opened, / And stirred up an
                    investigation into the Sabbath and the clay.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55"
                        n="55"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.7. See also Christine Shepardson, <hi
                                rend="italic">Anti-Judaism and Christian Orthodoxy, </hi>118–43 for
                            a discussion of Ephrem’s comparison of Arians to the Pharisees in the
                            Gospels. </p></note> Ephrem thus opposes theoretical discourse about God
                    to revelatory experience.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is commonly acknowledged that the <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> polemicize
                    theological discourse, and interpreters usually highlight Ephrem’s view of the
                    limited human capacity for knowing God and his faith-based approach. But many
                    have not recognized that these hymns also degrade the body and the senses as an
                    extension of this polemic, deploying perceptual language in their attack.
                    Ephrem’s position might seem counter-intuitive to modern readers, who tend to
                    distinguish between mental and somatic capacities. If Ephrem despises abstract
                    mental exercises, what need does he have to disparage the body, which he so
                    profoundly praises as a vehicle for encountering God in <hi rend="italic"
                        >McH</hi> 42-44? I argue that it is because Ephrem does not conceive of
                    cognition as distinct from the body; he thinks that the only way to gain
                    knowledge is through the body’s senses, just as he assumes in the <hi
                        rend="italic">McH</hi>. Therefore, to counter excessive theological
                    conjecture, he laments the limitations of the senses and degrades the body for
                    its lowliness and inability to access God. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Because Ephrem conceives of all knowledge as derived from perceptual experience,
                    he uses a range of sensory language in these four hymns to attack theological
                    discourse. As stated above, Ephrem describes minds and souls as “gazing
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܕ</foreign>)” and “seeing (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܚܙܐ</foreign>)”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 70.2, 27.1.</p></note> while this may be a
                    standard way to describe the action of souls, this visual terminology sets the
                    stage for Ephrem’s heavy engagement with perceptual language. Ephrem goes on to
                    lament that “natures think they see (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܙܝܢ</foreign>)
                    him, whom they have never been able to see.” He believes that humans have erred
                    if they “think they have seen (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܙܘ</foreign>) him in an
                        image.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.3</p></note> In these descriptions,
                    theology fails to account for the human inability to perceive God visually;
                    theologians perceive something that they think is God, but in reality, it is not
                    Him. Ephrem deems the investigators “blind” because they fail to perceive, for
                    “The blind soul, which itself / cannot see (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܬܚܙܐ</foreign>): how could it gaze (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܬܨܕ</foreign>)
                    / upon divinity?”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 70.4. </p></note> In these four hymns, Ephrem
                    consistently refers to theological investigation as an act of seeing—or rather,
                    failing to see—God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For the preponderance of vocabulary related to
                            sight and vision in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi>, see Wickes, <hi
                                rend="italic">Bible and Poetry</hi>, 84-103, especially 85-86.
                        </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem further argues that the investigators mistakenly perceived certain things
                    as God Himself. “Instead of Him,” he posits, “they have seen (<foreign
                        xml:lang="syr">ܚܙܝܢ</foreign>) themselves and thought, lo, they had seen
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܙܐܘܗܝ</foreign>) him,” referring to their use of
                    human categories and characteristics to define God.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.2.</p></note> He states that “They have
                    touched (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܫܘ</foreign>) gold and likened it to light. /
                    They have handled (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܫܘ</foreign>) jewels, thinking light
                    was within. / They have touched everything and handled everything, / and look:
                    fools think they have handled the light.” Ephrem commonly uses “light” to refer
                    to God, and he thinks that people often perceive one thing to be God, when it is
                    really not Him. Even though they “stand inside the light,” they “go around
                    looking for it,” simply failing to perceive God who is present around them.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.4.</p></note> In this case, theological
                    reasoning is a misperception because the soul does not correctly interpret the
                    data about God that it perceives. While one could argue that Ephrem is speaking
                    metaphorically with this sensory terminology, Syriac views on the unity of body
                    and soul and Greco-Roman theories of the role of physiological perception in
                    cognition provide a better context with which to understand Ephrem’s
                    synonymization of knowing and perceiving.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62"
                        n="62"><p rend="footnote text"> In particular, see Modrak, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aristotle: The Power of Perception</hi> and Philip Van der Eijk,
                                <hi rend="italic">Medicine and Philosophy in Classical
                            Antiquit</hi>y, 206–37 for Aristotle’s influential theorization of
                            perception as the basis of cognition. See Beck, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie, </hi>97-105 for Ephrem’s equation
                            of sensory knowledge and intellectual knowledge, which he thinks
                            indicates Ephrem’s vague familiarity with Stoic theories of cognition.
                        </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem’s continued engagement with the physiological details of perception
                    demonstrates his assumption that knowledge derives from the senses.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text"> Beck, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie, </hi>136 acknowledges
                            the similarity of Ephrem’s notion that perception is the basis for
                            knowledge with Stoicism. Whereas Beck engages Stoic theories of
                            cognition as points of comparison with Ephrem, my argument shows his
                            general familiarity with a variety of ancient theories of
                            perception.</p></note> He attacks his opponents by appealing to the
                    limitations of each sense in relation to their proper sensibles. For example, he
                    posits that </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>They do not think of how they have</l>
                        <l>One sense like the light (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܕ ܪܓܫܐ ܐܚܝܢܗ
                                ܕܢܗܝܪܐ</foreign>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">), </foreign></l>
                        <l>[While] the other senses are concealed,</l>
                        <l>And all are foreign to the light.</l>
                        <l>[The light’s] color is not tasted, its scent not smelled.</l>
                        <l>Its brightness is inaudible, and its light cannot be touched.</l>
                        <l>Only seeing is similar (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܙܝܐ ܠܚܘܕ ܒܪ
                                ܛܘܗܡܐ</foreign> ):</l>
                        <l>It understands it, as a child its parent.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.5.</p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem is engaging ancient theories of perception, such as that of Plato,
                    Aristotle, and Galen, which discuss each sense and its proper object: vision
                    sees color, audition hears sounds, olfaction smells scents, and so on.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> Plato, <hi
                                rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> 61C–68D, LCL 234, ed. and trans. R. G.
                            Bury (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1929), 155-77; Aristotle, <hi
                                rend="italic">De Anima</hi> 2.6-11 (418a8–424a17) in LCL 288, ed.
                            and trans. W.S. Hett, <hi rend="italic">On the Soul. Parva Naturalia. On
                                Breath</hi> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1936), 100-35;
                            Galen, <hi rend="italic">On the Doctrines of Hippocrates and Plato</hi>
                            7.5.33, Corpus Medicorum Graecorum 4:1:2, ed. and trans. Phillip De Lacy
                            (Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1980), 461. For an extensive engagement with
                            classical theories of perception in another Syrian author, who wrote in
                            Greek, see Nemesius, <hi rend="italic">On the Nature of Man</hi>, 6–13,
                            trans. R. W. Sharples and P. J. van der Eijk (Liverpool: Liverpool
                            University Press, 2008).</p></note> He argues that humans have only one
                    sense that accords with light, namely vision; the others cannot perceive light
                    because it is not their proper sensible, thus demonstrating the limitations of
                    the human sensorium. He elaborates further on the inability of the other senses
                    to perceive the light: “The light dwells in the mouth unperceived (<foreign
                        xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܪܓܫ</foreign> ). / Shining, it dwells in the ear without
                    suffering (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܚܐܫܐ</foreign> ). / It dwells in the hand,
                    yet how has [the hand] not felt it? / The nostril has not inhaled what rises up
                    to it.” Light—that is, God—is all around and within the human body: in the
                    mouth, ears, and limbs, yet it is unable to be perceived because it is not
                    proper to the other sense organs. If the senses cannot perceive God, then “the
                    mind and the heart (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܥܐ ܘܠܒܐ</foreign> )—king,
                    commander— / And assembly of the thoughts (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܢܫܐ
                        ܕܚܘ̈ܫܒܐ</foreign>)—and the soul (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܦܫܐ</foreign>),
                    their dwelling, / Have failed to understand the light.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.6. </p></note> Many ancient thinkers
                    considered the heart the seat of cognition, which derived thoughts and knowledge
                    from sensory impressions made upon the body.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67"
                        n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> John I. Beare, <hi rend="italic">Greek
                                Theories of Elementary Cognition from Alcmaeon to Aristotle</hi>
                            (Oxford: Clarendon, 1906), 326–36; Van der Eijk, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Medicine and Philosophy</hi>, 119–38. For this idea in Ephrem, see
                            Possekel, <hi rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical
                                Concepts</hi>, 193.</p></note> Like these thinkers, Ephrem considers
                    cognition, which takes place in the mind or soul that resides in the heart, to
                    be a result of perception. Therefore, if the body’s senses are incapable of
                    grasping God, then the mind cannot understand Him as theologians think it can. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In <hi rend="italic">MdF 75</hi>, Ephrem further discusses the inabilities of
                    each of the five senses in light of ancient perceptual theories. He notes that </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>The subtlety of that light</l>
                        <l>Cannot be touched; it is not concealed</l>
                        <l>By things that hold it.</l>
                        <l>The heat from that ray</l>
                        <l>Cannot be seen by the eyes—</l>
                        <l>It is [too] fine.</l>
                        <l>It has conquered the eyes with its heat</l>
                        <l>And the hands with its subtlety,</l>
                        <l>For they cannot touch or see [it] . . . </l>
                        <l>No mouth has ever tasted</l>
                        <l>That light, nor a nose</l>
                        <l>Inhaled [its] scent. </l>
                        <l>Nor has the ear ever heard</l>
                        <l>The light’s voice, as it moves</l>
                        <l>Across creation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.3–8. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Even sight, the sense proper to the light, is limited because it cannot perceive
                    the light’s other aspects, such as its heat and fineness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text"> For Ephrem’s understanding of
                            the physiology of vision, see Possekel, <hi rend="italic">Evidence of
                                Greek Philosophical Concepts</hi>, 203-28.</p></note> Each of the
                    senses is circumscribed in being able to perceive but one sensible aspect, but
                    even those aspects of God that are proper to each sense organ are too subtle for
                    them. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">There is also the matter of the senses’ unlikeness to God. Although in some cases
                    Ephrem admits that sight has a likeness with God’s light, in other cases he
                    denies any particular sense organ’s capacity to be like God. In <hi
                        rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41, he proclaims, </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>Though scent, color, and taste are truly</l>
                        <l>Rarefied and subtle, and cannot be felt by the hand,</l>
                        <l>They can be understood through the senses, their close allies (<foreign
                                xml:lang="syr">ܐܚ̈ܝܢܝܗܘܢ</foreign>):</l>
                        <l>One [sense] smells and another tastes.</l>
                        <l>What sense, though, is like (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܚܝܢܐ</foreign>)
                            that Greatness?</l>
                        <l>Through what similar thing (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܪ ܛܘܗܡܗܿ</foreign> )
                            could we approach to discuss it?</l>
                        <l>That which is unlike us (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ . . .
                            ܐܚܝܢܢ</foreign>), or our race:</l>
                        <l>Who can seek it out? Who can investigate it?<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.5–6. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although scent, color, and taste are perceptible to their allied sense organs,
                    Ephrem here denies that any sense is like God and able to perceive him. Certain
                    ancient perceptual theories, such as those of Aristotle and Plotinus, posited
                    that perception occurred because of a likeness or assimilation of qualities
                    between the percipient body and the perceptible object.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"> See for example,
                            Theophrastus, <hi rend="italic">On the Senses</hi>, which compares and
                            contrasts the perceptual theories of those who ascribe sensation to
                            “likeness (τὸ ὁμοῖον)” and those who ascribe it to “contrast (τὸ
                            ἐνάντιον)” [George Malcom Stratton, ed. and trans., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Theophrastus and the Greek Physiological Psychology before
                                Aristotle</hi> (New York: MacMillan and Co., 1917)]. Aristotle, <hi
                                rend="italic">DA</hi> 2.5 (418a6-9) in Hett, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                                >On the Soul</hi>, 100-01 and Plotinus <hi rend="italic">Ennead</hi>
                            4.4.3, LCL 440, ed. and trans. A.H. Armstrong (Cambridge: Harvard
                            University Press, 2014), 144-45 also claim that sensation occurs when
                            the percipient sense organ becomes like to the object of perception.
                            Beck, <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie</hi>, 24 notes the influence of
                            the Platonic notion that like perceives like. Possekel, <hi
                                rend="italic">Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts</hi>, 197-203
                            also shows Ephrem’s familiarity with this aspect of ancient perceptual
                            theories.</p></note> Thus, Ephrem offers the ontological distinction
                    between God and humanity to deny human perception of the divine. Theologians are
                    mistaken if they think that “God is like them (<foreign xml:lang="syr"
                        >ܠܗܘܢ</foreign>
                    <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܡܐ</foreign>)” such that they can perceive and thus
                    know Him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.2. </p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In several other instances, Ephrem denies the ability of the human senses to
                    perceive God because of this ontological gap. The investigators cannot “see /
                    that tiny glimmer before them. / Look: it has rubbed itself on them, spread its
                    color on them, / . . . And although they are well clothed in it, / it is far-off
                    in the distance, / And the weak have perceived it only by report.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27.7. </p></note> Although God is present in
                    the world, right before human eyes and interacting with them, people can only
                    indirectly see Him. In another case, he argues that just as no one can see the
                    inner workings of miraculous natural phenomena, God is imperceptible to humans
                    because he exceeds human nature: </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>Who has ever seen a raven mating,</l>
                        <l>Or a virgin bee consummating a marriage?</l>
                        <l>The virgin bee gives birth virginally,</l>
                        <l>And the worm brings forth alone.</l>
                        <l>A cloud, too, bears lightning gloriously,</l>
                        <l>And a sprout is manifest within a rock miraculously.<note place="foot"
                                xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.1.</p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem thought all these things were miracles of nature, impossible to
                    understand. Like God, their nature cannot be perceived by human senses.
                    Continuing his focus on this ontological distinction in <hi rend="italic"
                        >MdF</hi> 70, he opens with the question, “With what eye could a thing-made
                    look / upon the Maker? [The eye] is a creature, / And he is the Creator.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 70.1.</p></note> The chasm between Creator
                    and creation renders the human eye incapable of seeing God. Indeed, humanity is
                    so inferior to God, that “There cannot be, among creatures, / a vessel so great
                    that in it is contained / that Greatness. / There cannot be among minds
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܥܝܢܐ</foreign>) / a space capable [of containing]
                    that knowledge of divinity.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 70.20–1. </p></note> Ephrem’s language of
                    mental containment likely relies on ancient theories of perception and cognition
                    wherein the perceiver took on the qualities of the perceptible object in their
                    bodies, which were then stored as images in the mind.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"> For the influential
                            Aristotelian theory of perceptual images stored in the mind, see Modrak,
                                <hi rend="italic">Aristotle</hi>, 81–132. For the ancient tendency
                            to attribute to memory the material capacity for containment, largely
                            derived from Aristotle, see Carruthers, <hi rend="italic">The Book of
                                Memory, </hi>18–55. </p></note> He rejects that the material body
                    can assimilate and contain the qualities of the divine essence. Ultimately for
                    Ephrem, although “the senses (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܓܫܐ</foreign>) of the
                    sons of the High One / [are] subtle and spiritual,” they “are weaker than the
                    discussion of divinity” and simply “insufficient” for knowing God fully.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.25–6.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">But Ephrem does not end his argument against theological exercise by denying the
                    human capacity to understand God fully through perception; he further disparages
                    the body more generally, given that Ephrem sees all knowledge as derived from
                    the body. He exhorts his audience to “Examine and see your lowly body (<foreign
                        xml:lang="syr">ܦܓܪܟ ܡܫܦܠܐ</foreign> ). / Be ashamed of its intestines, all
                    of which are filthy (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܨܐܝܢ</foreign>). / Let its defects
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܘܡ̈ܘܗܝ</foreign>) be your bridle, [to restrain]
                    your debating.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.8. </p></note> Ephrem depicts the body as
                    a shameful, filthy, and broken vessel, starkly contrasting it with the sacred,
                    exalted God whom it is incapable of understanding. He even conjures imagery of
                    polluting bodily fluids to show humanity’s unfitness to examine the divine
                    object, exclaiming, “Cease from discussion, / O dense senses of the fat body
                        (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܪ̈ܓܫܐ ܥܓܪ̈ܐ ܕܦܓܪܐ ܥܒܝܐ</foreign>), / causing pus to
                        flow!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.27. </p></note> This approach diverges
                    sharply from his laudation of the healed body that can encounter God in his <hi
                        rend="italic">McH</hi>. Whereas Ephrem praises the body to attack Marcionite
                    dualists who disparage it, here Ephrem degrades the body to attack theologians
                    who attempt to know more than they can because he sees knowledge not as abstract
                    and disembodied but as derived from the body’s senses. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">His rhetoric against the body becomes even harsher when he discusses how “the
                    mouth, the ears, and the nose, / three senses: they cannot sense / the three,”
                    speaking about the particular inability of taste, hearing, and smell to help
                    humans understand the Trinity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p
                            rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.6. </p></note> He calls these three senses
                    “useless (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒ̈ܛܝܠܝܢ</foreign>)” for perceiving the light
                    that is God, reasoning that if these senses are useless, </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>Then your whole body (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܟܠܗ ܓܘܫܡܟ</foreign> ) [is
                            useless], if the senses</l>
                        <l>Cannot meet the divinity</l>
                        <l>Hidden from all.</l>
                        <l>The three useless senses,</l>
                        <l>Along with the Trinitarian symbols</l>
                        <l>Within the sun,</l>
                        <l>Call out that they are alien</l>
                        <l>To the discussions of the Father, Son,</l>
                        <l>And Holy Spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.9–12. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">As far as theological exercises go, the senses are ineffectual for trying to
                    understand the relationship of the members of the Trinity. Furthermore, if the
                    senses cannot understand God, Ephrem reasons, then the entire body—senses,
                    limbs, and mind—are useless, again a stark divergence from his praise of the
                    body’s role in encountering God in the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi>. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Another variation in these hymns from the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44 is his
                    association of the body with Satan and demons. In the <hi rend="italic"
                        >McH,</hi> Ephrem denied the affinity of natures between the human body and
                    the demons, insisting that even if the body had been an instrument coopted by
                    Satan for sin, Christ had healed it through his Incarnation. In <hi
                        rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75, however, Ephrem changes his tune and argues that </p>

                <cit>
                    <quote>
                        <l>Your body’s senses can speak to us</l>
                        <l>About the spiritual senses</l>
                        <l>Of the stinking demons:</l>
                        <l>With these nostrils Legion breathes.</l>
                        <l>With these feet, the Evil One runs</l>
                        <l>Over all creation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p
                                    rend="footnote text">
                                    <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 75.29–30. </p></note></l>
                    </quote>
                </cit>
                <p xml:lang="en">The demons work in and through human bodies and senses, causing theologians to
                    propagate erroneous doctrines. Demonic entities invade not only bodies, but also
                    minds, as “the Evil One swarms us with his thinking / . . . His movements and
                    extensions becoming like our mind / and our understanding.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 41.9. </p></note> Human beings, body and
                    mind, are subject to demonic influence and are thus unfit for theological
                    reasoning.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Overall, Ephrem presents a negative valuation of the human body and senses in the
                        <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi> 27, 41, 70, and 75. Its senses misperceive, fail
                    to perceive, and are ultimately incapable of perceiving God’s nature, separated
                    by an epistemic gap, rendering the body lowly, useless, and demonically
                    corrupted. What makes these polemics against the body—which offer a striking
                    contrast to his acclaim for the body in the <hi rend="italic">McH</hi>
                    42-44—comprehensible is Ephrem’s consistency in ascribing knowledge to bodily
                    perception. Because he sees perception and cognition as inseparable, he attacks
                    theological reasoning by noting the limits of the human sensorium. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="h25n2freeman.4" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Ephrem was a prolific poet who composed a vast amount of
                    poetry and prose in various contexts throughout his career. In his madrashe, he
                    weaves an intricate web of polemical invective, biblical exegesis, and
                    philosophical theory to instruct his audiences. Ephrem’s different approaches to
                    the human body and sensorium examined in these two sets of hymns can be
                    attributed to their different polemical situations: his contestation of
                    Marcionite scorn for human corporeality in <hi rend="italic">McH</hi> 42-44 and
                    his attack on abstract theological investigation in <hi rend="italic">MdF</hi>
                    27, 41, 70, and 75. Nevertheless, in both cases, he retains a firm commitment to
                    a perception-centered epistemology, primarily derived from Syrian conceptions of
                    body-soul unity and Greek theories of perception and cognition. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en"> According to Ephrem, God created the material world for humans to encounter with
                    their bodies; he gave them bodies to experience his creation. Christ has healed
                    the human sensorium, worn out by sin, and thus enabled humans to experience his
                    activity and symbols placed in nature, Scripture, and the sacraments and thus to
                    achieve salvation. Yet the body also limits the human capacity to know God
                    fully. Humans cannot directly see, hear, touch, taste, or smell God, who is
                    beyond physical perception, and therefore they cannot go on to reason about his
                    nature. Humans can experience God’s creation and symbolic refractions within it,
                    but they cannot understand God himself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> See n. 2. </p></note> Ephrem’s approaches to
                    epistemology betray an underlying assumption that bodily perception is the
                    source of knowledge. My analysis thus contributes to scholarly efforts to
                    recognize the positive role of the body and the senses in many ancient Christian
                    epistemologies of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Primary Sources: </head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Aristotle. <hi rend="italic">On the Soul. Parva Naturalia. On
                                Breath</hi>. Translated by W. S. Hett. LCL 288. Cambridge, MA:
                            Harvard University Press, 1957. </bibl>
                        <bibl>E. Beck, ed. and trans. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des
                                Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses</hi>. CSCO 77. Leuven: Peeters, 1957. </bibl>
                        <bibl>E. Beck, ed. and trans.<hi rend="italic"> Des heiligen Ephraem des
                                Syrers Hymnen de Fide</hi>. CSCO 73. Vol. 1-2. Louvain: Peeters,
                            1955. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Cerbelaud, Dominique, trans. <hi rend="italic">Ephrem de Nisibe:
                                Hymnes contre les heresies; Hymnes contra Julien</hi>. Vol. 2.
                            Paris: Les editions du cerf, 2017.</bibl>
                        <bibl>De Lacy, Phillip, ed. and trans. <hi rend="italic">Galen: On the
                                Doctrines of Hippocrates and Plato</hi>. Corpus Medicorum Graecorum
                            4:1:2. Berlin: Akademie Verlag, 1980.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Nemesius. <hi rend="italic">On the Nature of Man</hi>. Translated by
                            R. W. Sharples and P. J. van der Eijk. Liverpool: Liverpool University
                            Press, 2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Plato.<hi rend="italic"> Timaeus. </hi>Translated by R. G. Bury. LCL
                            234. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press, 1929. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Plotinus. <hi rend="italic">Enneads</hi>. Translated by A. H.
                            Armstrong. LCL 440. 5 volumes. Cambridge: Harvard University Press,
                            2014.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Ruani, Flavia, trans. <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de Nisibe: Hymnes
                                contre les hérésies</hi>. Bibliotèque de L’Orient Chrétien. Paris:
                            Les Belles Lettres, 2018.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Wickes, Jeffrey, trans. <hi rend="italic">St. Ephrem the Syrian: Hymns
                                on Faith</hi>. Washington, D.C.: Catholic University of America
                            Press, 2015.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Stratton, George Malcolm, ed. and trans.<hi rend="italic">
                                Theophrastus and the Greek Physiological Psychology before
                                Aristotle</hi>. New York: MacMillan and Co., 1917. </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
                <div xml:lang="en">
                    <head>Secondary Sources: </head>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Beare, John I. <hi rend="italic">Greek Theories of Elementary
                                Cognition from Alcmaeon to Aristotle</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon,
                            1906.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Beck, E. <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie des heiligen Ephrem in Seinen
                                Hymnen über den Glauben</hi>. Rome: Pontifium Institutum S. Anselmi,
                            1949.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____. <hi rend="italic">Ephräms des Syrers Psychologie und
                                Erkenntnislehre</hi>. Louvain: CSCO, 1980.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Beggiana, Seeley Joseph. “The Typological Approach of Syriac
                            Sacramental Theology.” <hi rend="italic">Theological Studies</hi> 64
                            (2003): 543-57.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Botha, Phil J. “The Poetic Face of Rhetoric: Ephrem’s Polemics against
                            the Jews and Heretics in <hi rend="italic">Contra Haereses</hi> 25.” <hi
                                rend="italic">Acta Patristica et Byzantina</hi> 2 (1991):
                            16-36.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “The Significance of the Senses in St. Ephrem’s Description of
                            Paradise.” <hi rend="italic">Acta Patristica et Byzantina</hi> 5 (1994):
                            28-37. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____ “The Textual Strategy of Ephrem the Syrian’s Hymn Contra Haereses
                            I.” <hi rend="italic">Acta Patristica et Byzantina</hi> 15 (2004):
                            57-75.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bukovec, Predrag. “Gotteserkenntnis in Ephraems des Syrers <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymni de fide</hi>.” <hi rend="italic">Saeculum</hi>
                            60 (2010): 17-40.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Bundy, David. “Language and the Knowledge of God in Ephrem Syrus.” <hi
                                rend="italic">The Patristic and Byzantine Review</hi> 5 (1986):
                            9-103. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Brock, Sebastian. “The Dispute between Body and Soul: An Example of a
                            Long-Lived Mesopotamian Literary Genre.” <hi rend="italic">ARAM</hi> 1
                            (1989): 53-64. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____<hi rend="italic">. The Luminous Eye: The Spiritual World Vision
                                of Saint Ephrem.</hi> Cistercian Studies 124. Spencer, MS:
                            Cistercian Publications, 1992. Originally published Rome: Center for
                            Indian and Inter-Religious Studies, 1985.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Carruthers, Mary. <hi rend="italic">The Book of Memory: A Study of
                                Memory in Medieval Culture</hi>. 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi>
                            edition. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Cassingena-Trevedy, Francoise. "Le Rationalisme Theologique Comme Mal
                            Radical a travers Les Hymnes sur La Foi d'Ephrem de Nisibe.” Pages 65-75
                            in <hi rend="italic">Les forces du bien et du mal dans les premiers
                                siecles de l'eglide: actes du colloque de Tours</hi>, ed. Yves-Marie
                            Blanchard, Bernard Pouderon, and Madeleine Scopello. Paris: Beauchesne,
                            2010.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Frank, Georgia. <hi rend="italic">The Memory of the Eyes: Pilgrims to
                                Living Saints in Late Antiquity</hi>. The Transformation of the
                            Classical Heritage 30. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Gavrilyuk, Paul L. and Sarah Coakley, eds. <hi rend="italic">The
                                Spiritual Senses: Perceiving God in Western Christianity</hi>.
                            Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Griffith, Sidney. “‘Denominationalism’ in Fourth-Century Syria:
                            Readings in Saint Ephraem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns against
                                Heresies</hi>.” Pages 79-100 in <hi rend="italic">The Garb of Being:
                                Embodiment and the Pursuit of Holiness in Late Ancient
                                Christianity,</hi> Orthodox Christianity and Contemporary Thought,
                            ed. Georgia Frank, Susan Holman, and Andrew Jacobs. New York: Fordham
                            University Press, 2020.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “Faith Seeking Understanding in the Thought of St. Ephraem.”
                            Pages 35-55 in <hi rend="italic">Faith Seeking Understanding: Learning
                                and the Catholic Tradition, </hi>ed. George Charles Berthold
                            Manchester, NH: Saint Anselm College Press, 1991.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint Ephraem’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies</hi>.” Pages 97-114 in <hi
                                rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient Christianity: Essays on Late
                                Antique Thought and Culture in Honor of R. A. Markus, </hi>ed.
                            William E. Klingshirn and Mark Vessey. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan
                            Press, 1999. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “The Image of the Image Maker in the Poetry of St. Ephraem the
                            Syrian.” <hi rend="italic">StPatr</hi> 25 (1993): 258-69. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “The Marks of the True Church According to Ephrem’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns Against Heresies</hi>.” Pages 125-40 in <hi
                                rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on Continuity and Change in
                                Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professir Han J. W. Drijvers</hi>,
                            ed. G. J. Reinink and Alexander Cornelis Klugkist. Leuven: Peeters,
                            1999.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Hartung, Blake. “The Authorship and Dating of the Syriac Corpus
                            Attributed to Ephrem of Nisibis: A Reassessment.” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Zeitschrift für Antikes Christentum</hi> 22 (2018): 296-321.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Harvey, Susan Ashbrook. <hi rend="italic">Asceticism and Society in
                                Crisis: John of Ephesus and the Lives of the Eastern Saints</hi>.
                            Berkeley: University of California Press, 1990. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “Locating the Sensing Body: Perception and Religious Identity in
                            Late Antiquity.” Pages 140-62 in <hi rend="italic">Religion and the Self
                                in Antiquity</hi>, ed. David Brakke, Michael L. Satlow, and Steven
                            Weitzman. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 2005.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____<hi rend="italic">. Scenting Salvation: Ancient Christianity and
                                the Olfactory Imagination</hi>. Berkeley: University of California
                            Press, 2006.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “St. Ephrem on the Scent of Salvation.” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Journal of Theological Studies</hi> 49 (1998): 109-28. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Kiger, David. “Fire in the Bread, Life in the Body: The Pneumatology
                            of Ephrem the Syrian.” Ph.D. diss., Marquette University, 2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Kim, Jaehyun. “Body and Soul in Ephrem the Syrian.” <hi rend="italic"
                                >Syriac Studies</hi> (2002): 79-117.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Koonammakkal, Thomas Kathanar. “Ephrem’s Polemics on the Human Body.”
                                <hi rend="italic">StPatr</hi> 35 (2001): 428-32. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “The Self-Revealing God and Man in Ephrem.” <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Harp</hi> 6 (1993): 233-48.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Miller, Patricia Cox. <hi rend="italic">The Corporeal Imagination:
                                Signifying the Holy in Late Antiquity</hi>. Divinations: Rereading
                            Late Ancient Religion. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press,
                            2009. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Modrak, Deborah K. <hi rend="italic">Aristotle: The Power of
                                Perception</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1987.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Murray, Robert. <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A
                                Study in Early Syriac Tradition</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press, 1975. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Mourachian, Mark J. “Human Freedom in the Context of the Theological
                            Anthropology of St. Ephrem the Syrian.” PhD diss., Catholic University
                            of America, 2012.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Possekel, Ute. “Ephrem’s Doctrine of God.” Pages 195-237 in <hi
                                rend="italic">God in Early Christian Thought: Essays in Memory of
                                Lloyd G. Patterson, </hi>ed. Andrew B. McGowan. Leiden: Brill,
                            2009.</bibl>
                        <bibl>____<hi rend="italic">. Evidence of Greek Philosophical Concepts in
                                the Writings of Ephrem the Syrian. </hi>Louvain: Peeters,
                            1999.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Russel, Paul S. “A Note on Ephraem the Syrian and ‘The Poison of the
                            Greeks’ in Hymns on Faith 2.” <hi rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 10 (1997):
                            45-54. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. “Ephraem the Syrian on the Utility of Language and the Place of
                                Silence.” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian
                            Studies</hi> 8 (2000): 21-37. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Saber, Georges. "La Typologie Sacramentaire et Baptismale de Saint
                            Ephrem." <hi rend="italic">ParOr</hi> 4 (1973): 73-91. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Shemunkasho, Aho. <hi rend="italic">Healing in the Theology of Saint
                                Ephrem</hi>. Gorgias Dissertations: Near Eastern Studies 1.
                            Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2002.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Shepardson, Christine. <hi rend="italic">Anti-Judaism and Christian
                                Orthodoxy: Ephrem’s Hymns in Fourth-Century Syria</hi>. Washington,
                            D. C.: Catholic University of America Press, 2008.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Smith, Mark A. <hi rend="italic">From Sight to Light: The Passage from
                                Ancient to Modern Optics</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
                            2015.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Van der Eijk, Philip J. <hi rend="italic">Medicine and Philosophy in
                                Classical Antiquity: Doctors and Philosophers on Nature, Soul,
                                Health, and Disease</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                            2005.</bibl>
                        <bibl>Vleugels, Charis. “The Response to Chasm and Bridge: The Wings of
                            Truth and Attitude in Ephrem the Syrian’s Hymns on Faith.” <hi
                                rend="italic">The Harp</hi> 22 (2007): 183-92. </bibl>
                        <bibl>Wickes, Jeffrey. “Between Liturgy and School: Reassessing the
                            Performative Context of Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi>.” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 26 (2018):
                            25-51. </bibl>
                        <bibl>____. <hi rend="italic">Bible and Poetry in Mesopotamia: Ephrem’s
                                Madrashe on Faith</hi>. Christianity in Late Antiquity 4. Berkeley:
                            University of California Press, 2019. </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
