<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Valentin Vesa, <hi rend="italic">Knowledge and Experience in the Writings of St. Isaac of Nineveh</hi>
                    (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2018)</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Robert</forename>
                        <surname>Kitchen</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Saskatchewan, Canada</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n1prkitchen</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Robert Kitchen</author>
                        <title level="a">Valentin Vesa, <hi rend="italic">Knowledge and Experience in the Writings of St. Isaac of Nineveh</hi>
                            (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2018)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N1PRKitchen.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2021</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="305" to="309">305-309</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="11"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-03-04">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>

            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                <ab type="review-title">Valentin Vesa, <hi rend="italic">Knowledge and Experience in the Writings of St. Isaac of Nineveh</hi>
                (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2018). Pp. XIV + 331; $114.95.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">This monograph issues from the doctoral dissertation of Valentin Vesa at the
                University of Padova, Italy, under the supervision of Paolo Bettiolo. Vesa examines
                the concepts of knowledge and experience in the writings of the late seventh-century
                East Syriac author Isaac of Nineveh. Since 2020, Benedict-Valentin Vesa has been
                bishop-vicar of the Archdiocese of Vad, Feleac and Cluj, of the Romanian Orthodox
                Church. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">While the importance and originality of Isaac’s mystical theology has long been
                recognized—his works were translated and utilized more than those of any other
                Syriac writer, notably in the Greek and Slavonic collections of the <hi rend="italic">Philokalia</hi>—he is
                still understudied. Recent publications by Sebastian Brock, Sabino Chiala, Hilarion
                Alfeyev, Patrick Hagman, Jason Scully, Serafim Seppala, as well as an international
                colloquium in Moscow, have yielded fruitful explorations of this prolific but
                enigmatic author. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Beginning with an excellent survey of what is known about Isaac’s life and writings,
                Vesa focuses on his unique ideas regarding salvation and grace for mere human beings
                in God’s providence. Instructive as well is Vesa’s description and analysis of the
                christological controversies in the East Syriac church during the sixth and seventh
                centuries. Vesa initially focuses on Sahdona (Martyrius) who defined the nature of
                Christ as one person in a manner that bordered on both Chalcedonian and Miaphysite
                tendencies. The Church of the East resisted allowing its unique dyophysite character
                to be compromised, which created considerable theological conflict. This culminated
                in Patriarch Ishoʿyahb III’s dismissal of Sahdona as bishop of Mahoze d’Arewan. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Vesa surveys the controversy in the seventh to ninth centuries in the Church of the
                East surrounding the views held by three spiritual theologians—John of Dalyatha,
                Joseph Ḥazzaya, and John the Solitary of Apamea—regarding the possibility of humans
                “seeing God,” and explains that it involved a misunderstanding of mystical language
                and theology. The mystics did not pretend to be able to see God’s essence; merely,
                if that is the expression, God’s glory and light. Isaac of Nineveh too speaks of the
                vision of God (<hi rend="italic">theoria</hi>) as part of the climactic state of the ascetic’s being.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Vesa’s book probes in detail Isaac of Nineveh’s process of knowledge—how does one
                think and know, in particular an ascetic-monastic person of faith? Vesa terms
                Isaac’s approach as “theanthropic”: it begins with the material world and its
                thought, and then progresses and matures to the ultimate state of seeing the glory
                of God when all movement ceases in order for the ascetic to dwell in it.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Vesa offers significant citations from Isaac’s corpus and from other scholarly
                interpretations. Numerous citations in this English monograph are presented in
                Italian and French, which impedes and slows down the reader.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The three major influences upon Isaac’s ascetical theology are Evagrius Ponticus (d.
                399), John the Solitary of Apamea (fl. 450), and Pseudo-Dionysius (ca. 500). Along
                with other spiritual writers, these three adopted a three-level-system on which the
                monk progressively ascends. Isaac adapts and develops their configurations. Evagrius
                posits the three stages of <hi rend="italic">praktikos</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gnostikos</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">theologikos</hi>. Dionysius
                describes the stages of purification, illumination, and unification. John the
                Solitary, with whom Isaac has the closest affinity, has <hi rend="italic">pagrana</hi>, <hi rend="italic">naphshana</hi>, and
                <hi rend="italic">ruḥana</hi> (bodily, of the soul, spiritual). Abba Isaiah (early 5th c.), another Greek
                ascetical writer whose <hi rend="italic">Asceticon</hi> was translated early into Syriac and was the
                subject of a commentary by Dadishoʿ Qatraya, a contemporary and fellow countryman of
                Isaac, also describes the path of solitaries as that of bodily labours, the mode of
                life of the mind, and spiritual contemplation (<hi rend="italic">theoria</hi>). </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">While Isaac’s system may have originated and intertwined with these earlier writers,
                he developed a more complex series of movements, totaling six. For Isaac, Vesa
                emphasizes, the goal is the Ultimate Truth, that is, God’s Truth, which is knowledge
                or understanding (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܕܥܬܐ</foreign>). </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The heart of the matter begins with knowledge and faith, as Isaac insists that
                knowledge is a gift, not the result of any ascetic struggle, but the consequence of
                the divine intervention (p. 235). As the monk progresses, faith swallows knowledge
                and gives the foretaste of the reality of the future life. Vesa cites Isaac’s
                observation that the inner senses now have received “intelligible resurrection”
                (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܩܝܡܬܐ ܡܬܝܕܥܢܝܬܐ</foreign>) in “the order of things which will be in the state of immortality
                and incorruptibility.” ( p.236) This is faith beyond dogmatic creeds or doctrines,
                and is now an experiential dimension participating in the divine mysteries by means
                of grace. Knowledge, as a collection of facts, no longer exists and is subsumed by
                faith which limpidly or clearly “sees.” One ascends to the heights of faith, as if
                on a ladder, but at the top, one no longer needs the ladder (p. 240).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The transition has now taken place to what Isaac terms un-knowledge (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܝܕܥܬܐ</foreign>). This
                does refer in a preliminary sense to the transcendence and incomprehensibility of
                God to human beings engaged passionately. No one is able to understand the thoughts
                of God without being crushed under the burden of the revelation. Vesa guides the
                reader through Isaac’s explication of this reality, but then moves to the higher
                level of un-knowledge—in which Vesa perceives Theodore of Mopsuestia’s concept of
                two ages influencing Isaac. Un-knowledge marks the entry in the second
                stage/post-Incarnation. Yet at the spiritual level, in one’s ascetic mind, one may
                mysteriously participate partially in divine knowledge. Nevertheless, the
                possibility of knowledge remains limited.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Isaac relies heavily upon Evagrius, citing him, “Blessed is he who has reached during
                prayer unconsciousness (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܝܕܥܬܐ</foreign>) which is not to be surpassed” (p. 244). The
                ascetic “gazes in ecstasy (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܚܘܪܐ ܕܒܬܡܗܐ</foreign>) at the unattainable things which do not
                belong to the world of mortals… this is the ignorance, the unknowledge (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܠܐ ܝܕܥܬܐ</foreign>)”
                (pp. 244–45). Vesa summarizes this mode of “knowledge beyond knowledge” to be
                “achieved in the grace of God, without any ascetic work, spontaneously and directly
                directed by God’s will” (p. 245).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Returning to the controversy that posthumously beset Isaac and other East Syriac
                mystical writers, Vesa reviews the condemnation by Timothy I in 787 of those who
                declare that the human nature of Christ can see his divinity, as well as those
                claiming that other created human beings are able to see the divine nature. But even
                Patriarch Timothy had to recognize that the event at Tabor demonstrates the
                possibility of knowing the royalty of Christ by means of the vision of the glory of
                God. John of Dalyatha is closest to expressing the possibility of Christ’s humanity
                seeing his divinity, understanding Christ as the icon and the knowledge of the
                Father, not only in his divinity, but in his humanity as well. John of Dalyatha,
                however, persistently notes that the divine vision occurs in “obscure light,” so
                that the difference between the nature or essence of God and divine glory are subtly
                distinguished.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Isaac of Nineveh draws a similar distinction between Creator and creation. Isaac uses
                three concepts—stirring, stupor or wonder, and vision—to express the spiritual stage
                in which the end result or knowledge will be the clothing of people in God’s light,
                effected by faith as the melding or mingling of active participation and divine
                intervention. <hi rend="italic">Theoria</hi> is also called “the vision of God”, when the intellect is
                moved without senses by the spiritual powers, and therefore, an experience of wonder
                as the highest cognitive order. It is the concept of revelation that most closely
                approximates his idea of divine vision, which remains essentially an analogous way
                of knowing. Isaac defines divine sight as “non-perceptible mental revelation” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܓܠܝܢܐ
                ܠܐ ܡܬܪܓܫܢܐ ܕܗܘܢܐ</foreign>). Revelation is silence of the intellect, so that knowledge is not
                an achievement of any mental or sense activity, but is generated out of the direct
                intervention of the Holy Spirit by the means of revelation.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">“Revelation is different from truth and knowledge in so far as revelation is not the
                exact truth, but only shows inclinations and signs corresponding to human strengths”
                (p. 270). Isaac suggests that revelation should not be called knowledge, but rather
                “overshadowing” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܓܢܢܘܬܐ</foreign>) caused by the direct intervention of the Spirit (pp.
                271–73).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Bishop Benedict-Valentin Vesa has steered the reader well through a complex web which
                the contemplative mind of the monk must navigate on the way to the attainment and
                participation in the reality of the divine ultimate truth. Admitting the difficulty
                of Isaac’s theology, Vesa has been able to systematically extract and contextualize
                Isaac of Nineveh’s steps along the way.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
