<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">J. F. Coakley, <hi rend="italic">Amphilochius of Iconium: The
                    opening of his homily on ‘My Father who sent me is greater than I’.</hi> The
                    Syriac text edited and translated (Alexandria, Virginia: Jericho Press, 2021)</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Mark</forename>
                        <surname>DelCogliano</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of St. Thomas, Minnesota</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2prdelcogliano</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Mark DelCogliano</author>
                        <title level="a">J. F. Coakley, <hi rend="italic">Amphilochius of Iconium: The
                            opening of his homily on ‘My Father who sent me is greater than I’.</hi> The
                            Syriac text edited and translated (Alexandria, Virginia: Jericho Press, 2021)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2PRDelcogliano.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="490" to="492">490-492</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="6"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                <head>J. F. Coakley, <hi rend="italic">Amphilochius of Iconium: The
                    opening of his homily on ‘My Father who sent me is greater than I’.</hi> The
                    Syriac text edited and translated (Alexandria, Virginia: Jericho Press, 2021). Pp.
                    iv + 10; $50.00.</head>
            </div>
            
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">Amphilochius of Iconium (340/345 to after 394) was an intimate
                part of the circle around the Cappadocian Fathers, being a cousin of Gregory of
                Nazianzus and a kind of disciple of Basil of Caesarea. With the latter he carried on
                an extensive correspondence about all matters of concern to the church of their day.
                Appointed bishop in 373, he acquired such a reputation in support of Basil’s
                ecclesiastical and theological agenda that he was designated as one of the
                guarantors of orthodoxy at the Council of Constantinople in 381
                (<hi rend="italic">Cod. Theod. </hi>16.1.3). His surviving
                corpus is not extensive, and much of it fragmentary, and yet enough remains to get a
                sense of Amphilochius as a Christian bishop and theologian, even if the precise
                contours of his genuine corpus remain debated.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"
                        ><p rend="H BR Footnote"> The best edition is
                        now<hi rend="italic"> Amphiloque d’Iconium: Homélies</hi>,
                        Tome I: <hi rend="italic">Homélies 1–5</hi>, Tome II: <hi rend="italic"
                            >Homélies 6–10</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Fragments divers; Épître
                            synodale; Lettre à Séleucos</hi>, introduction, translation, notes, and
                        index by Michel Bonnet in collaboration with Sever J. Voicu, Sources
                        chrétiennes 552 and 553 (Paris: Cerf, 2012).</p></note>
            </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Several of his homilies are extant in their entirety in Greek,
                but only a handful of Greek fragments from his homily on John 14:28 survive (really,
                John 14:28 combined with wording from John 14:24). There are also a few excerpts in
                Latin and Syriac. There is, however, a Syriac translation of the whole homily
                preserved on folios 95r–101v of British Library, Oriental ms. 8606, though the
                opening sections are missing. This Syriac text was edited and translated into
                English by Cyril Moss in 1930<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> Cyril Moss, “S. Amphilochius of Iconium on John 14:28:
                        The Father who sent me is greater than I,” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi>
                        43 (1930), 317–364.</p></note> and re-edited and translated into French in
                    2012.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="H BR Footnote"> Bonnet, <hi
                            rend="italic">Amphiloque d’Iconium: Homélies</hi>, Tome II,
                    192–225.</p></note> The slim volume under review here presents the Syriac text
                and an English translation of the formerly missing opening sections of the homily.
                This Syriac text is taken from two leaves of a manuscript in the archives of
                Westminster College, Cambridge (WGL 9/20), which once immediately preceded folios
                95r–101v in the above-mentioned British Library manuscript. At long last, then, the
                complete homily has been recovered in Syriac translation. In this homily
                Amphilochius engages in polemics over the exegesis of John 14:28, which was disputed
                in the Trinitarian and Christological debates of his era.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> The title of the homily was previously known, even if its
                beginning was missing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="H BR Footnote"
                        > The fragments discussed in this paragraph are edited in
                        Bonnet,<hi rend="italic"> Amphiloque d’Iconium: Homélies</hi>,
                        Tome II, 226–241.</p></note> Theodoret of Cyrrhus quoted this homily three
                times in his <hi rend="italic">Eranistes</hi> (see 1.56, 2.54, and 3.51), each time
                stating that it was a discourse on John 14:28 (ὁ πατὴρ μείζων μού ἐστιν) rather than
                on John 14:28 combined with John 14:24 as the newly edited Syriac text has it.
                Timothy Aelurus quoted two excerpts from this homily, both of which overlap with the
                newly edited Syriac text. The passages agree almost exactly; Coakley notes the few
                textual differences in his translation. The title Timothy gives to the homily also
                corresponds with the title in the newly edited Syriac text. The homily’s title was
                also preserved in Latin by Facundus in his <hi rend="italic">Pro defensione trium
                    capitulorum</hi> XI.3.2, as a sermon on the verse <hi rend="italic">qui misit me
                    pater maior me est</hi>, which accurately reflects the Syriac title. Facundus
                also preserved the opening words of the homily as <hi rend="italic">laborare nos
                    fecit certamen haereticorum</hi>, which matches the Syriac <foreign  xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܐ̣ܝ ܠܢ ܐܓܘܢܐ ܕܠܘܬ ܗܪ̈ܛܝܩܘ</foreign><hi
                    style="font-size:13pt">.</hi> Therefore, the newly edited Syriac text verifies
                this report of Facundus.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en"> Coakley’s very readable translation is preceded by a four-page
                introduction which in brief compass describes the manuscript’s history,
                Amphilochius’s life and writings, and the contents of the homily. The reader is
                referred to the previous translations in English and French to see what follows the
                beginning portion presented in this volume.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">I consider myself quite lucky to be the recipient of a copy of
                this exquisite volume for review, which was handcrafted at the private press of J.
                F. Coakley. The Syriac type is Oxford’s pica large face estrangela, and the volume
                consists of sixteen pages of Zerkall mould-made paper bound in chiyogami decorated
                paper boards. In this age of shoddily made books from major publishers, crappy
                print-on-demand copies, and the ubiquity of pdf scans, this volume has reminded me
                of just how beautiful books can be as physical objects.</p>
            </div>      
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

