<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Vast Lessons: Jacob of Edessa’s <hi rend="italic">The Six
                    Days</hi> and the Tools of Knowledge</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Ellen</forename>
                        <surname>Muehlberger</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Michigan</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n1muehlberger</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Ellen Muehlberger</author>
                        <title level="a">Vast Lessons: Jacob of Edessa’s <hi rend="italic">The Six
                            Days</hi> and the Tools of Knowledge</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N1Muehlberger.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="9" to="42">9-42</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="2"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-03-04">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Jacob of Edessa’s early eighth-century work <hi rend="italic">The Six
                    Days</hi> bursts with information about the cosmos and its inhabitants, the earth’s geography, its
                    species, and other details of nature. Scholars have long classified it in the genre
                    of hexameral literature; in the first part of this essay I explore the limits of
                    that identification. In the second part of the essay, I consider another ancient
                    genre by which <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> might be described—compendiary literature—but
                    demonstrate that the features of the text do not square with the generic conventions
                    scholars have identified as central to that literature. <hi rend="italic">The Six
                    Days</hi> thus bears a lesson for us: it cautions us to rethink our systems of classification for ancient
                    literature.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>          
           <div xml:id="hv25n1muehlberger.0" xml:lang="en">
               <p xml:lang="en">The surviving works attributed to Jacob of Edessa,
                fragmentary though some of them are, trace for us a picture of a deeply erudite,
                industrious scholar who spent almost as much time caring for the traditions he
                inherited as he did writing new work. Born in the middle of the seventh century,
                Jacob lived in an era of literary curation. He was one of its most energetic
                participants, translating and frequently glossing the work of earlier writers like
                Severus of Antioch;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >This essay derives from a keynote lecture I delivered at the Eighth North
                        American Syriac Symposium, and I am grateful to Kristian S. Heal and Susan
                        Ashbrook Harvey for the invitation. The comments and questions I received
                        there, particularly from Adam Becker, helped shape my thoughts, and this
                        article was substantially improved by the comments of the anonymous
                        reviewers for <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi>, to whom I am also
                        grateful.</p><p rend="footnote text"> Sebastian P. Brock, “Jacob the
                        Annotator. Jacob’s Annotations” in Gregorios Yohanna Ibrahim and George
                        Anton Kiraz, ed., <hi rend="italic">Studies on Jacob of Edessa</hi>, Gorgias
                        Eastern Christian Studies 25 (Piscataway, N.J.: Gorgias, 2010),
                    1–13.</p></note> preparing a reworked Old Testament from multiple extant ancient
                translations; refining and transmitting philological knowledge of both Greek and
                    Syriac<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text"> Alison G.
                        Salvesen, “Ya‘qub of Edessa” in Sebastian Brock et al, eds.,
                        <hi rend="italic">Gorgias Encyclopedic Dictionary of the Syriac Heritage </hi>(Piscataway,
                        N.J.: Gorgias Press, 2011), which draws from the chronicles of Gregory
                        Barhebraeus (1226–1286) and Michael the Syrian (1126–1199).</p></note>; and
                clarifying philosophical terms and their usage, especially as they entered into
                discussions of Christology.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                        rend="footnote text"> Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek Philosophy in
                        His Hexaemeron” in Bas ter Haar Romeny, ed., <hi rend="italic">Jacob of
                            Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His Day</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 2008),
                        223–38; Richard Price, “The Christological Controversies of the Age of Jacob
                        of Edessa” in Ibrahim and Kiraz, ed., <hi rend="italic">Studies on Jacob of
                            Edessa</hi>, 81–92; Daniel King, “Why Were the Syrians Interested in
                        Greek Philosophy?” in Philip Wood, ed., <hi rend="italic">History and
                            Identity in the Late Antique Near East</hi>, Oxford Studies in Late
                        Antiquity (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013), 61–82. See also the
                        survey of Jacob's career in Jack Boulos Victor Tannous, "Syria between
                        Byzantium and Islam: Making Incommensurables Speak" (PhD diss., Princeton
                        University, 2010), 169–211.</p></note> The range of Jacob’s interests aligns
                with what much later chroniclers would tell us about the terrain of Jacob’s life: he
                moved from place to place, entering the monastery at Qenneshrin, possibly moving to
                Alexandria for a period of further study, then coming to Edessa to serve as its
                bishop, twice, in two short offices that were interrupted by a long period, in which
                he lived in some of the most active and important centers of learning of his
                    day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"> Alison G.
                        Salvesen, “Jacob of Edessa’s Life and Work: A Biographical Sketch” in ter
                        Haar Romeny, ed., <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Edessa and the Syriac Culture
                            of His Day</hi>, 1–10. </p></note> In life, Jacob explored his world,
                working in established networks and institutions centered on the transmission of
                knowledge, yet was ungoverned by any single one of them. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">What remains to us from his pen is similarly expansive and thus challenging to
                characterize. As an example, consider the large work Jacob composed in the first
                decade of the eighth century, of which Jean-Baptiste Chabot published an edition in
                    1928.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">
                        Jean-Baptist Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron seu
                            in opus creationis libri septem</hi>, Scriptores Syri, series secunda 56
                        (Paris: CSCO, 1928); A. Vaschalde, trans. (Leuven: CSCO, 1932).</p></note>
                The text survives in at least five manuscripts, but rather than collate them, Chabot
                chose to reproduce the best preserved among them, a piece dated to 837 C.E. and thus
                remarkably close to the era of the work’s composition. Chabot’s choice to represent
                a single manuscript allows us to see the choices other editors in antiquity made to
                categorize the text. In his edition we encounter the stylized header superimposed
                periodically across the top of successive leaves of the manuscript, marking
                variously what book of the work we are in, the author’s name, and the topic of the
                work. So, across the top of the printed pages 168–69 there are a few small
                decorative elements intermixed with words a little larger than the columns of the
                text, that say, “the fourth book of the six days, by the holy Jacob of Edessa”;
                similar headers appear every ten pages throughout the manuscript, identifying which
                of the six books a reader has turned to and usually repeating the topic and the
                author: “the third book on the six days by the holy Jacob of Edessa,” or “the fifth
                book on the six days by the holy Jacob of Edessa.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                    n="6"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                            Hexaemeron</hi>, 108–9, 188–89. The pattern is regularized with few
                        exceptions: at times only one folio bears the header, usually for a shorter
                        version that includes only the book and the title (see Book 4, marked at 148
                        or 158; Book 6 marked at 238 or 268); there are a few interruptions, such as
                        when a part of Book 5 receives a header that marks it as Book 4 (198–99), or
                        when the pattern is skipped entirely (there is no header where one is
                        expected at 248).</p></note> Thus intoned throughout the text are indices of
                what one is reading and where one is in the text. Books are technologies, and their
                format has an effect on how we process the material they convey. Though there are
                few explicit signals in this text—no regular indentation, minimal variation in hand,
                few marginal marks— the headers are implicit prescriptions for interpretation: we
                should read this work knowing it was written by Jacob of Edessa, and it is a work
                that treats the six-day creation, that is to say the origin of the world as
                described in the book of Genesis.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">An alternate summation preserved in the manuscript Chabot reproduced gives a broader
                sense of work’s contents. The very first lines in the text offer an abstract
                description, or perhaps even a title, for what is to come: “The book of the treatise
                on existence, which is to say, the establishment of the creatures.”<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                            rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 2.</p></note> This lede,
                though it appears only once, may be a clue to Jacob’s sense of his work’s
                predecessors, as it is precisely the same slug used for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hexaemeron</hi> by Jacob of Serugh, written two centuries earlier.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"> T. Muraoka, <hi
                            rend="italic">Jacob of Serugh’s Hexaemeron</hi> (Leuven: Peeters, 2018),
                        6n1. I thank an anonymous reviewer for pointing out this overlap and its
                        significance.</p></note> But it also prepares readers to expect a treatment
                to follow that will be perhaps more capacious than what the headers on the text
                indicate. From it, one might await a general exposition on existence and the natural
                order, without necessarily expecting a text that is bounded by, or even pays much
                attention to, Genesis 1:1 to 2:3. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">These two summaries signal different scopes for the work. Scholarship on <hi
                    rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> has consistently elected to follow the headers,
                pinning it as one example among the other homilies, treatises, and commentaries that
                focus on the six-day creation that opens the book of Genesis. Chabot, for instance,
                does so at the very first lines of his introduction to the text.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                            >Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, i.</p></note> Having been located in
                this category, Jacob’s text has benefitted from a number of studies, most recently
                essays in a volume edited by Gregorios Yohanna Ibrahim and George Anton Kiraz
                comprising several talks from a 2008 conference in Aleppo, as well as several pieces
                in the volume edited by Bas ter Haar Romeny in the same year.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text"> Ibrahim and Kiraz, eds., <hi
                            rend="italic">Studies on Jacob of Edessa</hi>; ter Haar Romeny, ed., <hi
                            rend="italic">Jacob of Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His
                        Day.</hi></p></note> Marina Greatrex’s 2000 University of Wales, Cardiff
                College dissertation provided a translation of parts of Book 1, Book 2, and Book
                    4.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> Marina
                        Greatrex, “Memre One, Two and Four of the Hexaemeron of Jacob of Edessa:
                        Introduction, Translation and Text” (PhD diss., University of Wales,
                        Cardiff, 2000); see also her later articles, “The Angelology in the
                        Hexaemeron of Jacob of Edessa,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the Canadian
                            Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 4 (2004): 33–46 and as Marina Wilks,
                        “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek Philosophy in His Hexameron” in ter Haar
                        Romeny, ed., <hi rend="italic">Jacob of Edessa and the Syriac Culture of His
                            Day</hi>, 223–38.</p></note> Before that, the text had received
                attention in the form of extended articles and books, grouped in the late nineteenth
                century and in the latter half of twentieth century.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"> Jean-Pierre Paulin Martin,
                        “L’Hexaméron de Jacques d’Édesse,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                        asiatique</hi> 8,11(1888): 155–219, 401–90; James Darmester, “Jacques
                        d’Édesse et Claude Ptolémée,” <hi rend="italic">Revue des études
                            grecques</hi> 3 (1890): 180–88; Arthur Hjelt,
                        <hi rend="italic">Études sur l’Hexaméron de Jacques d’Edesse, notamment sur ses notions géographiques contenues dans le 3ième traité </hi>(Helsingfors:
                        J.C. Frenckell, 1892) and “Pflanzennamen aus dem Hexaëmeron Jacob’s von
                        Edessa” in Carl Bezold, ed., <hi rend="italic">Orientalische Studien:
                            Theodor Nöldeke zum siebzigsten Geburtstag (2. März 1906) gewidmet von
                            Freunden und Schülern</hi> (Gieszen: Alfred Töpelmann, 1906), 571–79;
                        Thomas Hunter Weir, “L’Hexaméron de Jacques d’Édesse,” <hi rend="italic"
                            >Journal asiatique</hi> 9,12 (1898): 550–51; Lorenz Schlimme,
                        “Synkretismus in der syrischen Hexaemeron-Literatur (exemplarisch
                        dargestellt an der Rezeption der antiken Zoologie)” in Gernot Weissner, ed.,
                            <hi rend="italic">Erkenntnisse und Meinungen I</hi>., Göttinger
                        Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 3 (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1973),
                        164–88 and “Die Lehre des Jakob von Edessa vom Fall des Teufels,” OrChr 61
                        (1977): 41–58; Erik ten Napel, “Some Remarks on the Hexaemeral Literature in
                        Syriac” in Hans J. W. Drijvers et al., <hi rend="italic">IV Symposium
                            Syriacum, 1984: Literary Genres in Syriac Literature (Groningen –
                            Oosterhesselen
                        10</hi>–<hi rend="italic">12 September), </hi>OCA 229
                        (Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1987),
                    57–69.</p></note> All of these begin from the premise that <hi rend="italic">The
                    Six Days</hi> is, foremost, the text described in the headers, namely, Jacob’s
                contribution the hexameral genre.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">That premise is not wrong, on its face: <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> does draw
                from the Genesis account, and the name I use in this essay follows on that fact. But
                I want to create some space between the text and the label “hexameral” in order to
                facilitate consideration of what that label does. In asking us to pause this way, I
                join other scholars of Syriac literature from antiquity, and specialists in early
                Christian studies, who have drawn attention to the habits of categorization. The
                recent work of writers like James E. Walters, Jeffrey Wickes, and Peter Martens
                emphasizes that the apparatus of knowledge we choose to adopt can shape both what we
                recognize when we look at ancient texts and what we think when we read them.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"> Exemplary in this
                        are James E. Walters, “Reconsidering the Compositional Unity of
                            Aphrahat’s <hi rend="italic">Demonstrations</hi>” in Aaron Michael Butts
                        and Robin Darling Young, ed., <hi rend="italic">Syriac Christian Culture:
                            Beginnings to Renaissance</hi> (Washington, DC: Catholic University of
                        America Press, 2020), 50–65, as well as his forthcoming monograph,
                        “Deconstructing the Demonstrations: Reconsidering the Composition and
                        Context of an Early Syriac Corpus”; Jeffrey Wickes, “Imagining Ephrem the
                        Author” in Lewis Ayres, Matthew Crawford, and Michael Champion, ed.,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Intellectual World of Christian Late Antiquity: Reshaping the Classical Tradition, 100 – 600 </hi>CE
                        (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, <hi rend="italic">forthcoming</hi>);
                        and Peter Martens, “Classifying Early Christian Writings: Boundaries,
                        Arrangements, and Latent Dynamics,”
                        <hi rend="italic">Early Christianity </hi>12 (2021):
                        1–16. I am grateful to all three of these scholars for generously sharing
                        their work in draft with me.</p></note> In the case of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Six Days</hi>, which treats almost every type of creature and natural phenomenon
                and place in existence, to label it “hexameral” is to lead readers to see it as
                invested in, even defined by, its relationship to scripture—and this despite the
                fact that we understand that the text of Genesis is only the barest of scaffolds
                unifying the otherwise quite harlequin collection of texts so labeled. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">So, this essay is a call to allow <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> to be more than
                what it has been labeled, to encourage readers new and veteran to grapple with just
                how ambitious a text it is, all toward the end of them seeing the sheer amount of
                information it is trying to convey and hearing its lessons about how to bear such a
                magnitude of knowledge. Encouraging this readership is not just a matter of applying
                new labels, however. Though there are emerging options for describing
                <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>available in scholarship
                about ancient literature more generally, they can be as hidebound as earlier labels:
                like “hexameral,” not inaccurate, but surely insufficient. Any representation of
                complexity on the order of what is found in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> is
                necessarily an approximation, and approximations (as their name tells us) get close
                to what they represent while never quite landing directly on target. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The first section of the essay considers what calling <hi rend="italic">The Six
                    Days</hi> a hexameral text does to our understanding of its contents and its
                purpose. The section following tries out one of the newer scholarly categories in
                which the text could be located—namely, compendiary works—but then details how that
                label, too, fails at a certain point. Paradoxically, the tools of knowledge we might
                use to encourage new readers to engage with <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> can
                in fact stand in the way of their comprehension and even blunt their curiosities. As
                we will see, <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>bears vast
                lessons for scholars working in Syriac literature, but could also bear on other
                areas of interest in the ancient world. The earnest disposition Jacob displays in
                the text, registering its expansiveness and attempting to represent its breadth
                while understanding the hard limits of taxonomy, is a model for us of how to manage
                unruly knowledge without circumscribing it.</p>
           </div>
            <div xml:id="hv25n1muehlberger.1" xml:lang="en">
                <head>I: <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> and the Hexameral Genre</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">In North America, the academic study of the Syriac
                    tradition has taken a welcoming, and welcome, turn in the last twenty years.
                    Scholars recognize the immense value that Syriac texts can have for the study of
                    antiquity; at the same time, we understand that those texts are understudied, in
                    part because scholarship on Syriac has never benefitted from the level of
                    institutional or disciplinary support that bolsters the study of, say, Greek and
                    Latin texts. So, several projects have aimed to approximate that institutional
                    benefit: for instance, to entice new readers by addressing the comparative
                    dearth of opportunities to learn the language outside a handful of universities
                    that regularly offer instruction, as Beth Mardutho has done; or, to compile
                    collections of free, accessible introductory materials and bibliographies, like
                    what is available at syriaca.org. This turn is in part
                    inspired by changes in university commitments to research here, where the value
                    of the study of the humanities in general has been under question, and where
                    pre-modern languages and literatures specifically have seen a decline in
                    support. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">But the turn would be apt at any moment, because a field is not constituted by
                    its experts alone; rather, it is the collection of people progressing in time
                    toward greater knowledge and familiarity with the field under study. In Syriac
                    studies, this includes the student learning the formal grammar of the language
                    for the first time alongside the postdoctoral fellow expanding their
                    dissertation toward a monograph and the senior scholar who commands
                    bibliographies barely imaginable in their magnitude. It acknowledges that the
                    new student can and may become the senior scholar, who was once that new student
                    herself. Attending to the progression of knowledge in this way practically
                    requires a welcoming orientation in the scholarship, and so a significant
                    portion of the field has been making an effort to contextualize the authors,
                    events, and texts we write about.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Much of this contextualizing work comes in the form of summaries or entries in
                    reference works, bearing signposts designed to guide a reader who has not yet
                    encountered or even begun to digest a text, but may want to have a sense of what
                    it comprises before she starts. In the case of Jacob of Edessa’s <hi
                        rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>, the summaries that scholars offer all point
                    in the same direction. They tell us, in a general way, that <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Six Days</hi> is a work of scriptural interpretation. The indications
                    can be spotted by glancing at where scholars locate the text. In his patrology
                    of Syriac texts, for example, Ignatius Ortiz de Urbina classified <hi
                        rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> as one example of Jacob’s “scriptural
                    studies,” placing it alongside his editions of biblical books and short
                    fragments of biblical commentary.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ortiz de Urbina, ed., <hi rend="italic">Patrologia
                                Syriaca</hi> (Rome: Pontificum Institutum Orientalium Studiorum,
                            1958), 168–69, where the Latin carries an extra implication in a single
                            abbreviated letter: <hi rend="italic">Studia de S.
                        Scriptura.</hi></p></note> Sebastian P. Brock, writing to introduce readers
                    to biblical work in Syriac, discussed
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>in a chapter on
                    “biblical commentaries,” where he names Jacob “the chief luminary of the field
                    of Syriac biblical exegesis in the seventh century.”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"> Brock,
                            <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac Tradition </hi>(Kottayam:
                            SEERI, 1989), 65.</p></note> Or, the character of a text can be conveyed
                    with a simple descriptor. Brock, again, labels <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> specifically as Jacob’s “most important work of exegesis.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"> Brock, <hi
                                rend="italic">Bible in the Syriac Tradition</hi>, 66.</p></note>
                    Jonathan Loopstra, writing thirty-five years later, followed Brock to identify
                        <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> as a commentary.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"> “The Syriac Bible and Its
                            Interpretation,” in <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World</hi>, ed. Daniel
                            King (Routledge, 2018), 301, where he also places it in line with
                            Jacob’s translation and edition work.</p></note> Introducing readers to
                    some scholia of Jacob’s, Michael Penn lists <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    among the “extant exegetical writings” of this “renowned interpreter of
                        Scripture.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Michael Philip Penn, <hi rend="italic">When Christians First Met
                                Muslims: A Sourcebook of the Earliest Syriac Writings on Islam</hi>
                            (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2015), 180.</p></note> These
                    are characterizations—just sketches, really, a phrase here or there—but they
                    make a difference, as they come from experts across different eras and in
                    different genres of scholarly writing. In light of their varied points of
                    origin, they cohere remarkably, such that almost any reader coming across
                    scholarly mention of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> gets the message is
                    that it is a commentary on a biblical text, a work of exegesis.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Let us consider for a moment what the term “exegesis” implies. It arrives in the
                    company of its supposed opposite, “eisegesis,” and the two together provide a
                    binary way to evaluate interpretations of texts. “Exegesis” takes place when
                    readers merely “lead out” from the text the information and meaning it already
                    contains, while “eisegesis” involves reading into the text things and senses
                    that lie external to it. In the context of biblical studies, there is such a
                    preference for one over the other that “exegesis” has come to be a synonym for
                    “interpretation,” the assumption being that no good reader would purposefully
                    import externalities to the text. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The thing is, all readers bring things when they read; texts do not mean anything
                    on their own. Thus, the imposition of the binary of exegesis and eisegesis onto
                    modes of reading is an epistemological claim, a way to assert that some ways of
                    interacting with a text are neutral, natural, and even necessary. Moreover,
                    given the historical alignment in Christian thought between the categories of
                    novelty and heresy, it is not difficult to see that the label of “eisegesis”
                    ports a theological claim about the modes of reading it describes. If, on the
                    other hand, one is engaged in “exegesis,” one is assumed not to bring anything
                    “in” to one’s interpretation, so that interpretation can be thought of as merely
                    an extension of the text and so in the case of reading scripture, bears the
                    authority of the text.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The term “exegesis” also suggests a context of composition and even a range of
                    intention for the texts it describes. One of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days’ </hi>closest readers over
                    the last few decades, Marina Wilks, has written that Jacob’s goal in creating
                    the text was “compiling a systematic exegesis.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19"
                        n="19"><p rend="footnote text"> Wilks, “Jacob’s of Edessa’s Use of Greek
                            Philosophy,” 225.</p></note> All of the other scholars whose
                    characterizations of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> I visited in the above
                    located it among examples of Jacob’s intensive textual work with the Bible, his
                    translations and revisions and editions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> For another example, see Raymond Marie
                            Tonneau, who groups the text in a lineage of exegetical pieces, from
                            Ephrem to anonymous catenists and collectors of scholia, who all aim to
                            provide a lens for better viewing the text they study. Tonneau, “Texte
                            syriaque de la Genèse, L’Héxaéméron,” <hi rend="italic">Le
                            Muséon</hi> 59 (1946): 333–44, at 334–35.</p></note> Doing so implies
                    that <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> was created through efforts oriented on
                    scripture, just as the tasks of edition and translation are; it also induces a
                    reader to assume that the text, if produced by tightly focused work, will be
                    subordinate to the scripture it exegetes. Approaching <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> with this context in hand does allow scholars to do certain kinds
                    of historical reconstruction that cannot be accomplished in other ways. For
                    example, assuming that Jacob’s purpose in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> is
                    accurate explication of a scriptural text, one could look over his shoulder, so
                    to speak, at the text he is working with, in order to capture the Bible as he
                    knew it and thus to have a historical snapshot of the Syriac Bible (or bible
                    traditions) in Jacob’s day. Alison G. Salvesen’s work recovering part of the
                    Syriac Bible from reading Jacob’s <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    demonstrates the productivity of such an approach.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"> Alison G. Salvesen, “The
                            Authorial Spirit? Biblical Citations in Jacob of Edessa’s
                                Hexaemeron,” <hi rend="italic">Aramaic Studies</hi> 6:2 (2008):
                            207–25.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The limits of this characterization come into greater relief, however, the moment
                    one turns to actually reading <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>, as it does
                    not conform to the expectations of fidelity to, and even intimacy with,
                    scripture that labels like “commentary” and “exegesis” convey. First of all, if
                    it is oriented to the creation account in Genesis, <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> makes reference to that text remarkably infrequently. Lorenz
                    Schlimme subtly registered this fact in 1977, confirming the prevalent scholarly
                    understanding that the work was “designed fundamentally as an exegetical
                    commentary,” while at the same time noting that Jacob “probably only understood
                    the genre of ‘exegetical commentary’ as a general framework or outline.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"> Schlimme,
                            <hi rend="italic">Der Hexaemeronkommentar des Moses bar Kepha: Einleitung, Übersetzung, und Untersuchungen </hi>(Wiesbaden:
                            Harrassowitz, 1977), 674. Framed in the terms laid out by Hilary A.
                            Clark, this would make the Genesis account the “encyclopedic figure” for
                                <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> (Clark, “Encyclopedic
                            Discourse,” <hi rend="italic">SubStance</hi> 21 [1992]:
                        95–110).</p></note> The relationship of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    to Genesis 1:1–2:3 is in reality even looser than Schlimme’s sober observation
                    lets on. The contents of the biblical index prepared by A. Vaschalde suggest
                    that the text of Genesis was only a faintly rendered backdrop for Jacob’s
                    thought. Passages or phrases from Genesis 1:1 to 2:3 appear in sequence over the
                    course of its seven books; however, those eighteen references are fewer than one
                    would expect in roughly one hundred seventy-eight manuscript pages of text
                    (about two and a half citations per book or roughly one every ten manuscript
                    pages). What is more, those eighteen references to the earliest portions of
                    Genesis are overmatched by the text’s attention to other biblical books: for
                    instance, Job is cited almost as many times (seventeen), while Matthew is cited
                    more often (twenty-three times); by far the Psalms receive the most referential
                    attention, with eighty-seven citations scattered over books one through
                        seven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Vaschalde, “Index Biblicus,” 307–10.</p></note> So, to suggest the
                    explication of Genesis 1:1 to 2:3 is the central task of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Six Days</hi> is to give readers a false sense of the text’s purview.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Its purpose is also broader than “commentary” would indicate. For under the
                    lightly sketched template of the six-day creation, Jacob offers an expansive, if
                    not entirely comprehensive, tour of the known world and its inhabitants, which
                    neither begins nor ends with reference to scripture. The first book of the work,
                    for example, opens with a long exposition about the nature of angels, their
                    minds, Satan’s rebellion and what his rebellion reveals about the corruptibility
                    of angels, the prospect of free will, and more, all intermixed, with no
                    demarcation of what is scriptural or unmentioned in scripture, and no reference
                    to specific phrases or passages from Genesis or any other biblical text.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">After that first book and its discourse on the nature and status of angels
                    contained therein, <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> turns toward a different
                    project: to catalog the components of the material world in encompassing detail.
                    To set the stage for his catalog, Jacob starts by describing the four elements
                    of Aristotelian physics—earth, air, water, and fire—explaining how they have
                    interacted to produce the peculiar landscape of this planet where they are mixed
                        together.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">
                            For a broader discussion of the influence of Aristotle on the entire
                            text, see Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek Philosophy.” To learn
                            more about its place in the trajectory of science in Syriac, see Muriel
                            Debié, “Sciences et savants syriaques: une histoire multiculturelle” in
                            Émilie Villey, ed., <hi rend="italic">Les sciences en syriaque</hi>
                            (Paris: Geuthner, 2014), 9–66.</p></note> Then, he details the
                    geological formations of the planet, from caves to volcanoes to the
                    peculiarities of the fossil record; he reckons every possible location of water
                    in the inhabited and uninhabited world—ice, rain, fog, humid wind, oceans, bays,
                    rivers, streams, and swamps among them. He enumerates the various kinds of
                    plants that exist as a gardener would, by their growth habits—which are annual,
                    which are biennial, and which are perennial?—and then as a farmer would—which
                    are edible and which are inedible? He treats the sun, the moon, the planets,
                    equinoxes and solstices, fish, cetaceans, crustaceans, shorebirds, raptors,
                    bees, carnivorous wild beasts and the array of domesticated animals: sheep and
                    oxen, cows and camels. Jacob’s treatise is, in a phrase, a massive education on
                    the categories of the world, originating from the simplicity of the four
                    Aristotelean elements and ramifying outward to the thousands of peculiar things
                    composed from them.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It appears that Jacob was aware that <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> defied
                    expectations about its content by encompassing far more than readers may have
                    expected from a treatment of the first few chapters of Genesis. He introduces a
                    textual device to voice and, at the same time, to mitigate that expectation. An
                    interlocutor named Constantine interrupts book one, just after Jacob has offered
                    his long discourse on divine beings, their wills, and their ranks, saying “I
                    know enough about [these beings], based on what you have said, but I am eager
                    for whatever can be produced and written about them from the holy scriptures. I
                    want them placed here for me here, alongside your discourse; elucidated and
                    shown to me, that I might know their meaning.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                                Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 17.</p></note> Constantine’s voice points
                    to what has been missing so far: a discussion of Genesis, or really, of any
                    scriptural reference that might anchor Jacob’s performance. In response, Jacob
                    offers a short florilegium, alighting briefly on various parts of Genesis
                    outside the creation account before he moves to more extensive reproductions
                    from several other books of the Old Testament and the New: Job, Psalms, Daniel,
                    letters from Paul or attributed to Paul, Acts, the Gospels.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The character of Constantine acts like other fictional characters in ancient
                    dialogue texts. They are there to introduce an alternate perspective, often to
                    challenge the author whose voice and goals dominate the work. Such characters
                    are an effect expressed by the very text that presents them to us, and we should
                    remember that they are a creation of the author who composes their words.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"> Interlocutors in
                            dialogues serve many purposes, but they are always present at the behest
                            of and literally under the hand of the author. For a survey of what
                            interlocutors accomplish, see the discussions in Alberto Rigolio,
                            <hi rend="italic">Christians in Conversation: A Guide to Late Antique Dialogues in Greek and Syriac, </hi>Oxford
                            Studies in Late Antiquity (New York: Oxford University Press, 2019);
                            Andrew S. Jacobs, “Gender, Conversion, and the End of Empire in the
                            Teaching of Jacob Newly Baptized,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies </hi>29
                            (2021): 93–120; and Michail Kitsos, “Speaking as the Other: Late Ancient
                            Jewish and Christian Multivocal Texts and the Creation of Religious
                            Legitimacy” (PhD diss., University of Michigan, 2020). </p></note> In
                    the case of Jacob’s Constantine, it is a half-hearted creation; as a
                    chararacter, he hovers on the periphery of the text and is never fully realized.
                    His first appearance is perhaps with the question that opens the text of the <hi
                        rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>; the Latin translator assumes so and
                    supplies the name to introduce the questioner, as if in a screenplay, while in
                    the Syriac, the question comes from nowhere.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                        n="27"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                                Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 2; Vaschalde, trans., 1.</p></note> The
                    second time Constantine appears, his name is spelled out in full, but the third
                    time, it is shortened. In that last appearance, Constantine only utters a brief
                    affirmation of what Jacob has said.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 3 and 4.</p></note> When Constantine asks for
                    scriptural references for the discussion of heavenly beings, his name is
                    abbreviated and marked with a supralinear stroke, and that is the final time he
                    appears in the work Jacob has written.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 17.</p></note> One last time he appears, in the
                    ending to <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>composed by
                    George of the Arabs after Jacob’s death, but there he is simply addressed in the
                    vocative and does not speak.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 356.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This is odd, because given the arrangement of content in the rest of the
                    work—heavy excursions into surveys, taxonomies, catalogs of knowledge, with very
                    little dependence upon the text of Genesis or any other biblical
                    book—Constantine could have in fact appeared throughout, popping up in each book
                    of the text to ask his one question again and again, “Show me where this is in
                    scripture?” Yet he does not appear, Jacob having laid aside the tool of the
                    conjured interlocutor and the dialogue format very early to move on to his
                    central task. For that task, exposition and exploration are the method, not
                    exegesis, and certainly not dialogue. Questions about attention to scripture
                    arise exactly once in this text, and then fall silent. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Jacob’s invented interlocutor draws attention to one way
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>runs against the
                    expectations created by placing it among hexameral texts, but there are
                    additional ways it is out of step with that group. Consider how it differs from
                    Basil of Caesarea’s <hi rend="italic">Homilies on the Hexaemeron</hi>, which
                    were already important in the Greek tradition of this genre, but also were
                    translated multiple times into Syriac and served as a model for Jacob’s
                        text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> In
                            addition to the translation edited by <hi rend="italic">The Syriac
                                Version of the Hexaemeron by Basil of Caesarea</hi>, ed. Robert W.
                            Thomson, Syr 222–23 (Leuven: CSCO, 1995), there is the literal
                            translation documented by the presence of several excerpts in a masora
                            discussed by Jonathan Loopstra (<hi rend="italic">The Patristic
                                “Masora”: A Study of Patristic Collections in Syriac Handbooks from
                                the Near East</hi>, CSCO 689 [Leuven: Peeters, 2020], 130–31); cf.
                            Paul J. Fedwick,
                            <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Basiliana Universalis: A Study of the Manuscript Tradition of the Works of Basil of Caesarea: The Homiliae morales; Hexaemeron, De litteris, with additional coverage of the letters, </hi>vol
                            2.1 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1996), 243–44, cited by Loopstra,
                            <hi rend="italic">Patristic “Masora”, </hi>131n31.
                            I am grateful to Dr. Loopstra for sharing these pieces with me. For
                            Basil’s <hi rend="italic">Hex</hi> as a model for <hi rend="italic">The
                                Six Days</hi>, see Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek
                            Philosophy,” 224.</p></note> Basil’s work exemplifies a tendency common
                    to the genre, in that it examines the natural world not to know that world or
                    its inhabitants in themselves, but in order to develop from it ethical models
                    for humanity to follow. As Patricia Cox Miller has argued, the primary reason to
                    understand the fauna of creation, for writers like Basil, was to draw moral
                    wisdom from what one sees. Basil argues that we are by the order of nature on
                    the one side of a divide between animal and human, yet we possess qualities from
                    both and thus we must constantly remain vigilant in our deeds so that we do not
                    slip to the other side by prioritizing the bestial. He observes that in reality
                    many animals manage to do just this—that is, they manage to act according to
                    reason and against their animal nature, to do what is morally right. So, Basil
                    claims, if animals can act rightly, despite their lower nature, we certainly
                        can.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Patricia Cox Miller,
                            <hi rend="italic">In the Eye of the Animal: Zoological Imagination in Ancient Christianity </hi>(Philadelphia:
                            University of Pennsylvania Press, 2018), 104.</p></note> His exploration
                    of animals and their actions leads to reflections on
                    <hi rend="italic">us </hi>and <hi rend="italic">our</hi>
                    actions. Or, as Miller puts it, “When one ‘reads’ animals along with Basil, one
                    is also reading the human self.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Miller, <hi rend="italic">In the Eye of the
                                Animal</hi>, 112. For more on how Basil’s take on creation does
                            align with Jacob’s, see Aboud Ishaq, “Jacob of Edessa’s Hexaemeron: A
                            Primitive Comparison with Basil of Caesarea’s Hexaemeron,” <hi
                                rend="italic">ParOr</hi> 38 (2013): 109–38.</p></note> In this key
                    text, human beings are the obvious problem at the center of creation; our
                    ethical failings need correction, and the payoff for investigating the filigreed
                    corners of the landscape, for knowing all the habits of the sentient creatures,
                    is the ability for human beings to correct our failings through judicious
                    imitation of the animals we learn about—the busy bee, the docile deer, and
                    others. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In Jacob’s discussion of humanity, however, ethical issues barely register, and
                    the animal world does not bear lessons for us. Instead, his concerns are
                    mechanical, anatomical, and taxonomical. Jacob’s exposition on humanity and our
                    place in the created order occurs in the first portion of Book seven.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"> Part way through
                            book seven, the manuscript notes Jacob’s death and reports that the
                            remainder of the work, the last five folios or so, were composed by
                            Jacob’s former student George (Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                                Edesseni Hexaemeron,</hi> 347).</p></note> He considers just what in
                    the human being represents the “image and likeness” that God posited as a
                    template for making humanity. There is the problem that, though God spoke of
                    using a single “image” and a single “likeness,” humanity is several and varied,
                    so Jacob offers a discussion of the Hebrew text and how its use of an idiom for
                    humanity, rather than the single word for human being, means the entire species
                    of human beings bear the likeness and image as a group.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 283–84. For a
                            parallel discussion of the seeming singularity of the “image” or
                            “likeness” in contrast with the variety of human beings, see Candace
                            Buckner’s discussion of the <hi rend="italic">Life of Aphou</hi>
                            in “Made in an Imperfect Image: Race, Ethnicity, Disability, and
                            Infirmity in the Life of Aphou,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the
                                American Academy of Religion</hi> 87 (2019): 483–511, at
                        493.</p></note> Jacob then enters an anatomical catalog in the record,
                    detailing the composition of the human body from feet to head to spine to
                    genitalia, in that order.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 246–58.</p></note> The other inhabitants of the
                    world, who in other readings of Genesis are moral exemplars for humanity to
                    follow, appear here only as contextual proof of our superior design. To further
                    demonstrate, Jacob makes a list, forensically comparing the mechanical
                    advantages human bodies have over animal bodies, showing how we (literally)
                    stand apart: we walk on two feet, not four; our knees bend in a different
                    direction than what seem to be animals’ “knees”; our hands are dexterous; our
                    heads are round.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>,
                            304–6.</p></note> Later, Jacob offers other lists, detailing the
                    qualities of the mind, relative to God, and the properties of the human
                        soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 310–12
                            and 326–28, respectively, though neither is marked in the margins like
                            the first list.</p></note> The cumulative effect of the lists of Book
                    seven is to position humanity between the animals and God, clarifying how our
                    existence confirms the skillful work of the creator, who made us more capacious
                    than the animals. This is practically speaking orthogonal to the perspective in
                    Basil’s hexameral work, where animals are <hi rend="italic">better</hi> at
                    showing human values than we are. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">At this point it may be fair to ask, just what does “hexameral” indicate? Texts
                    that have been given that label come in many forms—in verse and in prose, in
                    homily and confession and commentary—and are written from multiple perspectives.
                    Consider just this selective range of texts beyond Basil’s and Jacob’s, here in
                    alphabetical order by author: Anastasius of Sinai, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anagogicarum contemplationum in Hexaemeron</hi>; Augustine, <hi
                        rend="italic">Confessions</hi>; George of Pisidia, <hi rend="italic">Opus
                        sex dierum seu mundi opificium</hi>; Gregory of Nazianzus, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Third Theological Oration</hi>; Jacob of Serugh, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hexaemeron</hi>; John Philoponus, <hi rend="italic">De opificio mundi</hi>;
                    Moses bar Kepha, <hi rend="italic">Hexaemeron</hi>. They are so various that
                    this is only one thing that unites them. The mere fact of treating, in whatever
                    depth, the early chapters of Genesis appears to be the qualifying
                    characteristic, a situation which reveals a deeper function for the label. If
                    reference to the early parts of Genesis is enough to qualify a work for the
                    hexameral genre, then the reference to the early parts of Genesis is the most
                    salient part of that work when it is classified as “hexameral.” By extension,
                    the other topics covered or books drawn from by such a work are secondary to its
                    discussion of the early parts of Genesis. That puts scripture at the center of
                    any text that uses Genesis 1 and 2 to speak about the natural world, in any way
                    that it might. In turn, seeing scripture as automatically at the center of any
                    writing that refers to it upholds an assumption on which the study of early
                    Christianity has long depended, namely, that writers who are Christian concern
                    themselves with only pious topics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Ellen Muehlberger, “On Authors, Fathers, and Holy
                            Men,” <hi rend="italic">Marginalia Review of Books</hi>, September 20,
                            2015; Peter Martens, “Classifying Early Christian Writings: Boundaries,
                            Arrangements, and Latent Dynamics,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Early Christianity </hi>12.4
                            (2021): 3n4.</p></note>
                </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">That assumption remains implicit in scholarship, for the most part, but we can
                    catch a glimpse of how it works in the case of <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> by considering a curious repetition in scholarship about the
                    function of the text. In different contexts, while pursuing different arguments,
                    scholars who study the text most closely present it as a work of accommodation
                    on Jacob’s part, in which he stitches together two distinct and possibly
                    opposite realms of knowledge. At times, the assumption surfaces in peripheral
                    comments. For example, Alison Salvesen’s work draws attention to Jacob’s use of
                    Hebrew in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>and argues
                    that his etymological efforts serve as “a bridge between the biblical and
                    scientific information” in the text.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Salvesen, “Was Jacob Trilingual?”, 94.</p></note>
                    For other readers, the assumption is more pervasive. In her consideration of the
                    text, Marina Wilks understands Jacob to be aiming to marry what can be known
                    outside of scripture with what is in scripture. His work in <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Six Days</hi>, she writes, “brings the scientific account into line
                    with his interpretation of Genesis,”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek
                            Philosophy,” 226.</p></note> making as a result “a superb—and possibly
                    original—combination of science and theology.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="42"><p rend="footnote text"> Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek
                            Philosophy,” 236. Even those readers who seem to hold a neutral view of
                            the topics included in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> divide the
                            work into two regimes of knowledge. See P. Martin, “L’Hexaméron de
                            Jacques d’Édesse,” 165 (“C’est moin une ouvre de theologie qu’une ouvre
                            de science”), cited by Schlimme, <hi rend="italic">Der
                                Hexaemeronkommentar des Moses bar Kepha</hi>, 674 n4; and see
                            Schlimme’s discussion to the same effect (680–81). Ortiz de Urbina
                            extends this regime of divided knowledge to characterize Jacob himself:
                            “Eminet inter syros jacobitas sua ampla eruditione sacra <hi
                                rend="italic">et</hi> profana” (emphasis mine, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Patrologia Syriaca</hi>, 166).</p></note> If one considers
                    “science” and “theology” to be separate systems of knowledge for late ancient
                    writers, then <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> is indeed remarkable for
                    combining them, and so skillfully. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">But is there evidence that Jacob understood the content, or the purpose, of his
                    work this way? Being Christian in antiquity did not necessarily require drawing
                    this line. There are, certainly, works by Christian authors that make a point to
                    distinguish between sacred and profane topics. Similarly, there are surely
                    pieces of early Christian literature that take content referring to biblical
                    material as “theological” and locate it opposite to other kinds of knowledge.
                    Within Syriac literature, there is a deep tradition of scientific knowledge
                    contained in Christian texts, as Muriel Debié has so extensively documented.
                    Even Debié’s survey, though, also bears the assumption that there are two realms
                    of knowledge; in the case of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>, she
                    characterizes it as “un bon example de l’alliance entre science antique et
                    religion chrétienne.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Debié, “Sciences et savants syriaques: une
                            histoire multiculturelle,” 30. </p></note> What the Roman historian
                    Daryn Lehoux observed a decade ago remains true for many who study early
                    Christianity: “it is often taken as definitional that ancient science begins
                    where ancient theology ends.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Lehoux, <hi rend="italic">What Did the Romans
                                Know? An Inquiry into Science and Worldmaking</hi> (Chicago:
                            University of Chicago Press, 2012), 60.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">And yet many other pieces do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> port the same assumptions
                    and instead bear a remarkable continuity of use between what others might
                    separate as their “theological” and “scientific” claims.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> For an example, see
                            Theodoret’s use of medical knowledge in Ellen Muehlberger, “Simeon and
                            Other Women in Theodoret’s <hi rend="italic">Religious History</hi>:
                            Gender in the Representation of Asceticism,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies </hi>23
                            (2015): 583–606.</p></note> In the case of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>specifically, the
                    notion that there is some division in the knowledge of the world into two kinds
                    is not evident. Jacob makes no apology for the sources from which he draws his
                    information, and he does not offer any justification for why he is able to
                    combine material from two seemingly opposite epistemological orders, so we
                    should not assume he saw a division in the content of his own work. Rather, his
                    method of collation assumes continuity, rather than contrast, between what his
                    later readers have seen as separate realms. <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    draws from Genesis, but it also relies upon many non-biblical sources: Ptolemy’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Geography</hi>, Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Meteorology</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">De mundo</hi> attributed to
                    Aristotle, and a treatise on stone by Theophrastus all have a part in the
                        work.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Wilks, “Jacob of Edessa’s Use of Greek Philosophy,” 224; Schlimme, <hi
                                rend="italic">Der Hexaemeronkommentar des Moses bar Kepha</hi>,
                            676–77; Debié, “Sciences et savants syriaques: une histoire
                            multiculturelle,” 32.</p></note> What comes from these sources is not
                    flagged as being different in character or reliability from what Genesis offers.
                    Indeed, the very fact that Jacob writes this text suggests they are <hi
                        rend="italic">already</hi> compatible in his mind. To look to
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>as if it confirms the
                    existential reality of two categories of knowledge in “science and theology” or
                    even “science and scripture” is to read into it.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">If the hexameral label enables such confusion about the content and purpose of
                    Jacob’s work, is there some other way to classify <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi>?</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv25n1muehlberger.2" xml:lang="en">
                <head>II: <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> and Compendiary Texts</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">As Lorenz Schlimme observed, there is something far more
                    “encyclopedic” than “exegetical” about <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>. If
                    we were to take the quality he is noting as the central feature of the text, we
                    could locate it among another cohort of ancient writings. In the last three
                    decades of scholarship, attention has gathered on texts that we can call, if not
                    exactly “encyclopedic,” then at least “compendiary.” <note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text"> David Maldonado Rivera
                            recounts the scholarly conversation about encyclopedism in the
                            introduction to his dissertation, highlighting Paolo Odorico’s important
                            critique of the inevitable modern valences resident in the term
                            “encyclopedic.” Odorico for his part suggests “syllogistic” as an
                            alternative, a term that focuses on the production of texts by gathering
                            sources; yet this term also has its limits, as it suggests the kind of
                            excerpting that happens in florilegia and collections of scholia, while
                            the textual type I am trying to indicate includes such texts, alongside
                            others that draw from prior works without verbatim quotation (David
                            Maldonado Rivera, “Encyclopedic Trends and the Making of Heresy in Late
                            Ancient Christianity, 360–460 CE” [PhD diss., Indiana University, 2017],
                            5–11; commenting on Paolo Odorico, “La cultura della ΣΥΛΛΟΓΗ: 1) Il
                            cosiddetto enciclopedismo bizantino. 2) Le tavole del sapere di Giovanni
                            Damasceno,” <hi rend="italic">Byzantinische Zeitschrift</hi> 83 [1990]:
                            1–21). Another option, beyond “encyclopedic” or “compendiary,” is
                            “knowledge-ordering texts,” as Jason König and Greg Woolf offer in the
                            introduction to
                            <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedism from Antiquity to the Renaissance </hi>(Cambridge:
                            Cambridge University Press, 2013), 3.</p></note> Compendia do what their
                    name says they do, namely, they compound, placing together in new arrangements
                    material that has been recorded before, whether in tradition or in writing, and
                    whether they make a point of representing the material as excerpts and
                    quotations (that is, preserving some presence of the donor text), or whether
                    they simply incorporate the extant material into new structures. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Examples of compendia are found in most ancient literatures. For the ancient
                    Mediterranean, they include writing from the first century BCE, like Varro’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Hebdomades</hi>, or from the first century CE, like Pliny’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48"
                        n="48"><p rend="footnote text"> A short history of compendia is recounted in
                            Anna Bonnell Freidin, “The Birthday Present: Censorinus’ <hi
                                rend="italic">De die natali</hi>,”
                            <hi rend="italic">Journal of Roman Studies </hi>110
                            (2020): 141–66, as context for Censorinus’s text.</p></note> Texts in
                    the group need not aspire to universality: the same impulse is visible in works
                    composed for more circumscribed occasions or contexts, too, like Censorinus’s
                        <hi rend="italic">De die natali</hi>, or the <hi rend="italic">Untitled
                        Treatise</hi> in the Bruce Codex.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Bonnell Freidin, “The Birthday Present”; Ellen
                            Muehlberger, “Preserving the Divine: αὐτο-Prefixed Generative Terms and
                                the <hi rend="italic">Untitled Treatise</hi> in the Bruce
                                Codex,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 65 (2011):
                            311–28.</p></note> The genre crosses disciplines. Much of what we know
                    of the Hippocratic and other schools of medicine from the ancient Mediterranean
                    is preserved in compendia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> See, for a start, the essays of Philip van der
                            Eijk, ed., <hi rend="italic">Ancient Histories of Medicine: Essays in
                                Medical Doxography and Historiography in Classical Antiquity</hi>
                            (Leiden: Brill, 1999). </p></note> It also crosses linguistic
                    boundaries. Greek-speaking authors like Epiphanius of Cyprus wrote in this vein;
                    and there are examples of its presence in Syriac literature as well.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"> Andrew S.
                            Jacobs, “Epiphanius of Salamis and the Antiquarian’s Bible,” <hi
                                rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies</hi> 21 (2013):
                            437–64, and the development of this essay in his book, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Epiphanius of Cyprus: A Cultural Biography of Late Antiquity</hi>
                            (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2016), esp. in Chapter 4; for
                            Syriac, see especially <hi rend="italic">The Cause of All Causes</hi>, a
                            fair introduction to which can be found in Adam C. McCollum, “A Syriac
                            Fragment from <hi rend="italic">The Cause of All Causes</hi> on the
                            Pillars of Hercules,” <hi rend="italic">ISAW Papers</hi> 5 (2012). For a
                            more in-depth consideration see G. J. Reinink, “Communal Identity and
                            the Systematicization of Knowledge in the ‘Cause of All Causes’” in <hi
                                rend="italic">Pre-Modern Encyclopaedic Texts: Proceedings of the
                                Second COMERS Congress, Gronigen, 1</hi>–<hi rend="italic">4 July
                                1996</hi>, ed. Peter Binkley (Leiden: Brill, 1997),
                        275–88.</p></note> All of these exempla pull together previously composed
                    material, sometimes but not usually flagging their sources. Given the wide range
                    of texts from which it draws, <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> fits easily
                    within this group, and putting it there comes with the boon of expanding the
                    pool of potential comparanda for the text beyond just other Christian literature
                    that touches upon the Genesis creation story. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">And yet, this classification also falls short. To show how, let me highlight an
                    important vein of recent scholarly work on compendiary texts. The rhetorical
                    orientation of compendia is related to their content. Such texts tend to present
                    themselves as simple records of what is, as preservations of what is already
                    known, and thus tend to obscure their advancement of a unique agenda resulting
                    from their specific geographic, linguistic, or temporal context. Because
                    compendiary texts do not advertise their novelty, many have been neglected or
                    underanalyzed in scholarship because they seem, on their face, merely
                    “derivative,” dependent on the earlier literature that they reproduce. As more
                    scholars of the ancient world become attuned to the variation in the production
                    of knowledge across cultures—including the registers in which knowledge is
                    created, presented, and heralded—they have realized the importance of
                    compendiary works for our grasp of ancient culture.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text"> A sample of scholarship that
                            investigates ways of knowing can be found most recently in two
                            collections of essays:
                            <hi rend="italic">Late Ancient Knowing: Explorations in Intellectual History, </hi>ed.
                            C. M. Chin and Moulie Vidas (Berkeley: University of California Press,
                            2015); and <hi rend="italic">Ordering Knowledge in the Roman
                            Empire</hi>, ed. Jason König and Tim Whitmarsh (Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press, 2007). See also Daryn Lehoux, <hi rend="italic">What
                                Did the Romans Know?</hi>.</p></note> The fact that ancient authors
                    spent attention, time, and expense to create such texts suggests there is more
                    to be learned from them than what modern sensibilities, so attuned to the hails
                    of originality, might realize.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This is the opening that recent scholarly attention has entered, not to dismiss
                    such works as being without value, but to assume, by virtue of their initial
                    composition and preservation, that these works <hi rend="italic">were</hi>
                    considered valuable and then set to logicking out what made them so.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text"> In the case of
                            the Talmud, for instance, Sergey Dolgopolski has argued that its bent
                            toward inclusion is the evidence of a rabbinic inclination to manage the
                            ultimately unmanageable amount of information that could be known of the
                            past. See
                            <hi rend="italic">The Open Past: Subjectivity and Remembering in the Talmud </hi>(New
                            York: Fordham University Press, 2013). I thank Mira Balberg for this
                            reference.</p></note> There are many possible ways to reckon the value
                    afforded to a text in the past: one could ask about its use, or its
                    distribution, or consider how many copies and translations were made. Contained
                    in the text itself, too, is evidence for sussing out why it came into being in
                    the first place; compendia are the result of a process of curation, and by their
                    contours we might envision the curator.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"
                            ><p rend="footnote text"> This is arguably true for any text, but the
                            nature of compendia reflects on particular aspects of their composers,
                            because it is their knowledge and selectivity at the
                        forefront.</p></note> Scholars like Andrew S. Jacobs, Anna Bonnell Freidin,
                    and Annette Yoshiko Reed have all taken this approach to reveal writers who
                    arrange sources, expound on them, and position them relative to contemporary
                    cultural and political forces.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Jacobs, <hi rend="italic">Epiphanius of
                                Cyprus</hi>; Bonnell Freidin, “The Birthday Present”; Reed,
                            <hi rend="italic">Demons, Angels, and Writing in Ancient Judaism </hi>(New
                            York: Cambridge University Press, 2020), 238–39, citing J. Z. Smith,
                            “Wisdom and Apocalyptic,” in
                            <hi rend="italic">Religious Syncretism in Antiquity, </hi>ed.
                            Birger Pearson (Missoula, MT: SBL Press, 1975), 131–56.</p></note> There
                    is often a person holographed by the implicit argumentation of a compendium, an
                    expert who arranged it all just so. Thus, a compendium is usually a compound of
                    sources, but also a demonstration of the knowledge and power of the person who
                    wrote it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Often, scholars have seen an imperial framework expressed in the
                            compendium, though that is harder to apply to those works created
                            outside the confines of the empire most often the reference for this
                            observation, the Roman Empire. See König and Whitmarsh, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ordering Knowledge in the Roman Empire</hi>,
                            especially “Ordering Knowledge,” 3–39.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> is certainly a compendium, at least by dint
                    of its contents. Yet as it offers an erudite, almost voracious, collection of
                    facts about the world, the text departs from the what are now-standard
                    expectations for compendiary texts. Instead of performing a mastery that could
                    be attributed to Jacob, the text makes a considerable effort to display the
                    opposite of mastery. In fact, it brings mastery as a concept into question,
                    marking demonstrations of knowledge with clear indications of the limits on that
                    knowledge. Caution and a commitment to displaying <hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi>expertise appear across multiple registers and domains, pervading the
                    text so thoroughly as to be a defining feature of <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi>. In short, Jacob fails, and what is more, he purposefully shows us
                    that he fails. Though the text is not a failure, it models for readers an
                    approach that is quite different from that of the most well-studied among
                    compendiary texts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For discussion of another text that models a lack
                            of knowledge in order to induce among readers a certain style of
                            learning, see Jason König, “Fragmentation and Coherence in Plutarch’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Sympotic Questions</hi>” in König and Whitmarsh,
                                <hi rend="italic">Ordering Knowledge in the Roman Empire</hi>,
                            43–68.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The first domain where Jacob’s disavowal of expertise appears is in the mental
                    map of the world revealed by his narration of geography. Jacob writes as if he
                    has vast knowledge of earthly places. His reports about physical landscapes come
                    from Britannia, Skandia and Cimbria<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 112.</p></note> in the north of Europe to Hispania
                    and Gaul in the west. He knows West Asia, north to the Caucasus<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 114.</p></note>; east
                    to India and Sri Lanka and Malaysia<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni
                                Hexaemeron</hi>, 116, Sri Lanka being Taprobane; cf. Malaysia (i.e.,
                            “The Golden Island,” on 84).</p></note>; the southern reaches of his
                    knowledge include all of Africa north of the Sahara, and deep into the Upper
                    Nile Valley.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 102.
                        </p></note> He also has clear opinions about global geography. For instance,
                    the center of the world he represents, you might recognize, was not the
                    Mediterranean. In fact, Jacob pointedly describes his center, the Red Sea, as
                    the “center of the habitable world,” punning subtly on the claims of what he
                    might have termed the Not-So-Middle Sea. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Beyond these places, we could be left to simply imagine what might be there, or
                    to pretend that Jacob’s knowledge extends beyond what he names in the text, but
                        <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> makes the implicit explicit. The world
                    outside what is cataloged in its pages is consistently labeled as unknown: in
                    Jacob’s words, it is uninhabitable or inaccessible or simply “unnamed among
                    human beings.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot,
                            ed.,<hi rend="italic"> Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>,
                            102.</p></note> There are places “unsubjected” and seas “unsailed”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 111.</p></note> and
                        “impassable”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>,
                            111.</p></note> and “unnavigable.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                        n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                                Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 104.</p></note> God put islands at the
                    very edge of the seas, in places practically unreachable; we might at some point
                    know their names but we cannot know <hi rend="italic">them</hi>.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 104.</p></note> Over
                    and over again in Jacob’s tour of the world, when we learn about a location, we
                    also learn that what is known eventually gives way to <hi rend="italic">terra
                        incognita</hi>; there is a point, far distant but existing for every known
                    place, where Jacob’s geographic knowledge fails.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Failure is also built in to the structures that Jacob uses to organize his
                    information. The mode of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> is taxonomic—we are
                    given orderly classes, populated by species and examples—but even the most
                    exhaustive lists eventually end with a reminder that they stand incomplete. Fish
                    and crocodiles and crabs are known to Jacob, at least in their reproductive
                    cycles, but there is only so much that he knows, and there must be, he
                    concludes, “many different kinds that I do not know and cannot describe.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 197.</p></note> Among
                    quadrupeds there are donkeys, horses, deer, goats, and, remarkably, unicorns,
                    but there are also “many others in other places whose names and kinds we do not
                        know.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>,
                        206.</p></note> The same is true of the wilder beasts, like lions and tigers
                    and bears; beasts of burden, too, can only be partially and locally known—there
                    must be others like them, in other regions, but they go unrecorded.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 207, 224.</p></note>
                    When there is an extended show of the particulars that Jacob might know of
                    something, it usually arrives with a gesture to those things of the class or
                    species he <hi rend="italic">does not </hi>know, the
                    details he has not seen or recorded.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The failure to capture all potential facts is identified as an inherent fault of
                    lists, but for Jacob that failure also seems to stem from the limit of any one
                    human being’s capacity to know. After listing the many extracts of the earth
                    that can be useful to humanity, for example, Jacob warns that there are still
                    more—so many more in fact that he says “it is impossible for the mind to
                    comprehend or this treatise to gather” them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70"
                        n="70"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi
                                Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 55.</p></note> The cause of ignorance
                    resides in the form of the list and also the person who uses the list to
                    organize his thought. Adding more users can expand what is known: when Jacob
                    enumerates the differences between human beings an animals, he ends the list
                    with an admission that others could surely add to it, but as each of us bears an
                    individual limit, collectively we are limited, too.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 306–7.</p></note>
                    Perhaps we are able to approach complete knowledge when there are more of us,
                    yet we are always kept from completion, asymptotically proximate and yet
                    separate from the whole of what can be known. Tagging its most frequent tool for
                    organizing information—i.e., the list—in this way, <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi>, full of lists, constantly intones ignorance, sounding it over and
                    over again alongside the brighter and perhaps louder peals of knowledge. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The incompleteness of knowledge resonates too in <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi>’ representation of its own place in literature and the failings of
                    the textual enterprise as a whole. Those who read <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> are brought to understand that there is for every author a book
                    that is missing, either not written or written and lost.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text"> For more on the trope of the
                            lost book, see the research project, “Books Known Only by Title:
                            Exploring the Gendered Structures of First Millennium Imagined
                            Libraries,” hosted at the Centre for Advanced Study at the University of
                            Oslo by Marianne Bjellard Kartzow and Liv Ingeborg Lied<hi rend="italic"
                                >.</hi>
                        </p></note> This is even true of Jacob, for at the very start of
                    <hi rend="italic">The Six Days </hi>we learn it is not
                    Jacob’s first account of the universe and its wonders. He had written an earlier
                    treatise that covered the fundament of being, the first principle, in its
                    omnipotence, and presented it in consultation with quoted passages of Christian
                        scripture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>,
                        2.</p></note> That book does not survive for us to read. In truth, it may
                    never have existed, as the notion of the missing book seems central to his way
                    of conceptualizing knowledge. At least, the notion holds true for authors other
                    than Jacob. For instance, <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> relies upon Moses
                    as the writer of scripture and a most trustworthy source of knowledge, but
                    Moses, too, left things unwritten: specifically, any knowledge about the
                    immaterial world, to which he was privy. Jacob practically sighs as he reports
                    it: “Though he knew the secrets of [the spiritual beings’] creation, he did not
                    record a single word, long or short, about the creation of noetic beings.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 15–16.</p></note> In
                    Jacob’s understanding, for every text there is another that is unavailable to
                    us, beyond our reach. The volumes we possess are mirrored by all those we cannot
                    possess, and this too is a manifestation of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>’
                    insistence on the limits of knowledge.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Finally, those limits appear in the experience represented for the author of the
                    text, which Jacob creates in humanizing asides. Already, Syriac literature
                    reaching back to the fourth century writer Ephrem has emphasized the failings of
                    humanity’s grasp of the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> As Adam Becker commented on an early version of
                            this paper, it begins as a theme in Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
                                Faith</hi> and resonates from there through Syriac literature.
                        </p></note> But rarely are those failings expressed as personally as they
                    are in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days. </hi>There is not,
                    as we might expect, any well-reasoned exposition of how knowledge fails;
                    instead, there appear different individual expressions of the difficulty of
                    obtaining and preserving knowledge, a poignant sense that what is required for
                    knowing as much as the text can preserve is, in reality, beyond our abilities.
                    That sense first appears as fatigue. In a discussion of lakes, for instance,
                    Jacob begins to list existing lakes, prioritizing those that contribute to major
                    rivers—Lake Mareotis, Lake Asphaltites (i.e., the Dead Sea), the Lakes that
                    contribute to the Orontes and the Tigris. But then he stops and he asks—himself?
                    us?—“for what purpose am I wearing myself out, listing and providing the names
                    for all of these? To make a varied and nonsensical collection to be read and
                    heard?” He resigns and says, “There are as many of them as there are rivers in
                    the world; I reckon it is enough to just name and list the ones I have already.”
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot,
                            ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 107.</p></note>
                    When listing later the kinds of stones in the world and their potential uses,
                    Jacob peters out, begging off finishing the work by saying, “It is too much to
                    gather and list here all these things that can be fashioned from stones.” <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"> Chabot, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 117.</p></note> He is
                    tired; frankly, by that time of the text, readers are too. Another sign of
                    fatigue comes through as humility bordering on self-disparagement. More than a
                    dozen times over the course of the six books, Jacob excuses himself for this
                    “weak and prattling account,” his “stammering,” his “childish” ways of
                        writing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 68, 93,
                            106, 183, 188.</p></note> And thus, between author and imagined readers
                    is shared this failing: none of us are capable of grasping all details conveyed
                    by the text, not even the person who composed it.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"> Still, we all have forceful
                            powers of the imagination at hand for our use. Jacob encourages that use
                            at Chabot, ed., <hi rend="italic">Iacobi Edesseni Hexaemeron</hi>, 175:
                            “If one wishes to approach the north, but cannot do so in body or
                            actuality in this thinking instead he can do it via
                        consideration.”</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">So, if the compendiary genre has recently been interpreted as a performance of
                    the compiler’s mastery over knowledge, then <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    does not quite fit there either. The solidarity Jacob expresses with other human
                    beings alone is enough to require setting the text apart. For in other
                    compendiary treatises, the relationship between the writer as he presents
                    himself and the reader as the writer imagines them is one of distance and
                    difference: here are the things I know, which you do not and perhaps you would
                    not have been able to know, to collect, or to collate, as I have. But, in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>, Jacob allows for ignorance, his own and
                    others’, and even projects equality with the reader. That is because his
                    experience, as he imagines it, is similar to the reader’s; they are both facing
                    an avalanche of information that threatens to overwhelm them, or worse, to
                    escape them unrecorded. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Yet we should be clear: Jacob’s constant acknowledgment of the limitations of
                    human knowledge in <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> does not reflect
                    ignorance. It instead reflects a dynamic situation, of a learner who is gaining
                    knowledge, perhaps grasps that there is more to gain that what he can manage,
                    and yet tries anyway. Historical contexts never fully determine the nature of
                    knowledge, but in this case, Jacob’s orientation to the world is aligned with
                    what we know of the political and social contexts he inhabited. As noted, he was
                    intrepid, living and working in multiple communities over the course of his
                    life. During that life, West Asia was becoming the center of the world, as the
                    emergent movement around Muhammad coalesced into a government at Damascus, whose
                    power would eventually rival that of Constantinople. The interchange and the
                    establishment of new networks during this development likely felt enlivening but
                    also perhaps unmanageable, more than the ability of any single individual to
                    contain or comprehend. Yet at the same time, this was not an intellectual
                    tradition long-enough established to be convinced of its own centrality and
                    importance. If there is an affect to be associated with <hi rend="italic">The
                        Six Days</hi>, it is not domination but ingenuity. That is to say, though
                    the text shares some characteristics with the compendiary genre, it also
                    transcends the usual pattern of texts in that genre, perhaps so much so as to
                    dislodge it from that group, too.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="hv25n1muehlberger.3" xml:lang="en">
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p rend="H Paragraph Normal">Jacob’s text bears many lessons, but in its disposition
                    may reside its most transformative insight for modern readers. As a compiler,
                    reader, and yes, teacher, Jacob is very much like us. We, too, stand before an
                    overwhelming amount of information—say, the catalog of late ancient Syriac
                    literature—and some of us find the good in trying to convey its outlines, at
                    least in part, to those who have less familiarity than we do and perhaps induct
                    them into knowing it as we do. At least part of the goal is to bring new readers
                    to the literature, and with them, fresh perspectives. At the same time, many
                    fields of study could benefit from drawing Syriac texts into their catchment.
                    For instance, <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> has been read primarily as a
                    work of biblical exegesis, but it could also be read alongside other works of
                    natural and medical history, or as one example of the peculiar ways of knowing
                    instantiated in the ancient world, or even simply in comparison with other texts
                    that compile information from multiple sources.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The tools that we have for encouraging these new readers are helpful to a point,
                    but they also fail eventually. Filing <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi> under
                    the label “hexameral” or “commentary” is correct, but only in the narrowest of
                    terms, and it can lead readers both new and veteran alike to see the text only
                    from certain angles. The newer approach of labeling it “compendiary” bears some
                    promise, but also fails, as to think of <hi rend="italic">The Six Days</hi>
                    among other compendia may convey a false expectation that Jacob will attempt to
                    display mastery by his arrangement of prior materials, as have other
                    compilers—an expectation thwarted by Jacob’s insistence on the limits of
                    knowing. Our task, then, is simple and challenging. <hi rend="italic">The Six
                        Days</hi> demonstrates that we must hold our labels and classifications
                    lightly. We can read deeply, observe specificity, and yet still be wary of those
                    tools of knowledge that are designed mostly for the management of information at
                    scale. We can join Jacob in understanding that taxonomies are incomplete by
                    their nature and aim to consistently recognize these limits of knowledge, just
                    as he does the unknown spaces at the borders of the world, the unregistered
                    entries on any list, or the inaccessible books that linger beyond our ken.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
