<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Aho Shemunkasho, ed. and tr., <hi rend="italic">John of Dara,
                    On the Resurrection of Human Bodies</hi> (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2020)</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Kelli Bryant</forename>
                        <surname>Gibson</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Abilene Christian University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2022</date>
                <idno>Volume 25.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv25n2prgibson</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Kelli Bryant Gibson</author>
                        <title level="a">Aho Shemunkasho, ed. and tr., <hi rend="italic">John of Dara,
                            On the Resurrection of Human Bodies</hi> (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2020)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol25/HV25N2PRGibson.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2022</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="25">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="497" to="501">497-501</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="8"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2022-08-23">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en">
                <ab type="review-title">Aho Shemunkasho, ed. and tr., <hi rend="italic">John of Dara,
                    On the Resurrection of Human Bodies</hi> (Piscataway, NJ: Gorgias Press, 2020).
                    Pp. ix + 597; $165.</ab>
            </div>
            
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">    
            <p xml:lang="en">While little is known about the life of the ninth-century
                Syriac Orthodox metropolitan bishop John (Iwannis) of Dara (d. 860), he has left
                behind a rich literary corpus. Apart from the commentary <hi rend="italic">On the
                    Divine Liturgy</hi>, published 50 years ago,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1"
                    n="1"><p rend="H BR Footnote"> Syriac edition and French translation: Jean
                        Sader, <hi rend="italic">Le De Oblatione de Jean de Dara</hi>, CSCO 308–309
                        / Syr. 132–133 (Louvain: Peeters, 1970); English translation: Baby Varghese,
                            <hi rend="italic">John of Dara: Commentary on the Eucharist</hi>, Moran
                        Etho 12 (Kerala, India: SEERI, 1999).</p></note> none of John of Dara’s
                works are available in modern editions and translations. Aho Shemunkasho’s edition
                and translation of John of Dara’s four
                    memre<hi rend="italic"> On the Resurrection of Human Bodies </hi>(<hi
                    rend="italic">On the Resurrection</hi>)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> This volume is a publication of Shemunkasho’s 2017
                        habilitation thesis, completed in the course of his work for the Department
                        of Biblical and Ecclesiastical History at the University of Salzburg (p.
                        vii).</p></note> is a valuable contribution to the study of an
                underappreciated author. According to Shemunkasho, John’s treatises
                <hi rend="italic">On the Resurrection </hi>are “the most
                detailed and offer the richest exposition of the concept of resurrection . . . in
                the whole Syriac tradition” (p. 4). In these works, John proves to be a skilled
                exegete who is well-versed in a wide range of patristic and philosophical sources.
                One outstanding achievement of the volume is Shemunkasho’s painstaking effort to
                identify John’s many citations and allusions and compare them to known Syriac
                versions of biblical, patristic, and philosophical works. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The first three chapters offer a literary review of scholarship
                on John of Dara, sketch his ninth-century context, and introduce his life and work.
                The fourth chapter explains the conventions of the edition, followed by the Syriac
                text. The fifth chapter contains the English translation. A bibliography and an
                index of biblical, patristic, and other citations complete the volume. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">After the introduction and literature review in the first
                chapter, Shemunkasho’s second chapter outlines the broad contours of Syriac
                Christianity in the ninth-century Abbasid Caliphate. With little biographical
                information to go on, Shemunkasho attempts to reconstruct a plausible cultural and
                religious context for John, as though to trace his silhouette by filling in the
                negative space. Shemunkasho compiles all the available information about the city of
                Dara and its Syriac Orthodox bishops. He surveys the political situation of
                Christians in the Golden Age of the Abbasid Caliphate, Christian reactions to the
                growth of Islam, and the Graeco-Arabic translation movement. He situates John of
                Dara’s works among those of his Syriac contemporaries, especially other Syriac
                treatises on the resurrection. Shemunkasho has indeed pulled together many useful
                details for understanding John of Dara’s works in context, but it is a broad sweep
                rather than a deep one. At times the reader is left wondering about the rationale
                for including certain details; a stronger authorial voice would be welcome here.
                Overall, Shemunkasho’s historical sketch underscores the need for a more complete
                narrative of Syriac Christianity in the Abbasid Golden Age. Editions and
                translations of primary sources like this one are vital for that larger task.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Chapter three includes extensive tables of all of John of
                Dara’s known works in the oldest extant manuscripts, listing the individual chapter
                titles in Syriac with English translations. The information provided in these tables
                goes far beyond the scope of the present study, but they are certainly a boon to
                scholars who wish to find particular subjects across John of Dara’s corpus. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">One curious omission is a discussion of the authorship of <hi
                    rend="italic">On the Resurrection</hi>, especially since the attribution to John
                of Dara has been questioned. In 1973, Werner Strothmann argued that the real author
                of these treatises is Mushe bar Kepha.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> Werner Strothmann, <hi rend="italic">Moses Bar Kepha.
                            Myron-Weihe</hi> (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 1973), 23–25.</p></note>
                Anton Baumstark had listed identically titled works <hi rend="italic">On the
                    Resurrection of the Body</hi> for John of Dara and Mushe bar Kepha.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="H BR Footnote"> Anton Baumstark, <hi
                            rend="italic">Geschichte der syrischen Literatur, mit Ausschluss der
                            christlich-palästinensischen Texte</hi> (Bonn: A. Marcus und E. Webers,
                        1922), 277 and 281, respectively.</p></note> Strothmann assumed these are a
                single work by a single author and put forth two arguments in favor of Mushe bar
                Kepha. First, he noted that the treatise <hi rend="italic">On the Resurrection</hi>
                employs a question-and-answer format, a style used frequently by Mushe. Based on the
                absence of this literary device in
                John’s<hi rend="italic"> Commentary on the Divine Liturgy</hi>,
                Strothmann assumed that John never used the question-and-answer format. However,
                Shemunkasho reveals that John did sometimes use this literary device.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="H BR Footnote"> E.g., the memra “On
                        the Divine Economy” (p. 45). </p></note> Strothmann’s second argument
                apparently relies on a manuscript description in the catalog of the Mingana
                Collection. Strothmann observes that John’s “three” treatises on the resurrection
                contain a total of 34 chapters, the same number of chapters that Mushe wrote on the
                topic. He concludes that these must be the same work, abruptly declaring Mushe the
                author. However, the entry in the Mingana Collection catalog obscures the fact that
                John wrote <hi rend="italic">four</hi> treatises on the topic, not three, for a
                total of 58 chapters.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> Alphonse Mingana, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the
                            Mingana Collection of Manuscripts now in the Possession of the Trustees
                            of the Woodbrooke Settlement</hi> (Cambridge: W. Heffer and Sons, 1933),
                        I:154–155. The catalog description of the first three memre expressly
                        mentions the resurrection of the body, but it simply describes the fourth
                        memra as “on the end of the world, on the next world, and on heaven and
                        hell.” Shemunkasho’s work demonstrates that this memra belongs with the
                        three preceding it.</p></note> Though Strothmann’s arguments are based on
                shaky evidence, simply raising the question has placed these memre in the category
                of “disputed writings” for some.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> For example, Elizabeth L. Anderson’s dissertation
                        excludes consideration of texts “that are more disputed such as those on the
                        resurrection and the soul.” Anderson, “The Interpretation of
                        Pseudo-Dionysius in the Works of John of Dara” (Ph. D. dissertation, Yale
                        University, 2016), 4.</p></note> Shemunkasho is familiar with Strothmann’s
                work, and he observes that there are some similarities between Mushe bar Kepha’s and
                John of Dara’s treatises
                <hi rend="italic">On the Resurrection </hi>(pp. 34–35). He does
                not, however, directly engage the question of authorship, even though his own work
                shows how untenable Strothmann’s argument is. While questions may remain about the
                relationship between these two works, the notion that they are identical works by
                the same author should be laid to rest. Addressing the question of authorship is
                essential for a study like this one, especially as it would help scholars move
                beyond out-of-date arguments.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Shemunkasho uses a manuscript from the Syriac Orthodox
                Bishopric of Mosul (M) as his base manuscript; presumably it has no shelf mark, as
                none is given. The manuscript is not dated, but based on the paleography,
                Shemunkasho estimates that it is from the tenth century. The script in M is similar
                to that of Shemunkasho’s second main manuscript, Vatican Syriac 100 (V), which was
                among the manuscripts taken from Baghdad to Egypt by Mushe of Nisibis in 932 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">ce</hi>. Shemunkasho posits a close relationship between the
                two manuscripts: either they are copies of the same manuscript or V was copied from
                M. Though Shemunkasho uses M as the base text, he sometimes prefers a reading from
                V, and he uses readings from V where M is defective; square brackets clearly mark
                these passages. In the apparatus, Shemunkasho lists variant readings from V, gives
                information about the condition of the manuscript(s), and identifies quotations of
                and allusions to the Bible, along with a select number of patristic citations. In
                the body text of the edition, he has included the folio number, recto/verso, and
                columns for both manuscripts. While this information is valuable, a marginal note or
                footnote would have been less disruptive. Shemunkasho’s decision to format
                quotations from verse homilies according to their meter is a nice editorial touch. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Shemunkasho notes in the introduction that his translation
                follows the Syriac text very closely, sometimes resulting in an awkward English
                style (p. 6). The translation is indeed quite wooden, though it is usually accurate
                and the meaning discernible. Sometimes, however, following the Syriac text so
                closely renders the translation confusing or opaque. In many cases, small changes to
                the English word order would improve the clarity and flow without straying far from
                the Syriac.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The book does contain many typos, formatting issues, and
                spelling inconsistencies, especially of proper nouns (for example, ‘Umayyad’ is
                spelled three different ways, see pp. 13 and 23). This problem particularly affects
                the first three chapters, but the footnotes in the edition and translation also
                contain occasional errors. While these do not detract from the quality of
                Shemunkasho’s scholarship, they are distracting. One mistake worth noting is that
                the edition attributes a quotation to Jacob of Serugh (p. 122), whereas the
                translation has “Jacob [of Edessa]” in the main text (p. 382). The supporting
                footnote on p. 382 correctly indicates that Jacob of Serugh is intended, but the
                index still lists p. 382 under Jacob of Edessa, not Jacob of Serugh. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Overall, Aho Shemunkasho has done a great service with his
                thorough introduction to John of Dara’s work and context and his edition and
                translation of this remarkable collection of
                memre<hi rend="italic"> On the Resurrection of Human Bodies</hi>.
                His detailed analysis of John of Dara’s biblical, patristic, and other sources is
                valuable. Hopefully, more of John of Dara’s works will appear in comparably skillful
                editions and translations—perhaps without the interval of half a century this
                time!</p>
            
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

