<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">East Syrian Identity in the Early Qajar Period (Early 19th c.)</title>
                <title type="sub">Sāḇā of Ūlā’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi> on Syriac Language and
                    Ethnicity</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Sergey</forename>
                        <surname>Minov</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Institute for Oriental and Classical Studies, HSE University,
                            Moscow</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2023</date>
                <idno>Volume 26.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv26n2minov</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Sergey Minov</author>
                        <title level="a">East Syrian Identity in the Early Qajar Period (Early 19th c.): Sāḇā of Ūlā’s <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi> on Syriac Language and
                            Ethnicity</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol26/HV26N2Minov.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2023</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="415" to="465">415-465</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="3"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term>East Syriac</term>
                    <term>Identity</term>
                    <term>Sābā of Ūlā</term>
                    <term>Syriac language</term>
                    <term>Ethnicity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2024-01-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="article">
        <front>
            <div type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
            <head>Abstract</head>
            <p xml:lang="en">This article contributes to current research on the development of
                Syriac Christian identity during the modern period by bringing into discussion a
                previously unknown literary source, the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi>, composed in the year 1829
                by Sāḇā, an East Syrian priest from the village of Ūlā in the Salmas district of the
                Urmī region. In this apologetic work, aimed to protect his community from the
                pervasive influence of Western missionaries, the parish priest Sāḇā offers an
                exposition of the origins and early history of the Syriac people and their language.
                While doing that, he asserts the superiority of the East Syrian Christians over
                other Christian denominations by emphasizing Syriac as the language of biblical
                patriarchs and Jesus himself and by claiming that by way of his human nature, Jesus
                belonged to the Syriac nation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">∗ An
                    earlier version of this paper has been presented at the <hi rend="italic"
                        >International Conference dedicated to the Centenary of the Birth of
                        Academician Konstantine Tsereteli</hi> (20–22 December 2021, Tbilisi). I
                    am most grateful to Jeanne-Nicole Mellon Saint-Laurent and to the two
                    anonymous reviewers for their careful reading of the manuscript and their
                    many insightful comments and suggestions. I am also indebted to Michael Rand
                    (z"l), who very kindly provided me with a complete copy of the manuscript
                    Add. 2052 from the Cambridge University Library.</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </front>

        <body>
            <div xml:lang="en" xml:id="h26n2minov.0">
                <p xml:lang="en">The nineteenth century was a turning point in the history of the
                    Christian communities of the Middle East, both in the Ottoman Empire and in
                    Qajar Iran. It was the period of political and military instability in Northern
                    Mesopotamia and the Southern Caucasus, because of the continuing rivalry between
                    the two Muslim empires and the appearance in the region of another major
                    imperialist power, the Russian Empire. A significant factor in redrawing the
                    religious map of the region was the expansion of Western Christian missions of
                    all sorts: Roman Catholic, Protestant, and Russian Orthodox. As a result of the
                    missions’ ever-expanding activities, many traditional Christian confessions of
                    the two Muslim empires began to lose ground, demographically and culturally.
                    Another important development was the rise of nationalist ideologies among
                    various minorities of the Middle East, both Christians and Muslims. The new
                    political and socio-confessional circumstances posed a serious challenge that
                    led many Christians of the region to rethink and readjust their traditional
                    identity repertoire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="2"><p> For a general
                            picture, see B. Heyberger, <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens au
                                Proche-Orient: de la compassion à la compréhension</hi> (Manuels
                            Payot; Paris: Payot &amp; Rivages, 2013); contributions in B. Heyberger
                            (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à l’époque
                                ottomane</hi> (Études syriaques 17; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2020). On
                            Muslim-Christian relations during this period, see J.L. Joseph, <hi
                                rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations and Inter-Christian
                                Rivalries in the Middle East: The Case of the Jacobites in an Age of
                                Transition</hi> (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1983);
                            J. Jakob, <hi rend="italic">Ostsyrische Christen und Kurden im
                                Osmanischen Reich des 19. und frühen 20. Jahrhunderts</hi>
                            (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 7; Wien: LIT, 2014); D.R. Thomas
                            and J. Chesworth (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christian-Muslim Relations: A
                                Bibliographical History. Volume 18: The Ottoman Empire
                                (1800‒1914)</hi> (History of Christian-Muslim Relations 44; Leiden:
                            Brill, 2021). On the impact of Western missions, see C.A. Frazee, <hi
                                rend="italic">Catholics and Sultans: The Church and the Ottoman
                                Empire, 1453</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1923</hi> (London: Cambridge
                            University Press, 1983); A. Schlicht, <hi rend="italic">Frankreich und
                                die syrischen Christen 1799–1861: Minoritäten und europäischer
                                Imperialismus im Vorderen Orient</hi> (Islamkundliche Untersuchungen
                            61; Berlin: Klaus Schwarz, 1981); J.F. Coakley, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Church of the East and the Church of England: A History of the
                                Archbishop of Canterbury’s Assyrian Mission</hi> (Oxford: Oxford
                            University Press, 1992); T.S.R. O Flynn, <hi rend="italic">The Western
                                Christian Presence in the Russias and Qājār Persia, c. 1760–c.
                                1870</hi> (Studies in Christian Mission 47; Leiden: Brill, 2017); D.
                            Hopwood, <hi rend="italic">The Russian Presence in Syria and Palestine,
                                1843–1914: Church and Politics in the Near East</hi> (Oxford:
                            Clarendon Press, 1969); I.M. Okkenhaug and K.S. Summerer (eds.), <hi
                                rend="italic">Christian Missions and Humanitarianism in the Middle
                                East, 1850–1950: Ideologies, Rhetoric, and Practices</hi> (Leiden
                            Studies in Islam and Society 11; Leiden: Brill, 2020).</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Affected by all these developments, East Syrian Christians were not
                    exceptional in adjusting to the new reality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
                        n="3"><p> For a general introduction into identity politics of Syriac
                            Christians during the modern period, see H.L. Murre-van den Berg,
                            “Syriac Identity in the Modern Era,” in: D. King (ed.), <hi
                                rend="italic">The Syriac World</hi> (Routledge Worlds; London:
                            Routledge, 2019), 770-782. For discussions that focus on East Syrian
                            identity, see H.L. Murre-van den Berg, <hi rend="italic">From a Spoken
                                to a Written Language: The Introduction and Development of Literary
                                Urmia Aramaic in the Nineteenth Century</hi> (Publications of the
                            ‘De Goeje Fund’ 28; Leiden: Brill, 1999); A.H. Becker, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Revival and Awakening: American Evangelical Missionaries in Iran
                                and the Origins of Assyrian Nationalism</hi> (Chicago, Illinois: The
                            University of Chicago Press, 2015); M. Tamcke, “Nestorianisch, syrisch
                            oder assyrisch? Beobachtungen zum Selbstverständnis der lutherischen
                            Nestorianer in der Periode von 1875-1915,” in: U. Pietruschka (ed.), <hi
                                rend="italic">Hermeneutik und Exegese: Verstehenslehre und
                                Verstehensdeutung im regionalen System koexistierender
                                Religionsgemeinschaften im Orient, Leucorea-Konferenz 2005</hi>
                            (Hallesche Beiträge zur Orientwissenschaft 43; Halle an der Salle:
                            Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg, 2009), 159-169.</p></note>
                    In this article, I would like to deepen our understanding of the development of
                    the collective self-understanding of Syriac Christians during this transitional
                    period by bringing into discussion the relevant evidence found in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi>, a hitherto unpublished and unstudied
                    literary composition, produced by a member of the Church of the East in Iranian
                    Azerbaijan during the early decades of the nineteenth century.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en" xml:id="h26n2minov.1">
                <head>1. The <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi>: general information</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">The text of the work entitled the <hi rend="italic">Book of the
                        Rule</hi>, composed and transmitted in the Classical Syriac language, is
                    attested in the three following manuscripts:</p>
                <list>
                <item>A – Cambridge University Library, Add. 2052;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5"
                        n="4"><p> See W. Wright, <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac
                                Manuscripts Preserved in the Library of the University of
                                Cambridge</hi><hi>. 2 vols (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
                                1901), vol. 2, 1188-1189.</hi></p></note> produced in 1829.</item>
                <item>B – Cambridge University Library, Add. 2051;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                        n="5"><p> See Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Syriac
                                Manuscripts</hi><hi>, vol. 2, 1185-1188.</hi></p></note> copied in
                    1842, by the deacon Lazar, son of the priest Sāḇā.</item>
                <item>C – Library of the Museum Association of Urmia College, 58.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="6"><p> See O. Sarau and W.A. Shedd, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the Library of the Museum
                                Association of Oroomiah College</hi> (Oroomiah, Persia: [s.n.],
                            1898) [in Syriac], 12.</p></note> According to the information provided
                    by the cataloguers, it was produced in 1829 by the same Lazar, son of the priest
                    Sāḇā. Unfortunately, it seems that the manuscript is now lost, together with
                    many other manuscripts of the Library of Urmia College, which was plundered by
                    bandits around 1918 during the flight of Christians from the city and the
                    surrounding area in the wake of World War I.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8"
                        n="7"><p> See W.F. Macomber, “The Oldest Known Text of the Anaphora of the
                            Apostles Addai and Mari,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
                                Periodica</hi> 32 (1966), 335-371 (335, n. 2).</p></note></item>
                </list>
                <p xml:lang="en">In what follows, I offer an overview of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Book</hi>’s content, accompanied by a brief discussion of its authorship,
                    date, and message. This discussion is based on the Syriac text of the
                    composition as it is presented in ms. A, i.e., Cambridge University Library,
                    Add. 2052, considered by William Wright to be the autograph. </p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> is introduced with the following
                    title on f. 1r:</p>
                <p xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܚܝܠܗ ܕܡܪܢ ܝܫܘܥ ܡܫܝܚܐ ܡܫܪܝܢܢ ܠܡܟܬܒ ܟܬܒܐ ܕܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ
                    ܕܣܘܖ̈ܝܝܐ ܕܡܬܩܪܐ ܟܢܘܢܬܐ. ܡܛܠ ܐܝܟ ܕܒܟܢܘܢܬܐ ܡܗܕܐ ܠܟܪܝܣܛܝܢܐ ܬܪܝܨܐܝܬ ܒܐܘܪܚܗ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ
                    ܡܪܢ. ܕܠܗ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܘܥܠܝܢ ܖ̈ܚܡܘܗܝ ܐܡܝܢ. ܕܟܢܫܗ ܡܢ ܟܬܒ̈ܐ ܩ̈ܕܝܫܐ ܗܘ ܓܒܪܐ ܡܚܝܠܐ ܟܬܘܒܐ ܣܒܐ
                    ܩܫܝܫܘܢܐ.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Translation:</hi></p>
                <p>By the power of Our Lord Jesus Christ, we begin to write the book of the faith of
                    the Syriacs, which is called the “Rule,” because, like with a rule, it correctly
                    guides the Christian on the path of Our Lord Christ, to whom be glory and whose
                    mercy be upon us. Amen. Scribe Sāḇā, the weak man and insignificant priest,
                    assembled it from the holy books.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The main body of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> can be divided
                    into the following sections (some of them are written in prose and some in
                    verse), which are marked with subtitles and concluding sentences written in red
                    ink:</p>
                <list>
                <item>(1) ff. 1r–3r: a brief discussion of the origins of the Syriac nation and their
                    language; in prose.</item>
                <item>(2) ff. 3r–19v: an extended exposition of the Christological doctrine; in
                    verse.</item>
                <item>(3) ff. 19v–27r: an extended exposition of the seven sacraments; in verse.</item>
                <item>(4) ff. 27r–32v: an exposition on the “holy oil”; in prose.</item>
                <item>(5) ff. 32v–36v: an exposition on the practice of confession; in prose.</item>
                <item>(6) ff. 36v–44r: an exposition on the sign of the Cross; in prose.</item>
                <item>(7) ff. 44r–47r: an explanation of the fatherhood of the priest; in prose.</item>
                <item>(8) ff. 47r–55v: a poem (<hi rend="italic">‛ōnīṯā</hi>) on the deceit of this
                    world.</item>
                <item>(9) ff. 55v–60r: a poem on the soul’s repentance.</item>
                <item>(10) ff. 60r–63r: another poem (<hi rend="italic">‛ōnīṯā</hi>) on the soul’s
                    repentance.</item>
                </list>
                <p xml:lang="en">At the conclusion of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, the following
                    colophon is provided (ff. 63r–64v):</p>
                <p xml:lang="syr"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡ ܟܬܒܐ ܕܡܬܩܪܐ ܟܢܘܢܬܐ. ܕܟܢܫܗ ܡܚܝܠܐ ܣܒܘܢܐ ܡܢ |f. 63v| ܟܬܒ̈ܐ
                    ܩ̈ܕܝܫܐ ܘܥܒܕܗ ܠܖ̈ܚܡܝ ܝܘܠܦܢܐ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ ܡܪܢ ܕܠܗ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܥܠܡ ܥܠܡܝܢ ܐܡܝܢ. ܒܥܝܢܐ ܡܢ ܐܒܗ̈ܝ
                    ܩܖ̈ܘܝܐ ܚܣ̈ܝܐ ܘܐ̈ܚܝ ܫܡܘ̈ܥܐ ܓܒ̈ܝܐ. ܕܠܐ ܢܥܕܠܘܢܢܝ ܕܥܒܕܬ ܡܪܚܘܬܐ ܗܕܐ. ܐܦܢ ܢܬܗܕܘܢ
                    ܒܡܚܝܠܘܬ ܝܘܠܦܢܝ ܒܣܘܖ̈ܛܐ ܗ̈ܠܝܢ ܒ̈ܠܝܠܐ ܕܟܬܒܘܢܢ ܗܢܐ ܐܠܐ ܛܢܬ ܒܐܢ̈ܫܐ ܕܝܠܢ ܣ̈ܟܠܐ
                    ܕܡܚܝܠܝܢ ܠܡܥܡܠܘ ܒܒܝܬܐ ܪܘܚܢܝܐ ܕܐܒܗ̈ܝܢ ܐܖ̈ܬܕܘܟܣܐ ܕܒܢܘ ܠܢ ܪܘܚܢܐܝܬ. ܕܐܝܬ ܒܗ ܛܘ̈ܒܐ
                    ܖ̈ܘܚܢܝܐ ܕܠܐ ܡܬܚܙܝܢ ܒܥܝܢ̈ܐ ܘܦܬܘܪܐ ܕܡܠܐ ܒܘ̈ܣܡܐ ܫܡܝܢܐ. ܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܣ̈ܟܠܐ ܡܛܠ ܡܚܝܠܘܬܗܘܢ
                    ܦܗܝܢ ܒܒ̈ܬܐ ܢܘܟܖ̈ܝܐ ܦܓܪܢܐܝܬ |f. 64r| ܕܥܕܬܐ
                    ܡܗܝܡܢܬܐ. ܘܡܕܒܪܢܐ ܕܟܪܣܛܝܢܘܬܐ. ܘܫܘܡܠܝܐ ܕܟܗܢܘܬܐ. ܘܡܘܠܝܐ ܕܙܕܝܩܘܬܐ. ܡܠܐܟܐ ܦܓܪܢܐ ܘܣܪܦܐ
                    ܒܣܪܢܐ. ܘܥܝܪܐ ܓܘܫܡܢܐ. ܘܬܐܘܦܘܪܘܤ ܩܕܝܫܐ. ܡ̇ܫܚ ܟܗ̈ܢܐ ܠܩܘܕܫܐ. ܡܪܝ ܫܡܥܘܢ ܩܬܘܠܝܩܐ ܦܛܪܝܪܟܝܤ ܕܡܕܢܚܐ. ܢܬܩܝܡ ܟܘܪܣܝܗ
                   </foreign> ܒܥܠܡ. ܠܫܘܒܗܪܐ ܕܥ̈ܕܬܐ ܕܟܪܣܛܝܢܘܬܐ. ܐܡܝܢ.</p>
                <p xml:lang="syr"><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܥܒܕܗ ܩܕܡܐܝܬ ܟܬܒܐ ܗܢܐ. ܡܚܝܠܐ ܩܫܝܫܐ ܣܒܐ. ܒܫܢܬ ܐܐܩܡ
                    ܕܝܘ̈ܢܝܐ ܒܖ̈ܝܟܐ. ܘܒܗ̇ܝ ܫܢܬܐ ܐܬܘ ܐܘ̇ܖܹ̈ܣܢܵܝܹܐ ܘܫܩܠܘ
                    ܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܐܕܘܪܒܝܓ̰ܢ ܘܝܬܒܘ ܒܗܘܢ ܚܕܐ ܫܢܬܐ. ܒܬܪܟܢ ܐܬܪܥܝܘ ܥܡ ܡܠܟܐ ܕܦܖ̈ܣܝܐ ܘܫܩܠܘ ܡܢܗ
                    ܟܣܦܐ ܣܓܝܐܐ. ܘܝܗܒܠܗ</foreign><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > The correct form should be <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܝܗܒܘܠܗ</foreign>.</p></note> <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܡܢ ܐܪܨ ܘܠܟܐ.
                                ܘܡܢ ܐܪܨ</foreign> |f. 64v| <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܠܗܠ ܠܐ ܝܗܒ</foreign><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"> The correct form
                            should be <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܗܒܘ</foreign>.</p></note><foreign xml:lang="syr"> ܠܗ. ܐܠܐ ܐܘܒܠܘ ܣܓܝ ܐܖ̈ܡܢܝܛܐ. ܘܚܕܚܕܢ̈ܐ ܡܢ
                    ܣܘܖ̈ܝܝܐ ܠܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ. ܘܫܥܒܕܘ ܐܢܘܢ ܥܕܡܐ ܠܝܘܡܢܐ. ܘܒܚܪܬܐ ܐܠܗܐ ܝܕܥ ܫܘ [ܒܚܐ] ܠܫܡܗ ܐܝܢ
                        ܘܐܡܝܢ.</foreign></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Translation:</hi></p>
                <p>Completed is the book called the “Rule” that the poor Sāḇūnā assembled from the
                    holy books and made for the lovers of the teaching of Our Lord Christ, to whom
                    be glory unto the ages of ages, Amen. I beseech my fathers, the pious readers,
                    and my brothers, the eminent listeners, not to blame me for this audacity, even
                    if they may be guided by my scanty learning in these confused scribbles of this
                    little book of ours. But I have been moved with indignation against the foolish
                    people among us, who are too weak to take care of the spiritual home that our
                    orthodox fathers have built for us spiritually, wherein there are spiritual
                    goods that are not seen by the eyes and the heavenly table, full of delights.
                    Because of their weakness, those fools wander bodily in the foreign houses
                        &lt;…&gt;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Judging by the syntactic and semantic incongruity between the sentence
                            concluding f. 63v and one that opens f. 64r, it seems that at least one
                            folio is missing at this point. Perhaps, it was removed intentionally,
                            as one would expect it to contain a further elaboration of the
                            anti-Chaldean polemic that starts in a subdued manner in the surviving
                            part of the colophon.</p></note></p>
                <p>&lt;…&gt; of the believing Church, and the leader of Christianity, the perfection
                    of priesthood and fullness of righteousness, the bodily angel and seraph in the
                    flesh, the corporeal watcher and holy God-bearer, who consecrates priests to the
                    sanctuary, Mār Šem‘ōn Catholicos and Patriarch of the East, let his seat be
                    established forever, for the glory of the Christian churches, Amen.</p>
                <p>The poor priest Sāḇā made this book first in the year 2140 of the blessed Greeks
                    (i.e., 1828 or 1829). And in this year the Russians came and took over the lands
                    in Azerbaijan and dwelt in them for one year. After that, they made an agreement
                    with the king of the Persians and took a lot of money from him. And they gave
                    him the lands from the river Aras up to here,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12"
                        n="11"><p rend="footnote text"> I.e., the district of Salmas.</p></note> and
                    (those) from Aras up to there they did not give him. Moreover, they led away
                    many Armenians and some from among the Syriacs to those lands, and brought them
                    into subjection until this day. And God knows the end, glory be to His name, so
                    be it, Amen.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As one can infer from the work’s title and the manuscript’s
                    colophon, the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi> was composed by a priest
                    named Sāḇā. Although in its surviving form ms. A provides no clues about its
                    geographical provenance,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> It may have been mentioned in the lost part of the
                            colophon.</p></note> the colophon of ms. B, produced by Sāḇā’s son Lazar
                    thirteen years later, indicates that the book was copied “in the blessed village
                    of Ūlā” (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܒܩܪܝܬܐ ܒܪܝܟܬܐ
                        ܐܘ̣ܠܵܐ</foreign>).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="13"><p> For the Syriac
                            text, see Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of the Syriac
                                Manuscripts</hi><hi>, vol. 2, 1187. This colophon is shorter than
                                that of A, and does not repeat its information.</hi></p></note> One
                    can conclude with a considerable degree of certainty that not only Lazar, but
                    his father Sāḇā as well, lived in the village of Ūlā in the Salmas district of
                    the Urmī region, which now forms a part of the West Azerbaijan province of
                        Iran.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"> On
                            the location of the village and what little is known about it, see D.
                            Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical Organisation of the
                                Church of the East, 1318–1913</hi> (CSCO 582, Subs. 104; Louvain:
                            Peeters, 2000), 326-330, as well as map #7.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Undoubtedly, the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>’s author was a member
                    of the traditional faction of the East Syrian community. This point can be
                    inferred from the laudatory mention in the colophon of the patriarch Mār Šem‘ōn
                    XVII Oraham (r. 1820–1860), as well as from the content and apologetic purpose
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> itself (on which see below). The <hi
                        rend="italic">Book</hi> appears to be the only significant literary
                    composition produced by Sāḇā.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> For a reference to a <hi rend="italic"
                                >dūrekṯā</hi> poem possibly composed by him, see H.L. Murre-van den
                            Berg, <hi rend="italic">Scribes and Scriptures: The Church of the East
                                in the Eastern Ottoman Provinces (1500‒1850)</hi> (Eastern Christian
                            Studies 21; Louvain: Peeters, 2015), 353.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> is written in the Classical Syriac
                    language. While reading it, however, one comes across a number of elements that
                    deviate from the classical standards. Even though this subject should be
                    discussed only after the work’s complete text has been edited, it seems helpful
                    to point out some elements in the colophon and sections published below. Some of
                    such non-standard variants can be explained as a result of formal constraints or
                    inadvertent mistakes. For example, in the poetic part, the author uses the
                    shortened pronominal forms <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܢ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܕ</foreign> alongside the
                    regular <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܢܐ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗܕܐ</foreign>, apparently for
                    metrical reasons. At the same time, the singular verbal forms ܝܗܒܠܗ and ܝܗܒ,
                    which in the context should be plural, can be explained as a <hi rend="italic"
                        >lapsus calami</hi>, with the scribe omitting the silent final <hi
                        rend="italic">waw</hi>.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Other instances of non-classical usage seem to be due to the
                    interference from the author’s everyday language, most likely one of the
                    Northeastern Neo-Aramaic dialects.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="16"><p>
                            For a similar phenomenon in another East Syrian literary work, see S.
                            Minov, <hi rend="italic">The Marvels Found in the Great Cities and in
                                the Seas and on the Islands: A Representative of ‘Aǧā’ib Literature
                                in Syriac</hi> (Cambridge Semitic Languages and Cultures 6;
                            Cambridge: Open Book Publishers, 2021), 16.</p></note> Among the salient
                    Neo-Aramaic elements, one can point out the use of inflectional L-suffixes in
                    some verbal forms and constructions, such as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܲܫܠܹܐ</foreign> instead of
                        <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܦܫ ܠܗ</foreign> (this
                    classical construction is used as well), and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬܘܵܠܹܐ</foreign> instead of
                    the standard <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬ ܗܘܐ
                        ܠܗ</foreign>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="17"><p> On this suffix, see G.
                            Khan, <hi rend="italic">The Neo-Aramaic Dialect of the Assyrian
                                Christians of Urmi</hi><hi>. 4 vols (Studies in Semitic Languages
                                and Linguistics 86; Leiden: Brill, 2016), vol. 1,
                        265.</hi></p></note> The spelling of the 3m.sg. imperfect of the verb <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܛܐ</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܛܐ</foreign> instead of the
                    standard <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܢܣܛܐ</foreign>
                    probably also belongs to this category. The appearance of the consonant /<hi
                        rend="italic">ṣ</hi>/ instead of /<hi rend="italic">s</hi>/ in this form
                    seems to reflect a phonological shift that took place in some Neo-Aramaic
                    dialects, during which the historical emphatic phoneme <hi rend="italic">*ṣ</hi>
                    lost the feature of pharyngalization and merged with historical <hi
                        rend="italic">*s</hi>, resulting in one phoneme /<hi rend="italic"
                        >s</hi>/.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="18"><p> See Khan, <hi
                                rend="italic">Neo-Aramaic Dialect</hi><hi>, vol. 1,
                        107.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">A word should be said about the remarkable historical circumstances
                    in which the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> was composed. The colophon of ms. A
                    states that it was produced in the year 1828/1829. The scribe informs us further
                    that during this time the region of Iranian Azerbaijan was invaded by the
                    Russian army, which held it under its control for one year. The Russians
                    withdrew after making a peace agreement with the king of Persians, as a result
                    of which the latter had to pay them a considerable monetary contribution and
                    concede Persian territories to the north of the river Aras. This description
                    refers to historical events that are well documented, namely the second
                    Russo-Persian war (1826–1828), the last major military conflict between the
                    Russian Empire and Qajar Iran, which ended with the defeat of Persia and the
                    signing of the humiliating Treaty of Turkmenchay on 10 February 1828.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="19"><p> For the Russian text of the treaty,
                            see Ц.П. Агаян, В.А. Дилоян, and А.В. Алексанян, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Присоединение Восточной Армении к России: Сборник документов. Том
                                II (1814–1830)</hi> (Материалы по истории армянского народа 17;
                            Ереван: Издательство Академии наук Армянской ССР, 1978), 446-451; on its
                            historical and political context, see Б.П. Балаян, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Дипломатическая история русско-иранских войн и присоединения
                                Восточной Армении к России</hi> (Ереван: Издательство Академии наук
                            Армянской ССР, 1988), 179-211. On the course of military operations, see
                            J.F. Baddeley, <hi rend="italic">The Russian Conquest of the
                                Caucasus</hi> (London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1908),
                        152-181.</p></note> In the course of this military campaign, the Russian
                    troops occupied for one year the Urmī region of Iranian Azerbaijan, including
                    the district of Salmas, where Sāḇā lived.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The colophon adds that when the Russians left the region, they took
                    “many Armenians” and some “Syriacs” with them. This statement agrees well with
                    what we know about the policy pursued by the Russian military administration of
                    the Urmī region. The Russians encouraged the local Christians to immigrate <hi
                        rend="italic">en masse</hi> to the territory of Eastern Armenia, which would
                    remain under their control after the army’s withdrawal beyond the newly
                    established border line of the river Aras.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
                        n="20"><p> For the Russian official documents that shed light on this
                            project, see Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной
                                Армении</hi>. For a discussion, see D.L. Sherry, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Imperial Alchemy: Resettlement, Ethnicity, and Governance in the
                                Russian Caucasus, 1828–1865</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation; University of
                            California, 2007); F. Shafiyev, <hi rend="italic">Resettling the
                                Borderlands: State Relocations and Ethnic Conflict in the South
                                Caucasus</hi> (Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press, 2018),
                            43-95.</p></note> Approved by the Tsarist government, the policy of
                    resettlement was implemented by the Russian general Ivan Paskevich and his
                    special envoy for this mission Lazar Lazarev, a Russian army colonel of Armenian
                    descent. As a result of their efforts, a relatively large number of Armenians
                    seized this opportunity and moved to the Russian-controlled part of the Southern
                    Caucasus, where they were settled in the regions of Erivan, Karabakh, and
                        Nakhichevan.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="21"><p> The number of the
                            Armenian settlers is reported to be as high as 8,000 families or about
                            40,000 people; see Shafiyev, <hi rend="italic">Resettling the
                                Borderlands</hi><hi>, 60.</hi></p></note> However, the number of
                    East Syrians who followed their example was relatively modest.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="22"><p> Modern scholars estimate it around 100 families;
                            see J. Dum-Tragut, “Assyrians in Armenia – An Interdisciplinary Survey,”
                            in: L. Tang and D.W. Winkler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From the Oxus
                                River to the Chinese Shores: Studies on East Syriac Christianity in
                                China and Central Asia</hi> (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 5;
                            Zürich: LIT Verlag, 2013), 341-353 (342).</p></note> They settled in
                    what is now the territory of the Republic of Armenia, where they established the
                    village of Koylasar (modern Dimitrov). This group became the first wave of East
                    Syrian émigrés to move to the Russian Empire’s territory due to political and
                    military upheavals in the Ottoman-Persian borderlands during the nineteenth and
                    early twentieth centuries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="23"><p> On the
                            history of the Assyrian diaspora in Russia, see К.П. Матвеев, “К истории
                            переселения ассирийцев в Россию,” <hi rend="italic">Народы Азии и
                                Африки</hi> 5 (1980), 165-168; И.Ю. Зая, “Ассирийцы и Россия (вторая
                            половина XIX – начало XX в.),” <hi rend="italic">Восток</hi> 4 (1997),
                            23-36; С. Садо, <hi rend="italic">Материалы к биографическому словарю
                                ассирийцев в России (XIX – середина XX века)</hi> (С.-Петербург:
                            Издательство Олега Абышко, 2006).</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It is noteworthy that Sāḇā describes the experience of the
                    Christian émigrés in negative terms, saying that the Russians “led them away”
                    and brought them into a state of “subjection” in their new homeland. This
                    description contradicts the Russian government’s general policy, according to
                    which the resettlement of Christian population from the Iranian territories was
                    supposed to occur purely on a voluntary basis.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="24"><p rend="footnote text"> Some scholars argue that the Russians did
                            not hesitate occasionally to use force to compel the Christians of
                            Persia to resettle; see F. Mostashari, <hi rend="italic">On the
                                Religious Frontier: Tsarist Russia and Islam in the Caucasus</hi>
                            (London: I.B. Tauris, 2006), 41-42. Regardless of whether such cases did
                            or did not take place, the general policy of the Russian military
                            administration was that of peaceful inducement. See §2 of the official
                            document meant to regulate the process of resettlement that was issued
                            by Paskevich; Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной
                                Армении</hi>, 564. For the explicit rebuttals by Russian officials
                            of the accusations of forced resettlement made by the Persian side, see
                            reports of Paskevich from 9 March 1828 and of Lazarev from 1 May 1828;
                            Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>,
                            472, 492.</p></note> At the same time, we know that the Russian
                    initiative of resettling the Christian subjects of Persia to their territory was
                    met with resistance not only from the Qajar authorities, but also from some
                    among the local Christian hierarchs. Thus, from the exchange of letters between
                    the pro-Russian Armenian bishop Nerses and Paskevich, we learn about Izrail, the
                    Armenian bishop of Albāgh in the Salmas district, who campaigned actively among
                    the local Armenians against immigration to the Russian Empire.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="25"><p> For the Russian text, see Агаян et alii, <hi
                                rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>, 474-475. For
                            more information on the pro-Persian stand of some members of the
                            Armenian clergy, see G.A. Bournoutian, <hi rend="italic">Eastern Armenia
                                in the Last Decades of Persian Rule, 1807–1828: A Political and
                                Socioeconomic Study of the Khanate of Erevan on the Eve of the
                                Russian Conquest</hi> (Malibu, California: Undena Publications,
                            1982), 35-40.</p></note> There may have been an even more pronounced
                    resistance to the Russian policy on the side of Persia’s Syriac Christians. In
                    his report from 1 May 1828, Lazarev informs Paskevich that his efforts aimed at
                    persuading “Nestorians” from the Urmī region to follow the example of those
                    Armenians eagerly moving to Russian territory were met without much enthusiasm
                    and ascribes such reluctance to the detrimental influence of Catholicos Mār
                    Šem‘ōn based in Kurdistan, who was approached by the Qajar prince ‘Abbās Mīrzā
                    with gifts and promises of future privileges in order to prevent his subjects
                    from leaving Persia.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="26"><p> For the Russian
                            text, see Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной
                                Армении</hi>, 491-493. Cf. also his report from 12 April 1828, in
                            which he complains to Paskevich about the lack of sincere desire to
                            resettle among the Assyrians of the Urmī region; Агаян et alii, <hi
                                rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>,
                        486-487.</p></note> Moreover, according to Lazarev’s report from 2 April
                    1828, Persian officials were spreading rumors among Christians of the Urmī
                    region that those who would immigrate to Russian territory were going to suffer
                    there from the lousy climate, hunger, and enslavement.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="27"><p> “В Урмии нашел я много препятствий действиям моим
                            и нелепых слухов, распространенных Персидским правительством на счет
                            нас. Для устрашения переселенцев уверяют их что за Араксом ожидает их
                            дурной климат, голод и что подданные государя продаются.”; Агаян et
                            alii, <hi rend="italic">Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>, 481. Cf.
                            also Lazarev’s letter to the Armenians of Persia from 30 March 1828, in
                            which he rebuffs such rumors; Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>, 479-480.</p></note> These
                    allegations were, in fact, at least partially true since some of the Christian
                    settlers did find themselves in dire straits when the Russian administration
                    failed to keep the promise of allocating them appropriate agricultural lands and
                    providing sufficient monetary stipends.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="28"
                            ><p> Cf. the letter of complaint by Armenian settlers to Catholicos
                            Efrem from 8 September 1828 in Агаян et alii, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Присоединение Восточной Армении</hi>, 541-542. See also Sherry, <hi
                                rend="italic">Imperial Alchemy</hi><hi>, 44-48.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">It appears then that by making the vague references to the
                    hardships inflicted upon the Christian émigrés, whether real or imagined, Sāḇā
                    sided with the negative attitude toward the Russian project of resettlement
                    adopted by Catholicos Mār Šem‘ōn. Sāḇā’s support of the patriarch’s policy could
                    also be inferred from the simple fact that he did not leave his village and move
                    to Russian territory, even when he had such an opportunity during the Russian
                    occupation of the Salmas district.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Another aspect of Sāḇā’s literary project, crucial for
                    understanding its social and cultural circumstances, is its apologetic
                    dimension. The <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>’s content could be roughly divided
                    into three main parts: a brief historical introduction (Section 1), a
                    theological part (Sections 2–7), and a devotional part (Sections 8–10). Sāḇā’s
                    primary goal, stated explicitly in the title, was to offer his community a
                    concise and accessible handbook explaining the basics of Christian life. Yet, as
                    one reads through the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, it becomes clear that the
                    author composed it to protect his audience from the lure of Western
                    Christianity.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The apologetic purpose of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> is made
                    explicit in the colophon, where Sāḇā points out that in composing his work, he
                    was moved not only by the desire to provide a guide-book for Christian living
                    but by a strong feeling of disapproval aimed against those among his fellow
                    “Syriacs” who neglect their “spiritual home,” that is the East Syrian
                    ecclesiastical tradition, and seek guidance “in the foreign houses”. Similar
                    statements are found in the main body of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> as
                    well. For example, in Section 2, which deals with Christology, the author
                    castigates this group of Syriacs, while referring to them as “that people who
                    have separated from us, abrogated our authority and our law, and engaged in
                    controversy with us, while taking our name.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30"
                        n="29"><p rend="footnote text"> F. 17r: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܗ̇ܢ ܥܡܐ ܕܦܪܫ ܡܢܢ. ܒܛܠ ܫܘܠܛܢܢ ܘܕܝܢܢ.
                            ܘܥܒܕ ܚܪܝܢܐ ܥܡܢ. ܕܫܩܠ ܫܘܡܗܐ ܕܝܠܢ</foreign></p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although he does not name this separatist group, it seems almost
                    certain that Sāḇā’s animosity in these passages is aimed against Chaldean
                    Syrians. This faction group within the East Syrian community, whose entangled
                    history could be traced back to the sixteenth century, had broken their
                    allegiance to the Church of the East and entered into full communion with the
                    Roman Catholic Church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="30"><p> See on them
                            M. Tamcke, “Assyro-Chaldean Christians,” in: M. Raheb and M.A. Lamport
                            (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Rowman &amp; Littlefield Handbook of
                                Christianity in the Middle East</hi> (The Rowman &amp; Littlefield
                            Handbook Series; Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2021), 237-243;
                            H.G.B. Teule, <hi rend="italic">Les Assyro-chaldéens: chrétiens d’Irak,
                                d’Iran et de Turquie</hi> (Fils d’Abraham; Turnhout: Brepols, 2008);
                            L. Parker, “The Ambiguities of Belief and Belonging: Catholicism and the
                            Church of the East in the Sixteenth Century,” <hi rend="italic">English
                                Historical Review</hi> 133:565 (2018), 1420-1445.</p></note> While
                    the apologetic agenda of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> requires further,
                    detailed investigation, the kind which cannot be carried out in the framework of
                    this article, it is safe to posit at this point that a considerable part of its
                    author’s efforts is devoted to defending the doctrines and practices of the
                    Church of the East against those of the Roman Catholic Church. This concern
                    seems to be a primary rationale behind Section 2, where Sāḇā goes to a
                    considerable length to make the traditional language of East Syrian Christology
                    more accessible to his audience. Furthermore, this aspect comes to the fore in
                    Section 5, where he expounds upon the practice of confession among the “Eastern
                    Syriacs.” At the beginning of this exposition, the author expresses his
                    disagreement with the opinion of “the men from other nations, who are saying
                    that confession is one of the seven sacraments of the Church,”<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"> F. 33r: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬ ܐܢ̈ܫܐ ܕܡܢ ܥܡ̈ܡܐ
                            ܐܚܖ̈ܢܐ ܕܐܡܪܝܢ ܡܘܕܝܢܘܬܐ ܚܕ ܐܪܙܐ ܐܝܬܝܗ̇ ܡܢ ܫܒܥܐ ܐܖ̈ܙܐ ܕܥܕܬܐ</foreign></p></note> and
                    argues that penance cannot be considered a proper sacrament.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="32"><p> On the practice and theology of penance among the
                            East Syrians, see W. de Vries, <hi rend="italic">Sakramententheologie
                                bei den Nestorianern</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 133; Roma:
                            Pontificium Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1947), 265-280.</p></note>
                    It is most likely that this passage is directed against the Roman Catholic
                    tradition of regarding confession as one of the seven sacraments that Chaldean
                    Syrians also adopted.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In order to understand better Sāḇā’s rhetoric, one should analyze
                    it against the background of the shift in socio-confessional dynamics that took
                    place among the Christians of Iranian Azerbaijan during the eighteenth and early
                    nineteenth centuries. Roman Catholic missionaries started to make their first
                    inroads into this region several centuries before his time.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"> On the Catholic presence and
                            activities in the region, see Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Ecclesiastical Organisation</hi>, 315-318; O Flynn, <hi
                                rend="italic">Western Christian Presence</hi>, 600,
                        712-713.</p></note> The history of Catholic presence in the district of
                    Salmas can be traced back to 1318 when a Franciscan mission had been established
                    in Khosrōwā. This village, located just about four kilometers north of Ūlā,
                    eventually became a major center of Roman Catholic missionary activity.
                    According to David Wilmshurst, there was a decisive demographic shift in favor
                    of Catholicism in the Salmas district during the last quarter of the eighteenth
                    century as a result of the efforts of the metropolitan Īšō‘yahb Šem‘ōn (ob.
                        1789).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">
                            Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Organisation</hi>,
                        316.</p></note> After he entered into communion with the Catholic Joseph
                    line at Amid,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="35"><p> On Joseph and his
                            successors, see Wilmshurst, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                                Organisation</hi>, 57-60; L. Parker, “Yawsep I of Amida (d. 1707)
                            and the Invention of the Chaldeans,” in: B. Heyberger (ed.), <hi
                                rend="italic">Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à l’époque
                                ottomane</hi> (Études syriaques 17; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2020),
                            121-152.</p></note> most of the East Syrians of the region were
                    incorporated into the Roman Catholic fold. That portion of Sāḇā’s community that
                    still kept its allegiance to the East Syrian patriarch Mār Šem‘ōn were, most
                    likely, outnumbered by their Chaldean neighbors. In light of these
                    circumstances, Sāḇā’s concern with the influence that Catholicism might have had
                    on members of his flock, which finds expression in the apologetic stance of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, becomes quite understandable.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en" xml:id="h26n2minov.2">
                <head>2. The <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi> on Syriac language and
                    ethnicity</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Turning now to the article’s main subject, I will discuss what Sāḇā
                    has to say about Syriac language and ethnicity and how he makes these two
                    markers of the East Syrian identity to serve his apologetic agenda. With that
                    goal in mind, I would like to present, first, the original Syriac text and an
                    English translation of two main parts of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, in
                    which he addresses these topics: Section 1, written in prose, and the opening
                    part of Section 2, written in verse. The Syriac text follows that of ms. A, i.e.
                    Cambridge University Library, Add. 2052. A few significant variants from ms. B
                    are given in the apparatus.</p>
                <div>
                <head>Syriac text</head>
                    
                <p xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="bold">[1]</hi>
                    ܩܕܡܐܝܬ ܡܘܕܥܝܢܢ ܝܘܒܠܐ ܕܣܘܖ̈ܝܝܐ ܘܠܫܢܗܘܢ. ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܡܢ
                    ܫܡ ܣܘܪܝܐ ܫܩܠ. ܐܠܗܐ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܠܫܡܗ. ܒܗ ܡܠܠ ܥܡ ܐܒܘܢ ܐܕܡ. ܘܒܗ ܡܡܠܠܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܒܢ̈ܝܢܫܐ
                    ܥܕܡܐ ܠܦܘܠܓ ܠܫܢ̈ܐ. ܒܦܘܠܓ ܠܫܢ̈ܐ ܟܕ ܟܢܝܫܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܟܠܗܘܢ ܒܢܝܢܫܐ ܠܒܢܝܢ ܡܓܕܠܐ ܬܡܢ ܦܠܓ
                    ܐܠܗܐ ܠܫܢ̈ܝܗܘܢ. |f. 1v| ܦܪܫܘ ܫܒܥܝܢ ܘܚܕ ܠܫܢܐ ܡܢ ܗܢܐ ܠܫܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ. ܘܐܬܒܕܪܘ
                    ܠܐܪܒܥܦܢܝܬܗ ܕܥܠܡܐ. ܘܗܢܐ ܠܫܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܦܫ ܠܗ ܠܘܬ ܐܪܒܥܐ ܐܓܘܖ̈ܣܐ<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"> B + ܪܘܖ̈ܒܐ</p></note>
                    ܒܒܝܬܢܗܪܝܢ. ܕܗ̣ܝ ܗ̣ܝ ܪܫܐ ܕܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܣܘܪܝܐ. ܘܣܘܪܝܐ ܗܘܝܐ ܡܢ ܐܢܛܝܘܟܝ ܘܥܕܡܐ ܠܐܘܪܗܝ ܡܛܠ
                    ܗܕܐ ܠܫܢܐ ܗܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܡܬܩܪܐ ܕܒܝܬܢܗܪܝܢ. ܘܗܠܝܢ ܐܪܒܥܐ ܐܓܘܖ̈ܣܐ ܕܒܝܬܢܗܪܝܢ ܐܬܒܕܪܘ
                    ܒܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܟ̈ܠܕܝܐ ܡܛܠ ܗܕܐ ܥܡܐ ܗܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܡܬܩܪܐ ܟܠܕܝܐ.<lb/>ܘܓܢܣܐ ܕܐܒܗ̈ܬܐ ܖ̈ܫܢܐ
                    ܕܟܬܝܒܝܢ ܫܡܗ̈ܝܗܘܢ ܒܥܬܝܩܬܐ ܘܒܚܕܬܐ ܒܗ ܒܥܡܐ ܗܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ. ܘܡܬܩܪܐ ܗܘܐ ܓܢܣܐ
                    ܕܡܗ̈ܝܡܢܐ. ܡܛܠ ܕܪܫܝܬܢ ܒܓܢܣܗܘܢ ܗܘܬ. ܕܗ̣ܝ ܗ̣ܝ ܐܢܫܘܬܗ ܕܡܪܢ. ܗ̣ܘ ܗܢܐ ܓܢܣܐ ܥܡܪ ܗܘܐ |f.
                    2r| ܒܩܪܝܬܐ ܐܪܡ ܒܥܘܪ ܕܟ̈ܠܕܝܐ. ܕܗ̣ܝ ܗ̣ܝ ܟܫܟܪ. ܐܦ ܐܒܘܢ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܡܢܗ ܗܘܐ ܕܗܢܐ ܓܢܣܐ
                    ܡܗܝܡܢܐ. ܘܐܝܬܘܵܠܹܐ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> B ܐܝܬܗ̄ܘܵܠܹܐ</p></note> ܬܖ̈ܝܢ ܐ̈ܚܐ. ܚܕ ܡܬܩܪܐ ܗܘܐ
                    ܗܪܢ ܘܐܚܪܢܐ ܢܚܘܪ. ܗܪܢ ܐܒܘܗܝ ܕܠܘܛ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ ܗܘܐ. ܗܪܢ ܡܝܬ. ܟܕ ܥܒܕܗ ܐܠܗܐ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܪܫܐ
                    ܕܐܒܗ̈ܬܐ ܦܪܫ ܡܢ ܒܝܬ ܐܒܘܗܝ ܬܪܚ. ܘܡܢ ܩܪܝܬܗ ܐܪܡ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39"
                        n="38"><p rend="footnote text"> B + ܕܥܘܪ ܕܟ̈ܠܕܝܐ</p></note> ܘܫܢܝܗ<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"> B
                        ܘܫܢܝܐ</p></note> ܠܐܪܥܐ ܕܟܢܥܢ̈ܝܐ ܘܕܚܬܝܐ ܘܫܪܟܐ. ܐܘܒܠܗ ܐܦ<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn41" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"> B ܠܬܪܚ ܐܒܘܗܝ ܘ</p></note> ܠܘܛ
                    ܥܡܗ. ܘܢܚܘܪ ܦܲܫܠܹܐ ܒܩܪܝܬܗܘܢ ܐܪܡ. ܘܐܣܓܝ ܐܠܗܐ ܙܪܥܗ ܬܡܢ ܘܐܬܒܕܪܘ ܒܐܬܖ̈ܘܬܐ ܕܟ̈ܠܕܝܐ.
                    ܡܬܩܪܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܐܖ̈ܡܝܐ. ܡܛܠ ܕܡܢ ܐܪܡ ܢܦܝܩܝܢ ܗܘܘ. ܘܠܐܠܗܐ ܝܕܥܝܢ ܗܘܘ. ܐܠܐ ܐܦ ܠܦܬܟܖ̈ܐ
                    ܣܓܕܝܢ ܗܘܘ. ܥܘܖ̈ܠܐ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܗܘܘ. ܘܐܒܪܗܡ ܫܢܝܗ ܐܠܗܐ |f. 2v| ܠܐܪܥܐ ܢܘܟܪܝܬܐ<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="41"><p rend="footnote text"> B + ܘܝܗܒ ܠܗ
                            ܓܙܘܪܬܐ</p></note> ܐܘܠܕ ܠܐܝܣܚܩ. ܘܐܝܣܚܩ ܐܘܠܕ ܠܝܥܩܘܒ. ܘܝܥܩܘܒ ܟܕ ܚܙܐ ܕܡܘܬܐ
                    ܕܐܠܗܐ ܒܫܡܝܐ ܐܬܩܪܝ ܝܣܪܝܠ. ܘܐܣܓܝ ܐܠܗܐ ܙܪܥܗ. ܘܡܬܩܪܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܒܢ̈ܝ ܝܣܪܝܠ ܘܝܕܥܝܢ ܗܘܘ
                    ܠܐܠܗܐ. ܘܐܝܬ ܗܘܐ ܠܗܘܢ ܓܙܘܪܬܐ ܘܟܢ ܢܡܘܣܐ. ܥܕܡܐ ܕܐܬܝܠܕ ܡܫܝܚܐ ܒܒܝܬܠܚܡ ܘܐܬܪܒܝ
                        ܒܢܨܪܬ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="42"><p rend="footnote text"> B +
                            ܡܕܝܢܬܐ ܕܓܠܝܠܐ</p></note> ܘܐܬܝܕܥ ܢܨܪܝܐ. ܘܩܪܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܠܗ ܝܫܘܥ ܢܨܪܝܐ. ܡܛܠ ܗܕܐ
                    ܟܠܗܘܢ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܒܗܢܐ ܠܫܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܡܡܠܠܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܕܗܝܡܢܘ ܒܗ ܐܬܩܪܝܘ ܢܨܖ̈ܝܐ. ܝܣܖ̈ܠܝܐ ܐܘ
                    ܐܖ̈ܡܝܐ. ܡܛܠ ܕܡܢ ܓܢܣܗܘܢ ܒܐܢܫܘܬܗ ܗܘܐ ܘܡܢ ܠܫܢܗܘܢ. ܘܗܫܐ ܠܐ ܝܕܥܝܢܢ ܐܝܢܐ ܡܢܢ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ
                    ܝܣܪܠܝܐ. ܘܐܝܢܐ |f. 3r| ܐܪܡܝܐ. ܡܛܠ ܕܟܠܢ ܒܚܕ ܠܫܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܡܡܠܠܝܢܢ. ܘܒܚܕ ܢܡܘܣܐ ܡܫܝܚܝܐ
                    ܪܕܝܢܢ. ܓܙܝܖ̈ܝ ܠܒܐ. ܥܘܖ̈ܠܝ ܒܣܪܐ. ܘܟܢ ܐܠܗܐ ܝܕܥ ܫܪܝܪܘܬܐ.</p>
                    <lg>
                <l xml:lang="syr"><hi rend="bold">[2]</hi>
                    ܬܘܒ ܒܚܝܠ ܡܪܢ ܟܬܒܝܢܢ ܦܘܪܫܢ ܟܝܢܐ ܘܩܢܘܡܐ. ܒܩܠ ܐܝܘ ܠܟ ܥܘܒܐ ܐܩܝܡ ܡܪ܀
                        ܕܠܐ ܢܨܛܐ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Instead of the regular ܢܣܛܐ.</p></note> ܠܒܝ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܪܝܐ ܗܘܝ ܠܝ ܡܥܕܪܢܐ. ܘܡܠܦܢܐ ܘܡܚܟܡܢܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܗܕܝܢܐ ܘܡܫܒܠܢܐ. ܘܐܦ ܠܪܘܝܘܬܝ ܡܥܝܪܢܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܕܢܬܥܝܪ ܗܢ ܠܒܝ ܚܒܢܢܐ. ܡܢ ܪܘܝܘܬ ܣܛܢܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܗܘܐ ܒܒܪܟ ܡܘܕܝܢܐ. ܩܕܡ ܗܢ ܥܡܟ ܟܪܝܣܛܝܢܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܒܫܡ ܘܚܝܠܐ ܕܐܠܗܘܬܐ. ܐ̇ܡܪ ܗܢܐ ܡܠܐ ܚܛܝܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܩܠܝܠ ܡܢ ܗܝܡܢܘܬܐ. ܠܘܬ ܡܣܩܡܝ ܗܕ ܬܘܕܝܬܐ܀ |f. 3v|</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܬܘܕܝܬ ܕܢܣܛܘܪܝܢܘܬܐ. ܡܬܩܪܝܐ ܒܥܕܠܝܘܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܬܝܗ̇ ܐܪܬܕܘܟܣܝܬܐ. ܕܡܬܣܝܡܐ ܡܢ ܫܠܝܚܘܬܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܫ̈ܠܝܚܐ ܕܡܕܢܚܐ ܥܗ̈ܝܕܐ. ܐܪܒܥܐ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܣܗ̈ܝܕܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܬܪܝܢ ܫ̈ܠܝܚܐ ܬܪܝܢ ܬܠܡ̈ܝܕܐ. ܟܠ ܚܕ ܠܚܕ ܐܬܪܐ ܦܩܝܕܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܦܩܕ ܬܐܘܡܐ ܠܗܢܕܘ ܪܒܬܐ. ܘܒܪܬܘܠܡܝ ܠܐܪܡܢܝܐ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Blank space after this word in the manuscript. B +
                            ܐܬܐ</p></note></l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܘܐܕܝ ܠܩܛܣܦܘܢ ܡܕܝܢܬܐ. ܘܡܪܝ ܠܨܛ ܐܘ ܠܩܘܢܝ ܩܪܝܬܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܗܕܐ ܥܕܬܐ ܕܡܕܢܚܐ. ܐܝܬ ܒܗ̇ ܛܥܡܐ ܐܦ ܡܠܚܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܫܪܪܐ ܡܘܕܝܐ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"> The
                            gloss ܐܢܬܘ ܡܫܝܚܐ ܒܪܗ ܕܐܠܗܐ is added by the same hand between the lines,
                            in red ink. B places it in the left margin.</p></note> ܒܡܫܝܚܐ. ܐܝܟ ܡܠܬܗ
                    ܕܦܛܪܘܤ ܫܠܝܚܐ܀ |f. 4r|</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܗܢ ܥܡܐ ܕܣܘܪܝܝܘܬܐ. ܐܝܬܘܗܝ ܪܫܐ ܘܫܬܐܣܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܕܥܡ̈ܡܐ ܕܟܪܝܣܛܝܢܘܬܐ. ܕܡܪܝ ܡܢܗ ܫܩܠ ܐܢܫܘܬܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܐܦ ܢܨܪܝܐ ܩܪܝܢ ܠܗ. ܕܡܢ ܢܨܪܬ ܗܘܐ ܝܘܒܠܗ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܘܢܨܪܝܐ ܩܪܝܢ ܠܡܪܗ. ܕܐܢܫܘܬܗ ܗܘܬ ܡܢ ܛܘܗܡܗ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܛܠ ܗܕܐ ܐܦ ܡܫܝܚܐ. ܕܡܢ ܣܘܖ̈ܝܝܐ ܗܘܐ ܕܢܝܚܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܫܕܪ ܐܢܘܢ ܠܡܕܢܚܐ. ܕܡܨܡܚܝܢ ܝܘܠܦܢܐ ܕܪܘܚܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܕܢܚܐ ܢܗܝܪܘܬܐ. ܝܗܒܐ ܠܐܖ̈ܒܥܦܢܝܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܣܘܖ̈ܝܝܐ ܡܠܦܢܘܬܐ. ܝܗܒܝܢ ܠܟܪܝܣܛܝܢܘܬܐ܀ |f. 4v|</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܐܦ ܡܪܢ ܒܝܘܡܐ ܕܚܪܬܐ. ܡܢ ܓܒܐ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The gloss ܡܕܢܚܐ is added by the same hand in the
                            right margin, in red ink.</p></note> ܕܣܘܪܝܝܘܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܕܢ̇ܚ ܠܟܠܗ̇ ܐܢܫܘܬܐ. ܕܡܬܥܝܪ ܠܗ̇ ܡܢ ܫܢܬ ܡܘܬܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܫܝܚܐ ܡܪܢ ܘܐܠܗܢ. ܐܢܫܘܬܗ ܫܩܠ ܡܢ ܛܘܗܡܢ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܘܥܡ̈ܡܐ ܐܚܖ̈ܢܐ ܕܚܣܡܘ ܒܢ. ܛܠܡܘ ܩܢܘܡ ܐܢܫܘܬܗ ܕܡܪܢ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܬܘܒ ܗܦ̇ܟ ܥܒܕܟܘܢ ܠܕܘܟܬܗ. ܣܓܝ ܢܦܩ ܠܗ ܡܢ ܟܢܘܢܬܗ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܐ̇ܡܪ ܠܗ̇ ܗܝܡܢܘܬܗ. ܘܕܟܠܗܘܢ ܒܢ̈ܝ ܬܘܕܝܬܗ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܡܗܝܡܢ ܗܢܐ ܡܠܐ ܚܛܝܬܐ. ܒܗ̇ܘ ܚܝܠܐ ܕܐܠܗܘܬܐ.</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">ܚܕ ܟܝܢܐ ܩܢܘ̈ܡܐ ܬܠܬܐ. ܠܗ ܫܘܒܚܐ ܐܦ ܬܘܕܝܬܐ܀</l>
                <l xml:lang="syr">&lt;…&gt;</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div>
                <head>English translation</head>
                    
                <p xml:lang="en">[1] First, we are going to make known the descent of the Syriacs
                    and their language. “Syriac” is derived from the name “Syria.” God, let His name
                    be glorified, spoke it with our father Adam, and all people used to speak it
                    until the division of languages. At the division of tongues, when all people
                    were gathered for the building of the tower, there God divided their tongues.
                    Seventy-one languages separated themselves from this Syriac language, and they
                    were scattered to the four corners of the world. This Syriac language remained
                    in the four districts of Mesopotamia, which is the chief among the regions of
                    Syria. Syria stretches from Antioch and up to Edessa. For this reason, this
                    Syriac language is called Mesopotamian. These four districts of Mesopotamia were
                    scattered through the regions of the Chaldeans. For this reason, this Syriac
                    people is called Chaldean. The forefathers whose names are written down in the
                    Old and New (Testament) belonged to this Syriac people by their race. It was
                    called the race of believers, because our beginning, that is the human nature of
                    Our Lord, belonged to their race. This race dwelt in the town of Aram in Ur of
                    the Chaldeans, that is Kashkar.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="47"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> A city in southern Mesopotamia, located on the
                            river Tigris, opposite the later medieval city of Wasit.</p></note> Our
                    father Abraham also belonged to this believing race. He had two brothers, one
                    was called Haran and another Nahor. Haran was father of Lot. Haran died. When
                    God made Abraham first of the patriarchs, he departed from the house of his
                    father Terah and from his town of Aram, and He (i.e. God) transferred him to the
                    land of Canaanites, Hittites and the rest. He brought also Lot with him. Nahor
                    remained in their town of Aram. God multiplied his seed there, and they
                    scattered through the regions of Chaldeans. They were called Aramaeans, because
                    they had come from Aram. They knew God, but also worshipped idols; (and) they
                    were uncircumcised. God transferred Abraham to the foreign land,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="48"><p rend="footnote text"> B + “and gave
                            him circumcision”.</p></note> (and) he begat Isaac, and Isaac begat
                    Jacob. When Jacob saw the image of God in the heaven, he was called Israel. God
                    multiplied his seed, and they were called the Sons of Israel. They knew God, and
                    they had circumcision and then the Law, until Christ was born in Bethlehem and
                    grew up in<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"> B +
                            “the Galilean city of”.</p></note> Nazareth and became known as
                    Nazarene. He was called Jesus the Nazarene. For this reason, all those who spoke
                    this Syriac language and believed in him were called Nazarenes, Israelites as
                    well as Aramaeans, because he was from their race by his human nature and from
                    their language. Nowadays, we do not know who among us is an Israelite and who is
                    an Aramaean, because we all speak one Syriac language, and follow one Christian
                    law, circumcised in heart, uncircumcised in the flesh, and so God knows the
                    truth.</p>
                    <lg>
                <l>[2] Again, by the power of Our Lord we are writing an explanation
                    of nature and person;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Or “hypostasis”. It is the nature and person of
                            Christ that are meant here.</p></note> to the tune of “Well done, O
                    (splendid) womb!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="51"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> This tune, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܝܘ ܠܟ ܥܘܒܐ</foreign>, was popular during
                            the late period of East Syrian poetry, among such poets as Gīwargīs
                            Wardā; see A. Pritula, <hi rend="italic">The Wardā: An East Syriac
                                Hymnological Collection. Study and Critical Edition</hi> (Göttinger
                            Orientforschungen, I. Reihe: Syriaca 47; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag,
                            2015), 97.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">O Lord, set up … so that my heart might not turn
                        aside.</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">
                            An abbreviated quote from Ps 141:3-4, with which this chant was
                            augmented.</p></note></l>
                <l>O Lord, be my helper,</l>
                <l>And teacher, and imparter of wisdom,</l>
                <l>Guide and director,</l>
                <l>And one who awakes<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> The idea and language of “awakening” became very
                            popular in the nineteenth and early twentieth-century conversations
                            about identity and nationalism among Syriac Christians. Cf. the famous
                            poem “Awaken, son of Assyria, awaken!” by the Assyrian writer Naum Faiq
                            (1868–1930), reproduced and translated in R. Isaf, “Awakening, or
                            Watchfulness: Naum Faiq and Syriac Language Poetry at the Fall of the
                            Ottoman Empire,” in: H.L. Murre-van den Berg, K. Sanchez Summerer and
                            T.C. Baarda (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Arabic and its Alternatives:
                                Religious Minorities and their Languages in the Emerging Nation
                                States of the Middle East (1920–1950)</hi> (Christians and Jews in
                            Muslim Societies 5; Leiden: Brill, 2020), 171-200 (175, 192).</p></note>
                    (me) from my drunkenness,</l>
                <l>So that this slothful heart of mine should awaken</l>
                <l>From the drunkenness of Satan,</l>
                <l>And I might become a confessor of your Son</l>
                <l>Before this Christian people of yours.</l>
                <l>In the name and power of the Godhead,</l>
                <l>This sinner,</l>
                <l>One of little faith,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="54"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> I.e., the author.</p></note></l>
                <l>Is going to speak about definitions of this confession.</l>
                <l>It is called in a derogatory manner</l>
                <l>The confession of Nestorianism.</l>
                <l>(But) it is orthodox,</l>
                <l>Since it is established by Apostolicity.</l>
                <l>Four are they, the apostles of the East,</l>
                <l>Who are remembered and acknowledged:</l>
                <l>Two apostles (and) two disciples,</l>
                <l>Each one appointed over one region.</l>
                <l>He appointed Thomas over the Great India,</l>
                <l>And Bartholomew over Armenia,</l>
                <l>And Addai over the city of Ctesiphon,</l>
                <l>And Mārī over Ṣāṭ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="55"><p rend="footnote text"
                            > The identity of this toponym is uncertain.</p></note> or the town of
                        Qūnī.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="56"><p> The toponym <hi
                                rend="italic">Qūnī</hi> is a shortened form of the place-name <hi
                                rend="italic">Dūrā d-Qūnī</hi>, mentioned in the Syriac <hi
                                rend="italic">Acts of Mār Mārī</hi> (28, 33) as one of the important
                            centres of this apostle’s missionary activity; ed. A. Harrak, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Acts of Mār Mārī the Apostle</hi> (SBL Writings
                            from the Greco-Roman World 11; Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature,
                            2005), 62, 76. </p></note></l>
                <l>This Church of the East</l>
                <l>Has taste<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="57"><p rend="footnote text"> Or
                            “discernment”.</p></note> as well as salt.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn59" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"> An allusion to Mt
                        5:13.</p></note></l>
                <l>It professes<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"> An
                            interlinear gloss to this word states: “You are the Christ, the Son of
                            God,” a slightly modified version of Peter’s profession of faith in Mt
                            16:16.</p></note> Christ in truth,</l>
                <l>According to the word of Apostle Peter.</l>
                <l>This nation of Syrianness</l>
                <l>Is the head and foundation</l>
                <l>Of the nations of Christianity,</l>
                <l>Since the Lord took (his) human nature from it.</l>
                <l>It<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"> I.e. the
                            Syriac people.</p></note> is also called Nazarene,</l>
                <l>Because its origin was from Nazareth</l>
                <l>And its Lord is called Nazarene,</l>
                <l>Since his human nature was from its lineage.</l>
                <l>Because of this also Christ,</l>
                <l>Who shone forth from among the Syriacs,</l>
                <l>Sent them<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"> I.e.
                            the four apostles, mentioned above.</p></note> to the East,</l>
                <l>To cause the doctrine of the Spirit to shine.</l>
                <l>The East gives</l>
                <l>Brightness to the four corners (of the world).</l>
                <l>The Syriacs give</l>
                <l>Instruction to Christianity.</l>
                <l>And Our Lord at the end of days</l>
                <l>From the country of Syriacs</l>
                <l>Shone forth to the whole humanity,</l>
                <l>Awakening it from the slumber of death.</l>
                <l>Christ, Our Lord and Our God,</l>
                <l>Took his human nature from our lineage.</l>
                <l>And other nations that envied us</l>
                <l>Denied the hypostasis of the human nature of Our Lord.</l>
                <l>Yet, your servant returns to his place,</l>
                <l>He went quite astray from his rule.</l>
                <l>He is going to affirm his faith,</l>
                <l>And that of all sons of his confession.</l>
                <l>This sinner believes</l>
                <l>In that power of Godhead,</l>
                <l>One nature (and) three persons, –</l>
                <l>To Him glory and praise!</l>
                    </lg>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Commentary</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Reading through these sections, one discerns several argumentative
                    strategies that are important for Sāḇā’s promotion of his vision of East Syrian
                    identity. They can be divided into those that focus on language and those
                    related to genealogical descent. In what concerns the linguistic argumentation,
                    Sāḇā starts his exposition with claiming that Syriac was the primeval language
                    of humanity. At the very beginning of Section 1, he relates that God spoke in
                    this language with Adam, and that all people used to speak it until the
                    destruction of the Tower of Babel.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">This portrayal of Syriac as the language of Paradise, spoken by all
                    humanity before the division of the tongues, is not unique to our writer. In
                    fact, it has a long history that could be traced back to Late Antiquity.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="62"><p> For a discussion of the early stage
                            in the development of this notion, see M. Rubin, “The Language of
                            Creation or the Primordial Language: A Case of Cultural Polemics in
                            Antiquity,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Jewish Studies</hi> 49:2
                            (1998), 306-333; Y. Moss, “The Language of Paradise: Hebrew or Syriac?
                            Linguistic Speculations and Linguistic Realities in Late Antiquity,” in:
                            M. Bockmuehl and G.G. Stroumsa (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Paradise in
                                Antiquity: Jewish and Christian Views</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press, 2010), 120-137; F. Briquel-Chatonnet, “La langue du
                            Paradis, la langue comme patrie,” in: M. Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                                >Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi> (Études syriaques 15;
                            Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 9-25; M. Debié, ““La reine de toutes les
                            langues”: les relations hiéroglossiques du syriaque avec les langues
                            environnantes,” in: J.-N. Robert (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Hiéroglossie
                                III: persan, syro-araméen et les relations avec la langue arabe.
                                Collège de France, 25 juin 2018</hi> (Bibliothèque de l’Institut des
                            hautes études japonaises; Paris: Les Éditions du Collège de France,
                            2022), 83-138.</p></note> The roots of this notion can be found in the
                    works of Theodoret of Cyrus (5th c.), but in its fully articulated form it is
                    attested somewhat later, in the <hi rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>, which
                    was composed in Syriac during the sixth or early seventh century. In the part of
                    the narrative that retells the biblical account of the division of languages
                    after the destruction of the Tower of Babel, its author claims that “from Adam
                    and until that time all the peoples spoke this language, that is to say, Syriac,
                    which is Aramaic. For this language is the king of all languages” (24.10).<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="63"><p> For the Syriac text, see S.-M. Ri,
                                <hi rend="italic">La Caverne des Trésors: les deux recensions
                                syriaques</hi> (CSCO 486, Syr. 207; Louvain: Peeters, 1987), 186.
                            For a discussion of this passage in its late antique context, see S.
                            Minov, <hi rend="italic">Memory and Identity in the Syriac</hi>Cave of
                                Treasures<hi rend="italic">: Rewriting the Bible in Sasanian
                                Iran</hi> (Jerusalem Studies in Religion and Culture 26; Leiden:
                            Brill, 2021), 271-283.</p></note> Due to the popularity of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Cave of Treasures</hi>, the notion that Syriac was the
                    primeval language became widely disseminated among Syriac and Arabic-speaking
                    Christians during the Islamic period.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> Cf. Theodore bar Koni, <hi rend="italic">Book of
                                Scholia</hi> II.113; Īšō‘dāḏ of Merv, <hi rend="italic">Commentary
                                on Genesis</hi>, on Gen 11:1; Solomon of Basra, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Book of the Bee</hi> 22-24; Bar Hebraeus, <hi rend="italic">Scholia
                                on Genesis</hi>, on Gen 11:1.</p></note> As the example of Sāḇā
                    demonstrates, it retained its appeal among the East Syrians well into the modern
                    period.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">In addition, it seems that Sāḇā held an opinion that Syriac was the
                    language of Jesus. At the end of Section 1, he explains his statement that all
                    Syriac-speaking followers of Jesus, be they of Israelite or Aramaean descent,
                    came to be known as “Nazarenes” (one of the synonyms used to refer to
                    “Christians” in Syriac) by claiming that it was because Jesus “was from their
                    race by his human nature, and from their language”. The first part of this
                    claim, i.e., that Jesus belonged to the Syriac race, which is discussed below,
                    appears in a slightly more developed form in Section 2.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As in the case of the notion of Syriac as the primeval language,
                    Sāḇā was not the first to identify it as the language of Jesus.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"> For a discussion
                            of the history of this idea, see S. Ruzer, “Hebrew versus Aramaic as
                            Jesus’ Language: Notes on Early Opinions by Syriac Authors,” in: R. Buth
                            and R.S. Notley (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Language Environment of
                                First Century Judaea: Jerusalem Studies in the Synoptic Gospels.
                                Volume Two</hi> (Jewish and Christian Perspectives 26; Leiden:
                            Brill, 2014), 182-205.</p></note> Yet, contrary to the claim of Syriac
                    primacy, this notion gained currency among Syriac Christians relatively late,
                    during the early modern period, and its genesis seems to be somewhat more
                    complicated. Some scholars point to the West Syrian theologian Dionysius bar
                    Ṣalibi (12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c.) as an example of one of the first
                    Syriac writers to hold this opinion. In the polemical tractate <hi rend="italic"
                        >Against the Melkites</hi>, Dionysius rebuffs his imaginary interlocutor,
                    who claims that Syriacs depended heavily on the corpus of Christian writings in
                    Greek, by pointing out that “the Lord was a Syrian, and they (i.e. Greek
                    Christians) have translated all His teaching into their language”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="66"><p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܗܐ ܡܪܝ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܗܘܐ. ܘܟܠܗ̇ ܡܠܦܢܘܬܗ ܐܦܩܘܗ̇
                                ܠܘܬܗܘܢ</foreign>; ed. A. Mingana, <hi rend="italic">Woodbrooke
                                Studies: Christian Documents in Syriac, Arabic, and Garshuni, Edited
                                and Translated with a Critical Apparatus. Vol. 1: Barsalibi’s
                                Treatise against the Melchites; Genuine and Apocryphal Works of
                                Ignatius of Antioch; A Jeremiah Apocryphon; A New Life of John the
                                Baptist; Some Uncanonical Psalms</hi> (Cambridge: W. Heffer &amp;
                            Sons, 1927), 57 [trans. (modified)], 88 [Syr.].</p></note> It should be
                    noted, however, that the wording of Dionysius’ apologetic statement is not
                    unambiguous, and that it could be understood in the sense that Syriac was the
                    language of the written version of Jesus’ teaching, from which the Greek
                    translation was then made, and not the language that he actually spoke.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="67"><p rend="footnote text"> For an example
                            of such approach, cf. the Armenian historiographer Mekhitar of Ayrivank
                            (13th c.) who relates that Luke wrote his Gospel in Syriac; ed. К.П.
                            Паткановъ, “Хронографическая исторiя, составленная отцомъ Мехитаромъ,
                            Вардапетомъ Айриванкскимъ,” <hi rend="italic">Труды Восточнаго отдѣленія
                                Императорскаго русскаго археологическаго общества</hi> 14 (1869),
                            223-418 (257 [Arm.], 360 [trans.]).</p></note> If that is indeed the
                    meaning intended by Dionysius, it could be related to the notion, espoused by
                    some Syriac authors, that the immediate disciples of Jesus spoke Syriac. Thus,
                    when Īšō‘dāḏ of Merv (9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> c.) in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Commentary on the Acts of the Apostles</hi> praises the
                    success of the twelve apostles in spreading Christianity, he describes them as
                    “fishermen, country born, acquainted only with the Syriac tongue, of a plebeian
                        education”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="68"><p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܢ̈ܫܐ ܨ̈ܝܕܐ ܕܐܬܝܠܕܘ ܒܐܓܘܖ̈ܣܐ ܘܒܠܫܢܐ ܣܘܪܝܝܐ ܠܚܘܕ
                                ܡܦܣܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܘܒܪܕܝܘܬܐ ܗܕܝܘ̈ܛܐ</foreign>; ed. M.D. Gibson, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Commentaries of Isho‘dad of Merv, Bishop of
                                Hadatha (c. 850 A.D.), in Syriac and English</hi>. 5 vols (Horae
                            Semiticae 5-7, 10-11; Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1911,
                            1916), vol. 4, 1 [Syr.], 1 [trans.]. This notion goes back to Eusebius,
                                <hi rend="italic">Dem</hi><hi>.</hi><hi rend="italic"> ev</hi>.
                            III.7.10. For a discussion of the linguistic aspect of the ethnonym <hi
                                rend="italic">Sūryāyā</hi>, see Minov, <hi rend="italic">Memory and
                                Identity</hi><hi>, 263-266.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The whole issue of the spread and reception of the idea of Syriac
                    as the language of Jesus among Syriac Christians needs a more detailed
                    investigation, which cannot be carried out here. At this point, one should
                    consider seriously the possibility that this notion gained currency in the
                    Syriac Christian milieu due to the influence of Western missionaries. This idea
                    was expressed by Roman Catholic Orientalists as early as the sixteenth century.
                    For example, Johann Albrecht Widmannstetter refers to Syriac as <hi
                        rend="italic">Iesu Christo vernacula</hi> on the title page of the first
                    printed edition of the Peshitta version of the New Testament, published in
                        1555.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="69"><p> J.A. Widmannstetter, <hi
                                rend="italic">Liber sacrosancti Evangelii de Jesu Christo, Domino
                                &amp; Deo nostro</hi> (Vienna: Michael Cymbermannus, 1555). Similar
                            statements can be found in works of Guillaume Postel (1510–1581); see
                            M.L. Kuntz, “Hebrew and the “Other Sister” Arabic: The Language of Adam
                            as a Paradigm for the <hi rend="italic">Restitutio Omnium</hi> in the
                            Thought of Guillaume Postel,” <hi rend="italic">Quaderni di Studi
                                Arabi</hi> 15 (1997), 21-44 (25). See also Debié, “La reine de
                            toutes les langues,” 99.</p></note> Apparently, this notion started
                    gaining momentum during the nineteenth century among Syriac Christians.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="70"><p> For some examples from the
                            Assyro-Chaldean milieu, see Becker, <hi rend="italic">Revival and
                                Awakening</hi><hi>, 316-318.</hi></p></note> Very soon, it became an
                    essential part of the identity vocabulary of Syriac communities of various
                    denominations and continues to enjoy broad popular support until today.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"> Cf. the data
                            from the Assyrian community in Georgia in K. Khutsishvili, “Religious
                            Aspects of Structuring the Ethnocultural Identity of the Assyrian
                            Community in Georgia,” in: M. Mollica (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                                >Fundamentalism: Ethnographies on Minorities, Discrimination and
                                Transnationalism</hi> (Freiburger Sozialanthropologische Studien 44;
                            Zürich: LIT Verlag, 2016), 65-76 (69).</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Another essential aspect of Sāḇā’s construction of East Syrian
                    identity is his strong emphasis on a genealogical connection between the
                    “Syriacs” and several key figures of the Christian sacred history. In his
                    exposition of the origins of the Syriac people in Section 1, Sāḇā “Syrianizes”
                    the biblical history of salvation by claiming that both the patriarchs of the
                    Old Testament and Jesus himself belonged to the Syriac “race” (<hi rend="italic"
                        >gensā</hi>) or “nation” (<hi rend="italic">‘ammā</hi>). According to him,
                    the original unity of the “Syriac people” that emerged after the division of
                    languages at the Tower of Babel was split into two principal branches,
                    “Aramaeans” and “Israelites”. In the genealogical scheme presented by Sāḇā, the
                    figure of Abraham constitutes a major point of bifurcation in the history of the
                    Syriac people. One branch of it, the descendants of Abraham, was transferred by
                    God to the land of Canaan and eventually became “Israelites,” while another
                    branch, the descendants of Abraham’s brother Nahor (mentioned in Gen 11:26-29),
                    remained in their homeland and became “Aramaeans”. While separated, both groups
                    kept the knowledge of the true God. The coming of Jesus is understood, then, as
                    another turning point in the history of Syriacs. Coming himself from the Syriac
                    lineage, Jesus restores the lost unity of the Syriac people by incorporating
                    into his new community of “Nazarenes” (one of the nouns used in Syriac to refer
                    to Christians in general), descendants of both the Israelites and Aramaeans.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">One should not overlook an additional layer of meaning in Sāḇā’s
                    use of the ethnic label “Aramaean” (<hi rend="italic">Ārāmāyā</hi>), which in
                    classical Syriac usage can also mean “pagan”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73"
                        n="72"><p rend="footnote text"> See J. Joosten, “West Aramaic Elements in
                            the Old Syriac and Peshitta Gospels,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                                Biblical Literature</hi> 110:2 (1991), 271-289 (279-280).</p></note>
                    This meaning of “Aramaean” becomes manifest when, while explaining the origins
                    of the Aramaeans, Sāḇā describes them as worshippers of idols and uncircumcised.
                    However, he mitigates this negative portrayal by adding, in a somewhat
                    self-contradictory manner, that they nevertheless knew God.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Although Sāḇā does not say this explicitly, it seems to follow from
                    his description that the Israelite branch of the Syriac people continued to use
                    Syriac as their language.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="73"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> It is unclear from Sāḇā’s elliptic description how
                            he understood the relationship between these Israelites and contemporary
                            Jews.</p></note> Thus, when he mentions the coming of Jesus at the end
                    of Section 1, Sāḇā makes the following statement: “[A]ll those, who spoke this
                    Syriac language and believed in him, were called Nazarenes, Israelites as well
                    as Aramaeans”. On the one hand, this unusual idea could be a distant echo of the
                    modern reconstructions of the socio-linguistic situation in Palestine during the
                    lifetime of Jesus by scholars, who were arguing that Aramaic was the common
                    language of the Roman province, used by its Jewish and non-Jewish population
                        alike.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="74"><p> For a brief genealogy of
                            this idea, see H.T. Ong, <hi rend="italic">The Multilingual Jesus and
                                the Sociolinguistic World of the New Testament</hi> (Linguistic
                            Biblical Studies 12; Leiden: Brill, 2016), 44-53.</p></note> On the
                    other hand, it may be related somehow to the socio-linguistic situation of the
                    district of Salmas at the time of the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>’s composition,
                    that is, during the early nineteenth century. We should not forget that this
                    region was home to a considerably sized Jewish community, who used their
                    Northeastern Neo-Aramaic dialect for everyday communication.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn76" n="75"><p> On this dialect, see R.J.H. Gottheil, “The
                            Judaeo-Aramaean Dialect of Salamas,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of the
                                Americal Oriental Society</hi> 15 (1893), 297-310; I. Garbell, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Jewish Neo-Aramaic Dialect of Persian Azerbaijan:
                                Linguistic Analysis and Folkloristic Texts</hi> (Janua linguarum,
                            Series practica 3; The Hague: Mouton &amp; Co, 1965); А.Г. Габриелова,
                            “Образец арамейской речи салмасских евреев,” <hi rend="italic">Восточная
                                филология</hi> 1 (1969), 47-58 [in Georgian].</p></note> Although it
                    was quite distinct from the Neo-Aramaic dialect used among local East Syrian
                        Christians,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">
                            See H. Mutzafi, “Christian Salamas and Jewish Salmas: Two Separate Types
                            of Neo-Aramaic,” in: G. Khan and L. Napiorkowska (eds.), <hi
                                rend="italic">Neo-Aramaic and its Linguistic Context</hi> (Gorgias
                            Neo-Aramaic Studies 14; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2015),
                            289-304.</p></note> one might wonder whether the latter would still
                    consider that their Jewish neighbors were speaking the same “Syriac”
                    language.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The claim of Jesus’ Syriac descent serves Sāḇā as the key premise
                    for asserting the superiority of the East Syrian Christian community over all
                    other Christian denominations. In Section 2, he extols the Syriac nation as “the
                    head and foundation” of the Christian nations, and declares that “the Syriacs
                    give instruction to Christianity”. The supremacy of East Syrian Christianity is
                    enhanced further by the claim of its apostolic origins. To prove this point,
                    Sāḇā refers to the missionary activity of the four “apostles of the East”:
                    Thomas, Bartholomew, Addai, and Mārī.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="77"
                            ><p> For a discussion of the early development of traditions about
                            missions of Thomas, Addai, and Mārī, see J.-N. Saint-Laurent, <hi
                                rend="italic">Missionary Stories and the Formation of the Syriac
                                Churches</hi> (Transformation of the Classical Heritage 55; Oakland,
                            California: University of California Press, 2015). On Bartholomew, see
                            R. Burnet, <hi rend="italic">Les Douze Apôtres: histoire de la réception
                                des figures apostoliques dans le christianisme ancien</hi> (Judaïsme
                            ancien et origines du christianisme 1; Turnhout: Brepols, 2014),
                            451-487.</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">As in the case of Syriac’s primacy, in his discussion of the
                    origins and superiority of the Syriac nation, Sāḇā makes use of some traditional
                    motifs, although he develops some of them further. Thus, the roots of his
                    strategy of identifying Abraham and other patriarchs from the pre-Mosaic period
                    of Old Testament history as “Syriacs” can be traced back to Late Antiquity. For
                    example, in the<hi rend="italic"> Hymns on Julian Saba</hi> by Ephrem the
                        Syrian,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="78"><p rend="footnote text"> For
                            a recent discussion of Ephrem’s authorship of these hymns, see B.A.
                            Hartung, “The Authorship and Dating of the Syriac Corpus attributed to
                            Ephrem of Nisibis: A Reassessment,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                                Antikes Christentum</hi> 22:2 (2018), 296-321 (esp. 308-311,
                            319-320).</p></note> one comes across the following praise of the land
                    of Aram: </p>
                <p>Let a myriad tongues give thanks for our land</p>
                <p>In which walked Abraham and his [grand]son Jacob</p>
                <p>Sarah, Rebekah, Leah and Rachel,</p>
                <p>and eleven heads of the tribes.</p>
                <p>Out of this your treasury Zion was enriched by the sons of Jacob:</p>
                <p>The name of our land is greater than that of its fellow.</p>
                <p>For in it was born Levi, origin of priesthood</p>
                <p>And Judah, source of kingship</p>
                <p>And Joseph, the boy who left but became lord of Egypt.</p>
                <p>By the light from you [Aram], the world was enlightened.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="79"><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jul. Saba</hi> 4.8-9: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܖ̈ܒܘ
                                ܠܫܢ̈ܝܢ ܢܘܕܘܢ ܚܠܦ ܐܪܥܢ \ ܕܒܗ̇ ܗܠܟ ܗܘܐ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܘܒܪܗ ܝܥܩܘܒ \ ܣܪܐ ܘܪܦܩܐ
                                ܠܝܐ ܘܪܚܝܠ \ ܐܦ ܚܕܥܣܖ̈ ܖ̈ܝܫܝ ܫܒ̈ܛܐ \ ܡܢ ܓܙܟܝ ܗܘ ܥܬܪܬ ܨܗܝܘܢ ܒܒܢ̈ܝ
                                ܝܥܩܘܒ. \\ ܫܡܗ̇ ܕܐܪܥܢ ܪܒ ܗܘ ܡܢ ܫܡ ܚܒܪܬܗ̇ \ ܒܗ̇ ܗܘ ܓܝܪ ܝܠܝܕ ܟܘܝ ܪܝܫ
                                ܟܘܡܖ̈ܐ \ ܐܦ ܝܗܘܕܐ ܪܝܫ ܡܠܟܘܬܐ \ ܘܝܘܣܦ ܛܠܝܐ ܕܢܦܩ ܘܗܘܐ \ ܡܪܐ ܕܡܨܪܝܢ
                                ܒܢܘܗܪܐ ܕܡܢܟܝ ܢܗܪܬ ܬܒܝܠ</foreign>; ed. E. Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des
                                heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen auf Abraham Kidunaya und Julianos
                                Saba</hi> (CSCO 322, Syr. 140; Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO,
                            1972), 46; trans. by A. Salvesen, “Keeping it in the Family? Jacob and
                            his Aramean Heritage according to Jewish and Christian Sources,” in: E.
                            Grypeou and H. Spurling (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Exegetical
                                Encounter between Jews and Christians in Late Antiquity</hi> (Jewish
                            and Christian Perspectives 18; Leiden: Brill, 2009), 205-220
                        (218).</p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Moreover, the author of the<hi rend="italic"> Hymns</hi>, similarly
                    to Sāḇā, identifies Jesus as a Syrian by forging a close connection between him
                    and the region of Aram/Syria through the figure of Abraham:</p>
                <p>The trickle from our land has watered every region</p>
                <p>Since from it Abraham the great river traveled</p>
                <p>And poured forth springs and fountains</p>
                <p>and streams. From that River</p>
                <p>Gushed forth the great Sea [Christ] that was concealed in it.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn81" n="80"><p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jul. Saba</hi> 4.11: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܚܠܐ ܕܡܢ
                                ܐܪܥܢ ܐܫܩܝ ܠܟܠ ܦܢ̈ܝܢ \ ܕܡܢܗ̇ ܪܕܐ ܗܘܐ ܐܒܪܗܡ ܢܗܪܐ ܪܒܐ \ ܘܐܪܕܝ ܢܒ̈ܥܐ ܐܦ
                                ܡܥܝܢ̈ܐ \ ܐܦ ܡܒܘ̈ܥܐ ܘܡܢܗ ܕܢܗܪܐ \ ܓܚ ܬܘܒ ܘܢܦܩ ܝܡܐ ܪܒܐ ܕܟܣܐ ܗܘܐ
                                ܒܗ</foreign>; ed. Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen
                                Ephraem</hi><hi>, 46-47; trans. Salvesen, “Keeping it in the
                                Family,” 218.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Later on, during the Islamic period, one finds an even closer
                    connection made between Jesus and the region of Aram/Syria in the works of the
                    East Syrian catholicos Timothy I (ob. 823). In <hi rend="italic">Letter 26</hi>,
                    addressed to Māranzḵā, the bishop of Nineveh, Timothy constructs an argument for
                    the independence and primacy of his patriarchal see of Seleucia-Ctesiphon,
                    bringing as a proof, among other claims, the genealogically close kinship
                    between his Christian community and Jesus:</p>
                <p><cit><quote xml:lang="en">We can demonstrate that Christ appeared in the flesh from
                    among us thus: for if Christ appeared in the flesh from David, then David is a
                    descendant of Abraham, Abraham, however, is from among us, the sons of the East,
                    and from the East. It is, then, known and manifest that Christ according to the
                    flesh is from the East and from the sons of the East.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn82" n="81"><p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܘܕܡܢܢ ܕܝܠܢ ܐܬܚܙܝ ܡܫܝܚܐ ܒܒܣܪ ܗܟܢܐ ܡܚܘܝܢܢ. ܐܢܗܘ̣
                                ܓܝܪ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ ܡ̇ܢ ܒܒܣܪ ܡܢ ܕܘܝܕ ܐܬܚܙܝ. ܕܘܝܕ ܕܝܢ ܒܪ ܐܒܪܗܡ. ܐܒܪܗܡ ܕܝܢ ܡܢܢ
                                ܒܢ̈ܝ ܡܕܢܚܐ ܘܡܢ ܡܕܢܚܐ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ. ܝܕܝܥܐ ܐܪܐ ܘܓܠܝܐ ܕܡܫܝܚܐ ܒܒܣܪ ܡܢ ܡܕܢܚܐ
                                ܘܡܢ ܒܢ̈ܝ ܡܕܢܚܐ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ.</foreign>; ed. M. Heimgartner, <hi
                                rend="italic">Die Briefe 3‒29 des ostsyrischen Patriarchen Timotheos
                                I.</hi> (CSCO 700, Syr. 269; Leuven: Peeters, 2021), 141. For a
                            discussion of this letter, see F. Briquel-Chatonnet, F. Jullien, Ch.
                            Jullien, Ch. Moulin Paliard, and M. Rashed, “Lettre du patriarche
                            Timothée à Maranzek<hi rend="superscript">h</hi>ā, évêque de Nineve,”
                                <hi rend="italic">Journal asiatique</hi> 288:1 (2000),
                        1-13.</p></note></quote></cit></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">The genealogical link between Jesus and “Easterners” (read East
                    Syrians) serves Timothy as a ground for claiming the superiority of the East
                    Syrian patriarchal see over other ecclesiastical centers of Christendom. In the
                    same letter, he affirms this superiority in the following manner:</p>
                <p><cit><quote xml:lang="en"><hi rend="jlqj4b">So then, the source of life of
                        Christianity appeared and sprang from the sons of the East, and it is from
                        us that it was divided into four streams which irrigate the entire Paradise
                        of the Catholic Church with the divine and</hi><hi rend="viiyi"> </hi><hi
                        rend="jlqj4b">spiritual drink of the kingdom of heaven.</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="82"><p>
                            <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܒܘܥܐ ܐܪܐ ܡܕܝܢ ܕܚ̈ܝܐ ܕܟܪܣܛܝܢܘܬܐ ܡܢ ܒܢ̈ܝ ܡܕܢܚܐ
                                ܐܬܓܠܝ ܘܢܒܥ. ܘܡܢܢ ܐܬܦܪܫ ܠܐܪܒܥܐ ܖ̈ܫܝܢ܆ ܗ̇ܢܘܢ ܕܠܟܠܗ ܦܪܕܝܣܗ̇ ܕܥܕܬܐ
                                ܩܬܘܠܝܩܐ ܡܫܩܝܢ ܫܩܝܐ ܐܠܗܝܐ ܘܪܘܚܢܝܐ ܕܡܠܟܘܬܐ ܕܫܡܝܐ.</foreign>; ed.
                            Heimgartner, <hi rend="italic">Die Briefe 3‒29</hi><hi>,
                        141.</hi></p></note></quote></cit></p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Comparing Sāḇā’s affirmation of the East Syrian ecclesiastical
                    superiority with that of Timothy, one recognizes that the former’s rhetoric,
                    which revolves around the supposed kinship of the Syriac Christians with the
                    biblical patriarchs as well as with Jesus, follows the general line of the
                    catholicos’ argumentation. It is noteworthy, however, that while Timothy refers
                    to the identity of his Christian community by resorting to such vague regional
                    terms as “the East,” Sāḇā uses the somewhat more ethnically pronounced language
                    of “Syriacs” and “Syriac nation”. One wonders whether this shift reflects the
                    general process of the spread of nationalist consciousness among Christian
                    minorities of the Middle East.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="83"><p> On
                            Syriac Christians in this context, see Becker, <hi rend="italic">Revival
                                and Awakening</hi>; H.L. Murre-van den Berg, “Chaldæans and
                            Assyrians: The Church of the East in the Ottoman Period,” in: E.C.D.
                            Hunter (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Christian Heritage of Iraq:
                                Collected Papers from the Christianity of Iraq I-V Seminar Days</hi>
                            (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 13; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias
                            Press, 2009), 146-164; B. Heyberger, “Les chrétiens de tradition
                            syriaque à l’époque ottomane: systèmes de connaissance et transferts
                            culturels,” in: B. Heyberger (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens de
                                tradition syriaque à l’époque ottomane</hi> (Études syriaques 17;
                            Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2020), 1-33; S. Roussos, “The Collapse of the
                            Ottoman Empire and Survival Strategies of Christian Communities in
                            Greater Syria,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary Levant</hi> 6:1 (2021),
                            51-64.</p></note></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en" xml:id="h26n2minov.3">
                <head>3. Conclusion</head>
                <p xml:lang="en">Completed in the aftermath of the short-term conquest of the Urmī
                    region of Iranian Azerbaijan by Russian troops in 1828–1829, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Book of the Rule</hi> was written during a difficult time for
                    the local East Syrian community, to which its author, the parish priest Sāḇā,
                    belonged. On the one hand, the author and his flock were embroiled in the
                    political and social upheavals caused by the military conflict between the
                    Russian and Qajar empires. In this confrontation, some of the local Armenian and
                    Syriac Christians seriously considered leaving their homeland and resettling in
                    Russian territory.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">On the other hand, an even more serious and long-term danger that
                    threatened the existence of Sāḇā’s community was posed by the increasing
                    pressure from Western missionaries, especially the Roman Catholics. As a result
                    of their efforts, many members of the Church of the East in the district of
                    Salmas had forsaken their traditional ecclesiastical affiliation and joined the
                    ranks of the Assyro-Chaldean Church. It is, first and foremost, in response to
                    this threat that Sāḇā composed his work, which was meant not only to provide his
                    community with spiritual guidance but also to strengthen their self-confidence.
                    With that goal in mind, Sāḇā starts the <hi rend="italic">Book</hi> by offering
                    his audience a condensed exposition of the origins and early history of the
                    Syriac people and their language. Blending traditional and innovative elements,
                    he forges a new vision of Syriac collective identity that asserts the
                    superiority of the East Syrian ethno-religious community over other Christian
                    denominations.</p>
                <p xml:lang="en">Sāḇā’s work provides us with a unique insight into the dynamic
                    evolution of the traditional repertoire of East Syrian collective identity, just
                    before the process of its “Assyrianization” was set in motion as a result of the
                    discovery of the rich archaeological and textual legacy of the Assyrian empire
                    by Western scholars.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text"> On this development, see Becker, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Revival and Awakening</hi>, 299-338; A.M. Butts, “Assyrian
                            Christians,” in: E. Frahm (ed.), <hi rend="italic">A Companion to
                                Assyria</hi> (Blackwell Companions to the Ancient World; Hoboken,
                            New Jersey: Wiley Blackwell, 2017), 599-612 (602-605).</p></note> In his
                    vision, the superiority of the East Syrian Christians stems, first and foremost,
                    from the fact that they speak Syriac, the language of Adam, Abraham, and Jesus
                    himself. It receives additional support in the claim that Jesus was a part of
                    the Syriac nation by way of his human nature. As has been demonstrated, in
                    making these claims, Sāḇā stands at the end of the centuries-long process of
                    localization and indigenization of the biblical history of salvation by Syriac
                        Christians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">
                            For discussion of the early stages of this process, see A.H. Becker,
                            “The Ancient Near East in the Late Antique Near East: Syriac Christian
                            Appropriation of the Biblical East,” in: G. Gardner and K.L. Osterloh
                            (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Antiquity in Antiquity: Jewish and Christian
                                Pasts in the Greco-Roman World</hi> (Texts and Studies in Ancient
                            Judaism 123; Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2008), 394-415; Salvesen, “Keeping
                            it in the Family”; Minov, <hi rend="italic">Memory and
                            Identity</hi>.</p></note> A remarkable development in itself, this
                    identity strategy deserves further investigation, including its role in the
                    emergence of a nationalist discourse among Syriac Christians during the late
                    nineteenth and twentieth centuries.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="86"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For some examples of this phenomenon, see Becker,
                                <hi rend="italic">Revival and Awakening</hi>; Butts, “Assyrian
                            Christians”.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="en" type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                <bibl>Baddeley, J.F. <hi rend="italic">The Russian Conquest of the Caucasus</hi>
                    (London: Longmans, Green and Co., 1908).</bibl>
                <bibl>Beck, E. <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen auf Abraham
                        Kidunaya und Julianos Saba</hi> (CSCO 322, Syr. 140; Louvain: Secrétariat du
                    CorpusSCO, 1972).</bibl>
                <bibl>Becker, A.H. “The Ancient Near East in the Late Antique Near East: Syriac
                    Christian Appropriation of the Biblical East,” in: G. Gardner and K.L. Osterloh
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Antiquity in Antiquity: Jewish and Christian Pasts in
                        the Greco-Roman World</hi> (Texts and Studies in Ancient Judaism 123;
                    Tübingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2008), 394-415.</bibl>
                <bibl>Becker, A.H. <hi rend="italic">Revival and Awakening: American Evangelical
                        Missionaries in Iran and the Origins of Assyrian Nationalism</hi> (Chicago,
                    Illinois: The University of Chicago Press, 2015).</bibl>
                <bibl>Bournoutian, G.A. <hi rend="italic">Eastern Armenia in the Last Decades of
                        Persian Rule, 1807–1828: A Political and Socioeconomic Study of the Khanate
                        of Erevan on the Eve of the Russian Conquest</hi> (Malibu, California:
                    Undena Publications, 1982).</bibl>
                <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F. “La langue du Paradis, la langue comme patrie,” in: M.
                    Farina (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les auteurs syriaques et leur langue</hi>
                    (Études syriaques 15; Paris: Geuthner, 2018), 9-25.</bibl>
                <bibl>Briquel-Chatonnet, F., Jullien, F., Jullien, Ch., Moulin Paliard, Ch., and
                    Rashed, M. “Lettre du patriarche Timothée à Maranzek<hi rend="superscript"
                        >h</hi>ā, évêque de Nineve,” <hi rend="italic">Journal asiatique</hi> 288:1
                    (2000), 1-13.</bibl>
                <bibl>Burnet, R. <hi rend="italic">Les Douze Apôtres: histoire de la réception des
                        figures apostoliques dans le christianisme ancien</hi> (Judaïsme ancien et
                    origines du christianisme 1; Turnhout: Brepols, 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl>Butts, A.M. “Assyrian Christians,” in: E. Frahm (ed.), <hi rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Assyria</hi> (Blackwell Companions to the Ancient World;
                    Hoboken, New Jersey: Wiley Blackwell, 2017), 599-612.</bibl>
                <bibl>Coakley, J.F. <hi rend="italic">The Church of the East and the Church of England:
                        A History of the Archbishop of Canterbury’s Assyrian Mission</hi> (Oxford:
                    Oxford University Press, 1992).</bibl>
                <bibl>de Vries, W. <hi rend="italic">Sakramententheologie bei den Nestorianern</hi>
                    (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 133; Roma: Pontificium Institutum Orientalium
                    Studiorum, 1947).</bibl>
                <bibl>Debié, M. ““La reine de toutes les langues”: les relations hiéroglossiques du
                    syriaque avec les langues environnantes,” in: J.-N. Robert (ed.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Hiéroglossie III: persan, syro-araméen et les relations avec
                        la langue arabe. Collège de France, 25 juin 2018</hi> (Bibliothèque de
                    l’Institut des hautes études japonaises; Paris: Les Éditions du Collège de
                    France, 2022), 83-138.</bibl>
                <bibl>Dum-Tragut, J. “Assyrians in Armenia – An Interdisciplinary Survey,” in: L. Tang
                    and D.W. Winkler (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From the Oxus River to the Chinese
                        Shores: Studies on East Syriac Christianity in China and Central Asia
                    </hi>(Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒ Oecumenica 5; Zürich: LIT Verlag, 2013),
                    341-353.</bibl>
                <bibl>Frazee, C.A. <hi rend="italic">Catholics and Sultans: The Church and the Ottoman
                        Empire, 1453</hi>–<hi rend="italic">1923</hi> (London: Cambridge University
                    Press, 1983).</bibl>
                <bibl>Garbell, I. <hi rend="italic">The Jewish Neo-Aramaic Dialect of Persian
                        Azerbaijan: Linguistic Analysis and Folkloristic Texts</hi> (Janua
                    linguarum, Series practica 3; The Hague: Mouton &amp; Co, 1965).</bibl>
                <bibl>Gibson, M.D. <hi rend="italic">The Commentaries of Isho‘dad of Merv, Bishop of
                        Hadatha (c. 850 A.D.), in Syriac and English</hi>. 5 vols (Horae Semiticae
                    5-7, 10-11; Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1911, 1916).</bibl>
                <bibl>Gottheil, R.J.H. “The Judaeo-Aramaean Dialect of Salamas,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of the American Oriental Society</hi> 15 (1893), 297-310.</bibl>
                <bibl>Harrak, A. <hi rend="italic">The Acts of Mār Mārī the Apostle</hi> (SBL Writings
                    from the Greco-Roman World 11; Atlanta: Society of Biblical Literature,
                    2005).</bibl>
                <bibl>Hartung, B.A. “The Authorship and Dating of the Syriac Corpus attributed to
                    Ephrem of Nisibis: A Reassessment,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Antikes
                        Christentum</hi> 22:2 (2018), 296-321.</bibl>
                <bibl>Heimgartner, M. <hi rend="italic">Die Briefe 3‒29 des ostsyrischen Patriarchen
                        Timotheos I.</hi> (CSCO 700, Syr. 269; Leuven: Peeters, 2021).</bibl>
                <bibl>Heyberger, B. <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens au Proche-Orient: de la compassion
                        à la compréhension</hi> (Manuels Payot; Paris: Payot &amp; Rivages,
                    2013).</bibl>
                <bibl>Heyberger, B. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à
                        l’époque ottomane</hi> (Études syriaques 17; Paris: Paul Geuthner,
                    2020).</bibl>
                <bibl>Heyberger, B. “Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à l’époque ottomane: systèmes
                    de connaissance et transferts culturels,” in: B. Heyberger (ed.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à l’époque ottomane</hi>
                    (Études syriaques 17; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2020), 1-33.</bibl>
                <bibl>Hopwood, D. <hi rend="italic">The Russian Presence in Syria and Palestine,
                        1843–1914: Church and Politics in the Near East</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                    Press, 1969).</bibl>
                <bibl>Isaf, R. “Awakening, or Watchfulness: Naum Faiq and Syriac Language Poetry at the
                    Fall of the Ottoman Empire,” in: H.L. Murre-van den Berg, K. Sanchez Summerer
                    and T.C. Baarda (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Arabic and its Alternatives: Religious
                        Minorities and their Languages in the Emerging Nation States of the Middle
                        East (1920–1950)</hi> (Christians and Jews in Muslim Societies 5; Leiden:
                    Brill, 2020), 171-200.</bibl>
                <bibl>Jakob, J. <hi rend="italic">Ostsyrische Christen und Kurden im Osmanischen Reich
                        des 19. und frühen 20. Jahrhunderts</hi> (Orientalia ‒ Patristica ‒
                    Oecumenica 7; Wien: LIT, 2014).</bibl>
                <bibl>Joosten, J. “West Aramaic Elements in the Old Syriac and Peshitta Gospels,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Biblical Literature</hi> 110:2 (1991), 271-289.</bibl>
                <bibl>Joseph, J.L. <hi rend="italic">Muslim-Christian Relations and Inter-Christian
                        Rivalries in the Middle East: The Case of the Jacobites in an Age of
                        Transition</hi> (Albany: State University of New York Press, 1983).</bibl>
                <bibl>Khan, G. <hi rend="italic">The Neo-Aramaic Dialect of the Assyrian Christians of
                        Urmi</hi>. 4 vols (Studies in Semitic Languages and Linguistics 86; Leiden:
                    Brill, 2016).</bibl>
                <bibl>Khutsishvili, K. “Religious Aspects of Structuring the Ethnocultural Identity of
                    the Assyrian Community in Georgia,” in: M. Mollica (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fundamentalism: Ethnographies on Minorities, Discrimination and
                        Transnationalism</hi> (Freiburger Sozialanthropologische Studien 44; Zürich:
                    LIT Verlag, 2016), 65-76. </bibl>
                <bibl>Kuntz, M.L. “Hebrew and the “Other Sister” Arabic: The Language of Adam as a
                    Paradigm for the <hi rend="italic">Restitutio Omnium</hi> in the Thought of
                    Guillaume Postel,” <hi rend="italic">Quaderni di Studi Arabi</hi> 15 (1997),
                    21-44.</bibl>
                <bibl>Macomber, W.F. “The Oldest Known Text of the Anaphora of the Apostles Addai and
                    Mari,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 32 (1966),
                    335-371.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mingana, A. <hi rend="italic">Woodbrooke Studies: Christian Documents in Syriac,
                        Arabic, and Garshuni, Edited and Translated with a Critical Apparatus. Vol.
                        1: Barsalibi’s Treatise against the Melchites; Genuine and Apocryphal Works
                        of Ignatius of Antioch; A Jeremiah Apocryphon; A New Life of John the
                        Baptist; Some Uncanonical Psalms</hi> (Cambridge: W. Heffer &amp; Sons,
                    1927).</bibl>
                <bibl>Minov, S. <hi rend="italic">Memory and Identity in the Syriac </hi>Cave of
                        Treasures<hi rend="italic">: Rewriting the Bible in Sasanian Iran</hi>
                    (Jerusalem Studies in Religion and Culture 26; Leiden: Brill, 2021).</bibl>
                <bibl>Minov, S., <hi rend="italic">The Marvels Found in the Great Cities and in the
                        Seas and on the Islands: A Representative of ‘Aǧā’ib Literature in
                        Syriac</hi> (Cambridge Semitic Languages and Cultures 6; Cambridge: Open
                    Book Publishers, 2021).</bibl>
                <bibl>Moss, Y. “The Language of Paradise: Hebrew or Syriac? Linguistic Speculations and
                    Linguistic Realities in Late Antiquity,” in: M. Bockmuehl and G.G. Stroumsa
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Paradise in Antiquity: Jewish and Christian Views</hi>
                    (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010), 120-137.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mostashari, F. <hi rend="italic">On the Religious Frontier: Tsarist Russia and
                        Islam in the Caucasus</hi> (London: I.B. Tauris, 2006).</bibl>
                <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L. <hi rend="italic">From a Spoken to a Written Language:
                        The Introduction and Development of Literary Urmia Aramaic in the Nineteenth
                        Century</hi> (Publications of the ‘De Goeje Fund’ 28; Leiden: Brill,
                    1999).</bibl>
                <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L. “Chaldæans and Assyrians: The Church of the East in the
                    Ottoman Period,” in: E.C.D. Hunter (ed.), <hi rend="italic">The Christian
                        Heritage of Iraq: Collected Papers from the Christianity of Iraq I-V Seminar
                        Days</hi> (Gorgias Eastern Christian Studies 13; Piscataway, New Jersey:
                    Gorgias Press, 2009), 146-164.</bibl>
                <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L. <hi rend="italic">Scribes and Scriptures: The Church of
                        the East in the Eastern Ottoman Provinces (1500‒1850)</hi> (Eastern
                    Christian Studies 21; Louvain: Peeters, 2015).</bibl>
                <bibl>Murre-van den Berg, H.L. “Syriac Identity in the Modern Era,” in: D. King (ed.),
                        <hi rend="italic">The Syriac World</hi> (Routledge Worlds; London:
                    Routledge, 2019), 770-782.</bibl>
                <bibl>Mutzafi, H. “Christian Salamas and Jewish Salmas: Two Separate Types of
                    Neo-Aramaic,” in: G. Khan and L. Napiorkowska (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Neo-Aramaic and its Linguistic Context</hi> (Gorgias Neo-Aramaic Studies
                    14; Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2015), 289-304.</bibl>
                <bibl>O Flynn, Th.S.R. <hi rend="italic">The Western Christian Presence in the Russias
                        and Qājār Persia, c. 1760–c. 1870</hi> (Studies in Christian Mission 47;
                    Leiden: Brill, 2017).</bibl>
                <bibl>Okkenhaug, I.M. and Summerer, K.S. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christian Missions
                        and Humanitarianism in the Middle East, 1850–1950: Ideologies, Rhetoric, and
                        Practices</hi> (Leiden Studies in Islam and Society 11; Leiden: Brill,
                    2020).</bibl>
                <bibl>Ong, H.T. <hi rend="italic">The Multilingual Jesus and the Sociolinguistic World
                        of the New Testament</hi> (Linguistic Biblical Studies 12; Leiden: Brill,
                    2016).</bibl>
                <bibl>Parker, L. “The Ambiguities of Belief and Belonging: Catholicism and the Church
                    of the East in the Sixteenth Century,” <hi rend="italic">English Historical
                        Review</hi> 133:565 (2018), 1420-1445.</bibl>
                <bibl>Parker, L. “Yawsep I of Amida (d. 1707) and the Invention of the Chaldeans,” in:
                    B. Heyberger (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Les chrétiens de tradition syriaque à
                        l’époque ottomane</hi> (Études syriaques 17; Paris: Paul Geuthner, 2020),
                    121-152.</bibl>
                <bibl>Pritula, A. <hi rend="italic">The Wardā: An East Syriac Hymnological Collection.
                        Study and Critical Edition</hi> (Göttinger Orientforschungen, I. Reihe:
                    Syriaca 47; Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2015).</bibl>
                <bibl>Ri, S.-M. <hi rend="italic">La Caverne des Trésors: les deux recensions
                        syriaques</hi> (CSCO 486, Syr. 207; Louvain: Peeters, 1987).</bibl>
                <bibl>Roussos, S. “The Collapse of the Ottoman Empire and Survival Strategies of
                    Christian Communities in Greater Syria,” <hi rend="italic">Contemporary
                        Levant</hi> 6:1 (2021), 51-64.</bibl>
                <bibl>Rubin, M. “The Language of Creation or the Primordial Language: A Case of
                    Cultural Polemics in Antiquity,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Jewish
                        Studies</hi> 49:2 (1998), 306-333.</bibl>
                <bibl>Ruzer, S. “Hebrew versus Aramaic as Jesus’ Language: Notes on Early Opinions by
                    Syriac Authors,” in: R. Buth and R.S. Notley (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Language Environment of First Century Judaea: Jerusalem Studies in the
                        Synoptic Gospels. Volume Two</hi> (Jewish and Christian Perspectives 26;
                    Leiden: Brill, 2014), 182-205.</bibl>
                <bibl>Saint-Laurent, J.-N. <hi rend="italic">Missionary Stories and the Formation of
                        the Syriac Churches</hi> (Transformation of the Classical Heritage 55;
                    Oakland, California: University of California Press, 2015).</bibl>
                <bibl>Salvesen, A. “Keeping it in the Family? Jacob and his Aramean Heritage according
                    to Jewish and Christian Sources,” in: E. Grypeou and H. Spurling (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">The Exegetical Encounter between Jews and Christians in Late
                        Antiquity</hi> (Jewish and Christian Perspectives 18; Leiden: Brill, 2009),
                    205-220.</bibl>
                <bibl>Sarau, O. and Shedd, W.A. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in
                        the Library of the Museum Association of Oroomiah College</hi> (Oroomiah,
                    Persia: [s.n.], 1898) [in Syriac].</bibl>
                <bibl>Schlicht, A. <hi rend="italic">Frankreich und die syrischen Christen 1799–1861:
                        Minoritäten und europäischer Imperialismus im Vorderen Orient</hi>
                    (Islamkundliche Untersuchungen 61; Berlin: Klaus Schwarz, 1981).</bibl>
                <bibl>Shafiyev, F. <hi rend="italic">Resettling the Borderlands: State Relocations and
                        Ethnic Conflict in the South Caucasus</hi> (Montreal: McGill-Queen’s
                    University Press, 2018).</bibl>
                <bibl>Sherry, D.L. <hi rend="italic">Imperial Alchemy: Resettlement, Ethnicity, and
                        Governance in the Russian Caucasus, 1828–1865</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation;
                    University of California, 2007).</bibl>
                <bibl>Tamcke, M. “Nestorianisch, syrisch oder assyrisch? Beobachtungen zum
                    Selbstverständnis der lutherischen Nestorianer in der Periode von 1875-1915,”
                    in: U. Pietruschka (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Hermeneutik und Exegese:
                        Verstehenslehre und Verstehensdeutung im regionalen System koexistierender
                        Religionsgemeinschaften im Orient, Leucorea-Konferenz 2005</hi> (Hallesche
                    Beiträge zur Orientwissenschaft 43; Halle an der Salle:
                    Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg, 2009), 159-169.</bibl>
                <bibl>Tamcke, M. “Assyro-Chaldean Christians,” in: M. Raheb and M.A. Lamport (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">The Rowman &amp; Littlefield Handbook of Christianity in
                        the Middle East</hi> (The Rowman &amp; Littlefield Handbook Series; Lanham,
                    MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2021), 237-243.</bibl>
                <bibl>Teule, H.G.B. <hi rend="italic">Les Assyro-chaldéens: chrétiens d’Irak, d’Iran et
                        de Turquie</hi> (Fils d’Abraham; Turnhout: Brepols, 2008).</bibl>
                <bibl>Thomas, D.R. and Chesworth, J. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Christian-Muslim
                        Relations: A Bibliographical History. Volume 18: The Ottoman Empire
                        (1800‒1914)</hi> (History of Christian-Muslim Relations 44; Leiden: Brill,
                    2021).</bibl>
                <bibl>Widmannstetter, J.A. <hi rend="italic">Liber sacrosancti Evangelii de Jesu
                        Christo, Domino &amp; Deo nostro</hi> (Vienna: Michael Cymbermannus,
                    1555).</bibl>
                <bibl>Wilmshurst, D. <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical Organisation of the Church of
                        the East, 1318–1913</hi> (CSCO 582, Subs. 104; Louvain: Peeters, 2000).</bibl>
                <bibl>Wright, W. <hi rend="italic">A Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts Preserved in
                        the Library of the University of Cambridge</hi>. 2 vols (Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press, 1901).</bibl>
                <bibl>Агаян, Ц.П., Дилоян, В.А. and Алексанян, А.В. <hi rend="italic">Присоединение
                        Восточной Армении к России: Сборник документов. Том II (1814–1830)</hi>
                    (Материалы по истории армянского народа 17; Ереван: Издательство Академии наук
                    Армянской ССР, 1978).</bibl>
                <bibl>Балаян, Б.П. <hi rend="italic">Дипломатическая история русско-иранских войн и
                        присоединения Восточной Армении к России</hi> (Ереван: Издательство Академии
                    наук Армянской ССР, 1988).</bibl>
                <bibl>Габриелова, А.Г. “Образец арамейской речи салмасских евреев,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Восточная филология</hi> 1 (1969), 47-58 [in Georgian].</bibl>
                <bibl>Зая, И.Ю. “Ассирийцы и Россия (вторая половина XIX – начало XX в.),” <hi
                        rend="italic">Восток</hi> 4 (1997), 23-36.</bibl>
                <bibl>Матвеев, К.П. “К истории переселения ассирийцев в Россию,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Народы Азии и Африки</hi> 5 (1980), 165-168.</bibl>
                <bibl>Паткановъ, К.П. “Хронографическая исторiя, составленная отцомъ Мехитаромъ,
                    Вардапетомъ Айриванкскимъ,” <hi rend="italic">Труды Восточнаго отдѣленія
                        Императорскаго русскаго археологическаго общества</hi> 14 (1869),
                    223-418.</bibl>
                <bibl>Садо, С. <hi rend="italic">Материалы к биографическому словарю ассирийцев в
                        России (XIX – середина XX века)</hi> (С.-Петербург: Издательство Олега
                    Абышко, 2006).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
