<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Hubert Kaufhold, <hi rend="italic">Ebedjesus von Nisibis,
                    „Ordo iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum”. Eine Zusammenstellung der kirchlichen
                    Rechtsbestimmungen der ostsyrischen Kirche im 14. Jahrhundert</hi> (Wiesbaden:
                    Harrassowitz, 2019)</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Matthias</forename>
                        <surname>Perkams</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Universität Jena</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2023</date>
                <idno>Volume 26.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv26n2brperkams</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Matthias Perkams</author>
                        <title level="a">Hubert Kaufhold, <hi rend="italic">Ebedjesus von Nisibis,
                            „Ordo iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum”. Eine Zusammenstellung der kirchlichen
                            Rechtsbestimmungen der ostsyrischen Kirche im 14. Jahrhundert</hi> (Wiesbaden:
                            Harrassowitz, 2019)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol26/HV26N2BRPerkams.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2023</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="565" to="567">565-567</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="7"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2024-01-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            <div type="title" xml:lang="en"><head>Hubert Kaufhold, <hi rend="italic">Ebedjesus von Nisibis,
                    „Ordo iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum”. Eine Zusammenstellung der kirchlichen
                    Rechtsbestimmungen der ostsyrischen Kirche im 14. Jahrhundert</hi> (Wiesbaden:
                Harrassowitz, 2019). Pp. xxiv + 628; €118.</head></div>
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">This volume offers the first critical edition of an
                important part of Syriac (ecclesiatico-)juridical literature, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >penqīṯā ḏ-ṭukkās dīnē ʿettānāyē</hi> by the East Syriac author ʿAbdīšōʿ bar
                Briḵā (d. 1318 AD). Kaufhold discusses the exact meaning of this title and proposes
                “Band (πινακίδιον) der Zusammenstellung der kirchlichen Rechtsbestimmungen” (volume
                of compilation of the ecclesiastical legal regulations; pp. 10*-12*). Thus, Kaufhold
                rejects the translation of <hi rend="italic">dīnē</hi> as “judgments,” even if the
                book’s title retains the traditional Latin translation
                as<hi rend="italic"> ordo iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum</hi>,
                which obviously conveys exactly this meaning. In his rich introduction, Kaufhold
                also summarizes the content of the work, which somewhat differs from its more famous
                precursor, the <hi rend="italic">Nomocanon</hi>, also compiled by ʿAbdīšōʿ. Whereas
                according to Kaufhold this earlier work builds upon the previous East Syrian
                juridical literature which can be traced back to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nomocanon</hi> of Gabriel of Basra, the <hi rend="italic">Ordo iudiciorum
                    ecclesiasticorum</hi> presents the subject matter in a new order, designed by
                ʿAbdīšōʿ, and contains much material that is not of a juridical nature strictly
                speaking. This is especially true for the first book where, for example, a
                chronological overview can be found. For this reason, Kaufhold describes the work
                rather as a “Handbuch für höhere Kleriker” (handbook for the higher clergy) than as
                a juridical manual.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Kaufhold’s edition, which has long been in preparation, could
                now be finished thanks to the availability of two copies from a lost manuscript
                dating from 1535 (which Addai Scher saw in 1902 in the library of Notre Dame des
                Semences, but which was reported as missing already in 1926/1927 when Jacques Vosté
                visited this monastery). Digital images of two copies of this now lost manuscript
                are available in the HMML collection. One of these (Zakho 28) does indeed appear to
                be a direct copy of the 1535 manuscript, whereas the other manuscript, Bagdad,
                Chaldean Monastery 518, might be separated by one intermediate from its <hi
                    rend="italic">Vorlage</hi>. Both have been copied in 1885, one of them in Seert,
                the other one in Alqōš, from where their model was later transferred to Notre Dame
                des Semences. It is unclear if the 1535 codex was kept in Seert before coming to
                Notre Dame des Semences. In any case, according to Kaufhold, both manuscripts, Zakho
                28 and Bagdad 518, can be considered as independent descendants of the 1535
                manuscript, which in turn might be a copy of the author’s autograph. Thus they
                allow, in spite of minor errors and differences, the reconstruction of a more
                correct and complete text than all other manuscripts as well as the Latin
                translation by Vosté. Other manuscripts are mostly not mentioned in the critical
                apparatus, except for deviations of the Vosté translation and the witnesses of the
                rather restricted indirect tradition of certain parts of ʿAbdīšōʿs work. Thus, from
                now on Kaufhold’s edition should serve as the basis of all further research and of
                any quotations of our text which do not go back directly to the manuscripts.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The new edition offers ample evidence of Kaufhold’s extensive
                research on the sources of ʿAbdīšōʿs handbook. Apart from ʿAbdīšōʿs own earlier <hi
                    rend="italic">Nomocanon</hi>, these sources include various documents of
                juridical nature. Especially interesting is the case of the Copto-Arabic juridical
                handbook by Ibn al-ʿAssāl, which ʿAbdīšōʿ might have consulted in Arabic
                translation. In the vast majority of instances, Kaufhold succeeds in identifying the
                sources, so that his edition should be consulted for any questions in this
                regard.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Kaufhold’s edition not only closes an important gap in the
                editorial situation of Syriac juridical literature, but his work also offers many
                important insights into the history, the literary form, and the sources of the text
                in question. It should be part of any library specialized in Syriac studies.</p>
 </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
