<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">In Memoriam: Fr. Abdo Badwi, O.L.M.</title>
                <author>
                    <name><forename>Ephrem Aboud</forename>
                        <surname>Ishac</surname></name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Yale Institute of Sacred Music, Yale
                            University</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2023</date>
                <idno>Volume 26.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p xml:lang="en">For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0
                            International license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv26n1obbadwi</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Ephrem Aboud Ishac</author>
                        <title level="a">In Memoriam: Fr. Abdo Badwi, O.L.M.</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol26/HV26N1OBBadwi.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2023</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="1" to="2">1-2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="1"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p xml:lang="en">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal
                    dedicated to the study of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in
                    January and July) by Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998,
                    Hugoye seeks to offer the best scholarship available in the field of Syriac
                    studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass/>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2023-05-13">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="obituary">
        <body>
            <div xml:lang="en" type="title">
                <head>In
                Memoriam:<lb/>Fr. Abdo Badwi, O.L.M. †<lb/>(8 December 1948 – 28 October 2022)</head>
            </div>
            
            <div xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">The community of Syriac scholars will always remember the late
                Maronite monk: Fr. Abdo Badwi, who passed away peacefully on 28<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> October 2022. He was especially well-known for
                founding the new Syriac school of Sacred Art at the Holy Spirit University of Kaslik
                – Lebanon. His Syriac icons, which he painted for several churches worldwide, showed
                his unique dedication to the whole Syriac tradition, crossing ecumenically church
                denominations, by concentrating on the Syriac Art he revived after studying most of
                the miniatures in Syriac manuscripts and archeological sites.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">He was born in the Maronite village of Mazra͑et Yeshu͑, Lebanon, on
                    8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 1948 (on the Catholic Feast of
                Immaculate Conception, which is also the Commemoration of the Virgin Mary’s parents
                in the Syriac Calendar), where he had shown since his early childhood a
                distinguished talent for learning languages, especially Syriac. In 1963, he joined
                the Lebanese Maronite Order (<hi rend="italic">Ordo Libanensis Maronitarum</hi>:
                O.L.M.) and was ordained as a priest in 1975. He studied in Rome, receiving a
                Diploma from the Academy of Fine Arts in 1979. He began teaching in 1980 on
                Iconography and Christian Sacred Art at the Holy Spirit University of Kaslik (USEK),
                where in 1986, he became the dean for the Faculty of Fine Arts. In 1994 he founded
                the Department of the Sacred Art, and in 2010 he was appointed as the director of
                the Institute of Liturgy. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">In addition to his dedicated paintings which covered the whole
                Syriac liturgical year and many other themes, he published in Kaslik several books
                and articles, such as: “Le syriaque pour tout le monde” (1984), “L'iconographie de
                l'année liturgique de l'église Syro-Maronite” (2006), and “Iconographie et peinture
                dans l'Église maronite” (2013).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">He was remarkably active in attending the Syriac international
                conferences, especially: Symposium Syriacum, North American Syriac Symposium, The
                Canadian Society for Syriac Studies Symposium, and the World Syriac Conferences at
                St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute (SEERI) in Kottayam – Kerala, where he
                taught and supported its program for years.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Those who have known him will keep the good memory of his
                extraordinary enthusiasm for Syriac art heritage and Eastern Christian legacy in the
                world, where he travelled personally to visit and study. He built friendly
                relationships with many of the Syriacists in the West and with most of the Syriac
                heritage scholars worldwide.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Abdo Badwi’s name will be remembered for many generations to come,
                especially while visiting the churches and seeing the icons he painted: <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܕܘܟ̣ܪܢܐ ܛܒܐ
                    ܠܐܒܘܢ ܥܒܕܐ ܒܕܘܝ</foreign> !</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> December 2022 (on
                Fr. Abdo Badwi’s 40<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> day memorial)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
