<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Alberto Rigolio, <hi rend="italic">Christians in Conversation:
                    A Guide to Late Antique Dialogues in Greek and Syriac</hi> (Oxford: University
                    Press, 2019)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>J. Edward</forename>
                        <surname>Walters</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>Hill Museum &amp; Manuscript Library</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2023</date>
                <idno>Volume 26.1</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv26n1prwalters</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>J. Edward Walters</author>
                        <title level="a">Alberto Rigolio, <hi rend="italic">Christians in Conversation:
                            A Guide to Late Antique Dialogues in Greek and Syriac</hi> (Oxford: University
                            Press, 2019)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol26/HV26N1PRWalters.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2023</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="311" to="315">311-315</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="10"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term></term>
                    <term></term>
                    <term></term>
                    <term></term>
                    <term></term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2023-05-13">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>


<div type="title" xml:lang="en">
<head>Alberto Rigolio, <hi rend="italic">Christians in Conversation:
                    A Guide to Late Antique Dialogues in Greek and Syriac</hi> (Oxford: University
                Press, 2019). Pp. xii + 297; $105.</head>
</div>
            <div type="body" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en">Scholars of both classical literature and Christian literature
                of late antiquity are certainly acquainted with texts that are presented in dialogue
                format, whether as a didactic tool or as a representation of a “real” historical
                conversation. Despite obvious connections, much previous scholarship on these bodies
                of literature has resisted the idea that late ancient Christian dialogues are an
                extension of the classical genre, preferring instead to view Christian dialogues as
                merely derivative in form and propagandistic in function. Yet, while some Christian
                dialogue texts have been studied at length (e.g., Justin Martyr’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dialogue with Trypho</hi>) many others remain understudied and undervalued as
                comparative points of study with classical dialogues. The present volume thus serves
                (at least) two purposes: first, the author, Alberto Rigolio provides a basic
                introduction to sixty Christian dialogue texts preserved in Greek and Syriac, many
                of which are little-known works, and second, Rigolio demonstrates time and again the
                ways that these late ancient dialogues show awareness of and/or influence by
                classical dialogues.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">In format, the volume Christians in Conversation is essentially a
                handbook for Christian dialogue texts in Greek and Syriac, with a single
                introductory chapter followed by the “guide” with sixty distinct entries for the
                dialogue texts being introduced. In the introduction, the author deftly covers a
                range of topics pertinent to the volume’s structure and content. First, Rigolio
                provides justification for the linguistic and chronological boundaries that
                determine which dialogue texts have been included. The volume is limited to Greek
                and Syriac. Rigolio notes that Latin dialogues have already been treated
                    systematically<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="H BR Footnote"> P.
                        L. Schmidt, “Zur Typologie und Literarisierung des frühchristlichen
                        lateinischen Dialogs,” in Al. Cameron, ed., <anchor xml:id="Hlk125009351"
                            /><hi rend="italic">Christianisme et formes littéraires de l’Antiquité
                            Tardive en Occident</hi> (Geneva, 1977), 109-190.</p></note> whereas
                Greek and Syriac dialogues “remain in greater need of systematic work” (3). The
                chronological scope of the volume begins with the earliest extant Christian dialogue
                texts of the second century and extends up to the beginning of the seventh century.
                Rigolio justifies this cutoff point by noting various developments in the dialogue
                genre that took place over the course of the seventh century that would have made
                the present work more complicated. Among these developments are the advent of
                Christian-Muslim dialogues, which likely would have required the volume to expand
                into Arabic and perhaps Coptic sources as well. Additionally, there are a number of
                Syriac dialogue poems of unknown composition date that would have needed to be
                included if the range had been extended beyond 600 CE. So, this chronological
                framework was likely a wise editorial decision for the scope of the volume. Indeed,
                Rigolio notes that this is largely an artificial chronological division, which
                should not “overemphasize conventional divides” (3). Otherwise, Rigolio provides
                justification for the exclusion of short dialogues that are inserted within
                otherwise narrative texts, and texts that are more properly described as “Question
                and Answer” format (<hi rend="italic">erotapokrisis</hi>) rather than dialogue.
                Rigolio addresses this distinction at some length (pp. 22–24).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Throughout the remainder of the introduction, Rigolio surveys
                previous literature on the dialogue genre for both classical and late antique
                Christian literature. The author is—again, wisely—reluctant to propose a formal
                typology of what constitutes a “dialogue” based on the various tropes and
                characteristics shared across the genre. Nevertheless, he has provided a detailed
                list in table format (pp. 34–36) of the various formal features that are common to
                dialogues, noting which texts discussed in the volume include each feature.
                Ultimately, Rigolio makes an appeal—building on recent work by Averil Cameron, Kate
                Cooper, and Matthew Dal Santo—for late ancient Christian dialogues to be read and
                understood as a natural development of—and not a radical departure from—classical
                dialogues. Indeed, as Rigolio contends, the dialogue genre did not disappear
                altogether after classical antiquity, but “emerged transformed and reinvigorated in
                the religiously diverse world of late antiquity” (36).</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The entries for the sixty dialogue texts featured in the guide
                follow a standardized format, though each entry varies in length, depending on the
                text. Some entries are quite short, such as no.  10, an anonymous fragmentary
                “Anti-Jewish Dialogue” which takes up less than a single page, while others require
                significantly more attention because of their complexity and/or history of
                scholarship. Methodius’ <hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi> (no. 13), by comparison,
                takes up roughly five and half pages. Each entry begins with a list of standardized
                data about the text: author, full title (generally provided in native
                language/script), original language, date of composition, edition(s), and modern
                translation(s). Following this list, most entries include two distinct sections: 1)
                summary and 2) discussion of scholarship. For many of the shorter entries, however,
                these two sections are combined under a single heading. Finally, each entry
                concludes with a short bibliography specific to the scholarship on that text.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">This volume is a welcome addition to scholarship on dialogues in
                Greek and Syriac. While the practical concerns of the chronological boundaries for
                the volume are certainly understandable, Syriac scholars in particular may wish that
                the artificial boundaries had allowed for the inclusion of at least some dialogue
                poems (<hi rend="italic">sogyātā</hi>), even if many of them are anonymous and
                difficult to date. Even without the <hi rend="italic">sogyātā</hi>, however, the
                present work provides a now standard reference work for those who wish to delve into
                the dialogue genre in both Greek and Syriac. Hopefully this volume will encourage
                even more scholarship on these important works.</p>
            <p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix" xml:lang="en">
            <p xml:lang="en"><hi rend="bold">Appendix: List of Syriac Works discussed
                    in the volume</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="H BR Footnote"
                        > In each case I have simply provided the name/title conventions employed by
                        Rigolio.</p></note></p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Readers of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> will likely be most
                interested in the Syriac texts discussed in the volume. Thus, for quick reference, I
                have created a list that provides the entry number and titles of the Syriac
                texts—that is, texts that were either composed in Syriac or for which the primary
                surviving witness is a Syriac translation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                        rend="H BR Footnote"> I have not included every single text that has a
                        Syriac witness in addition to a surviving Greek witness.</p></note>
            </p>
            <table rend="rules">
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Entry
                            Number</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Author
                            (if known)</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Text
                            title</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>?Hippolytus</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Chapters against Gaius</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>Philip Bardaisanite</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">The
                            Book of the Laws of the
                        Countries</hi> (also includes a discussion of Bardaisan’s lost dialogues)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell><hi>Anonymous</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Erostrophus</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>Gregory the Wonderworker</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Discourse of Saint Gregory the Great to Theopompus, on the
                            Impassibility of God</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>37</cell>
                    <cell>Theodotus of Ancyra</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Contra
                            Nestorium</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>38</cell>
                    <cell><hi>Nestorius</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Adversus Theopaschitas</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>39</cell>
                    <cell><hi>Nestorius</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Dialogue</hi> in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Bazaar of Heracleides</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>41</cell>
                    <cell>John of Apamea</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Six
                            Dialogues with Thomas</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>42</cell>
                    <cell>John of Apamea</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Four
                            Dialogues with Eusebius and Eutropius</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>43</cell>
                    <cell>John of Apamea</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Discourse on the Mystery of Baptism</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>48</cell>
                    <cell>Zacharias of Mytilene</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Life of
                            Severus</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>54</cell>
                    <cell>John bar Aphthonia</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Conversation with the Syrian Orthodox under Justinian</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>58</cell>
                    <cell>Paul of Nisibis</cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic"
                            >Conversation with Caesar</hi></cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
