<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Aaron M. Butts and Robin Darling Young, eds. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Syriac Christian Culture: Beginnings to Renaissance</hi> (Washington, DC:
                    Catholic University of America Press, 2021)</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename>Yuliya</forename>
                        <surname>Minets</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>University of Alabama</orgName>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
                    <name>James E. Walters</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="0.1"/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                <date>2023</date>
                <idno>Volume 26.2</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                            license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                            copyright.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv26n2brminets</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <author>Yuliya Minets</author>
                        <title level="a">Aaron M. Butts and Robin Darling Young, eds. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Syriac Christian Culture: Beginnings to Renaissance</hi> (Washington, DC:
                            Catholic University of America Press, 2021)</title>
                        <idno type="URI"/>
                        <!-- Insert Syriaca bibl URI when available -->
                        <idno type="PDF"
                            >https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol26/HV26N2BRMinets.pdf</idno>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                            <date>2023</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope type="vol" n="26">26</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp" from="568" to="572">568-572</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="order" n="8"/>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                    of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                    Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                    best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords xml:lang="en">
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="Published">
            <change when="2024-01-20">File created by James E. Walters</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="review">
        <body>
            
            <head>Aaron M. Butts and Robin Darling Young, eds. <hi rend="italic"
                >Syriac Christian Culture: Beginnings to Renaissance</hi> (Washington, DC:
                Catholic University of America Press, 2021). Pp. xii + 354; $75.00.</head>
      
            
            <p xml:lang="en">The edited volume <hi rend="italic">Syriac Christian
                Culture: Beginnings to Renaissance</hi> is a carefully organized and beautifully
                published collection of articles on various aspects of Syriac Christianity that
                offers valuable updates on the <hi rend="italic">status artis</hi> of the academic
                field. The volume contains thirteen chapters, organized into five thematic sections,
                that originate from the Seventh North American Syriac Symposium, held at the
                Catholic University of America in 2015. It represents a selection of papers with a
                shared goal to explore “<hi rend="italic">texts</hi> as sources and especially
                literary texts.” This theme –
                <hi rend="italic">Ad fontes, </hi>“to the sources” – remains
                the unifying principle of the thematically and methodologically diverse chapters
                covering various periods, authors, genres, and research tools and ranging from case
                studies to surveys and project overviews. The thematic sections exemplify the main
                foci of the volume. Individual articles within a section complement each other,
                while often offering different perspectives on the same issue. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The first section, <hi rend="italic">Aphrahaṭ and Ephrem: From
                Context to Reception</hi>, includes five articles. In “Making Ephrem One of Us,”
                Joseph Amar explores how the figure of Ephrem and his legacy have been reshaped and
                repurposed over the centuries, from the fifth- and sixth-century monastic writers
                and hagiographers to the inventors of the <hi rend="italic">Ephraem Graecus</hi>
                corpus, to seventeenth-century Vatican scholars, to modern editors and beyond. Above
                this, the article seeks to recover the historical Ephrem from the layers of later
                literary and scholarly interpretations and to speak about him on his own terms. If
                anything, the chapter is a cautionary tale against an attempt to force “a complex,
                multi-faceted creative genius” into a manageable mold and to make a deep and
                intentionally ambiguous thinker fit a certain agenda. Such an attempt would
                unavoidably tell more about us than about Ephrem, and “in the process, we do not
                simply cut Ephrem down to size; we cut him down to our own size.” Next, Blake
                Hartung in “The Significance of Astronomical and Calendrical Theories for Ephrem’s
                Interpretation of the Three Days of Jesus’ Death” zooms into a specific issue in
                this writer’s legacy, namely, Ephrem’s solution to the so-called three-day problem,
                the time between Jesus’ death and resurrection. Comparing his views with other early
                Christian authors and contextualizing them within the late antique calendar and
                astronomical knowledge, Hartung highlights the unique aspects of Ephrem’s chronology
                meant to emphasize “the fundamental agreement between scripture and nature.” He also
                argues that some of Ephrem’s compositions, such as the hymn <hi rend="italic">De
                    crucifixione</hi> analyzed here, better fit educational, rather than liturgical
                settings. The next article by J. Edward Walters, “Reconsidering the Compositional
                Unity of Aphrahaṭ’s <hi rend="italic">Demonstrations</hi>,” is an intriguing study
                that challenges our understanding of the authorship, structure, and editorial
                history of this collection. Upon reconsidering previously known evidence, Walters
                examines newly discovered manuscript passages that suggest that the <hi
                    rend="italic">Demonstrations</hi> in its current form is a result of later
                editing and that an earlier collection of texts was in circulation before the sixth
                century; moreover, the long-neglected attribution to Jacob of Nisibis may not be so
                outlandish after all. The section closes with a chapter by Erin Galgay Walsh on
                “From Sketches to Portraits: The Canaanite Woman within Late Antique Syriac Poetry.”
                She explores the evolution of this female image in the poetry of such theologically
                distinct authors as Ephrem, Narsai, and Jacob of Sarugh.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The second thematic block, <hi rend="italic">Translation</hi>,
                opens with Yury Arzhanov’s study “The Syriac Reception of Plato’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Republic</hi>.” Arzhanov demonstrates that Syriac writers were often familiar
                with (pseudo-)Platonic ideas not via original dialogues, but rather through
                summaries and pseudepigrapha mediated by Church authorities that provide a very
                special image of <hi rend="italic">Plato Christianus</hi>. The next chapter by Craig
                Morrison, titled “Did the Dying Jacob Gather His Feet into His Bed (MT) or Stretch
                Them Out (Peshiṭta)? Describing the Unique Character of the Peshiṭta,” explores
                unusual readings attested in the Peshiṭta that cannot be explained by traditional
                categories (“faithful” vs. “idiomatic” translations). He compares Hebrew, Aramaic,
                and Greek versions of Genesis 49 to gain insight into the social and intellectual
                milieu in which the Syriac translation appeared as well as the character of the
                original Hebrew passage.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">Two articles of the next section, <hi rend="italic"
                >Hagiography: Formation and Transmission</hi>, focus on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Persian Martyr Acts</hi>. While Adam Becker’s contribution (“The Invention of
                the <hi rend="italic">Persian Martyr Acts</hi>”) offers a valuable overview of the
                diverse origins, typology, manuscript history, and reception of various textual
                subgroups within the collection, Simcha Gross takes a deep dive into one of those
                texts and demonstrates its literary, rather than historical, background by pointing
                to an earlier Western source that underwent a multi-stage reworking process in Greek
                and Syriac (“The Sources of the <hi rend="italic">History of ʿAbdā damšiḥā</hi>: The
                Creation of a <hi rend="italic">Persian Martyr Act</hi>”). Similarly, Reyhan Durmaz
                explores the transmission of a fifth-century Syriac hagiographical text – on the
                journey of Bishop Paul and the priest John of Edessa to Himyar – into the Islamic
                literary tradition (“Stories, Saints, and Sanctity between Christianity and Islam:
                The Conversion of Najrān to Christianity in the <hi rend="italic">Sīra of
                    Muhammad</hi>”). She argues that the accompanying transformations bear witness
                to different Christian and Muslim visions of asceticism, sanctity, and religious
                communities. </p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The section <hi rend="italic">Christians in the Islamic
                World</hi> contains four articles: Thomas A. Carlson introduces a new integrated
                platform, the Historical Index of the Medieval Middle East (HIMME), which can
                facilitate and enrich the study of the complex multilingual environment of the
                region (“Syriac in the Polyglot Medieval Middle East: Digital Tools and the
                Dissemination of Scholarship Across Linguistic Boundaries”); Maria Conterno outlines
                the avenues for the future study of the early Christian Arabic historiographical
                tradition, a topic long awaiting a special monograph (“Christian Arabic
                Historiography at the Crossroads between the Byzantine, the Syriac, and the Islamic
                Traditions”); Zachary Ugolnik analyzes the spiritual program of John of Dalyatha, an
                eight-century East Syriac theologian, and his ideas about visuality, hierarchical
                revelations, and reflections of divine glory in human and angelic nature (“Seeing to
                be Seen: Mirrors and Angels in John of Dalyatha”). The final article of this
                section, “On Sources for the Social and Cultural History of Christians during the
                Syriac Renaissance” by Dorothea Weltecke, is a broad and very helpful survey for
                everyone working on the period of the eleventh to thirteenth century. Regardless of
                the cultural implications of the “renaissance” as a concept, the period invites a
                number of questions about sources of political and religious authority, social
                structures, milieus and networks, forms of cultural preservation, change, and
                synthesis. The author explores various groups of sources for the study of social and
                cultural history, including epigraphy, archaeology, art history, intellectual prose,
                and legal materials.</p>
            <p xml:lang="en">The volume ends with an epilogue, “Syriac Studies in the
                Contemporary Academy” by Kristian Heal, which fills the need for self-reflection on
                the current state of the academic field, proposing to focus on three tasks: editing
                and translating Syriac texts, producing
                <hi style="font-size:11pt">larger </hi>scholarly
                interpretations, and promoting the area among the wider public. The book is an
                important milestone in current Syriac scholarship.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
