<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Prayer and Spirituality in the Early Church: A Conference Exploring the Development of Christianity in the Ancient World Centre for Early Christian Studies, Australian Catholic University July 10-13, 2002</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>George A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kiraz</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>Vol. 5, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv5n1fcmorgan</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author/>
                  <title level="a">Prayer and Spirituality in the Early Church: A Conference Exploring the Development of Christianity in the Ancient World Centre for Early Christian Studies, Australian Catholic University July 10-13, 2002</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol5/HV5N1FCMorgan.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2002</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="5">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Conference</term>
               <term>Early Church</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="announcement">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>[ <ref target="HV5N1FCMorgan.pdf">PDF
    Version</ref> ]</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    Centre for Early Christian Studies at Australian Catholic
    University is pleased to announce the third of its triennial
    "Prayer and Spirituality in the Early Church" conferences,
    scheduled for 10th-13th July, 2002.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] These
    conferences provide an exciting opportunity for engagement by
    both scholars and lay people with an important and fascinating
    period of history, exploring the rise and development of
    Christianity in an ancient context. The conferences focus
    specifically on aspects of the temporal and spiritual concern
    of the Early Church and their expression in private and public
    prayer, liturgy, art, music, and the life of early Christians
    generally. With their concern to cultivate a vivified presence
    of this formative period for our own time, they are of interest
    to theologians, liturgists, historians, and biblical scholars;
    to scholars and students of spirituality, asceticism and
    monasticism; as well as to all who have even a general interest
    in this period of history and thought.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] This
    upcoming conference, entitled "Liturgy and Life", will also be
    the first of its series to host an "Inter-faith Seminar". This
    will examine the interaction and interrelationship between the
    faiths of Judaism, Christianity and Islam in the context of
    their earliest encounters.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] To find
    out more about this exciting and important upcoming event,
    please go to the Centre for Early Christian Studies website,
    <ref target="http://www.acu.edu.au/Earlychr">http://www.acu.edu.au/Earlychr</ref>. Follow the links
    through "Conferences" and then click on the icon for "Liturgy
    and Life". Access to registration forms and all other
    information concerning the conference can be found there.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] For
    other information, please contact the conference convenors via
    e-mail or postage to the addresses below:<lb/>
    Prayer and Spirituality Conference Convenor<lb/>
    c/o Centre for Early Christian Studies<lb/>
    Australian Catholic University<lb/>
    St. Patrick's Campus<lb/>
    Locked Bag 4115, Fitzroy 3065<lb/>
    Victoria AUSTRALIA<lb/>
            <lb/>
    E-mail: prayerspirit@patrick.acu.edu.au<lb/>
    Telephone: + 61 3 9953 3141<lb/>
    Fax: + 61 3 9953 3765<lb/>
         </p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>