<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Syriac Writings and Turkic Language according to Central Asian Tombstone Inscriptions †</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Wassilios</forename>
                  <surname>Klein</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>Vol. 5, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv5n2klein</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Wassilios KLEIN</author>
                  <title level="a">Syriac Writings and Turkic Language according to Central Asian Tombstone Inscriptions †</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol5/HV5N2Klein.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2002</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="5">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="order" n="5"/>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Syriac</term>
               <term>Turkic</term>
               <term>Tomb Inscriptions</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="article">
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>This paper presents the characteristics and
    pecularities in the Syriac tombstone inscriptions found near
    the Kirghiz capital Bishkek and nearby Tokmak. After a brief
    note on the use of Syriac as an ecclesiastical language amongst
    Turkic communities, the paper proceeds to show how those who
    erected the inscriptions were not familiar with Syriac, and
    then discusses forms of the letters used in the
    inscriptions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->



         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein3">1. Introduction</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] This
    paper presents the characteristics of Syriac writing based on
    Central Asian tombstone. The study is not a philologist one;
    rather, it aims at presenting some of the pecularities in the
    said tombstone inscriptions, from the standpoint of research
    into the history of religion.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Over 100
    years ago, around 600 tombstones were found near the Kirghiz
    capital Bishkek and nearby Tokmak, and they were edited very
    promptly by Daniil A. Chwolson.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Paper presented at the Conference of the
    American Oriental Society 2001 in Toronto/Canada.
         </p>
                </note> This was followed by further
    finds in the former Mongolian administrative town of Almalyk in
    the Kazakh-Chinese border area and from the Kirghiz Issyk-Kul,
    but these were individual items. During the Soviet period,
    Cetin Džumagulov published many newly-discovered
    inscriptions.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             His most important publications are: Ч.
    Джумагулов,
    Эпиграфика
    Киргиз ии,
    выпуск 1-3,
    Фрунзе 1963, 1982, 1987
    (Академия
    наук
    Киргизской
    ССР,
    Институт
    языка и
    литературы).
    
         </p>
                </note> Recent finds of around 40 tombstones on Kirghiz
    territory show clearly that the actual Christian center, with a
    large cemetery, was at Bishkek, whereas the second cemetery of
    Burana, near Tokmak, yielded relatively modest finds<note place="foot" xml:id="FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Cf. Wassilios Klein, <hi rend="italic">Das nestorianische
    Christentum an den Handelswegen durch Kyrgyzstan bis zum 14.
    Jh.</hi>, Turnhout 2000 (Silk Road Studies 3), and: Wassilios
    Klein, Christliche Reliefgrabsteine des 14. Jahrhunderts von
    der Seidenstraße, Ergänzungen zu einer
    alttürkischen und zwei syrischen Inschriften sowie eine
    bildliche Darstellung, in: <hi rend="italic">VI Symposium Syriacum</hi> 1992,
    University of Cambridge, Faculty of Divinity 30 August –
    2 September 1992, hrsg. v. René Lavenant, Rom 1994
    (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 247), 419-442; Wassilios Klein,
    Nestorianische Inschriften in Kirgizistan: Ein
    Situationsbericht, in: <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum VII</hi>, Uppsala
    University, Department of Asian and African Languages, 11
    – 14 August 1996, edited by René Lavenant, S. J.,
    Roma 1998 (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 256), 661-669.
    
         </p>
                </note> All these
    tombstones can be dated from circa 1250 to 1342, in Almalyk up
    to the 1370s.<lb/>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein4">2. Syriac as an ecclesiastical language in Turkic
    communities</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Apart
    from the St.-Petersburg scholars Daniil Chwolson and Wilhelm
    Radloff, it was primarily the Marburg-based ecclesiastical
    historian Wolfgang Hage who examined the relationship between
    local vernacular languages and the Syriac of the church in the
    'Nestorian' mission to Asia.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Wolfgang Hage, Einheimische Volkssprachen und
    syrische Kirchensprache in der nestorianischen Asienmission,
    in: <hi rend="italic">Erkenntnisse und Meinungen, Festschrift für Werner
    Strothmann zum 70</hi>. Geburtstag, Bd. 2, hrsg. v. Gernot
    Wießner, Wiesbaden 1978 (Göttinger Orientforschungen
    1. Reihe: Syriaca, Bd. 17), 131-160. 
         </p>
                </note> Their observations tally almost
    completely with my own. I would like to draw your attention to
    a few characteristic points:</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Together
    with Christianity and the Syriac language, Syrian proper names
    were also brought to Central Asia. A large number of Turkic
    proper names were retained, but they were supplemented with
    Syrian names. So in addition to biblical names such as
    <hi rend="italic">Abrāhām</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Marqōs</hi>, those of
    popular saints such as <hi rend="italic">Gīwargīs</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">Sargīs</hi>, and those of theologians who were important
    to Syrian Christianity, such as <hi rend="italic">Nestōrīs</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">Dī<hi rend="u">d</hi>ōrōs</hi>, we also
    find original Syrian theophore names, such as
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">A<hi rend="u">b</hi>dīšō<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi> (servant of
    Jesus), <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">H</hi>nānīšō<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi> (mercy
    of Jesus), <hi rend="italic">Sabrīšō<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi> (trust
    in Jesus), and finally also names that had their origins in the
    life of the Church, such as <hi rend="italic">Yaldā</hi> (birth),
    <hi rend="italic">Den<hi rend="u">h</hi>ā</hi> (epiphany),
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">S</hi>aumā</hi> (fast),
    <hi rend="italic">Qyāmā</hi> (m.) and <hi rend="italic">Qyāmtā</hi> (f.)
    (resurrection), <hi rend="italic">Šlī<hi rend="u">h</hi>ā</hi> (apostle), etc.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 141-143.
    
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Titles
    were preserved in the form in which the Syrians brought them.
    Examples are those of the metropolitan, archdeacon,
    <hi rend="italic">chorepiskopos</hi>, periodeut and visitator, and of the
    priest and other clergy. We also find Syriac words in Turkic
    inscriptions, such as <hi rend="italic">mhaymnā</hi> "believer" and
    <hi rend="italic">qabrā</hi> "grave".<note place="foot" xml:id="FN6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 
    144-145. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] Syriac
    greeting formulae, such as "bless, my Lord" or "the Cross is
    victorious", were according to Grīgōr bar
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Ebrāyā also used by Mongols in the Far
    East, so that they may also have been used by the Turkic people
    of Kirghizstan, although there is no concrete evidence for
    this.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN7" n="7">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 
    145-146 according to Gregorius Barhebraeus, Historia
    dynastarum, in: F. Risch, J. de Plano Carpini, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
    der Mongolen</hi>, Leipzig 1930 (Veröffentlichungen des
    Forschungs-Instituts für Vergleichende Religionsgeschichte
    an der Universtität Leipzig 2, 11), 329. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Among
    the Syrian traditions adopted in the tombstone inscriptions was
    the form of the cross. There was a large variety of
    forms,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN8" n="8">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Cf. Wolfgang Hage, Crosses with Epigraphs in
    Medieval Central and East Asian Christianity, in: <hi rend="italic">The
    Harp</hi> 8/9 (1995-1996), 375-382. 
         </p>
                </note> and these were sometimes combined with regional
    symbols such as a Zoroastrian altar or, further towards the
    Chinese East, the lotus flower.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN9" n="9">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, <hi rend="italic">Reliefgrabsteine</hi> (footn. 3), 425-431.
    
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] The
    dating of the tombstone inscriptions, which is so important to
    us, is fortunately not restricted to the Turkic dating system
    according to the twelve-year animal cycle, but also includes
    the Seleucid era, which was used by the Syrian Christians. It
    is this that makes it possible for us to establish precise
    dates for the tombstones and thereby the history of the
    communities. It is striking that only the Turkic-language
    tombstones add the information that it is the era of Alexander,
    and that the inscriptions on Chinese territory generally do not
    include this dating and the resulting association with
    Syria.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 
    146-147 and Klein, Das nestorianische Christentum (footn. 3),
    278-283. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] If
    Syriac dominates the tombstone inscriptions, then it follows
    that it must have played a substantial role as a liturgical
    language. And indeed, the Franciscan traveler Wilhelm of Rubruk
    repeatedly testifies to this being the case in the 13th
    century.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] More
    astonishing is the fact that Wilhelm of Rubruk had a letter
    from King Louis IX of France to the Mongol khan Sartaq
    translated not only into Arabic, but also into Syriac.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN11" n="11">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Wilhelm von Rubruk, <hi rend="italic">Reisen zum
    Großkhan der Mongolen, Von Konstantinopel nach Karakorum
    1253-1255</hi>, Neu bearbeitet und hrsg. v. Hans D. Leicht,
    Stuttgart 1984 (Alte abenteuerliche Reiseberichte), 78-79.
    
         </p>
                </note> He
    must therefore have assumed that Syriac had a certain amount of
    importance as a lingua franca. Whether or not he was right,
    however, is questionable, when we consider that even a figure
    such as the <hi rend="italic">catholikos</hi> Yahballāhā III, an
    Öngüt Turk from Koshang, had no knowledge of Syriac
    at the time of his election.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN12" n="12">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">Gregorii Barhebraei chronicon
    ecclesiasticum, quod ediderunt</hi>, Latinitate donarunt J. B.
    Abbeloos et Th. J. Lamy, vol. 3, Paris und Löwen 1877,
    col. 453-454. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein5">3. Lack of familiarity with the Syriac language of
    the inscriptions</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] That
    neither the stonemasons nor the people who commissioned the
    inscriptions were native speakers of Syriac is clear from a
    large number of peculiarities in the grammar as used in the
    Syriac inscriptions. The Syriac language of the inscriptions is
    decidedly clumsy and, even in the most frequently recurring
    formulae, it does not correspond to the Syriac feeling for
    language, as the following examples illustrate:</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] The
    compound dates should have been joined together using
    <hi rend="italic">waw</hi>. However, this is usually missing. For example, we
    see simply: <hi style="font-size: 12.0pt;">
               <hi rend="italic">bašnat
    ālp še<hi rend="u">t</hi>mā
    tlātīn <hi rend="u">h</hi>
               </hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ad</hi>
    "in the year one thousand six hundred and thirty-one".<note place="foot" xml:id="FN13" n="13">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, Das nestorianische Christentum
    (footn. 3), tombstone 41, 176. 
         </p>
                </note> Only
    rarely are the numbers in the correct gender, a category which
    is foreign to the Turkic languages. We find in the literature
    the opinion that instead of the usual
    <hi rend="italic">tre<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">sar</hi>"twelve", we often
    find <hi rend="italic">trēn <hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">esar</hi>, written
    using separate words, and instead of <hi rend="italic">ma''</hi> (with two
    <hi rend="italic">alaphs</hi>)"one hundred" we often see only <hi rend="italic">m'ā</hi>
    (with one <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi>), which contravenes only historical
    spelling, while the pronunciation <hi rend="italic">mā</hi> remains
    unchanged.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN14" n="14">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 151,
    153-154. 
         </p>
                </note> We must say that the last example and others
    occur often in manuscripts and are very common.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN15" n="15">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus</hi>, ed. by R. Payne
    Smith, vol. 2, Oxford 1901 (reprints Hildesheim), col. 1985.
    
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] Some
    account was taken of gender when specifying the sex of the
    deceased person, but only in a somewhat peculiar way. The
    phrase "this is the grave of N. N.", which recurs on almost
    every tombstone, is modified in such a way that the
    introductory demonstrative pronoun does not, as one might
    expect, refer as a copula to the masculine word for "grave",
    together with a following enclitic personal pronoun, but is
    varied according to the sex of the person buried. The only
    correct usage in this context is <hi rend="italic">hānaw qabreh</hi>,
    which is indeed used only for boys and men. For women and
    girls, on the other hand, the incorrect <hi rend="italic">hd'hy/hdy/hdhy</hi>
    (for <hi rend="italic">hādāy) qabrāh</hi> is generally
    used.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN16" n="16">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4),
    149-151. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Immediately after this formula comes the proper name. According
    to the rules, this should be introduced by the prefix <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.
    However, this is usually missing: <hi rend="italic">hānau qabreh
    arslān</hi>  "this is the grave of Arslan".<note place="foot" xml:id="FN17" n="17">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, Das nestorianische Christentum
    (footn. 3), tombstone 41, 176. Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi>
    (footn. 4), 150-151. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] The
    prepositions <hi rend="italic">b, l,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>al</hi> are
    occasionally missing. The concluding formula
    <hi rend="italic">l<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ālmīn</hi> "for ever", for
    example, occurs without the preposition <hi rend="italic">l</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN18" n="18">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4),
    151-152. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] The
    orthography leaves a great deal to be desired, so that in some
    cases it is impossible to work out the correct pronunciation
    without knowledge of the word in question. Thus we sometimes
    find the very frequent and therefore well-known word
    <hi rend="italic">mhaymnā</hi> "the believer" in the forms <hi rend="italic">mhymny'</hi>
    and <hi rend="italic">myhymn'</hi> extended by a <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi> in the wrong
    place. Letters are exchanged, as in <hi rend="italic">g'ywt'</hi>
    ( <hi rend="italic">gayūtā</hi> "glory"), which
    becomes <hi rend="italic">g'wyt'</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN19" n="19">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 152.
    
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    Occasionally the orthography suffers not only from lack of
    knowledge, but also from the influence of a Turkic feeling for
    language. Double consonants in initial position have as far as
    possible been avoided. An example of this are the forms
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>ylt'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>ylyt'</hi> for the correct <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>lyt'</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>elaytā</hi> "girl". That the dentals
    <hi rend="u">
               <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">eth</hi> and <hi rend="italic">taw</hi> have
    sometimes been confused is evidenced<note place="foot" xml:id="FN20" n="20">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">A Compendious Syriac Dictionary founded
    upon the Thesaurus Syriacus</hi> of R. Payne Smith, ed. by 
    J. Payne Smith, Oxford 1903 (reprint from 1985), 170 and 608.
    
         </p>
                </note> in the following
    example: <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>wrk'yt</hi> instead of
    <hi rend="italic">twrk'yt</hi> (<hi rend="u">
               <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ūrkāyi<hi rend="u">t</hi>
            </hi> "Turkish"). The same also occurs with the
    gutturals <hi rend="italic">gamal</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kaph</hi>. For example, we
    find  <hi rend="italic">kmyr'</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">gmyr'</hi>
    (<hi rend="italic">gmīrā</hi> "perfect").<note place="foot" xml:id="FN21" n="21">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4), 153.
    
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] It
    was not at all uncommon to follow the actual pronunciation,
    rather than the historical orthography. Examples of this are
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">s</hi>lyw'</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">s</hi>lyb'</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">s</hi>lībā</hi> cross) and also the word
    <hi rend="italic">qabrāh</hi> "her grave", which appears on almost every
    tombstone, and in the form <hi rend="italic">qwrh</hi> is orthographically
    incorrect, but accurately represents the phonetic spellings of
    Eastern Syriac.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN22" n="22">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Volkssprachen</hi> (footn. 4),
    153-154. 
         </p>
                </note> This also occurs in Syriac manuscripts.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein6">4. The use of Syriac script for Turkic
    inscriptions</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] The
    use of the Syriac script leads to difficulties because not all
    Turkic phonemes were covered by a corresponding symbol in the
    Syriac alphabet. There were two approaches to solving this
    problem, which I shall demonstrate using a specific example of
    an inscription from the Mongol residence town of Almalyk. The
    Mongol residence of the Chagatai ulus, Almalig, founded as late
    as the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, is situated to the East of the
    Chu Valley, in the valley of the upper Ili. The few tombstones
    found there are divided into Turkic and Syriac. In their
    external form they appear - unlike the tombstones of the Chu
    Valley - to have preferred the low relief technique. Apart from
    this, they are very similar to the Chu Valley tombstones. The
    first point I would like to mention is that the text is written
    vertically, as was already the norm on Syriac-language
    tombstones.</p>
         <quote>
            <p>
               <graphic url="HV5N2Klein19.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="307px" height="177px"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Transcription:</hi>
               <lb/>
      aleksandros qan sakïš<lb/>
      mi<hi rend="gr">g</hi> altï yüz
      yitmiš<lb/>
      toquz ärti bicin yïl<lb/>
      qutlunŋ tärim quštanc<lb/>
      ärtdi käcdi bu yirtüncü-<lb/>
      tin atï yat bolsun amïn<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Translation:<lb/>
               </hi> According to the computing of
      Alexander Khan it was<lb/>
      one thousand six hundred and seventy-nine (= 1368 AD),<lb/>
      that is the year of the monkey:<lb/>
      the grace-endowed Tärim Kuštanč<lb/>
      went across [and] departed this world.<lb/>
      May her name be remembered. Amen.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, Christliche Reliefgrabsteine (footn.
    2), 431-437. 
         </p>
                    </note>
            </p>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] The
    available characters were used for similar sounds, just as we
    do today when we want to transcribe foreign words using, for
    example, the symbols available on the 7-bit ASCII code. The
    Turkic front vowel ä was represented at the beginning of
    the second word in the third line by  <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi>.
    However, the same sound is also written in this and in one
    other inscription<note place="foot" xml:id="FN24" n="24">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">С. Е.
    Малов,
    Памятники
    древнетюркской
    письменности
    Монголии
    и
    Киргизии,
    Москва 1959
    (Академия
    Наук СССР,
    Институт
    языкознания),</hi>
    78 f. in connection with fig. 22. 
         </p>
                </note> as <hi rend="italic">alaph</hi> (e.g. second word in
    the fourth line, first word in the fifth line). No distinction
    was made between the Turkic sounds i and ï, normally
    distinguished as front and back; both were written as
    <hi rend="italic">yodh</hi>. In Turkic vowel harmony, the distinction between
    the front vowel ü and the back vowel u is also important,
    but for these, together with the sound o, our inscription has
    only one letter, the <hi rend="italic">waw</hi>. Among the consonants, it is
    striking that the soft g [gamma]<hi> </hi> is not
    necessarily written as <hi rend="italic">gamal</hi>, but rather as
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>ayn</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN25" n="25">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             More examples: <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">Ч.
    Джумагулов,
    Язык
    сиро-тюркских
    (несторианских)
    памятников
    Киргизии,
    Фрунзе 1971
    (Академия
    Киргизской
    ССР, Отдел
    востоковедения),
    122; П. К.
    Коковцовъ,
    Кь
    сиро-турецкой
    эпиграфик</hi>
    á <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">Семир</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicChurchSlavonicTimesSSi;">á</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">чья</hi>,
    in: <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">Извест</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicChurchSlavonicTimesSSi;">Ý</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">я
    Императорской
    академ</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicChurchSlavonicTimesSSi;">Ý</hi>
            <hi style="font-family:CyrillicRoman;">и
    наукъ,
    Санкт-Петербург
    1909, 773-796</hi> and plate, here <hi style="font-family:CyrillicChurchSlavonicTimesSSi">778.</hi>
            
         </p>
                </note> The same applies to the soft b,
    which is written as <hi rend="italic">pe</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">beth</hi>. Finally,
    there is nothing in Syriac that corresponds to the Turkic sound
    č. It was written using the otherwise rare <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">s</hi>adhe</hi>, which was apparently felt to sound
    similar. The Turkic word for monkey, <hi rend="italic">bičin</hi> (third
    line), was therefore written <hi rend="italic">p<hi rend="u">s</hi>yn</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] For
    an additional guttural, a special symbol was created based on
    the Syriac <hi rend="italic">k</hi> and supplemented by a diacritic check-mark.
    The result was a letter that is so similar to the Arabic
    <hi rend="italic">kāf</hi> that it could lead to confusion, but unlike the
    latter, which has a final form, it can occur in any position in
    the word and can also connect both to the left and to the
    right. The letter was used for a sound that corresponded to
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>
            </hi>, for example in the word
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>an</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] If I
    have lamented the inadequate orthography of the Syriac, we
    should not draw any far-reaching conclusions about lack of
    knowledge of the language on the part of the authors of the
    tombstone inscriptions. This is because it emerges that the
    orthography of the Turkic parts of these inscriptions is no
    better. Instead of the correct <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>byšk'n</hi> (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>avïškan</hi>i. e. <hi rend="italic">hare</hi>), the
    <hi rend="italic">k</hi> is simply omitted: <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>byš'n</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN26" n="26">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Hage, <hi rend="italic">Einheimische Volkssprachen</hi>
    (footn. 5), 152. 
         </p>
                </note> The stonemasons were here
    as elsewhere illiterate, uneducated people. So we should not
    draw too many conclusions about the education of their
    customers.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein7">5. The forms of the letters</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] The
    letters used on the tombstones basically follow the Estrangelo
    script. However, there are already small changes, so that
    Chwolson speaks of the "<hi rend="italic">transition from Estrangelo to the
    modern Nestorian script</hi>".<note place="foot" xml:id="FN27" n="27">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Chwolson, <hi rend="italic">Grabinschriften</hi> 1890
    (footn. 1), 119. 
         </p>
                </note> If we look at the table of
    characters put together so carefully by Julius Euting,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN28" n="28">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             In Chwolson, <hi rend="italic">Grabinschriften</hi> 1890
    (footn. 1), appendix; abridged version: Theodor Nöldeke,
    <hi rend="italic">Kurzgefasste Syrische Grammatik</hi>, Anhang: Die
    handschriftlichen Ergänzungen in dem Handexemplar Theodor
    Nöldekes und Register der Belegstellen bearbeitet von
    Anton Schall, Darmstadt 1977, appendix. 
         </p>
                </note> which
    is still useful given the lack of a Syriac paleography, we
    notice several changes.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN29" n="29">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, Reliefgrabsteine, (footn. 3),
    433-434. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] The
    tombstone inscriptions show a tendency to connect to the left
    letters that according to the rules of orthography should under
    no circumstances be connected to the left, for example the
    <hi rend="italic">waw</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25] A
    second innovation is the use of ligature for <hi rend="italic">taw-alaph</hi>,
    which was to become the norm in the Nestorian script, but is
    new in Estrangelo.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26] In
    addition, a new letter form emerges for the Alaf. In the second
    line of the above inscription, the second letter of the second
    word is very difficult to read because its form deviates from
    the usual <hi rend="italic">’alaph</hi>. The high line slanting towards
    the right is also common in other inscriptions, but the small
    check-mark underneath usually goes towards the right from the
    bottom of the vertical line, or crosses the vertical line. Here
    it runs upwards towards the left, so that the letter takes the
    form of a check-mark (√). Since no other letter has a
    similar form, it cannot have been confused with anything else.
    Euting's table of characters simply needs to be supplemented.
    The unusual form is somewhat confusing, because the usual form
    is also used in our inscription (second word of the fifth line,
    third word of the sixth line, fifth word of the sixth
    line).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27] The
    <hi rend="italic">rish</hi> is written twice without a diacritic point and can
    then hardly be deciphered, because it is easily confused with
    <hi rend="italic">daleh, zayn, yodh,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">nun</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28] The
    above short inscription of six lines has already shown that we
    can by no means speak of orthographical consistency. Of course,
    we cannot expect an orthography in the sense of a normalized
    spelling system, but surely we can expect the representation of
    each phoneme by the same character each time. This is not the
    case either here or in other Turkic texts, and it does not
    exactly make it easier to decipher these inscriptions,
    particularly as they are not in general carefully chiseled,
    and, as in the Syriac, plene spelling of the vowels, or any
    other vowel indication, is not usual.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein8">6. The Turkic inscriptions from China<note place="foot" xml:id="FN30" n="30">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Klein, Das nestorianische Christentum
    (footn. 3), 218-225. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29]
    These comments have related to Central Asia and the specific
    local characteristics. Every region has its own peculiarities,
    and for this reason we should be very careful about drawing
    generalized conclusions. In order at least to have mentioned
    this area briefly, and at the same time to draw attention to
    gaps in the research that have yet to be filled, I would like
    to direct our eye further towards to the East, to China. Unlike
    the Christians of the Chu Valley, their Öngüt Turkic
    fellow-believers on the Huanghe and in other parts of China all
    formulated their inscriptions in Turkic. The external form of
    the tombstones from Olon Sume-in Tor in the Ordos area, the
    Huanghe curve, where the Christian Öngüt owned a
    kingdom dependent on the Mongols, is also completely different.
    The tombstones from this region are not unhewn rocks from the
    riverbed, but monoliths in the form of sarcophagi.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN31" n="31">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Desmond Martin, Preliminary Report on
    Nestorian Remains North of Kuei-hua, Suiyüan, in:
    <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Serica</hi> 3 (1938) (Reprint New York 1970),
    232-249 and plates V-XIV, here 246 fig. 3. 
         </p>
                </note> They
    have short inscriptions on top. The cross shapes represented
    differ from those of the Chu in that they include fewer
    decorations in the form of precious stones, and instead are
    often based on the lotus flower. The inscriptions are extremely
    short and follow the simple scheme: <hi rend="italic">"Bu quwra ...</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">
               <hi style="font-family:&#34;Times New Roman&#34;;">nïŋ</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ol"</hi> (this is the grave of ...). No date is given. There
    are numerous and often very long Turkic-language inscriptions
    in Syriac script from the South Chinese port of Quanzhou,
    formerly Zaitun. In addition to the sarcophagus form known from
    the Öngüts, Zaitun has another form: tombstones that
    resemble altars. By far the majority of these inscriptions,
    already collected by our Chinese colleague Yang Qin Zhan, have
    not yet been edited, although they include particularly
    interesting bi- and tri-lingual inscriptions that have Syriac,
    Chinese and Latin in addition to the Turkic main text. In any
    case, they are of a completely different character to the
    Central Asian tombstones, and still need to be studied and
    evaluated by turkologists to a degree that is worthy of their
    significance. Texts in Turkic written in Syriac script have
    also been found at Bulayïq and Qurutqa,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN32" n="32">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             P. Zieme, Zu den
    nestorianisch-türkischen Turfantexten, in: <hi rend="italic">Sprache,
    Geschichte und Kultur der altaischen Völker</hi>,
    Protokollband der XII. Tagung der Permanent International
    Altaistic Conference 1969 in Berlin, Hrsg. v. Georg Hazai u.
    Peter Zieme, Berlin 1974 (Schriften zur Geschichte und Kultur
    des Alten Orients 5), 661-668, here 665-668. 
         </p>
                </note> but here we leave
    the stone inscriptions.</p>
         <p> </p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Klein9">Notes</head>
         
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> D. Chwolson, <hi rend="italic">Syrisch-Nestorianische
    Grabinschriften aus Semiretschie</hi>, Nebst einer Beilage:
    "Über das türkische Sprachmaterial dieser
    Grabinschriften von W. Radloff, mit drei phototypischen Tafeln
    und einer ebensolchen, von Julius Euting ausgearbeiteten
    Schrifttafel, St.-Pétersbourg 1890 (Mémoires des
    l´Académie Impériale des Sciences de
    St.-Pétersbourg, VIIe série, Tome XXXVII, No. 8);
    D. Chwolson, <hi rend="italic">Syrisch Nestorianische Grabinschriften aus
    Semiretschie</hi>, Neue Folge, St.-Pétersbourg
    1897.<ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>