<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Dispute between the Cherub and the Thief</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>Vol. 5, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv5n2brock</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Sebastian P. BROCK</author>
                  <title level="a">The Dispute between the Cherub and the Thief</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol5/HV5N2Brock.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2002</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="5">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="order" n="3"/>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>dispute/dialogue poems</term>
               <term>soghyatha</term>
               <term>Repentant Thief</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="article">
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>The lively verse dialogue between the
    Repentant Thief (Luke 23:43) and the Cherub guarding the
    entrance to Paradise (Genesis 3:24) is an excellent
    representative of the ancient literary genre of dispute
    literature that has remained popular in the Middle East in
    various languages for nearly four millennia. The aim of the
    present article is to make the poem available in translation to
    an English-speaking audience. The introduction gives an outline
    of the poem's wider context, and ends with some suggestions
    about how it might be revived for use today.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>




         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->

         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock3">An ancient Mesopotamian genre</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] One of
    the most long-lived literary genres of the Middle East is the
    Precedence Disputation, the oldest examples of which go back to
    Sumerian literature of the early second millennium
    BC.   The thread of continuity, over nearly four
    thousand years, can be traced through Akkadian, Middle Persian,
    Jewish Aramaic, Syriac, Arabic and Persian,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Overviews can be found in G.J. Reinink and H.L.J.
    Vanstiphout (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dispute Poems and Dialogues in the
    Ancient and Mediaeval Near East</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia
    Analecta 42;  Leuven, 1991);  R. Murray, "Aramaic and
    Syriac dispute poems and their connections", in M.J. Geller,
    J.C. Greenfield and M.P. Weitzman (eds),  <hi rend="italic">Studia
    Aramaica</hi> (Journal of Semitic Studies, Supplement 4; 
    1995), 157-87;   S.P. Brock, “The Dispute
    Poem:  from Sumer to Syriac”, <hi rend="italic">Journal of the
    Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 1 (2001), 1-10.
    
         </p>
                </note> right up to the
    present day when examples in Modern Syriac and in Modern Arabic
    have been collected.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Modern Syriac:  e.g. L. Yaure, “A poem
    in the Neo-Aramaic dialect of Urmia”, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near
    Eastern Studies</hi> 16 (1957), 73-87 (Samovar and Boys); 
    Modern Arabic:  e.g. C.D. Holes, “The rat and the
    ship’s captain”, <hi rend="italic">Studia Orientalia</hi> 75
    (1995), 101-20. 
         </p>
                </note> Among Syriac authors, it was Ephrem who, in
    the mid fourth century AD, first adapted this ancient literary
    genre to a Christian context, with a series of Precedence
    Disputes between Death and Satan, where each argues that he has
    the greater control over human beings.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">Carmina Nisibena</hi> LII-LIV;  English
    translation of  LII in S.P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Harp of the
    Spirit:  Eighteen Poems of Saint Ephrem</hi> (Studies
    Supplementary to Sobornost, 4;  1983), 70-72. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Although
    these formalized Precedence Disputes may be in either prose or
    verse, the vast majority of the Syriac examples are in verse,
    following a regular structure;  this consists of a short
    introduction, followed by the dispute or argument between two
    persons speaking in alternate stanzas, and ending with a brief
    conclusion (or sometimes, doxology).    The
    verse structure employed is that of the <hi rend="italic">soghitha</hi>, with
    short stanzas consisting of four isosyllabic lines;  very
    frequently the central dialogue has an alphabetic acrostic.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock4">The Syriac dialogue poems</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    great majority of the Syriac dispute and dialogue poems deal
    with biblical subjects, though there are a few on secular
    topics.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             A list is given in S.P. Brock, “Syriac
    dispute poems:  the various types”, in Reinink and
    Vanstiphout, <hi rend="italic">Dispute Poems and Dialogues,</hi> 109-19
    (reprinted in <hi rend="italic">From Ephrem to Romanos</hi> (Aldershot,
    1999), chap. VII (and Addenda, 4-5). 
         </p>
                </note> In those that take their starting point in an
    episode in the Bible, the dispute element is usually more in
    the form of an argument, and this, while presented in a lively
    (and sometimes humorous) manner, may at the same time convey
    some underlying teaching of a more profound
    nature.    It is not known what the exact
    context, liturgical or other, Ephrem had in mind for his
    Disputes between Death and Satan, but subsequently these
    dialogue <hi rend="italic">soghyatha</hi> came to be written and used for the
    Night Office (<hi rend="italic">Lelya</hi>/<hi rend="italic">Lilyo</hi>).   In
    the extant liturgical manuscripts the dialogue
    <hi rend="italic">soghyatha</hi> are mainly grouped around the
    Nativity-Epiphany and Holy Week.    The poems
    tend to be preserved in their complete form only in the
    earliest manuscripts, dating from the ninth to the twelfth
    century;  in manuscripts of a later date the poems are
    often either abbreviated or with alternate stanzas only (thus
    giving only one speaker's verses);  in the latter case,
    the manuscript was specifically intended for use by just one of
    two choirs.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    dialogue <hi rend="italic">soghyatha</hi> have unfortunately not fared well
    in the various printed editions of the West Syriac Fenqitho and
    East Syriac Hudra:  those that do feature are usually
    either in a very truncated form, or give just alternate
    verses;  only very rarely do they preserve the text
    complete.   As it happens, the Dialogue between the
    Cherub and the Thief, translated below, happens not to feature
    in any printed liturgical edition known to me, despite the fact
    that it has an extensive manuscript tradition and translations
    into Modern Syriac, indicating its continuing popularity over
    the centuries.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock5">The Cherub and the Thief</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Like
    many of the Dialogue <hi rend="italic">soghyatha</hi>, that between the
    Cherub and the Thief takes as its starting point a single
    biblical verse, namely Luke 23:43, where Christ tells the Thief
    who acknowledges him, "Today you shall be with me in
    Paradise".</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    unknown author, who probably belongs to the fifth century, sets
    the scene of the poem at the gates of Paradise, where the Thief
    encounters the Cherub<note place="foot" xml:id="FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Whereas the Hebrew and Septuagint have the plural,
    Cherubim, the Peshitta has the singular. 
         </p>
                </note> who has been given the task of guarding the
    entrance of Paradise against anyone from the banished human
    race who might try to approach (Genesis
    3:24).    The lively argument between the two
    continues until the Thief finally produces the key to
    Paradise—the cross—that he bears.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    Dispute between the Cherub and the Thief is to be found in
    numerous liturgical manuscripts of both the Syrian Orthodox
    Church and of the Church of the East, as well as in three
    Modern Syriac versions.   The Syriac text (based on
    an East Syriac manuscript) was first published by E. Sachau in
    1896, and this has been recently republished, along with the
    three Modern Syriac versions (one of which Sachau had also
    published), in an excellent and attractive volume entitled
    <hi rend="italic">Il ladrone e il cherubino</hi>.  <hi rend="italic">Dramma liturgico
    cristiano orientale in siriaco e neoaramaico</hi>, by Fabrizio
    Pennacchietti.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Torino, 1993.   On the cover will be
    found a reproduction of a medieval illustration of the topic
    (for this, see J.Leroy, “La sogitha du cherubin et du
    larron, source d’une miniature du manuscrit syriaque BM
    Add.7169”, <hi rend="italic">Parole de l’Orient</hi> 6/7
    (1975/6), 413-19. 
         </p>
                </note>  Another edition of the poem, this time
    based on much earlier Syrian Orthodox manuscripts, is included
    in my <hi rend="italic">Sughyotho Mgabbyotho</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="FN7" n="7">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Monastery of St Ephrem, Holland, 1982 (it features
    as no. 13, pp.61-5);  for the contents and sources of this
    collection of 26 pieces, see “Syriac  dialogue
    poems: marginalia to a recent edition”, <hi rend="italic">Le
    Muséon</hi> 97 (1984), 29-58. 
         </p>
                </note> an English translation of
    this was subsequently published in India,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN8" n="8">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             
            <hi rend="italic">Sogiatha</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Syriac Dialogue
    Hymns</hi> (Syrian Churches Series XI;  Kottayam, 1987),
    28-35.   There is also a French translation by F.
    Graffin, in <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien</hi> 12 (1967), 481-90.
    
         </p>
                </note>and it is basically
    the same translation which is republished
    below.    The differences between the East and
    West Syriac texts of the poem are not great, as will be seen
    from the list of more important differences given below, after
    the translation.   Although the West Syriac
    manuscripts are very considerably older than the East Syriac
    ones, it is likely that the latter sometimes preserve the
    original text (thus, for example, at 33b "He put on a body", in
    the East Syriac manuscripts, preserves the early Syriac
    metaphor for the incarnation which later Syrian Orthodox
    tradition tended to abandon).<note place="foot" xml:id="FN9" n="9">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             The East Syriac recension may also be original at
    3d, 18d, 25c, 28c, 33a  and 50c. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock6">Some other treatments of the theme</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] The
    <hi rend="italic">soghitha</hi> may well have been known to Jacob of Serugh
    (d. 521), one of whose verse homilies is on the same
    subject;  attention is drawn to the main parallels in the
    brief commentary which follows the translation.  
    After a long prologue (pp. 658-666), Jacob's <hi rend="italic">memra</hi>
    provides the following speeches:  Thief to Christ (pp.
    666-668), Christ to the Thief (pp. 668-669); these are followed
    by a narrative, and then the Cherub and the Thief are given
    alternating speeches:  Cherub to Thief:  pp. 671-672,
    673-673, 675, 676-677, 680-681, 684-685;  and Thief to
    Cherub:  pp. 672-673, 674-675, 675-676, 677-680, 681-683,
    685-687.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Jacob's
    older contemporary, Narsai, by contrast, does not provide any
    homily on this subject.   In Greek literature of the
    period there are occasional vague parallels, where the Cherub
    is introduced, but a sustained dialogue between the Cherub and
    the Thief is very rare, and is best attested in the second half
    of a Greek text attributed to John Chrysostom (<hi rend="italic">Clavis</hi>
            <hi rend="italic">Patrum</hi> 
            <hi rend="italic">Graecorum</hi> 4877), published by M. van
    Esbroeck, together with  early Georgian and Arabic
    translations.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             “Homélie
    éphrémienne sur le bon Larron en grec,
    géorgien et arabe”, <hi rend="italic">Analecta Bollandiana</hi>
    101 (1983), 327-62. 
         </p>
                </note>   The few parallels between this
    text and the <hi rend="italic">Soghitha</hi> are noted in the Commentary
    below.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock7">The dramatic potential and a suggestion for
    today</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] It
    would seem that it is only with this particular dialogue poem
    that the dramatic potential of the genre was exploited, with
    the poem being acted out in a stylised form of liturgical
    drama. A description of this, belonging to the early
    twentieth century, can be found in W.A.Wigram's <hi rend="italic">The
    Assyrians and their Neighbours</hi>:<note place="foot" xml:id="FN11" n="11">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             London, 1929, p.198. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <quote>
      ...the boy to whom it has been given to 'act the Penitent
      Thief' for that year, storms the sanctuary <hi rend="italic">vi et
      armis</hi>, and is driven back again and again by the blazing
      torches held by the deacons, who for the nonce represent the
      Cherubim that guarded Paradise with the flaming sword. 
      At last the Penitent Thief secures the cross that lies always
      on a table at the entrance of the sanctuary - and which each
      worshipper kisses on entering the church - and comes forward
      brandishing that passport to bliss.   Then the
      deacon-angels receive him, and - seeing that souls are always
      borne by angels into Paradise, and also that no unordained
      man my set foot in the sanctuary, the boy is carried
      pick-a-back into the 'Altar-enclosure'.
    </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] In a
    modern context both this, and the other dialogue poems on
    biblical topics would seem to offer excellent material for
    catechetical use, above all with children.   Here it
    is worth mentioning that the Dialogue between John the Baptist
    and Jesus (based on Matthew 3:14) was performed (in English
    translation, of course!) in England a few years ago at a school
    for children with learning disabilities. For use of this
    sort in church schools, the English translation could, if
    thought necessary, be abbreviated and/or adapted;  indeed,
    there is no reason why the dialogue might not be imaginatively
    rewritten, simply taking elements from here and there in the
    original Syriac poems.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] It
    is not only with children that these lively dialogue poems
    deserve to be brought back into life again, for they could also
    well be used to good effect set to music once again - either
    employing their traditional <hi rend="italic">qole</hi> (the most commonly
    found is ‘<hi rend="italic">Amo w-'amme</hi>), or to new musical
    settings.  It would seem that here is a wonderful
    opportunity for the various Suryoyo <hi rend="italic">gude</hi>, or musical
    groups, to draw creatively on this their splendid heritage,
    whose roots lie in ancient Mesopotamia.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock8">Text</head>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV5N2BrockFig01.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="500px" height="650px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV5N2BrockFig02.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="500px" height="650px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV5N2BrockFig03.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="500px" height="650px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV5N2BrockFig04.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="500px" height="650px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV5N2BrockFig05.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="500px" height="650px"/>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock9">Translation</head>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">1.</hi> At the Crucifixion I beheld a
    marvel<lb/>
    when the Thief cried out to our Lord,<lb/>
    "Remember me, Lord, on the day when You come<lb/>
    to that Kingdom which does not pass away". [Luke 23:43]</p>
         <p>REFRAIN<lb/>
    Praise to You, Lord, for at Your coming<lb/>
    sinners turned back from their wickedness;<lb/>
    they entered and found shelter<lb/>
    in the Garden of Eden - which is the holy Church.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">2.</hi> He made a petition, stretched
    out and gave it<lb/>
    to the crucified King, asking for mercy;<lb/>
    and He who is full of mercy heard his cry<lb/>
    and opened the door to his request.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">3.</hi> "Remember me, Lord", was what
    he cried out on the cross,<lb/>
    "in that Kingdom which does not pass away, [Luke 23:43]<lb/>
    and in that glory in which You will be revealed<lb/>
    may I behold Your rest, seeing that I have acknowledged You".
    [cp Luke 12:8]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">4.</hi> Our Lord replied, "Since you
    have acknowledged me<lb/>
    this very day you shall be in the Garden of Eden;<lb/>
    in very truth, man, you will not be kept back<lb/>
    from that Kingdom to which you are looking.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">5.</hi> "Take with you the cross as a
    sign, and be off:<lb/>
    it is a great key whereby the mighty gate<lb/>
    of that Garden shall be opened,<lb/>
    and Adam, who has been expelled, shall enter again". [Gen.
    3:24]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">6.</hi> The word of our Lord was
    sealed<lb/>
    like a royal missive from the palace;<lb/>
    it was handed over to the thief<lb/>
    who took it and made off for the Garden of Eden.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">7.</hi> The Cherub heard him and rushed
    up,<lb/>
    he grabbed the Thief at the gate,<lb/>
    stopping him with the sharp blade that he held.<lb/>
    All astonished, he addressed him as follows:</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">8.</hi> CHERUB "Tell me, my man, who
    has sent you?<lb/>
    What is it you want, and how did you get here?<lb/>
    What is the reason that brought you here?<lb/>
    Reveal and explain to me who it is who has sent you".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">9.</hi> THIEF "I will tell you who has
    sent me,<lb/>
    just hold back your blade and listen to my words.<lb/>
    I am a thief, but I supplicated for mercy,<lb/>
    and it was your Lord who sent me on my way here".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">10.</hi> CHERUB "By what powerful means
    did your arrival take place?<lb/>
    Who brought you to this dread spot?<lb/>
    Who transported you across the sea of fire<lb/>
    so that you could enter Eden? Who is it who sent you?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">11.</hi> THIEF "It was through the
    power of the Son, who sent me,<lb/>
    that I crossed over and came here without hindrance.<lb/>
    Through Him I subdued all powers<lb/>
    and I have come to enter here, seeing that He has given me
    confidence".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">12.</hi> CHERUB "You are indeed a
    thief, just as you have said,<lb/>
    but you can't steal into this region of ours:<lb/>
    it is fenced in with the sword that guards it. [Gen.
    3:24]<lb/>
    Turn back, my man, you have lost your way".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">13.</hi> THIEF "I was indeed a thief,
    but I have changed:<lb/>
    it was not to steal that I have come here.<lb/>
    Look, I've got with me the key to Eden,<lb/>
    to open it up and enter: I will not be prevented".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">14.</hi> CHERUB "Our region is awesome
    and cannot be trodden,<lb/>
    for fire is its indomitable wall;<lb/>
    the blade flashes out all around it.<lb/>
    How is it you have made so bold as to come here?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">15.</hi> THIEF "Your region is indeed
    awesome, just as you have said,<lb/>
    - but only until our Lord mounted the cross,<lb/>
    when He transfixed the sword of all suffering<lb/>
    so that your blade no longer kills".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">16.</hi> CHERUB "Ever since the time
    that Adam left<lb/>
    I haven't ever seen anyone turn up here;<lb/>
    your race has been banished from the Garden;<lb/>
    you shall not enter it, so don't argue any more".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">17.</hi> THIEF "Ever since the time
    that Adam left<lb/>
    your Lord has been angered at our race,<lb/>
    but now He is reconciled and has opened up the gate. [Rom.
    5:10; Eph. 2:16]<lb/>
    It is to no purpose that you are standing here".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">18.</hi> CHERUB "You should realize
    that it isn't possible<lb/>
    for an unclean man to enter in here<lb/>
    - and you are a murderer, and a shedder of blood.<lb/>
    Who is it who has brought you to this pure place?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">19.</hi> THIEF "You should realize that
    such is the wish<lb/>
    of Him who makes the unclean clean, who was crucified together
    with me;<lb/>
    with the blood from His side He has washed me completely clean.
    [John 19:34]<lb/>
    It was He who has sent me to Paradise".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">20.</hi> CHERUB "Be off with you, man,
    and don't argue any further,<lb/>
    for this is what I have been ordered:<lb/>
    to guard from your race, by means of the sword,<lb/>
    the Tree of Life that is to be found in here". [Gen. 3:22]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">21.</hi> THIEF "Be off with you, angel;
    you should learn and see<lb/>
    that I've left behind, hanging on Golgotha,<lb/>
    that very Fruit of Salvation that's in your garden<lb/>
    - so that our race may now enter without any hindrance".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">22.</hi> CHERUB "Eve and Adam fell into
    debt and wrote out<lb/>
    a document that will not be erased: [Col. 2:14]<lb/>
    they went out of here under sentence<lb/>
    to live in low estate in the land of thorns". [Gen. 3:18]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">23.</hi> THIEF "The debt is repaid.
    Just listen, O Cherub:<lb/>
    the document has now been transfixed on the cross; [Col.
    2:14]<lb/>
    by means of both blood and water your Lord has wiped it
    out,<lb/>
    and pinned it there with nails so that it won't be
    exacted".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">24.</hi> CHERUB "Adam was driven out
    from this Garden<lb/>
    and there is no way he can enter here again,<lb/>
    for the sword's blade is revolving<lb/>
    and he'll encounter it should he come near".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">25.</hi> THIEF "He who was driven out
    has returned to his father's house,<lb/>
    for the great Shepherd has gone out and found [John
    10:11]<lb/>
    that sheep that had left the Garden;<lb/>
    carrying him on His shoulders, He has escorted him back". [Luke
    15:5]</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">26.</hi> CHERUB "It is something
    totally novel that I've seen today:<lb/>
    a path leading back into the Garden.<lb/>
    But here are Adam's footprints, take a look:<lb/>
    he has left here and not returned again".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">27.</hi> THIEF "Jesus your Lord has
    performed a novel deed,<lb/>
    for now He has released Adam who had been confined;<lb/>
    He has raised up whole crowds from inside Sheol, [Matt.
    27:52]<lb/>
    and they have sent me in advance, to open up for them".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">28.</hi> CHERUB "I am the cherub: how
    is it you have transgressed<lb/>
    against my office of guarding, with which I've been
    entrusted?<lb/>
    A fiery being like me cannot be vanquished,<lb/>
    but as for you, an offspring of Adam, how bold you are!"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">29.</hi> THIEF "I am your companion and
    we have but a single Lord<lb/>
    in common for both of us;<lb/>
    His authority is much higher than either yours or mine,<lb/>
    and so I've no fear, seeing that it was He who has sent
    me".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">30.</hi> CHERUB "You simply cannot
    enter in here,<lb/>
    for it is a resplendent place that no one can tread:<lb/>
    the Shekhina is escorted around inside it,<lb/>
    and the sword of fire is guarding it".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">31.</hi> THIEF "You cannot hold anyone
    back,<lb/>
    for the sword is not blunted and made dull.<lb/>
    The cross has opened up the Garden of Eden;<lb/>
    there's no means by which it can still be kept closed".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">32.</hi> CHERUB "Haven't you heard from
    the Bible<lb/>
    how the cherub and the sword go round<lb/>
    guarding the way to the Garden of Eden,<lb/>
    so that none of Adam's offspring can enter here?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">33.</hi> THIEF "Haven't you heard from
    the Revelation<lb/>
    that your Lord has come down and become man,<lb/>
    thus reconciling Adam, who was in a state of anger,<lb/>
    bringing back to Eden the one who had been driven out?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">34.</hi> CHERUB "The sign of the
    revolving sword<lb/>
    that guards the Tree of Life<lb/>
    frightened off Adam when he was driven out,<lb/>
    so how is it that you're not afraid?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">35.</hi> THIEF "The sign of your Lord
    is with me,<lb/>
    and by it the sharp sword is blunted;<lb/>
    but it too is the sentence remitted,<lb/>
    and by it, Adam, once expelled, shall return".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">36.</hi> CHERUB "The ranks of fire are
    standing here,<lb/>
    thousands of them in bands innumerable;<lb/>
    the multitudes are awesome, and quite simply<lb/>
    you can't travel on any further and enter among them".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">37.</hi> THIEF "The multitudinous ranks
    of which you've told me<lb/>
    are themselves in awe as they look upon the Cross:<lb/>
    the sign of the Son inspires them with awe<lb/>
    and they worship before it, while me they hold in honour".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">38.</hi> CHERUB "The sign of my Lord is
    upon the Chariot, [Is. 66:15]<lb/>
    resplendent upon the Throne, but from us it is hidden, [Ezek.
    1:26-7]<lb/>
    so how is that you—as you are claiming—<lb/>
    carry this sign of His and escort it?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">39.</hi> THIEF "His sign is upon the
    Chariot above,<lb/>
    but look, His Cross is on Golgotha below,<lb/>
    and with His own blood He has written a new missive<lb/>
    permitting Adam to come back into the Garden".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">40.</hi> CHERUB "O agent in blood, who
    has brought you here?<lb/>
    Who is it has sent you, a murderer?<lb/>
    The sword is drawn, and if you make bold<lb/>
    the blade will flash out against you".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">41.</hi> THIEF "O agent for the King,
    don't be upset;<lb/>
    your authority is repealed, for your Lord has willed it
    so.<lb/>
    It is His cross that I've brought to you as a sign:<lb/>
    look and see if it's genuine, and don't be so angry".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">42.</hi> CHERUB "This Cross of the Son
    which you've brought to me<lb/>
    is something I dare not look upon at all.<lb/>
    It is both genuine and awesome; no longer will you be
    debarred<lb/>
    from entering Eden, seeing that He has so willed it".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">43.</hi> THIEF "The Cross of your Lord
    has breached the fence [Eph. 2:14]<lb/>
    that had been built up between us and you,<lb/>
    Anger has passed away and peace has come,<lb/>
    and the path to Eden is no longer cut off".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">44.</hi> CHERUB "He who was slain has
    sent to me and testified with His own blood<lb/>
    that I should let go of the blame which I've been
    wielding.<lb/>
    Fearful is this sign which you have brought me;<lb/>
    enter in, O heir; I will not turn you back".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">45.</hi> THIEF "Resurrection has
    occurred for the race of humankind<lb/>
    that had been thrust out of their home.<lb/>
    You cherubim and angels, rejoice with us, [cp Luke 15:10]<lb/>
    for we have returned now to your city".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">46.</hi> CHERUB "Great is the
    compassion that has been shown to you,<lb/>
    the descendants of Adam who sinned and thus died.<lb/>
    Enter, thief, you will not be kept back,<lb/>
    for the gate is now open for those who repent".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">47.</hi> THIEF "Great and most glorious
    is the compassion of my Lord,<lb/>
    for His mercy has effected and His love has constrained
    Him.<lb/>
    Rejoice with us, O spiritual beings,<lb/>
    for we have been mingled into your race".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">48.</hi> CHERUB "The Gentle One has
    held back from your race [Matt.11:29]<lb/>
    the blade and the sword that I have been wielding.<lb/>
    Outcasts who have returned, have no fear,<lb/>
    enter inside the Garden with exultation".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">49.</hi> THIEF "Praise be in Eden that
    is now at peace,<lb/>
    peace on earth which has been liberated.<lb/>
    Blessed is the Crucified One who has reconciled us<lb/>
    so that we shall not longer be deprived of your race".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">50.</hi> Thanks be to You, O Lord of
    all,<lb/>
    who have brought back Adam who had been driven out,<lb/>
    while to the thief who asked for mercy<lb/>
    You opened up the gate that had been closed.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="pNum">51.</hi> Thanks be to You, at whose
    word<lb/>
    the thief entered into the Garden of Eden,<lb/>
    and there was good hope for Adam again<lb/>
    and he returned to the place from which he had gone out.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] The
    following are the main variants in the East Syriac manuscript
    tradition (edited by Sachau and Pennacchietti):</p>
         <p>3:b       ..when you will be
    revealed.<lb/>
    c        ..you will
    come.<lb/>
    d        (May I see) Your
    compassion.</p>
         <p>8:d  (explain to me) who you are.</p>
         <p>9:a        ..who are
    questioning me.</p>
         <p>17:a  ...Adam sinned.</p>
         <p>18:d  to the place of the upright.</p>
         <p>24:a  Your race (was driven out...)</p>
         <p>25:b  the Good Shepherd<lb/>
    c  that had strayed from the flock.</p>
         <p>27:c  ..raised up the dead.<lb/>
    d  and He has sent me.</p>
         <p>28:c  (A fiery being) I am who..</p>
         <p>30:b  for this place may not be trodden.</p>
         <p>33:a  seen<lb/>
    b  and put on a body.<lb/>
    c  who had been driven out.<lb/>
    d  who had been in a state of anger.</p>
         <p>34:a  The fire and the...</p>
         <p>36:d  and pass through among them.</p>
         <p>38:b  seated upon..</p>
         <p>39:a  His radiance..</p>
         <p>40:cd  (transposed).</p>
         <p>42:a  of Jesus.<lb/>
    d  come and enter Eden.</p>
         <p>43:1  of the Son.</p>
         <p>44:d  I will not make bold;  enter in, O heir.</p>
         <p>45:d  we have arrive at.</p>
         <p>46:d  for those who enter in.</p>
         <p>47:b  His love willed it.<lb/>
    d  to your assembly.</p>
         <p>48:a  The Cross..</p>
         <p>49:d  ...your ranks.</p>
         <p>50:c  in (the person of) the thief.</p>
         <p>51:d  who returned.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock10">Commentary</head>
         <p>Abbreviation:  JS = P. Bedjan, <hi rend="italic">Homiliae Selectae
    Mar</hi>-<hi rend="italic">Jacobi Sarugensis</hi>, V (Paris/Leipzig, 1910),
    cited by page and line (other volumes of JS are cited by page
    alone).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">1c</hi> cp JS 666:11, 15;  668:18.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">2ab</hi> cp JS 666:19-20, "He (the Thief) sought from Him
    mercy, that He would have compassion on him in the
    Kingdom;  /  he made supplication that was full of
    suffering to present to Him".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">2d</hi> cp JS 666:22, "Open up the door of mercy to me so
    that I may enter the fair place".  And 668:21, "He opened
    up the great door of mercy before his petition".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">3d</hi> cp JS 668:5, "I have acknowledged You".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">4c</hi> cp JS 668:22-669:1, "Verily, verily I say to you,
    consider as true, O man, / that today you will rejoice with me
    in the Kingdom".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">5b</hi> For the Cross as a "key", see already Ephrem,
    Hymns on the Resurrection II:1;  in Jacob, cp JS 669:10,
    670:15, 674:3 (also in his Letters, ed. Olinder, 3:19-20).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">6ab</hi> For "royal missive" (<hi rend="italic">saqra</hi> = Latin
    <hi rend="italic">sacra</hi>), cp JS 669:20-21, and especially 670:4, "with
    His living name He would seal the royal missive
    (<hi rend="italic">saqra</hi>) for the thief on the right hand".  
    Though not yet found in Ephrem, the term <hi rend="italic">saqra</hi> is
    later frequently used to denote messages from the heavenly
    world to earth, above all in the context of the
    Annunciation.  That it was a letter from Christ which the
    Thief took with him is a theme found in a few Greek sources,
    notably Romanos' Kontakion on the Adoration of the Cross (ed.
    Maas-Trypanis, no 23), stanzas 10-11 (where the Thief tells the
    Cherub that he has with him a letter (<hi rend="italic">gramma</hi>) with
    Christ's seal on it;  likewise in the Greek text
    attributed to John Chrysostom, edited by van Esbroeck, Thief
    tells the Cherub that "Christ has written for me a letter
    (<hi rend="italic">epistolen</hi>)" (section 8).   In the Cave of
    Treasures 51:23 (ed. S-M.Ri),  Christ wrote with his own
    blood a <hi rend="italic">saqra</hi> of Adam's return and sent it by the
    hands of the Thief. </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">7d</hi> cp JS 671:2, "The Cherub met him and stood there
    in amazement to question him".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">8a</hi> cp JS 671:3-4, "Tell me, man, who are you? 
    Where are you from? / How did you come over the awesome path of
    flame?"</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">9c</hi> cp JS 673:1, "I am a thief who used to go about
    with hateful deeds".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">10c</hi> For "sea of fire", cp JS 670:18, 671:12,
    673:21.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">12c</hi> Behind the term "fenced" (<hi rend="italic">sig</hi>), lies an
    allusion to the "fence" (<hi rend="italic">syaga</hi>) of Eph. 2:14, "He has
    broken down the fence of hostility".  Syriac writers
    regularly understand this verse as referring to the "fence"
    keeping humanity out of Paradise, subsequent to the
    Fall);  thus already Ephrem, Madrashe on Paradise II.7,
    IV.1 etc;  cp JS 686:20, "He has broken down the fence,
    and so your standing here is redundant".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">13a</hi> cp JS 674:11, "I was a thief, but mercy captured
    me from (my) hateful deeds".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">14bcd</hi> cp JS 674:4-5, "And there is a wall of fire and
    you cannot break through the partition;  / the blade of
    fire flares out and is fearful, and if you should be so
    bold...".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">17d</hi> cp JS 686:20, cited above, on <hi rend="bold">12c</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">19c</hi> cp JS 674:12, "I bathed and was scoured clean of
    the evils with which I was befouled".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">23b</hi> The Georgian and Arabic text edited by van
    Esbroeck also adduces Col. 2:4 (section 12;  not in his
    Greek text).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">25bcd</hi> The Georgian and Arabic text likewise
    introduces the theme of the lost sheep (section 12;  again
    absent from the Greek).</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">30c</hi> The term "Shekhina" (<hi rend="italic">shkinta</hi>), or Divine
    Presence, is quite common in Syriac poets from Ephrem (e.g.
    Madrashe on Paradise II.11) onwards.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">33b</hi> The East Syriac text, with "put on a body" almost
    certainly preserves the original reading here.   This
    archaic phraseology (already found in the Acts of Thomas,
    Aphrahat, Ephrem, and in the earliest Syriac translation of the
    Nicene Creed) was subsequently disapproved of by Philoxenus in
    the light of the Christological controversies;  it was
    accordingly avoided by many (but by no means all) Syrian
    Orthodox writers.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">36a</hi> For "The ranks of fire" (<hi rend="italic">sedray nura</hi>),
    cp JS 669:19.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">40a</hi> For "man of blood", cp JS 675:19 and 677:2.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">44d</hi> cp JS 669:18, "Tell those who are lost that Adam,
    the heir, has returned".</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">47b</hi> The phrase "His love has constrained Him" also
    occurs in the <hi rend="italic">Soghitha</hi> on Mary and the Angel (verse
    1b), and in a <hi rend="italic">Soghitha</hi> attributed to Ephrem
    (<hi rend="italic">Soghitha</hi> II.2 in E. Beck, <hi rend="italic">Hymni de
    Nativitate</hi>):  "The daughter of poor parents has
    become mother to the Rich One / whose love has thus constrained
    Him".  The same verb (‘<hi rend="italic">sa</hi>) also features a
    number of times in Jacob's <hi rend="italic">memre</hi> (e.g. I, 507; 
    II, 137),<note place="foot" xml:id="FN12" n="12">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Jacob normally prefers the verb
    <hi rend="italic">ngad</hi> (e.g. I, 609;  II, 349, 507 etc.). 
         </p>
                </note> although not in that on the Cherub and the
    Thief, where the nearest parallel is 686:18, “He became a
    Mediator and pacified His Father for His love so wished
    it”.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock11">Notes</head>
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N2Brock12">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Brock, S.P. “The Dispute
    Poem:  from Sumer to Syriac”, <hi rend="italic">Journal of the
    Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</hi> 1 (2001), 1-10.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">The Harp of the
    Spirit:  Eighteen Poems of Saint Ephrem</hi> (Studies
    Supplementary to Sobornost, 4;  1983), 70-72.</p>
         <p>—
    <hi rend="italic">Sogiatha</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Syriac Dialogue Hymns</hi> (Syrian
    Churches Series XI;  Kottayam, 1987), 28-35.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Sughyotho
    Mgabbyotho</hi>, (Monastery of St Ephrem, Holland, 1982), pp.
    61-5.</p>
         <p>— “Syriac dispute
    poems:  the various types”, in Reinink and
    Vanstiphout, <hi rend="italic">Dispute Poems and Dialogues,</hi> 109-19
    (reprinted in <hi rend="italic">From Ephrem to Romanos</hi> (Aldershot,
    1999), chap. VII (and Addenda, 4-5).</p>
         <p>— “Syriac  dialogue
    poems: marginalia to a recent edition”, <hi rend="italic">Le
    Muséon</hi> 97 (1984), 29-58.</p>
         <p>Graffin, F. "La soghitha du
    chérubin et du larron," <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien</hi>
    12 (1967), 481-90.</p>
         <p>Holes, C.D. “The rat and the
    ship’s captain”, <hi rend="italic">Studia Orientalia</hi> 75
    (1995), 101-20.</p>
         <p>Leroy, J. “La sogitha du
    cherubin et du larron, source d’une miniature du
    manuscrit syriaque BM Add.7169”, <hi rend="italic">Parole de
    l’Orient</hi> 6/7 (1975/6), 413-19.</p>
         <p>Murray, R. "Aramaic and Syriac
    dispute poems and their connections", in M.J. Geller, J.C.
    Greenfield and M.P. Weitzman (eds),  <hi rend="italic">Studia
    Aramaica</hi> (Journal of Semitic Studies, Supplement 4; 
    1995), 157-87.</p>
         <p>Pennacchietti, F. <hi rend="italic">Il ladrone e
    il cherubino</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Dramma liturgico cristiano
    orientale in siriaco e neoaramaico</hi>, (Torino: Zamorani,
    1993).</p>
         <p>Reinink, G.J. and H.L.J. Vanstiphout
    (eds), <hi rend="italic">Dispute Poems and Dialogues in the Ancient and
    Mediaeval Near East</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta
    42;  Leuven, 1991).</p>
         <p>Sachau, E. "Über die Poesie in
    der Volkssprache der Nestorianer", Sitzungsberichte der
    Königlich-Preussischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu
    Berlin XI.8 (1896), 179-215.</p>
         <p>van Esbroeck, M.
    “Homélie éphrémienne sur le bon
    Larron en grec, géorgien et arabe”, <hi rend="italic">Analecta
    Bollandiana</hi> 101 (1983), 327-62.</p>
         <p>Yaure, L. “A poem in the
    Neo-Aramaic dialect of Urmia”, <hi rend="italic">Journal of Near
    Eastern Studies</hi> 16 (1957), 73-87.</p>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <p/>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>