<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">“Exchanging Reed for Reed” Mapping Contemporary Heretics onto Biblical Jews in Ephrem’s Hymns on Faith†</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Christine C.</forename>
                  <surname>Shepardson</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>1500 Duke University Rd., Apt. B-3A</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>Vol. 5, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv5n1shepardson</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Christine C. SHEPARDSON</author>
                  <title level="a">“Exchanging Reed for Reed” Mapping Contemporary Heretics onto Biblical Jews in Ephrem’s Hymns on Faith†</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol5/HV5N1Shepardson.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2002</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="5">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Ephrem</term>
               <term>anti-Judaism</term>
               <term>Hymns on Faith</term>
               <term>Arians</term>
               <term>heretics</term>
               <term>Jews</term>
               <term>Syria</term>
               <term>fourth-century</term>
               <term>scripture</term>
               <term>Christian self-definition</term>
               <term>rhetoric</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> are
    among the most stridently and explicitly anti-Arian of
    Ephrem’s numerous polemical writings.  Written in
    the midst of the struggle for political and social authority
    that raged between Arian and Nicene Christians, these hymns
    include a complex collection of both anti-Arian and anti-Jewish
    language.  Close examination of these hymns will
    demonstrate that Ephrem repeatedly connects Christian
    ‘heretics’ with Jews by mapping his opponents onto
    negative caricatures of Jews in Christian scripture. 
    Focusing primarily on the comparison that Ephrem makes in Hymn
    87 between biblical Jews who crucified Christ and contemporary
    Christians who comparably threaten God’s son, I argue
    that Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric in these hymns should
    be read primarily in light of his struggle against local
    Christians rather than Jews.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->

         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson3">Introduction</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1]
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> are among the most
    stridently and explicitly anti-Arian of Ephrem’s numerous
    polemical writings.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Although there are significant problems inherent in
    using the term ‘Arian’, it is difficult to identify
    Ephrem’s opponents any more specifically.  See
    Sidney Griffith’s recent observations in S.H. Griffith,
    “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint Ephrem’s
    <hi rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies,</hi>” in <hi rend="italic">The Limits of
    Ancient Christianity: Essays on Late Antique Thought and
    Culture in Honor of R.A. Markus,</hi> ed. by W.E. Klingshirn and
    M. Vessey (Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan, 1999),
    97-114; and in S.H. Griffith, “Ephraem, the Deacon of
    Edessa, and the Church of the Empire,” in <hi rend="italic">Diakonia:
    Studies in Honor of Robert T. Meyer,</hi> ed. by T. Halton and
    J. Williman (D.C.: CUA, 1986), 22-52; as well as Paul
    Russell’s observations in  <hi rend="italic">St. Ephraem the Syrian
    and St. Gregory the Theologian Confront the Arians</hi> (Kerala,
    India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute, 1994). 
    In his detailed studies of Ephrem’s Hymns on Faith,
    Edmund Beck concluded that in these hymns Ephrem argues against
    ‘Arianism’: “The main theme in all eighty
    Hymns on Faith is the defense of the church’s teaching
    over and against the innovation of Arianism” (E. Beck,
    <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie des heiligen Ephraem in seinen Hymnen
    über den Glauben,</hi> SA 21 [Vatican City, 1949],
    62).  In fact, Beck elsewhere uses the nuances of his
    investigation to argue for a later date for the Hymns of Faith
    in comparison with the Sermons on Faith: “The composition
    of the Hymns on Faith can in my opinion be rather precisely
    given.  That we are in Ephrem’s Edessene period is
    betrayed by the inclusion of the person of the holy spirit in
    the Arian argument, which many of that time treat and which is
    lacking in the polemic against the Arians in the Sermons on
    Faith from the Nisibene period” (E. Beck, trans. <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr 155/74
    [Louvain, 1955], i).  While the general claim of
    Beck’s conclusions about the identity of Ephrem’s
    opponents remains, scholars have rightfully challenged modern
    uses of the terminology of ‘Arianism’ itself, since
    the term includes many distinct groups, each with their own
    theological tenets.  For relevant scholarship and
    bibliography, see R.P. Vaggione, <hi rend="italic">Eunomius of Cyzicus and the
    Nicene Revolution,</hi> (NY: OUP, 2000); R.C. Gregg and D.E.
    Groh, <hi rend="italic">Early Arianism: A View of Salvation,</hi>
    (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1981); M.R. Barnes and D.H.
    Williams, eds., <hi rend="italic">Arianism after Arius,</hi> (Edinburgh, 1993);
    R.P.C. Hanson, <hi rend="italic">The Search for the Christian Doctrine of God:
    The Arian Controversy 318-381,</hi> (Edinburgh, 1988); and J.T.
    Lienhard, “The ‘Arian’ Controversy: Some
    Categories Reconsidered” (<hi rend="italic">TS</hi> 48 [1987]),
    415-437.  With regard to Ephrem’s opponents, I use
    ‘Arian’ in contrast to ‘Nicene’
    Christianity to reflect the strongly subordinationist nature of
    their theology.  
         </p>
                </note> Written in Syria in the midst of the
    struggle for political and social authority that raged between
    Arian and Nicene Christians in the decades following the
    Council of Nicea, these hymns include a complex collection of
    both anti-Arian and anti-Jewish language.  While scholars
    have traditionally read Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric as
    complaints against local Jews and
    ‘Jewish-Christians’,<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             There is no reason to doubt that there were Jews
    living in both Nisibis and Edessa during Ephrem’s
    lifetime, and some of Ephrem’s writings do complain about
    local Jewish practices (see, for example, Cruc. 19-20 in Edmund
    Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Paschahymnen [de
    azymis, de crucifixione, de resurrectione],</hi> CSCO Syr 
    248/108 [Louvain, 1964]).  As a result, early scholars
    assumed that all of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric was a
    straightforward attack on contemporary Jews.  For
    examples, see Stanley Kazan, “Isaac of Antioch’s
    Homily against the Jews” (<hi rend="italic">OrChr</hi> 46 [1962]), 87-98;
    (47 [1963]), 89-97; (49 [1965]), 57-78; J.B. Morris, <hi rend="italic">Select
    Works of St. Ephrem the Syrian, Library of the Fathers,</hi>
    (Oxford, 1847), 396n; and E. Beck, <hi rend="italic">Ephraems Reden über
    den Glauben</hi> (Rome, 1953), 118-119; as well as later works
    that accept and echo the conclusions of these authors (e.g., R.
    Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early
    Syriac Tradition</hi> [Cambridge, 1975]; S.D. Benin,
    “Commandments, Convenants and the Jews in Aphrahat,
    Ephrem and Jacob of Sarug,” in <hi rend="italic">Approaches to Judaism
    in Medieval Times,</hi> ed. by D.R. Blumenthal [Chico, CA:
    Scholars Press, 1985], 135-156; and A.P. Hayman, “The
    Image of the Jew in the Syriac Anti-Jewish Polemical
    Literature,” in <hi rend="italic">“To See Ourselves as Others See
    Us”: Christians, Jews, “Others” in Late
    Antiquity,</hi> ed. by J. Neusner and E.S. Frerichs [Chico, CA:
    Scholars Press, 1985], 423-441).  Scholars have begun to
    recognize, however, that not all of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish
    language can be read most fruitfully as literal attacks on
    Jews.  See, for example, R.A. Darling, “The
    ‘Church from the Nations’ in the Exegesis of
    Ephrem,” in <hi rend="italic">IV Symposium Syriacum, 1984,</hi> ed. by
    H.J.W. Drijvers et al. [Rome, 1987], 111-121; and H.J.W.
    Drijvers, “Jews and Christians at Edessa”
    (<hi rend="italic">JJS</hi> 36, no. 1 [1985]), 88-102.  Nonetheless, the
    details of the role of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric in a
    context of Nicene/Arian conflict have not yet been worked
    out.  For other relevant bibliography, as well as an
    earlier discussion of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric in
    this context, see C. Shepardson, “Anti-Jewish Rhetoric
    and Intra-Christian Conflict in the Sermons of Ephrem
    Syrus,” in <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica.</hi> Vol. XXXV, XIII
    International Conference on Patristic Studies (Peeters:
    Louvain, 2001), 502-507. 
         </p>
                </note> the combination of a
    predominantly anti-Arian agenda with this anti-Jewish language
    makes the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> key texts for investigating
    Ephrem’s use of anti-Jewish rhetoric in order to engage
    in a local intra-Christian struggle.  A close examination
    of these hymns will demonstrate how Ephrem repeatedly connects
    the ‘heretics’ with Jews by mapping his Christian
    opponents onto the negative caricatures of the Jews of
    Christian scripture.  Focusing primarily on the complex
    comparison that Ephrem makes in Hymn 87 between biblical Jews
    who crucified Christ and contemporary Christians who comparably
    threaten God’s son, I shall argue that Ephrem’s
    anti-Jewish rhetoric in these hymns should be read primarily in
    light of his struggle against local Christians rather than
    Jews.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson4">Hymns on Faith</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Edmund
    Beck and others have concluded that Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
    Faith</hi> were most likely written after 363 C.E. in Edessa,
    during the reign of the pro-Arian emperor Valens.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             See above for Beck’s dating.  This
    dating would place the writing of the Hymns on Faith in the
    context of political uncertainty for Ephrem, in the Roman
    East.  Except for the brief reigns of Julian and Jovian,
    Ephrem found himself under the political rule of emperors
    (Constantius and Valens) who actively supported
    subordinationist Christians such as Ephrem’s opponents
    instead of Nicene Christians. 
         </p>
                </note> Given the
    immediacy and strength of Arian Christianity in the East during
    this time, the sharpness of the anti-Arian language of Ephrem,
    a vociferous proponent of Nicene ‘orthodoxy’, comes
    as little surprise.  Along with the anti-Arian polemic,
    however, the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> also contain a striking
    amount of anti-Jewish language.  While less vitriolic than
    Ephrem’s most <hi rend="italic">ad hominem</hi> anti-Jewish attacks
    against the “foulness of the stinking
    Jews,”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, CH 56.8 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses,</hi> CSCO Syr 169/76
    [Louvain, 1957]).  All quotations from Ephrem in this text
    are my translations from the Syriac editions noted. 
         </p>
                </note> the rhetoric in the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> offers
    a significant example of Ephrem’s use of anti-Jewish
    rhetoric to attack Arian Christians.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    Rhetorically, Ephrem addresses these hymns to a Christian
    audience,<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             While it is difficult to know with any certainty
    the ‘real’ and/or ‘imagined’ audience
    of these hymns, Ephrem’s use of pronouns and his
    rhetorical arguments do suggest that rhetorically at least he
    addressed these hymns to Christians, supporting scholars’
    belief that Ephrem’s hymns were performed during
    Christian worship services.  For a discussion of the
    performance of Ephrem’s writings, see S.A. Harvey,
    “Spoken Words, Voiced Silence: Biblical Women in Syriac
    Tradition” (<hi rend="italic">JECS</hi>9:1 [2001]), 105-131; and K.E.
    McVey, “Were the Earliest <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi> Songs or
    Recitations?” in <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on
    Continuity and Change in Syriac Christianity in Honour of
    Professor Han J.W. Drijvers,</hi> ed. by G.J. Reinink and A.C.
    Klugkist, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 89 (Louvain: Peeters,
    1999), 185-199. 
         </p>
                </note> and the specific language and criticisms that
    Ephrem levels against Jews in the hymns provide him with an
    effective weapon with which to argue against his Christian
    opponents.  In Hymn 44, for example, Ephrem sets up a
    dichotomy between ‘them’, “that People”
    (the Jews), and ‘us’, Christians.  He writes
    of the Jews [yhwdy’] that “<hi rend="italic">they</hi> are not able
    to live... <hi rend="italic">they</hi> rejected... <hi rend="italic">they</hi> have been
    rejected,” and ends those observations by referring to
    “a chasm between <hi rend="italic">us</hi> and that
    People.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 44.4 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr 154/73
    [Louvain, 1955]). 
         </p>
                </note>  Nominally, then, Ephrem clearly delineates
    between Jews, on the one hand, and Christians, on the
    other.  In practice, however, Ephrem spends a good part of
    these hymns attempting to demonstrate that when this line is in
    fact drawn, his Arian opponents land squarely on the side of
    the Jews.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN7" n="7">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             This is not the only collection of Ephrem’s
    writings in which he marshals his arguments toward this
    end.  For example, he employs different methods toward a
    similar goal in his Sermons on Faith (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Sermones de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr
    212/88 [Louvain, 1961]).  See Shepardson,
    “Anti-Jewish”. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson5">Anti-Jewish/Anti-Arian Themes</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Many of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> contain examples that are
    relevant to the discussion of Ephrem’s use of anti-Jewish
    language in his fight against subordinationist
    Christians.  The majority of these scattered references
    rely on biblical stories and imagery with which anti-Jewish
    language is ‘proven’ through biblical prooftexting,
    and through which Ephrem’s Christian opponents are
    described as directly analogous to Jewish forerunners. 
    Ephrem’s numerous writings are replete with biblical
    language, examples, and imagery. In his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith,</hi>
    Ephrem uses a variety of Old and New Testament stories to
    support his arguments, frequently comparing his opponents to
    Jews who are portrayed negatively in the biblical text.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN8" n="8">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem’s easy transition between the Old and
    New Testaments reflects his belief that Christian scripture as
    a whole is the coherent story of salvation history. 
         </p>
                </note> One of
    Ephrem’s favorite comparisons from the New Testament
    (judging by the frequency with which it occurs in his writings)
    is to condemn the Arians for their inquiring actions by
    directly comparing them to the negatively-portrayed Pharisees
    who challenge Jesus in the New Testament Gospel
    stories.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN9" n="9">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             See, for example, SdF VI; de Dom. nos. 19ff (E.
    Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Sermo de Domino
    Nostro,</hi> CSCO Syr  270/116 [Louvain, 1966)]; Virg,
    13.2, 14.5 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers
    Hymnen de Virginitate,</hi> CSCO Syr  223/94 [Louvain,
    1962)]; and CNis 40 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des
    Syrers Carmina Nisibena, zweiter Teil.</hi> CSCO Syr 240/102
    [Louvain, 1963].) 
         </p>
                </note> The emphasis on the verbs for searching
    [b<hi rend="underline">s</hi>’], seeking
    [b<hi rend="sup">c</hi>’], and investigating [<hi rend="sup">c</hi>qb] in
    Ephrem’s rhetoric is frequently an attack against Arian
    Christians who, Ephrem argues, inappropriately seek to know God
    through reasoned inquiry, rather than simply believing through
    faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             In HdF 87, however, Ephrem himself describes
    in more detail one of the problems he has with his rivals:
    “With various names indeed [Satan] clothes him, either
    that of ‘creature’ or that of ‘made
    thing’, while he was the Maker” (HdF 87.14). 
    In this case, we are left with little doubt about the general
    subordinationist nature of Ephrem’s opponents. 
         </p>
                </note>   Such is the case in Hymn 44 when Ephrem
    warns his Christian audience, “Be reproved, bold ones,
    and be restrained, searchers!… It was thus the People
    strove with [Christ] through their questionings”.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN11" n="11">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 44.6, 9. 
         </p>
                </note> This
    is simply one example of Ephrem’s comparison of the
    theological investigation of his fourth-century Christian
    opponents to the challenging questions that the Pharisees asked
    Jesus in the Gospel stories.  Relying on Christians’
    familiarity with (and abhorrence of) Jesus’ narrative
    (‘Jewish’) opponents, Ephrem uses Christian
    anti-Jewish sentiment to denounce ‘heretical’
    contemporary Christian.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Another
    example of Ephrem’s scripturally-based anti-Jewish
    charges comes in Hymn 7 of his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith.</hi>  In
    this hymn Ephrem condemns “all these who
    investigated,”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN12" n="12">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. 
         </p>
                </note> again connecting contemporary Arian
    Christians with traditional Jewish antagonists of the Gospel
    narratives.  Ephrem elaborates by comparing the
    investigating Christians to Herod, to the unrepentant thief
    crucified with Jesus,<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN13" n="13">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Lk 23:32-33, 39-43 (cf. Mt 27:38,44; Jn
    19:17-18). 
         </p>
                </note> and to the Gospel scribes and
    Pharisees:</p>
         <quote>
      The [thief] of the left, he disputed.  His disputing cut
      off his hope.  The scribes disputed.  They fell
      with Herod who questioned him. . . . To all these who
      investigated, Christ did not give himself. . . . The
      Pharisees disputed, “who is this, and whose
      son?”  As searchers of truth, they fell from the
      truth.  As seekers of verity, in seeking it, they
      destroyed it.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN14" n="14">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7, 9. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </quote>
         <p>For Ephrem these negative examples are in direct contrast to
    the Gospel forerunners of proper Christians, those who are
    “innocent” to whom Christ <hi rend="italic">did</hi> give
    himself,<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN15" n="15">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. 
         </p>
                </note> those who follow the examples of the magi in
    Matthew’s Gospel, who “did not dare to search
    [Christ],”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN16" n="16">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. 
         </p>
                </note> and the other thief in Luke’s
    Gospel who “did not dispute; he believed when he did not
    search.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN17" n="17">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7 (cf. Lk 23:39-43). 
         </p>
                </note> In this hymn, Ephrem likens his Christian
    adversaries to the Jewish New Testament villains Herod, the
    scribes, and the Pharisees, and distances them from the Gentile
    magi, the forerunners of true Christians.  In Hymn 56
    Ephrem summarizes this critique of his rivals’ disputes
    about God: “Therefore both Testaments persuade us that
    the faithful never disputed or investigated, for they believed
    in God.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN18" n="18">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 56.8. 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In
    addition to using biblical stories, Ephrem also frequently
    draws comparisons between his opponents and biblical Jews by
    using the same negative adjectives to describe both of them,
    thereby implying a direct correlation between the two
    groups.  Specifically, Ephrem reiterates throughout his
    <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> his description of both Jews and Arians
    as ‘blind’.  In Hymn 8 Ephrem refers to the
    Jews at Mt. Sinai as “the blind People,” doubly
    blinded [veiled] by the veil of light surrounding Moses as well
    as by his stammering,<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN19" n="19">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 8.5; Ex 34:29-35 and Ex 4:10-17.
    
         </p>
                </note> and in Hymn 9 Ephrem compares “the
    blind People” of the Jews to “you [pl.]
    blind” among the Christians he accuses.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN20" n="20">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 9.13. 
         </p>
                </note> Hymn 27 also
    linguistically links the two groups by referring to his
    opponents as a “blind assembly of
    disputers.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN21" n="21">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 27.4. 
         </p>
                </note> In this case, not only are his disputing
    opponents again blind, but Ephrem uses the Syriac word
    <hi rend="italic">knsh’</hi> for ‘assembly’, a word that is
    from the same root as <hi rend="italic">knwsht’</hi>
    ‘synagogue’, the word that Ephrem consistently uses
    to refer to a Jewish space or group instead of the synonym
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>dt’</hi> that he uses for Christians. 
    Through the common trait of blindness, then, Ephrem
    rhetorically links his Arian opponents with the
    negatively-coded errors, history, and people of the Jews.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson6">Hymn 87</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Perhaps
    the most elaborate conflation of Jews and Arians in all of
    Ephrem’s writings, however, is in number 87 of his
    <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith.</hi>  In these verses, Ephrem maps the
    behavior of his contemporary Christian opponents point by point
    onto the Jews from the New Testament narratives of Jesus’
    Passion.  Ephrem describes the former as the contemporary
    equivalent to the Jews of Jesus’ time who, as described
    throughout Ephrem’s writings, harassed and murdered
    God’s son.  While this comparison between the Jews
    and Ephrem’s Christian opponents appears in several
    variations throughout the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith,</hi> in Hymn 87
    Ephrem draws a very physical connection based on the actions of
    each of the two groups.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8]
    Throughout his writings Ephrem vacillates about where to place
    the blame for the Jews’ actions (as described in
    scripture), sometimes making the Jews themselves solely
    responsible, and other times blaming Satan for manipulating
    history and using the blind and foolish Jews as unwitting
    minions to carry out his plans.  In Hymn 87 Ephrem places
    the blame on Satan, who in this construction of history
    orchestrates both the Jews’ and the heretics’
    reprehensible actions.  While this in some way alleviates,
    by removing the Jews’ agency, the vitriol that Ephrem
    elsewhere pours directly onto the Jews, at the same time it
    makes the Jews sinister lackeys, passive (and ultimately
    passé) pawns in a Satanic drama that is played out on
    the stage of human history.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9]
    According to Ephrem in this hymn, Satan had originally harbored
    himself among the Jewish People, as was clear from the history
    of the Jews’ destructive and ungodly behavior,
    culminating with Jesus’ Passion and what Ephrem describes
    elsewhere as the Jews’ murder of God’s own
    son.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN22" n="22">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             This accusation is frequent in
    Ephrem’s writings.  For only a small portion of the
    numerous examples, see de Dom. nos. 5, 6; Cruc. 1, 5 and Azym.
    1, 18; and CNis 67.  In Hymns on Fasting 5.6 Ephrem even
    accuses the Jews of killing God, not just God’s son, on
    the cross (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers
    Hymnen de Ieiunio,</hi> CSCO Syr  246/106 [Louvain,
    1964]).  These charges are not new with Ephrem, but
    Ephrem’s rhetoric does repeatedly accuse the Jews of this
    murder. 
         </p>
                </note>   In Hymn 87, however, Ephrem claims that
    after their actions during the Passion the Jews were no longer
    a viable means through which Satan could secretly influence the
    world, because after that time the Jews could no longer conceal
    their partnership with Satan.  Ephrem writes, “Satan
    saw that he had been exposed in the former things, for the
    spitting had been revealed, [as had] the vinegar and thorns,
    nails and wood, garments and reed, and the spear that struck
    him.  And they were hated and revealed, and he changed his
    deceits.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN23" n="23">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.16.   See Appendix
    A for a complete translation of this hymn. 
         </p>
                </note> The world’s alleged open recognition of
    the Jews’ partnership with Satan forced Satan to find new
    pawns through whom he could continue to influence history and
    attack God.  According to Ephrem, the Arians served as
    Satan’s new tool after the Jews had worn out their
    usefulness.  Ephrem writes, “The former scribes
    Satan disrobed; he clothed the later ones.  The People
    which had grown old, the moth and the louse gnawed it and ate
    it, and they released and let it go.  The moth came to the
    new garment of the new peoples.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN24" n="24">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.9. 
         </p>
                </note> Satan
    “began with the People, and he came to the peoples in
    order that he might finish.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN25" n="25">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.12. 
         </p>
                </note> Ephrem understands that
    Satan has recently changed players in his on-going effort to
    corrupt, to destroy, and to fight against God.  For
    Ephrem, it is subordinationist Christians who are the
    ‘new garment’, and in that respect the new Jews,
    through which Satan continues to harass God and God’s
    people.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] In
    Hymn 87 Ephrem identifies and describes his adversaries as the
    replacement for the Jews through a direct comparison between
    the behavior of the contemporary Christians and that of the
    Jewish characters in the Gospel scenes of Jesus’ trial
    and crucifixion.  One by one, Ephrem maps the concrete,
    literal actions of the New Testament Jews onto a figurative
    characterization of the ‘heretical’
    Christians’ own behavior, demonstrating to his audience
    that not only do both contemporary Arians and the Jews of
    Jesus’ time attack God and threaten true followers of
    Christ, but that both groups in fact present precisely the same
    threat.  Through his rhetoric, Ephrem conflates the Arians
    with the Jews blamed by Christian tradition for Jesus’
    death, ‘proving’ to his audience that although the
    contemporary blows may be less literal than the physical blows
    with which Jesus was struck, the Arians are in fact through
    their rebellious actions causing Christ to suffer a second
    Passion.  Ephrem writes of the Arians’ metaphorical
    mimicry of the New Testament narrative, “A second Passion
    did Satan want to reinstate.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN26" n="26">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.19. 
         </p>
                </note> Unsatisfied merely with
    Jesus’ physical death, Satan continues his attack upon
    Christians and God, figuratively reenacting Christ’s
    Passion through the Arians’ attacks upon Christ’s
    nature as well as upon Christ’s ‘true’
    followers, Nicene Christians.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Ephrem begins his analogy by comparing the reed with which
    Jesus was mocked and struck with the reed stylus with which the
    Arians record their ‘heretical’ inquiries into
    God.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN27" n="27">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             The details of who mocks Jesus, and whether
    or not they strike him with a reed vary in different ancient
    texts of the New Testament Gospels and the Diatesseron. 
    At this time, however, I am simply discussing Ephrem’s
    retelling of the narrative, and not trying to identify which
    texts he used as a source for these details. 
         </p>
                </note> Ephrem writes, “Instead of that reed
    that the former People gave the son to hold, [there are] later
    ones who dared in their tracts to write with a reed that he
    even is [only] human.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN28" n="28">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.13. In Hymns on Crucifixion 5
    and 8 Ephrem also compares a reed from the Passion narratives
    to reed styli, but he does so in different ways. In his Hymns
    on Crucifixion, he primarily compares the reed with which the
    crucified Jesus was offered a drink to the reeds with which
    prophets, kings, and scribes of Israel (especially King David
    as author of the Psalms) wrote against the behavior of
    Jesus’ crucifiers.  For example, Ephrem writes,
    “David wrote with a straight staff in order that he might
    shame that People who disgraced [Jesus] with that reed”
    (Cruc. 8.4).  Likewise, Ephrem notes, “Instead of
    the one reed with which they beat [Jesus], the [many] reeds of
    the scribes beat them... A thicket of reeds are the books of
    the writers; they beat the crucifiers with their books”
    [Cruc. V.14). 
         </p>
                </note> Instead of physically striking
    Jesus with a reed, the heretics, Ephrem claims, deal comparable
    blows against God through the tracts that they write with their
    reed pens.  Ephrem bemoans, “Reed for reed the evil
    one exchanged against our savior.”<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN29" n="29">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.13. 
         </p>
                </note> Whereas Satan
    could at one time openly strike at his enemy through the
    Jews’ attacks, he must now act more subtly, striking
    through the strife and falsehood espoused in the Arians’
    writings.  Ephrem argues that through their inquiry and
    contention the Arians harm Christ in a duplication of the
    actions of the Jews in the New Testament narrative.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Likewise, Ephrem also compares the “garments of various
    colors” with which he claims Jesus was clothed to the
    “various names” with which the Arians clothe
    Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN30" n="30">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.14. 
         </p>
                </note> Again here it is Christ, rather than Nicene
    Christians themselves, whom Ephrem portrays as the most direct
    victim of the intra-Christian disputes.  In Ephrem’s
    depiction, through the inquiries of the Arians Satan reenacts
    Jesus’ Passion at the hands of the Jews.  Ephrem
    describes a direct comparison for every detail of the Passion
    narrative:</p>
         <quote>
            <p>He changed the cross; a hidden cross dispute became. 
      And instead of nails, questions entered.  And instead of
      Sheol, [there was] denial... Instead of the sponge that
      dropped with vinegar, he gave arrows, [i.e.,] searching, all
      of which dripped with death.  The gall that they gave to
      him, our lord refused.  Fraudulent seeking that the
      bitter one gave, to fools is sweet.<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.19-20. 
         </p>
                    </note>
            </p>
         </quote>
         <p>More than merely participants in a struggle to claim the
    title ‘Christian’ for themselves, the Arians emerge
    from Ephrem’s texts as assailants and abusers of Christ
    himself, alike in every detail to the New Testament Jews whom
    Ephrem blames for mocking and abusing God’s son.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] In
    addition to the Arians’ investigating actions, in Hymn 87
    Ephrem portrays the Nicene/Arian dissension within Christianity
    as itself the direct outcome of Satan’s actions in
    Ephrem’s lifetime, just as the Jews’ murder of
    God’s son was in Jesus’ lifetime, and he describes
    this intra-Christian strife as also comparable to
    Christ’s Passion.  Ephrem writes about Satan,</p>
         <quote>
            <p>He brought in confusion instead of that blow with which
      our lord was struck; and instead of spitting, investigating
      came.  And instead of garments, secret divisions. 
      And instead of a reed, contention came so that he might slap
      all.  Haughtiness cried out to fury its sister, and envy
      and rage and pride and guile answered and came.  They
      took counsel against our savior, as on that day that they
      took counsel when he suffered [i.e., “that day. . . of
      his Passion”].<note place="foot" xml:id="#FN32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
             Ephrem, HdF 87.17-18. 
         </p>
                    </note>
            </p>
         </quote>
         <p>Through this rhetoric Ephrem thus attempts to construct a
    historical reality in which Arians, like the Jews before them,
    become the unquestioned enemy both of God and of true
    Christians.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson7">Conclusion</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] In
    Hymn 87 of his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> Ephrem uses the
    connections that he draws between fourth-century Arians and New
    Testament Jews in order to emphasize not the depravity of
    contemporary Jews so much as that of his more immediate
    opponents, Arian Christians.  Ephrem tars his
    rivals’ image by rhetorically connecting them with the
    Jews.  By portraying the Arians as new Jews, as the
    contemporary equivalent to, and in fact Satan’s direct
    replacement for, the Jews who murdered the son of God, Ephrem
    implies that the Arians are both theologically and perhaps even
    physically dangerous to God and to true (i.e., Nicene)
    Christians.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] In
    his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith</hi> Ephrem manipulates negative Christian
    depictions of and beliefs about Jews, rooted in (among other
    things) the New Testament Gospels, in order to discredit his
    Arian opponents.  In Hymn 87 Ephrem goes to great lengths
    in order to describe the Arians’ searching for the nature
    of God and Christ as the figurative equivalent to traditions of
    the Jews’ literal mocking and murder of Jesus. 
    Conflating the Arians’ verbal attacks with the abuse
    portrayed in the Gospel Passion narratives, Ephrem is able
    rhetorically to connect his contemporary Christian opponents
    with what he portrays as the well-known and universally
    despised people of the Jews.  In Ephrem’s hymns,
    Arian Christians found themselves in the perhaps surprising
    position of being portrayed both as acting under Satan’s
    control and also as attackers of Christ, the contemporary
    equivalent to the (despised) New Testament Jews, and
    consequently a dangerous threat to the safety and well-being of
    any true Christian, as well as an affront to God. 
    Recognizing the boundary lines that Ephrem’s rhetoric
    attempts to define and police within fourth-century
    Christianity demonstrates the power that his language and
    descriptions would have had within a Christian community torn
    by the Nicene/Arian struggle.  In his <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
    Faith,</hi> and especially in Hymn 87, Ephrem rhetorically
    redraws social boundaries in such a way as to crystallize a
    sharp distinction between two Christian communities.  By
    describing Arians as the contemporary equivalent of, and in
    fact replacement for, the Jewish enemies of Christian lore as
    Satan exchanges “reed for reed”, Ephrem replaces a
    blurred line between two Christian groups with what he presents
    as the unmistakable distinction between Christians and Jews,
    leaving the Christian Arians firmly on the side of the
    Jews.</p>
         <p>
            <hi style="color: #663300; font-size: 1.2em; font-weight: bolder; font-family:" times="" new="">Appendix</hi>
            <note place="foot" xml:id="#FN33" n="33">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             I translated this hymn from Edmund
    Beck’s edition of the Syriac, (E. Beck, trans., <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO 154
    [Louvain: 1955]).  Any errors are, of course, my own, but
    I owe many thanks to Lucas van Rompay for his patient
    assistance in working with me on this translation.  I have
    seen announced Paul Russell’s English translation of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith,</hi> but I have not yet been
    able to locate a copy of his translation, so I include my own
    here for the reader’s convenience (Paul Russell,
    <hi rend="italic">Ephraem the Syrian: 80 Hymns on Faith,</hi> Eastern Texts in
    Translation 3 (Louvain: Peeters). 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A1"/>1.   As in a contest I saw the
    disputants,<lb/>
    children of pride, who were troubling themselves<lb/>
    to taste fire, to see the wind,<lb/>
    to touch light.  They were tormenting themselves<lb/>
    to make divisions of the ray [of light].</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="italic">Refrain</hi>:  Glory be to the father, and to his son
    Jesus,<lb/>
    and to his holy spirit.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A2"/>2.   The son who is more subtle than the
    mind<lb/>
    they wanted to touch; and the holy spirit,<lb/>
    who is intangible, they also thought they had touched<lb/>
    through their questions; and the father who is never<lb/>
    being interpreted, they interpreted disputes about him.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A3"/>3.   [We have] a good model of our
    faith<lb/>
    from Abraham, and [of] our repentance<lb/>
    from the Ninevites, and also [of] our expectations<lb/>
    from the house of Rahab.  Ours are [the things] of the
    prophets,<lb/>
    and ours [those] of the apostles.  And [so] the evil one
    became envious.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A4"/>4.   The evil habit of the evil calf<lb/>
    [is] from the Egyptians; the hateful sight<lb/>
    of the hateful image of the four faces<lb/>
    [is] from the Hittites; accursed dispute,<lb/>
    a hidden moth, [is] from the Greeks.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A5"/>5.   That bitter one saw orderly
    things<lb/>
    and he perverted them; he saw hateful things<lb/>
    and he sowed them; and he saw hope<lb/>
    and he suppressed [it] and cut it off.  The dispute that
    he planted<lb/>
    indeed bore fruit that [is] a bitterness of the teeth.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A6"/>6.   Satan saw that truth suffocated
    him<lb/>
    and his offshoots, and he set himself apart<lb/>
    and committed deceits and set snares<lb/>
    for faith, and he hurled into the priests<lb/>
    arrows of the lust for authority.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A7"/>7.   Over that throne they made a
    contest<lb/>
    of who might precede.  There is the one who in
    secret<lb/>
    coveted and hid [desire to rule], and there is one who
    openly<lb/>
    contended for it.  The one acted contemptibly<lb/>
    and the other cunningly, and these are equal.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A8"/>8.   The one who is young also does not
    consider<lb/>
    that it is not his time; and he who is old<lb/>
    does not reckon that [his] end draws near.<lb/>
    [It is] an evil tumor: elders, youth,<lb/>
    even children are seeking rank.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A9"/>9.   The former scribes Satan
    disrobed;<lb/>
    he clothed the later ones.  The People that had grown
    old,<lb/>
    the moth and the louse gnawed it and ate it,<lb/>
    and they released and let it go.  The moth came<lb/>
    to the new garment of the new peoples.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A10"/>10.   [Satan] saw the crucifiers, who were
    rejected and<lb/>
    expelled as strangers.  From [our Christian]
    household<lb/>
    he made searchers; and from being worshippers<lb/>
    they became disputants.  From the garment itself<lb/>
    [Satan] begot the moth, and he wrapped [it] up and placed
    it.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A11"/>11.   He begot the louse in the storehouse
    of wheat<lb/>
    and he sat and looked: and indeed the pure heap [of
    grain]<lb/>
    is being corrupted, and indeed the garments of glory<lb/>
    are being gnawed.  He mocked us,<lb/>
    and even we [mocked] ourselves, for we had become drunk.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A12"/>12.   He sowed tares, and the thicket
    assaulted<lb/>
    the pure vineyard; he infected the flock<lb/>
    and leprosy spread, and sheep after sheep<lb/>
    became his possession.  He began with the People<lb/>
    and he came to the peoples in order that he might finish.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A13"/>13.   Instead of that reed that the former
    People gave the Son<lb/>
    to hold, [there are] later ones who dared<lb/>
    in their tracts to write with a reed<lb/>
    that he even is [only] human.  Reed for reed<lb/>
    the evil one exchanged against our savior.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A14"/>14.   And instead of the garments of
    various colors<lb/>
    in which he clothed him, he painted a designation<lb/>
    deceitfully.  With various names<lb/>
    indeed he clothes him, either that of
    ‘creature’<lb/>
    or that of ‘made thing’, while he is the Maker.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A15"/>15.   And he had plaited for him out of
    dumb things<lb/>
    silent thorns.  Speaking thorns,<lb/>
    [coming] from the mind, he plaited for him with a voice<lb/>
    as hymns, and he concealed the brambles<lb/>
    within songs which were not known [before].</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A16"/>16.   Satan saw that he had been
    exposed<lb/>
    in the former things, for the spitting had been revealed,<lb/>
    [as had] the vinegar and thorns, nails and wood,<lb/>
    garments and reed, and the spear that struck him.<lb/>
    And they were hated and revealed, and [Satan] changed his
    deceits.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A17"/>17.   He brought confusion instead of that
    blow<lb/>
    with which our lord was struck; and instead of spitting,<lb/>
    investigating came; and instead of garments,<lb/>
    secret divisions; and instead of a reed,<lb/>
    contention came so that he might slap all.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A18"/>18.   Haughtiness cried out to fury its
    sister,<lb/>
    and envy and rage and pride and guile<lb/>
    answered and came.  They took counsel<lb/>
    against our savior, as on that day<lb/>
    that they took counsel when he suffered [i.e., “that
    day… of his Passion”].</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A19"/>19.   He changed the cross; a hidden
    cross<lb/>
    dispute became.  And instead of nails,<lb/>
    questions entered; and instead of Sheol,<lb/>
    [there was] denial.  A second Passion<lb/>
    did Satan want to reinstate.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A20"/>20.   Instead of the sponge which dropped
    with vinegar,<lb/>
    he gave arrows, [i.e.,] searching, all of which<lb/>
    dripped with death.  The gall that they gave him,<lb/>
    our lord refused.  Fraudulent seeking<lb/>
    that the bitter one gave, to fools is sweet.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A21"/>21.   And while in that time there was a
    judge<lb/>
    against them, indeed judges<lb/>
    are [in the same way] against us.  And instead of the
    inscription,<lb/>
    [there are] their commands.  The crown is innocent<lb/>
    for the priests set stumbling blocks for the kings.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A22"/>22.   Rather than that the priesthood might
    pray<lb/>
    for the kingdom, that wars might cease<lb/>
    from humankind, perverse wars<lb/>
    they have taught them, for the kings have started<lb/>
    to struggle with their cities.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="A23"/>23.   Our lord, reconcile the priests and
    the kings,<lb/>
    and in one church let priests pray<lb/>
    for their kings, and let kings have mercy<lb/>
    on their cities; and let us have<lb/>
    inner peace in you, an outer wall.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson8">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef0">†</ref> I presented a version of this paper at the
    annual conference of the North American Patristic Society, June
    2001. <ref target="#FNRef0">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Although there are significant problems inherent in
    using the term ‘Arian’, it is difficult to identify
    Ephrem’s opponents any more specifically.  See
    Sidney Griffith’s recent observations in S.H. Griffith,
    “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint Ephrem’s
    <hi rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies,</hi>” in <hi rend="italic">The Limits of
    Ancient Christianity: Essays on Late Antique Thought and
    Culture in Honor of R.A. Markus,</hi> ed. by W.E. Klingshirn and
    M. Vessey (Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan, 1999),
    97-114; and in S.H. Griffith, “Ephraem, the Deacon of
    Edessa, and the Church of the Empire,” in <hi rend="italic">Diakonia:
    Studies in Honor of Robert T. Meyer,</hi> ed. by T. Halton and
    J. Williman (D.C.: CUA, 1986), 22-52; as well as Paul
    Russell’s observations in  <hi rend="italic">St. Ephraem the Syrian
    and St. Gregory the Theologian Confront the Arians</hi> (Kerala,
    India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute, 1994). 
    In his detailed studies of Ephrem’s Hymns on Faith,
    Edmund Beck concluded that in these hymns Ephrem argues against
    ‘Arianism’: “The main theme in all eighty
    Hymns on Faith is the defense of the church’s teaching
    over and against the innovation of Arianism” (E. Beck,
    <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie des heiligen Ephraem in seinen Hymnen
    über den Glauben,</hi> SA 21 [Vatican City, 1949],
    62).  In fact, Beck elsewhere uses the nuances of his
    investigation to argue for a later date for the Hymns of Faith
    in comparison with the Sermons on Faith: “The composition
    of the Hymns on Faith can in my opinion be rather precisely
    given.  That we are in Ephrem’s Edessene period is
    betrayed by the inclusion of the person of the holy spirit in
    the Arian argument, which many of that time treat and which is
    lacking in the polemic against the Arians in the Sermons on
    Faith from the Nisibene period” (E. Beck, trans. <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr 155/74
    [Louvain, 1955], i).  While the general claim of
    Beck’s conclusions about the identity of Ephrem’s
    opponents remains, scholars have rightfully challenged modern
    uses of the terminology of ‘Arianism’ itself, since
    the term includes many distinct groups, each with their own
    theological tenets.  For relevant scholarship and
    bibliography, see R.P. Vaggione, <hi rend="italic">Eunomius of Cyzicus and the
    Nicene Revolution,</hi> (NY: OUP, 2000); R.C. Gregg and D.E.
    Groh, <hi rend="italic">Early Arianism: A View of Salvation,</hi>
    (Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1981); M.R. Barnes and D.H.
    Williams, eds., <hi rend="italic">Arianism after Arius,</hi> (Edinburgh, 1993);
    R.P.C. Hanson, <hi rend="italic">The Search for the Christian Doctrine of God:
    The Arian Controversy 318-381,</hi> (Edinburgh, 1988); and J.T.
    Lienhard, “The ‘Arian’ Controversy: Some
    Categories Reconsidered” (<hi rend="italic">TS</hi> 48 [1987]),
    415-437.  With regard to Ephrem’s opponents, I use
    ‘Arian’ in contrast to ‘Nicene’
    Christianity to reflect the strongly subordinationist nature of
    their theology.  <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             There is no reason to doubt that there were Jews
    living in both Nisibis and Edessa during Ephrem’s
    lifetime, and some of Ephrem’s writings do complain about
    local Jewish practices (see, for example, Cruc. 19-20 in Edmund
    Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Paschahymnen [de
    azymis, de crucifixione, de resurrectione],</hi> CSCO Syr 
    248/108 [Louvain, 1964]).  As a result, early scholars
    assumed that all of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric was a
    straightforward attack on contemporary Jews.  For
    examples, see Stanley Kazan, “Isaac of Antioch’s
    Homily against the Jews” (<hi rend="italic">OrChr</hi> 46 [1962]), 87-98;
    (47 [1963]), 89-97; (49 [1965]), 57-78; J.B. Morris, <hi rend="italic">Select
    Works of St. Ephrem the Syrian, Library of the Fathers,</hi>
    (Oxford, 1847), 396n; and E. Beck, <hi rend="italic">Ephraems Reden über
    den Glauben</hi> (Rome, 1953), 118-119; as well as later works
    that accept and echo the conclusions of these authors (e.g., R.
    Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A Study in Early
    Syriac Tradition</hi> [Cambridge, 1975]; S.D. Benin,
    “Commandments, Convenants and the Jews in Aphrahat,
    Ephrem and Jacob of Sarug,” in <hi rend="italic">Approaches to Judaism
    in Medieval Times,</hi> ed. by D.R. Blumenthal [Chico, CA:
    Scholars Press, 1985], 135-156; and A.P. Hayman, “The
    Image of the Jew in the Syriac Anti-Jewish Polemical
    Literature,” in <hi rend="italic">“To See Ourselves as Others See
    Us”: Christians, Jews, “Others” in Late
    Antiquity,</hi> ed. by J. Neusner and E.S. Frerichs [Chico, CA:
    Scholars Press, 1985], 423-441).  Scholars have begun to
    recognize, however, that not all of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish
    language can be read most fruitfully as literal attacks on
    Jews.  See, for example, R.A. Darling, “The
    ‘Church from the Nations’ in the Exegesis of
    Ephrem,” in <hi rend="italic">IV Symposium Syriacum, 1984,</hi> ed. by
    H.J.W. Drijvers et al. [Rome, 1987], 111-121; and H.J.W.
    Drijvers, “Jews and Christians at Edessa”
    (<hi rend="italic">JJS</hi> 36, no. 1 [1985]), 88-102.  Nonetheless, the
    details of the role of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric in a
    context of Nicene/Arian conflict have not yet been worked
    out.  For other relevant bibliography, as well as an
    earlier discussion of Ephrem’s anti-Jewish rhetoric in
    this context, see C. Shepardson, “Anti-Jewish Rhetoric
    and Intra-Christian Conflict in the Sermons of Ephrem
    Syrus,” in <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica.</hi> Vol. XXXV, XIII
    International Conference on Patristic Studies (Peeters:
    Louvain, 2001), 502-507. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             See above for Beck’s dating.  This
    dating would place the writing of the Hymns on Faith in the
    context of political uncertainty for Ephrem, in the Roman
    East.  Except for the brief reigns of Julian and Jovian,
    Ephrem found himself under the political rule of emperors
    (Constantius and Valens) who actively supported
    subordinationist Christians such as Ephrem’s opponents
    instead of Nicene Christians. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, CH 56.8 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses,</hi> CSCO Syr 169/76
    [Louvain, 1957]).  All quotations from Ephrem in this text
    are my translations from the Syriac editions noted. <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             While it is difficult to know with any certainty
    the ‘real’ and/or ‘imagined’ audience
    of these hymns, Ephrem’s use of pronouns and his
    rhetorical arguments do suggest that rhetorically at least he
    addressed these hymns to Christians, supporting scholars’
    belief that Ephrem’s hymns were performed during
    Christian worship services.  For a discussion of the
    performance of Ephrem’s writings, see S.A. Harvey,
    “Spoken Words, Voiced Silence: Biblical Women in Syriac
    Tradition” (<hi rend="italic">JECS</hi>9:1 [2001]), 105-131; and K.E.
    McVey, “Were the Earliest <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi> Songs or
    Recitations?” in <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on
    Continuity and Change in Syriac Christianity in Honour of
    Professor Han J.W. Drijvers,</hi> ed. by G.J. Reinink and A.C.
    Klugkist, Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 89 (Louvain: Peeters,
    1999), 185-199. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 44.4 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr 154/73
    [Louvain, 1955]). <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             This is not the only collection of Ephrem’s
    writings in which he marshals his arguments toward this
    end.  For example, he employs different methods toward a
    similar goal in his Sermons on Faith (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Sermones de Fide,</hi> CSCO Syr
    212/88 [Louvain, 1961]).  See Shepardson,
    “Anti-Jewish”. <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem’s easy transition between the Old and
    New Testaments reflects his belief that Christian scripture as
    a whole is the coherent story of salvation history. <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             See, for example, SdF VI; de Dom. nos. 19ff (E.
    Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Sermo de Domino
    Nostro,</hi> CSCO Syr  270/116 [Louvain, 1966)]; Virg,
    13.2, 14.5 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers
    Hymnen de Virginitate,</hi> CSCO Syr  223/94 [Louvain,
    1962)]; and CNis 40 (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des
    Syrers Carmina Nisibena, zweiter Teil.</hi> CSCO Syr 240/102
    [Louvain, 1963].) <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             In HdF 87, however, Ephrem himself describes
    in more detail one of the problems he has with his rivals:
    “With various names indeed [Satan] clothes him, either
    that of ‘creature’ or that of ‘made
    thing’, while he was the Maker” (HdF 87.14). 
    In this case, we are left with little doubt about the general
    subordinationist nature of Ephrem’s opponents. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 44.6, 9. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Lk 23:32-33, 39-43 (cf. Mt 27:38,44; Jn
    19:17-18). <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7, 9. <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 7.7 (cf. Lk 23:39-43). <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 56.8. <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 8.5; Ex 34:29-35 and Ex 4:10-17.
    <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 9.13. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 27.4. <ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             This accusation is frequent in
    Ephrem’s writings.  For only a small portion of the
    numerous examples, see de Dom. nos. 5, 6; Cruc. 1, 5 and Azym.
    1, 18; and CNis 67.  In Hymns on Fasting 5.6 Ephrem even
    accuses the Jews of killing God, not just God’s son, on
    the cross (E. Beck, ed., <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers
    Hymnen de Ieiunio,</hi> CSCO Syr  246/106 [Louvain,
    1964]).  These charges are not new with Ephrem, but
    Ephrem’s rhetoric does repeatedly accuse the Jews of this
    murder. <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.16.   See Appendix
    A for a complete translation of this hymn. <ref target="#FNRef23">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.9. <ref target="#FNRef24">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.12. <ref target="#FNRef25">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.19. <ref target="#FNRef26">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             The details of who mocks Jesus, and whether
    or not they strike him with a reed vary in different ancient
    texts of the New Testament Gospels and the Diatesseron. 
    At this time, however, I am simply discussing Ephrem’s
    retelling of the narrative, and not trying to identify which
    texts he used as a source for these details. <ref target="#FNRef27">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.13. In Hymns on Crucifixion 5
    and 8 Ephrem also compares a reed from the Passion narratives
    to reed styli, but he does so in different ways. In his Hymns
    on Crucifixion, he primarily compares the reed with which the
    crucified Jesus was offered a drink to the reeds with which
    prophets, kings, and scribes of Israel (especially King David
    as author of the Psalms) wrote against the behavior of
    Jesus’ crucifiers.  For example, Ephrem writes,
    “David wrote with a straight staff in order that he might
    shame that People who disgraced [Jesus] with that reed”
    (Cruc. 8.4).  Likewise, Ephrem notes, “Instead of
    the one reed with which they beat [Jesus], the [many] reeds of
    the scribes beat them... A thicket of reeds are the books of
    the writers; they beat the crucifiers with their books”
    [Cruc. V.14). <ref target="#FNRef28">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.13. <ref target="#FNRef29">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.14. <ref target="#FNRef30">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.19-20. <ref target="#FNRef31">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             Ephrem, HdF 87.17-18. <ref target="#FNRef32">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
             I translated this hymn from Edmund
    Beck’s edition of the Syriac, (E. Beck, trans., <hi rend="italic">Des
    Heiligen Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide,</hi> CSCO 154
    [Louvain: 1955]).  Any errors are, of course, my own, but
    I owe many thanks to Lucas van Rompay for his patient
    assistance in working with me on this translation.  I have
    seen announced Paul Russell’s English translation of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on Faith,</hi> but I have not yet been
    able to locate a copy of his translation, so I include my own
    here for the reader’s convenience (Paul Russell,
    <hi rend="italic">Ephraem the Syrian: 80 Hymns on Faith,</hi> Eastern Texts in
    Translation 3 (Louvain: Peeters). <ref target="#FNRef33">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV5N1Shepardson9">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Barnes, M.R. and D.H. Williams, eds.
    <hi rend="italic">Arianism after Arius.</hi> Edinburgh, 1993.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. <hi rend="italic">Ephraems Reden über
    den Glauben.</hi> Rome, 1953.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. <hi rend="italic">Die Theologie des
    heiligen Ephraem in seinen Hymnen über den Glauben</hi> SA
    21. Vatican City, 1949.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Carmina Nisibena, zweiter Teil.</hi> CSCO Syr
    240/102. Louvain, 1963.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Hymnen contra Haereses.</hi> CSCO Syr 169/76.
    Louvain, 1957.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Hymnen de Fide.</hi> CSCO Syr 154/73. Louvain,
    1955.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Hymnen de Ieiunio.</hi> CSCO Syr 246/106.
    Louvain, 1964.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Hymnen de Virginitate.</hi> CSCO Syr  223/94.
    Louvain, 1962.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Paschahymnen (de azymis, de crucifixione, de
    resurrectione).</hi> CSCO Syr  248/108. Louvain, 1964.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Sermo de Domino Nostro.</hi> CSCO Syr  270/116.
    Louvain, 1966.</p>
         <p>Beck, E. ed. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Sermones de Fide.</hi> CSCO Syr 212/88. Louvain,
    1961.</p>
         <p>Beck, E., trans. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen de Fide.</hi> CSCO Syr 155/74.
    Louvain, 1955.</p>
         <p>Benin, S.D. “Commandments,
    Convenants and the Jews in Aphrahat, Ephrem and Jacob of
    Sarug.” In <hi rend="italic">Approaches to Judaism in Medieval
    Times.</hi> Ed. by D.R. Blumenthal. Chico, CA: Scholars Press,
    1985: 135-156.</p>
         <p>Darling, R.A. “The
    ‘Church from the Nations’ in the Exegesis of
    Ephrem.” In <hi rend="italic">IV Symposium Syriacum, 1984.</hi> Ed. by
    H.J.W. Drijvers, et al. Rome, 1987: 111-121.</p>
         <p>Drijvers, H.J.W. “Jews and
    Christians at Edessa.” <hi rend="italic">JJS</hi> 36, no. 1 (1985)
    88-102.</p>
         <p>Griffith, S.H. “Ephraem, the
    Deacon of Edessa, and the Church of the Empire.” In
    <hi rend="italic">Diakonia: Studies in Honor of Robert T. Meyer.</hi> Ed. by T.
    Halton and J. Williman. D.C.: CUA, 1986: 22-52.</p>
         <p>Griffith, S.H. “Setting Right
    the Church of Syria: Saint Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns against
    Heresies.</hi>” In <hi rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient Christianity:
    Essays on Late Antique Thought and Culture in Honor of R.A.
    Markus.</hi> Ed. by W.E. Klingshirn and M. Vessey. Ann Arbor,
    MI: University of Michigan, 1999: 97-114.</p>
         <p>Hanson, R.P.C. <hi rend="italic">The Search for the
    Christian Doctrine of God: The Arian Controversy 318-381.</hi>
    Edinburgh, 1988.</p>
         <p>Harvey, S.A. “Spoken Words,
    Voiced Silence: Biblical Women in Syriac Tradition,”
    <hi rend="italic">JECS</hi> 9:1 (2001) 105-131.</p>
         <p>Hayman, A.P. “The Image of the
    Jew in the Syriac Anti-Jewish Polemical Literature.” In
    <hi rend="italic">“To See Ourselves as Others See Us”: Christians,
    Jews, “Others” in Late Antiquity.</hi> Ed. by J.
    Neusner and E.S. Frerichs. Chico, CA: Scholars Press, 1985:
    423-441.</p>
         <p>Kazan, S. “Isaac of
    Antioch’s Homily against the Jews.” <hi rend="italic">OrChr</hi> 46
    (1962) 87-98; 47 (1963) 89-97; 49 (1965) 57-78.</p>
         <p>Lienhard, J.T. “The
    ‘Arian’ Controversy: Some Categories
    Reconsidered.” <hi rend="italic">TS</hi> 48 (1987) 415-437.</p>
         <p>McVey, K.E. “Were the Earliest
    <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi> Songs or Recitations?” In <hi rend="italic">After
    Bardaisan: Studies on Continuity and Change in Syriac
    Christianity in Honour of Professor Han J.W. Drijvers.</hi> Ed.
    by G.J. Reinink and A.C. Klugkist. Orientalia Lovaniensia
    Analecta 89. Louvain: Peeters, 1999: 185-199.</p>
         <p>Morris, J.B. <hi rend="italic">Select Works of St.
    Ephrem the Syrian, Library of the Fathers.</hi> Oxford,
    1847.</p>
         <p>Murray, R. <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and
    Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac Tradition.</hi> Cambridge,
    1975.</p>
         <p>Paul R. <hi rend="italic">Ephraem the Syrian: 80
    Hymns on Faith.</hi> Eastern Texts in Translation 3. Louvain:
    Peeters.</p>
         <p>Russell, P.S. <hi rend="italic">St. Ephraem the
    Syrian and St. Gregory the Theologian Confront the Arians.</hi>
    Kerala, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute,
    1994.</p>
         <p>Shepardson, C. “Anti-Jewish
    Rhetoric and Intra-Christian Conflict in the Sermons of Ephrem
    Syrus.” In <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica.</hi> Vol. XXXV, XIII
    International Conference on Patristic Studies. Louvain,
    Peeters, 2001: 502-507.</p>
         <p>Vaggione, R.P. <hi rend="italic">Eunomius of
    Cyzicus and the Nicene Revolution.</hi> NY: OUP, 2000.</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>