<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Hugoye's New Book Review Editor</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname/>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>July 2002</date>
            <idno>Vol. 5, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/letterFromTheGeneralEditor/hv5n2gekiraz</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author/>
                  <title level="a">Hugoye's New Book Review Editor</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2002</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="5">5</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] It is my
    pleasure to welcome a new member to the staff of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi>.
    Kristian S. Heal of Brigham Young University accepted an
    invitation to serve as <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> Book Review Editor. The
    position has thus far been occupied by Dr. Monica Blanchard of
    The Catholic University of America.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Kristian
    S. Heal joined the Institute for the Study and Preservation of
    Ancient Religious texts at BYU as a Research Associate in 2000.
    He is the coordinator of the Eastern Christian Digitizing
    Initiative and Associate Editor of the Eastern Christian Texts
    series. He received his bachelor's degree in Jewish History and
    Hebrew from University College, London and continued his
    education at the University of Oxford where he took a master's
    degree in Syriac Studies. He is currently undertaking research
    for his doctoral dissertation at the University of Birmingham.
    His research is focused on the Syriac exegetical tradition,
    with a particular emphasis on the figure of the Old Testament
    Patriarch Joseph (Genesis 37-50) in early Syriac literature.
    Kristian and his wife Vicki-Bronwen are the parents of five
    children.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Dr.
    Monica Blanchard continues to contribute to Beth Mardutho's
    various projects, especially The Syriac Digital Library project
    where she acts as the librarian liaison between Beth Mardutho
    and CUA.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Please
    join me in welcoming Kristian Heal and thanking Dr. Monica
    Blanchard.</p>
         <p>George A. Kiraz, Ph.D.<lb/>
    Hugoye General Editor<lb/>
    Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>