<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Patriarchal Funerary Inscriptions in the Monastery of Rabban Hormizd: Types, Literary Origins, and Purpose</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Amir</forename>
                  <surname>Harrak</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv6n2harrak</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Amir Harrak</author>
                  <title level="a">Patriarchal Funerary Inscriptions in the Monastery of Rabban Hormizd: Types, Literary Origins, and Purpose</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol6/HV6N2Harrak.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Funerary Inscriptions</term>
               <term>Rabban Hormizd</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <!-- <h1>Abstract</h1> 
  <p class="Abstract"> </p>
  <br /> -->

         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak2">1. Introduction</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    Monastery of Rabban Hormizd is located, like an eagle's nest,
    on the mountain of Alqosh, about 26 miles north of Mosul in
    Iraq. This mountain is part of a chain of mountains called
    Qardû, famous for no other reason than welcoming the ark
    of Noah or his Mesopotamian counterpart after the Flood,
    according to the Babylonian priest Berossus (4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    century B.C.), and then Jewish, Christian and Islamic
    traditions.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> The monastery was founded in the early
    7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, and was named after its founder
    Hormizd, native of Persia and an important monastic figure in
    Syriac Christianity.<ref target="#FN2">2</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    monastery became the official residence of the patriarchs of
    the Assyrian Church of the East (wrongly called Nestorian)
    between 1551 and 1804, although it also served as the
    patriarchal burial site before the end of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    century. Nine such patriarchal graves are still located near
    the grave of Rabban Hormizd, in the corridor that leads to the
    cell of this holy man. Marble slabs, bearing lengthy Syriac
    inscriptions, cover these tombs. The slabs are true
    masterpieces: the inscriptions are carved in relief and the
    Estrangela calligraphy is of immense beauty. Moreover, the
    literary value of the inscriptions is of great interest. In
    them the patriarchs speak in the first person, which is not
    typical. Even more striking, though the inscriptions are
    funerary in nature, their contents are mainly confessions of
    faith, reflecting the theology and particularly the Christology
    of the Assyrian Church of the East. In spite of their seemingly
    repetitive nature, all the inscriptions will be offered here in
    translation, so as to highlight the consistency and the purpose
    that must have been employed in producing them.<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> After subjecting
    them to a literary analysis, we will attempt to explain why
    such unique inscriptions came to exist in the first place.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak3">2. The Funerary Inscriptions</head>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak4">2.1. The Inscription of Mār <hi rend="u">H</hi>enān-Īšōʿ
    (died in 1497)<ref target="#FN4">4</ref>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] In the
    name of the Living One who is not mortal, and the wealthy who
    cannot be impoverished. In the name of the Father, Son, and
    Holy Spirit.</p>
         <p>As soon as I existed—I Mār
    Šimʿōn, Catholicos-Patriarch of
    the East—I came to know God the first Light. I confessed
    and believed in His Son Jesus Christ: perfect God and perfect
    Man, two natures, two qnōmē, and one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā.</hi> I loved his
    Spirit. I paid homage to his Cross. I shared his Body and
    Blood. And I died on his hope that he would raise me up. The
    ship arrived thus far, settling at the harbor of rest. They
    buried me here in your trust, O Christ King, so that on your
    Divine Day, I may see the light of your honorable and glorious
    countenance. I departed from this life on the twentieth, in the
    month of <hi rend="italic">Šebā<hi rend="u">t</hi>
            </hi>
    (February), in the year 1808 according to the computation of
    the Greeks: Glory to God, and his mercy and compassion upon us
    forever and ever amen.</p>
         <p>Lord: Remember this servant of yours, young Mār
    <hi rend="u">H</hi>enān-Īšōʿ,
    when you come with your Kingdom. Make him worthy of the bliss,
    along with the just and righteous ones who pleased your will,
    amen.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak5">2.2. The Inscription of Mār
    Šimʿōn VI Den<hi style="u">h</hi>ā (died in 1538)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    Living One who is not mortal. In the name of the Father, Son
    and Holy Spirit.</p>
         <p>As soon as I existed—I Mār
    Šimʿōn Catholicos-Patriarch of
    the East—God the first Light, I came to know. I confessed
    and believed in his Son Jesus Christ: perfect God and perfect
    Man, two natures, two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi>, and one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi>. I loved his
    Spirit. I paid homage to his cross. I shared his Body and
    Blood. And I died on his hope that he would raise me up.</p>
         <p>At this point, the ship arrived, settling at the harbor of
    rest. They buried me here in your trust, O Christ King, so that
    on your Divine Day I may see the light of your honorable and
    glorious countenance. I departed from this life on the fifth in
    the month of <hi rend="italic">Āb</hi> (August), in the year 1849,
    according to the computation of the Greeks: Glory to God, and
    his mercy and compassion upon us forever and ever amen.</p>
         <p>The Priest Israel, foolish and sinner wrote (it).</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak6">2.3. The Inscription of
    Šimʿōn VII bar Mama (died in
    1558)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] In the
    name of the Living One, who is not mortal. In the name of the
    Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.</p>
         <p>As soon as I existed—I Mār
    Šimʿōn the Catholicos—I
    came to know God the first Light. I confessed and believed in
    his Son Jesus Christ: perfect God and perfect Man, two natures,
    two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi>, and one <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā.</hi> I loved his Spirit. I paid
    homage to his cross. I shared his Body and Blood. And I died on
    his hope that he would raise me up.</p>
         <p>At this point, the ship arrived, settling at the harbor of
    rest. And here they buried me in your trust, O Christ King, so
    that on your Divine Day, I may see the light of your honorable
    and glorious countenance. I departed from this life on the
    first of Second <hi rend="italic">Tišrī</hi> (November), in the
    evening of Wednesday, in the year 1870 of the Greeks: Glory to
    God and upon us his mercy and compassion forever and ever
    amen.</p>
         <p>In the year 1870 of Alexander, on the first of Second
    <hi rend="italic">Tišrī</hi> (November), our venerated Father
    Mār Šimʿōn the Patriarch, of
    sweet name, departed from this world of grief. May the Lord
    cause him to rejoice in the Kingdom along with the sons of
    Zabedee.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak7">2.4. The Inscription of Elijah VII (died in
    1591)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] <hi rend="italic">To
    the left side of the cross placed in the center of the top
    section of the slab:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This venerable one has served the bishopric rank for fifteen
    years brilliantly.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] <hi rend="italic">To
    the right side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This Father of ours led the patriarchal see for thirty-two
    years.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] <hi rend="italic">Along
    the frame from the left side:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the year nineteen hundred and two of Alexander, King of
    the Greeks, left the world the Patriarch Mār Elijah, on
    the twenty-sixth of <hi rend="italic">Iyyār</hi> (May) Month of roses,
    during the Week of the Apostles, on first Wednesday.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] <hi rend="italic">The
    funerary inscription inside the frame:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature. I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures and two
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi>
            <ref target="#FN5">5</ref> in one <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship and one
    Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried, but he
    rose up on the third day as is written, and he ascended to
    Heaven to his Father. I paid homage to his living and
    life-giving cross, and partook of his body and blood in the
    hope of the forgiveness of my sins. When the ship reached the
    safety that is in the grave, I left this world at the sign of
    the Most High, looking forward to the great day of
    resurrection, so that our Lord may come and have mercy on me
    through his mercy, through the "amen" of the entire church. I
    beg you, reader: Pray, requesting from the Lord, and beseech
    (him) with a pure heart, so that he may pardon my failures.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak8">2.5. The Inscription of Elijah VIII (died in
    1617)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    <hi rend="italic">Alongside the four arms of the cross, the following
    inscription appears:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In you we fight our enemy and on account of your name we
    trample on our foes. In the name of the Living One who is not
    mortal, the wealthy One who cannot be impoverished. Look toward
    him and have hope in him.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    <hi rend="italic">The main inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature. I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures and two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> in one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship
    and one Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried,
    but he rose up on the third day as is written, and he ascended
    to Heaven to his Father. I paid homage to his living and
    life-giving cross, and partook of his body and blood in the
    hope of the forgiveness of my sins.</p>
         <p>When the ship of the body reached the safety that is in the
    grave, I left this world at the sign of the Most High, on
    Monday after the Sunday (called) "Unending Glory,"<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> in the
    month of <hi rend="italic">Iyyār</hi> (May), the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of
    it, the year 1928 of the blessed Greeks. I am looking forward
    to the great day of resurrection, so that our Lord may come and
    have mercy on me through his mercy. Pray, my lord the reader,
    beg with a pure heart, implore and ask the Lord so that he may
    show pardon of my failures.</p>
         <p>The end. Glory to God and upon us his mercy and compassion
    forever and ever. Pray for the sinner, who wrote (this).</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak9">2.6. The Inscription of Elijah IX
    Šimʿōn (died in 1660)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    <hi rend="italic">Alongside the four arms of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the name of the Living One who is not mortal, the wealthy
    One who cannot be impoverished.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    <hi rend="italic">To the right side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This Father of ours led the patriarchal see for forty-three
    years.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    <hi rend="italic">The main inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature. I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures and two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> in one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship
    and one Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried,
    but he rose up on the third day as is written, and he ascended
    to Heaven to his Father. I paid homage to his living and
    life-giving cross, and partook of his body and blood in the
    hope of the forgiveness of my sins.</p>
         <p>When the ship of the body reached the safety that is in the
    grave, I left this world at the sign of the Most High, on
    Sunday of the second Week of the Apostles, in the month of
    <hi rend="italic">Hezīrān</hi> (June), the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in it, the
    year 1971 of the blessed Greeks. I am looking forward to the
    great day of resurrection, so that our Lord may come and have
    mercy on me through his mercy, through the "amen" of the entire
    Orthodox church, indeed, and forever, amen. Pray, my lord the
    reader, beseech with a pure heart, beg and ask the Lord so that
    he may pardon my failures.</p>
         <p>The end. Glory to God and upon us his mercy and compassion
    forever amen.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    <hi rend="italic">Around the slab from the right side:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Let there be good and acceptable memory before the Lord for
    our honourable Father the Catholicos, and may the base and
    foolish writer of this computation be worthy of mercy and
    forgiveness on the Last Day.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak10">2.7. The Inscription of Elijah X (died in
    1700)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    <hi rend="italic">Top Line:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the name of the Father, who is immortal.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    <hi rend="italic">On the left side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>May our Lord make an acceptable and favorable remembrance
    before him for this blessed Father of ours, who departed in a
    heavenly hope.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18]
    <hi rend="italic">On the right side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This father of ours led the patriarchal see for forty
    years.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19]
    <hi rend="italic">The main funerary inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature. I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures and two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> in one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship
    and one Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried,
    but he rose up on the third day as is written, and he ascended
    to Heaven to his Father. I paid homage to his living and life
    giving cross. I partook of his body and blood in the hope of
    the forgiveness of my sins.</p>
         <p>When the ship of the body reached the safety that is in the
    grave, I left this world at the sign of the Most High, on
    Friday before Pentecost, in the month of <hi rend="italic">Iyyār</hi>
    (May), on the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of it, the year 2011 of the
    blessed Greeks. I am looking forward to the great day of
    resurrection, so that our Lord may come and have mercy on me
    through his mercy, through the "amen" of the entire Orthodox
    church, indeed, and forever, amen. Pray, O my lord the reader,
    beseech with a pure heart, beg and ask the Lord so that he may
    pardon my failures. The end. Glory to God and upon us his mercy
    and compassion forever.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20]
    <hi rend="italic">Along the frame of the inscription from the left, then right
    and bottom sides</hi>:</p>
         <p>Our Father Mār Elijah, the glorious shepherd, died and
    departed, trusting in Christ the King in the year 2011 of the
    Greeks, a famous nation, the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in computation, in
    the month of <hi rend="italic">Iyyā</hi>r (May). The departure of this
    venerable one took place four years after he built the great
    sanctuary of the Martyrs and the baptistery of Rabban Hormizd,
    which was the year 2007.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak11">2.8. The Inscription of Elijah XI (died in
    1722)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21]
    <hi rend="italic">Above the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the name of the Living One who is immortal.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22]
    <hi rend="italic">To the left side of the upper cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>May our Lord make an acceptable and favorable remembrance
    before him for this blessed Father of ours, who departed in a
    heavenly hope.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23]
    <hi rend="italic">To the right side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>This Father of ours, worthy of blessing, led the venerable
    and elevated see of the patriarchate for twenty-three years.
    Blessed be God.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24]
    <hi rend="italic">The main funerary inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature; I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures and two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> in one
    <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship
    and one Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried,
    but he rose up on the third day as is written, and he ascended
    to Heaven to his Father. I paid homage to his living and life
    giving cross. I partook of his body and blood in the hope of
    the forgiveness of my sins.</p>
         <p>When the ship of the body reached the safety that is in the
    grave, I left this world at the sign of the Most High, while
    looking forward to the great day of resurrection, so that our
    Lord may come and have mercy on me through his mercy, through
    the "amen" of the entire Orthodox church, indeed, and forever,
    amen. Pray, O my lord the reader, beseech with a pure heart,
    beg and ask the Lord so that he may pardon my failures.</p>
         <p>The end. To God, who gives power, unceasing glory and
    honour. May he cover the deceased one with mercy and make him
    worthy of the eternal blessing. This late and honourable Father
    of ours duly led and served the elevated and sublime
    Metropolitan see for seven years.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25]
    <hi rend="italic">Along the frame of the inscription from the left
    side:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Trusting on the heavenly King, our venerable and blessed
    shepherd, Mār Elijah, died and departed, in the year 2034,
    on the fourteenth day, in the First <hi rend="italic">Kānōn</hi>
    (December). May Christ make him take delight in the bliss.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak12">2.9. The Inscription of Elijah XIII (died in
    1804)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26]
    <hi rend="italic">Top line:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>In the name of the Living One, who is immortal.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27]
    <hi rend="italic">Around the four arms of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>The cross was victorious, the cross is victorious.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28]
    <hi rend="italic">On the left side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Our venerable father Išōʿyahb
    duly led and served the respectable and sublime Metropolitan
    rank for thirty-four years.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29]
    <hi rend="italic">To the right side of the cross:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>He led and served the glorious see of Peter—the
    elevated rank of the Catholicos-Patriarch (until) the year
    2115, according to the computation of the Greek nation. May his
    remembrance be made among the just ones in the Kingdom.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30]
    <hi rend="italic">The main funerary inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Since I—Mār Elijah Patriarch of the East thanks
    to the Grace-existed, I confessed the three
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> of the Father, Son, and Holy
    Spirit—One true God and eternal Nature; I believed in His
    Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, conjointly complete God and
    complete Man, two natures in one <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi> of one sonship and one
    Will—he suffered, was crucified and was buried, and rose
    up on the third day as is written, and he ascended to Heaven to
    his Father. I paid homage to his living and life-giving cross,
    and partook of his body and blood in the hope of the
    forgiveness of my sins.</p>
         <p>When the ship of the body reached the safety that is in the
    grave, I left this world at the sign of the Most High, and they
    placed me here on the hope of resurrection. I am looking
    forward to the great day of resurrection, so that our Lord may
    come and have mercy on me through his mercy, through the "amen"
    of the entire church. Pray, O reader, and beseech with a pure
    heart, beg and ask Christ, the Living Lord, so that he may
    overlook, remiss, and pardon my failures; may he count me with
    his chosen ones, and place me on his right side on the Last
    Day.</p>
         <p>The end. To God, who gives power, unceasing glory and
    honour. May he cover the deceased one with mercy and make him
    worthy of the eternal blessing. Our venerable Father and chosen
    shepherd, Mār Elijah, died and departed on the heavenly
    trust in the year 2115 of Alexander, the Greek king. May Christ
    the King expiate his faults that are both hidden and
    undisclosed, thanks to the "amen" of the entire Orthodox Church
    and Christian nation.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31]
    <hi rend="italic">To the left side of the Funerary inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>May our Lord make an acceptable and favorable remembrance
    before him for this blessed Father of ours, who departed in a
    heavenly hope.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32]
    <hi rend="italic">On the right side of the funerary inscription:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>May the compassionate Lord associate him with Simon son of
    Yona and the Sage Virgins. Make him take delight in your bridal
    feast.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33]
    <hi rend="italic">Inside the bottom frame:</hi>
         </p>
         <p>Know, O reader, that Mār Elijah (XII), who was the
    predecessor of the present one, had served the Metropolitan
    rank for three years, led the Patriarchal see for fifty-five
    years, and died in the year 2089 of the Greeks (AD 1778). May
    forgiveness be for the writer, amen.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak13">3. Literary Analysis</head>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak14">3.1. Content</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34] The
    nine funerary inscriptions are copies of each other for the
    most part. Each can be divided into two main sections. The
    first section is a profession of faith, where the difference
    consists in the name of the patriarch making the profession.
    The names are either Simon or Elijah, and both became titles
    for successive patriarchs as early as the patriarchates of
    Simon IV (1437-1497?) of Bēth <hi rend="u">S</hi>ayda
    (near Erbil) and Elijah VI (1558-1591). The preservation of
    both names has probably been strengthened by the fact that the
    patriarchate of the church of the East became officially
    hereditary under the afore-mentioned Simon IV.<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> The latter
    sanctioned that this highest ecclesiastical authority must be
    transmitted from brother to brother or from brother to
    nephew.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35] The
    profession of faith deals first with the belief in the Trinity,
    beginning with God the Father, "the first light". The
    profession dealing with Jesus is very elaborate. He is said to
    be the Son of the Father and "complete God and complete Man".
    In other words, Jesus was truly God and truly Man, and this is
    in line with the mainstream Christian Christology. Moreover,
    all the inscriptions consistently state that Jesus was "two
    natures, two <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi> and one <hi rend="italic">par<hi rend="u">s</hi>ōpā</hi>". This belief is not a novelty of
    the patriarchs of Rabban Hormizd, since its wording is attested
    as early as the time of Mār 'Abdā (died in
    420/1),<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> and was used by other East Syriac Theologians
    until it was canonized in the synodical confession of 612, made
    at the court of the Sassanian king Khusrau Parviz.<ref target="#FN9">9</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P36"/>[36] It
    is not very clear whether or not this wording literally
    corresponds to the "two <hi rend="italic">physes</hi>, two <hi rend="italic">hypostases</hi>,
    and one <hi rend="italic">prosopon</hi>" of Nestorius. Nestorius himself was
    misunderstood as far as these terms were concerned, since the
    Council of Ephesus (431) accused him of dividing Jesus into
    "two Sons" (=two persons). Thus, other Christian Churches
    throughout the centuries considered both Nestorius and the
    theology of the Church of the East heretical. It is important
    to note in this context that the words "two
    <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi>" in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> patriarchal
    inscription were chopped from the slab sometime later, and that
    inscriptions # 4 to 9 further developed the general patriarchal
    profession. These inscriptions state that the Trinity was of
    three <hi rend="italic">qnōmē</hi>, but altogether one True God and
    one eternal nature. About Christ, they added that he was "one
    sonship" (one Son of God the Father) and "one will". Other
    details known in the Nicene Creed were also added such as "he
    (Jesus) suffered, was crucified and was buried, but he rose
    up". The mention of the Holy Spirit is made in a statement
    shared by all the inscriptions: "I loved his (Christ's)
    Spirit".</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P37"/>[37] The
    second section in the funerary inscriptions provides details
    about the death of the patriarchs. All of them compare the
    death and the rest of the body inside the grave with the
    arrival of the ship to the harbour of safety. Inscriptions # 4
    to 9 use the analogy "body-ship". The patriarchs died on the
    hope to see the "radiant countenance" of Jesus on the day of
    the resurrection. Though here the wording is probably biblical
    (see Ps 4:6 and elsewhere in the Psalter), one cannot resist
    its echo in the native concept <hi rend="italic">melammu</hi> in Mesopotamia.
    In line with the profession of faith made in the first person,
    the deceased patriarchs provide the day, month, and the
    Seleucid year of their individual "departure from this present
    life".</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P38"/>[38]
    Inscriptions # 1 to 3 end with a few words made by the scribes,
    either a wish for the deceased patriarch for final rest, or a
    "signature" of the writer ("Priest Israel, sinful and foolish;"
    inscription # 2). Inscriptions # 4 to 9 are also typical in
    that a concluding request is made to the reader to pray for the
    soul of the deceased speaker, and that the prayer not only
    rhymes, but also that each stanza consists of six
    syllables.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak15">3.2. Genre</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P39"/>[39] The
    inscriptions of Rabban Hormizd were, quite obviously, written
    and erected sometime after the burial of the patriarchs. The
    problem is that the deceased patriarchs speak of their own
    death, giving pertinent chronological details, such as the day,
    month and year of their passing. The profession of faith could
    have originally been some kind of a last will in which the
    patriarchs expressed their basic theological beliefs. In this
    case, the monastic community would have inscribed the last will
    on tombstones, following the death of each patriarch.
    Nonetheless, the speech of the patriarchs in the first person,
    including chronological details of death and burial, is a
    literary device that came to the attention of the ecclesiastic
    and monastic community of Rabban Hormizd.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P40"/>[40]
    Funerary inscriptions with the speech in the first person are
    rather rare in Syriac Christianity, though they are widely
    known in the Classical and Near Eastern worlds. The earliest
    case is the Aramaic inscription of Agbar, the priest of the
    moon-god in Nerab (near Aleppo), dated to the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    century BC. In it he says:</p>
         <quote>
      On the day of my death, my mouth was not shut from (saying)
      words, and with my own eyes I saw my children of the fourth
      generation weeping for me.<ref target="#FN10">10</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P41"/>[41]
    Tabnit and Eshmun'azar, kings of Sidon during the early
    5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century BC, both begged the readers not to open
    their sarcophagi and disturb them:</p>
         <quote>
      I have been snatched away before my time… I am lying
      in this casket and this grave, in a place which I myself
      built" (Eshmun'azar).<ref target="#FN11">11</ref> Do not, do not open it (i.e.
      sarcophagus), and do not disturb me (Tabnit).<ref target="#FN12">12</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P42"/>[42] In
    Greek and Latin epitaphs, the speech of the dead in the first
    person is well documented. True, most of the cases consist of
    stereotyped formulae, all having death as the main theme, or
    treating it as a lesson to learn. A good example in this
    category is a Greek epitaph found in Rome and dated to the
    Christian era:</p>
         <quote>
      Wayfarer, do not pass by my epitaph, but stand and listen,
      and then when you have learned the truth, proceed…
    </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P43"/>[43]
    After telling the reader that there was no life after death
    (note the anti-Christian polemic), the dead concluded:</p>
         <quote>
      Now withdraw, wayfarer, so that you will not think that, even
      though dead, I talk too much!<ref target="#FN13">13</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P44"/>[44] The
    following Greek statement, like most of the Greek and Latin
    epitaphs, as well as the early Aramaic and Phoenician formulae,
    curses the one who disturbs the grave, and wishes blessings
    upon the one who does not harm it: "Whoever does not harm my
    gravestone, may he have the same fate as I."<ref target="#FN14">14</ref> (We assume that
    the lady-speaker in this instance had a positive fate.) There
    are also several Greek and Latin epitaphs that contain
    biographical details not necessarily related to death, a
    literary style reminiscent of the patriarchal
    inscriptions.<ref target="#FN15">15</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P45"/>[45]
    Though few Syriac funerary inscriptions exist in which the dead
    talk in the first person, the numerous cases attested in
    Aramaic, Phoenician, Greek and Latin epitaphs strongly suggest
    that the device was rather common in antiquity and in medieval
    times, and hence, the patriarchal funerary inscriptions are not
    unique in this regard. What makes the patriarchal inscriptions
    unique, however, is the fact that they contain a theological
    summa, which, though concise, covers the Christian dogma
    concerning the Trinity and, most importantly, Christology. Such
    highly technical details seem unusual and even unwarranted in
    the sepulchral context. A historical survey of the time between
    the end of the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and beginning of the
    19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> centuries may be able to explain these
    details.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak16">4. Historical Analysis</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P46"/>[46] The
    middle of the second millennium witnessed events that heavily
    and negatively affected Syriac Christianity. In 1445 the union
    of the so-called "Nestorians" of Cyprus with the Roman Catholic
    Church was undertaken. The long-lived Mār
    Šimʿōn Bēth <hi rend="u">S</hi>ayda (1437-1476), patriarch of the so-called
    "Nestorian" Church, took notice of this event. During the
    second half of the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, the forced
    Latinization of the "Nestorian" Christians of Malabar by the
    Portuguese invaders also took place and the shift of a large
    part of Malabar to Rome was also felt in Mesopotamia.
    Concomitantly, a forceful attempt to carve a Roman Catholic
    entity out of the Church of the East also happened in the
    heartland of Assyria. The patriarchs of the latter Church were
    forced to bitterly admit to new historical realities.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P47"/>[47] As
    mentioned above, it was Patriarch Mār
    Šimʿōn Bēth <hi rend="u">S</hi>ayda who made the East Syriac patriarchate
    hereditary, on the basis of an accidental patriarchal
    succession of related individuals, beginning with Patriarch
    Timothy II (1318-1332). One of the followers of Mār
    Šimʿōn Bēth <hi rend="u">S</hi>ayda, who took the name Mār
    Šimʿōn too, is the speaker of the
    first funerary inscription under study. Not much is known about
    the latter and his dates are subject to controversy. He was
    followed by Elijah V (1502-1503),<ref target="#FN16">16</ref> whose successor was
    Šimʿōn VI<ref target="#FN17">17</ref> (1504-38), author
    of the second funerary inscription in Rabban Hormizd. He
    himself was followed by Šimʿōn
    VII bar Mama (1551-1558), author of the 3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> funerary
    inscription.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P48"/>[48]
    Šimʿōn VII bar Mama witnessed
    with much disappointment the secession of a sizable East Syriac
    community that signed its union with the Catholic church of
    Rome. The bishops of Erbil, Salamas, and Adhurbaijan revolted
    against Šimʿōn VII, electing the
    Abbot of the monastery of Rabban Hormizd, Sūlāqā
    by name, to lead the newly born uniate church.
    Sūlāqā was established Patriarch in Rome in 1553
    by Pope Julius III, after the former presented to the Pope his
    confession of faith in line with the theology of the Roman
    Catholic Church. Then he returned to the Near East, accompanied
    by a Roman Catholic delegation made up of three Maltese
    clergymen, Ambrosius Boutitic (the Pope's delegate), Father
    Antonio Zahra and a third one named Mattai, and set his seceded
    patriarchal seat in Amida (Diyār Bakr, in south-east
    Turkey). The bitterness that the division of a long-lived and
    once glorious church created among its leaders and the faithful
    at large, and the subsequent assassination of the uniate
    patriarch Sūlāqā at the hands of the Ottoman
    lord of ʿAmādiyya Pasha Hussein Beg in
    1555, are subjects beyond the scope of the present paper.
    Suffice to say that the history of the East Syriac Church in
    following centuries would be dominated by controversies and
    difficulties generated by the union with Rome of portions of
    this old church.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P49"/>[49]
    While Šimʿōn VII bar Mama must
    have been a staunch opponent of union with Rome, Elijah VII
    (1576-1591), the author of the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> funerary
    inscription, sent his confession of faith to Pope Sextus V in
    1586, who judged it Nestorian in tendency. The Pope's position
    explains why the same Elijah left on his own grave an
    inscription declaring the traditional nature of his Christian
    faith. It is interesting to note here that the expanded
    profession of faith found in five funerary inscriptions of
    Rabban Hormizd is first detected in the grave of this
    Elijah.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref> Elijah VIII (1591-1617), the author of the
    5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> funerary inscription, succeeded Elijah VII.
    While Rome believed that he too took steps toward union, he in
    fact refused to compromise his "Nestorian" faith before the
    Roman Catholic delegation that met with him in the monastery of
    Mār Pethion (between Mardin and Amida) in 1615. The
    delegation was so disappointed with him that it declared that
    there was not one single true Roman Catholic in Diyār
    Bakr!</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P50"/>[50]
    Elijah IX (1617-1660) does not seem to have had any interest in
    union either. When he met two Franciscan Friars in 1629, he
    reiterated that his profession of faith echoed the principles
    of the Catholic faith; but then he denied the Virgin Mary her
    title "Mother of God", insisting that she was a mere human
    being. He added that that was the faith of his forefathers, and
    that he would die for it. He even claimed that the members of
    the uniate church usually returned to their original faith and
    kept it to death. Though this may not be true of every member
    of the uniate church, it was certainly true of Patriarch
    Elijah, since his profession of faith is inscribed on the
    marble covering his very grave, as is seen in the
    6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> funerary inscription above. The 15-year-old
    nephew of Elijah IX followed him on the patriarchal throne,
    taking the name Elijah X Yō<hi rend="u">h</hi>annā Marrōgui (1660-1700). In 1669 he
    wrote a letter to Pope Clemens IX, signed by him and three of
    his Metropolitans; in it he asked the Pope to help deliver his
    two envoys, whom he had sent to Rome but who fell in the hands
    of pirates. His correspondence with Rome may be seen as a sign
    that Elijah X was open to the idea of joining the Catholic
    Church but in his funerary inscription, the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in
    this article, he confessed none other than the faith of his own
    church.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P51"/>[51] His
    follower Elijah XI Marrōgui (1700-1722) bitterly opposed
    his Metropolitan of Amida when the latter submitted to the
    Roman Catholic faith in 1672 at the hands of the Capuchin
    Friars. His confession of faith found in the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    inscription indicated that he was as attached to his
    "Nestorian" faith as his predecessor. The last patriarch
    commemorated in Rabban Hormizd is Elijah XIII
    Išōʿyahb (1778-1804), owner of
    the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and last funerary inscription. He discussed
    with his predecessor the possibility of union with Rome, and
    indeed as soon as he became Patriarch, he declared his
    allegiance to the See of Peter. But when he obtained his
    confirmation as Patriarch from the Ottoman Sultan, he returned
    to his old faith, a fact that led the people of Mosul to depose
    him from the patriarchal throne with the help of European
    missionaries. Thanks to the protection of
    Ismaʿīl Pasha of Amadiyya, he kept his
    control over the East Syriac dioceses of the mountains.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak17">5. Conclusion</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P52"/>[52] In
    the previous section we surveyed the bilateral relations that
    existed between the Roman Catholic Church and the Assyrian
    Church of the East. The relations were mostly marked by mutual
    mistrust, misunderstanding of each other's religious beliefs,
    and sometimes even violence. One can then understand why the
    patriarchs, who experienced first hand these difficult
    relations, insisted on having their traditional theological
    beliefs inscribed on stone and placed on their graves. There is
    even a correlation between the funerary inscription of Elijah
    IX and his public declaration before the Franciscan Friars in
    1629 that he would die for the faith of his forefathers. Since
    funerary inscriptions bearing confessions of faith are not
    frequent in Syriac Christianity, one can safely conclude that
    the inscriptions of the Assyrian patriarchs originated in
    historical events that compromised their religious beliefs as
    well as their independence.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak18">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> A. Harrak, “Tales about Sennacherib: The
    Contribution of the Syriac Sources,” in P.M. Daviau et
    al., <hi rend="italic">The World of the Arameans: Studies in Honour of P.-E.
    Dion</hi>, vol. III, Sheffield 2001, pp. 168-189.<ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">The histories of Rabban Hôrmîzd the
    Persian and Rabban Bar-`Idtâ</hi>:  Syriac texts
    edited and translated by E.A. Wallis Budge (New York: AMS
    Press, 1976; reprint of the 1902 edition). <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> A full edition of the inscriptions, with
    photographs and English translations, will be found in my
    <hi rend="italic">Corpus of Syriac and Garshuni Inscriptions in Iraq</hi>, to
    be published in Paris late in 2003 or at the beginning of
    2004.<ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> This date is problematic in light of other sources;
    see Vosté, <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 43 (1930) pp.
    284-5.<ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> The expression was chiseled at a later
    date.<ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> The Sunday before Pentecost.<ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> But note that the East Syriac (Chaldean) patriarchs
    also adopted the same patriarchal name, in this case Joseph,
    from Joseph I to Joseph IV (1681-1781).<ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Chronique de Seert XIII</hi>, p. 548.<ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> J. Chabot, <hi rend="italic">Synodicon Orientale</hi> pp.
    564-582.<ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> M. Lidzbarski, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
    nordsemitischen Epigraphik</hi>, II: Tafeln, (Weimer, 1898), pl.
    XXV:2 lines 4-6.<ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> Lidzbarski, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch</hi>, pl. IV:1 lines
    2-3.<ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> Lidzbarski, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch,</hi> pl. IV:2 lines
    5-6.<ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> R. Lattimore, <hi rend="italic">Themes in Greek and Latin
    Epitaphs</hi>, Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1962, p.
    75.<ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> Lattimore, <hi rend="italic">Themes,</hi> p. 107.<ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Lattimore, <hi rend="italic">Themes</hi>, pp. 266ff.<ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> Elijah V was buried in the church of Saint
    Meskenta in Mosul, though no remains of his burial are
    found.<ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> The order of the various patriarchs bearing
    the name Šimʿōn is confusing and
    in this article I follow the list of J.-M. Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Oriens
    Christianus Novus: Répertoire des diocèses
    syriaques orientaux et occidentaux</hi> (Beirut 1993), pp.
    36-39.<ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> Vosté, who offered an edition of the
    inscriptions of Rabban Hormizd, wrote: “A noter dans
    cette confession, outre l’erreur nestorienne des deux
    qenōmē (hypostases=personnes) dans le Christ,
    l’erreur monothélite clairement
    exprimée.” <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 43 (1930), p.
    290. One would understand the historical misunderstanding as
    far as the theological nomenclature used by the East Syriac
    Church is concerned, but it is interesting to compare between
    Vosté’s attitude and that of the Roman delegation
    in 1615.<ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Harrak19">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Budge, E.A. Wallis. (tr.) <hi rend="italic">The
    histories of Rabban Hôrmîzd the Persian and Rabban
    Bar-ʿIdtâ</hi>:  Syriac texts
    edited and translated by (New York: AMS Press, 1976; reprint of
    the 1902 edition).</p>
         <p>Chabot, J. <hi rend="italic">Synodicon Orientale</hi>
    (Paris, 1902)</p>
         <p>Fiey, J.-M. <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus
    Novus: Répertoire des diocèses syriaques
    orientaux et occidentaux</hi> (Beirut 1993).</p>
         <p>Harrak, A. “Tales about
    Sennacherib: The Contribution of the Syriac Sources,” in
    P.M. Daviau et al., <hi rend="italic">The World of the Arameans: Studies in
    Honour of P.-E. Dion</hi>, vol. III, (Sheffield, 2001).</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Corpus of Syriac and
    Garshuni Inscriptions in Iraq</hi>, Forthcoming.</p>
         <p>Lattimore, R. <hi rend="italic">Themes in Greek and
    Latin Epitaphs</hi>, Urbana: University of Illinois Press,
    1962.</p>
         <p>Lidzbarski, M. <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
    nordsemitischen Epigraphik</hi>, II: Tafeln, (Weimer, 1898).</p>
         <p>Jacques Marie Vosté, "Les
    inscriptions de Rabban Hormizd et de N.-D. des Semences
    près d'Alqoš, Iraq." <hi rend="italic">Le Muséon</hi> 43
    (1930): 263-316.</p>
         <p>Addai Scher &amp; R. Griveau,
    <hi rend="italic">Histoire nestorienne inédite (Chronique de
    Séert)(Fin)</hi> (PO XIII,4; Paris, 1918) [Arabic text
    and French translation]</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>