<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Christoph Luxenberg (ps.) Die syro-aramaeische Lesart des Koran; Ein Beitrag zur Entschlüsselung der Qur’ānsprache. Berlin, Germany: Das Arabische Buch, First Edition, 2000. Pp. ix + 306, bibliography on pp. 307-311, no index. Paperback, Euros 29.70, no price available in US Dollars. ISBN 3-86093-274-8.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Robert R.</forename>
                  <surname>Phenix jr. and cornelia b. horn</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>University of St. Thomas</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>January 2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv6n1prphenixhorn</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Robert R. PHENIX Jr. and Cornelia B. HORN</author>
                  <title level="a">Christoph Luxenberg (ps.) Die syro-aramaeische Lesart des Koran; Ein Beitrag zur Entschlüsselung der Qur’ānsprache. Berlin, Germany: Das Arabische Buch, First Edition, 2000. Pp. ix + 306, bibliography on pp. 307-311, no index. Paperback, Euros 29.70, no price available in US Dollars. ISBN 3-86093-274-8.</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol6/HV6N1PRPhenixHorn.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Qur`an</term>
               <term>philology</term>
               <term>Luxenberg</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Not in
    the history of commentary on the Qur’ān has a work
    like this been produced. Similar works can only be found in the
    body of text-critical scholarship on the Bible. From its method
    to its conclusions on the language and content of the
    Qur’ān, Luxenberg’s study has freed scholars
    from the defective tradition of the Islamic commentators.
    Whether or not Luxenberg is correct in every detail, with one
    book he has brought exegetical scholarship of the
    Qur’ān to the “critical turn” that
    biblical commentators took more than a century ago. This work
    forces a choice on all exegetes of the Qur’ān:
    either to accept the scientific method of philology and its
    value in producing a clearer text of the Qur’ān, or
    to remain in the darkness. No longer will scholars of the first
    rank be able to hide behind any notion that the Islamic
    tradition is mostly reliable, as though it were immune to the
    human error that pervades the transmission of every written
    artifact. If biblical scholarship is any indication, the future
    of Qur’ānic studies is more or less decided by this
    work.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The book
    presents the thesis, sources, method, and examples of its
    application in eighteen sections. Sections one through ten
    cover the background, method, and the application of that
    method to unlocking the etymology and meaning of the word
    <hi rend="italic">Qur’ān</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             The transcription of Arabic and Syriac letters
    mostly follows the standard transcription with the following
    difference: Arabic <hi rend="italic">dad</hi> and <hi rend="italic">za</hi> are written
    <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z.</hi> respectively; Arabic kh in
    <hi rend="italic">khalifa</hi> and Syriac <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>et</hi> is
    written <hi rend="italic">x</hi> except in widely recognized words (like
    <hi rend="italic">khalifa</hi>). 
         </p>
                </note> which Luxenberg argues is the key
    to understanding the text as a whole. Sections eleven through
    eighteen follow the conclusions set out in the first half by
    arguing solutions to several problematic expressions throughout
    the text. These include lexical, morphological and syntactic
    problems that illustrate the basic principles underlying the
    many errors in the transmission of the Qur’ān
    (11-14) and the extension of the method to examine problems
    that create misunderstandings of thematic material throughout
    the text (15-16). Luxenberg then applies his conclusions to an
    exegesis of suras 108 and 96. A synopsis of the work follows in
    section 18.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    Luxenberg aims to make available a selection of findings from
    an ongoing investigation into the language of the
    Qur’ān so that a preliminary discussion about
    methods of text linguistics as well as about the implications
    of the findings of such methods on the content of the
    Qur’ān might begin without waiting for the complete
    work. This work is only a sketch, developed with a heuristic
    and supported by extensive evidence. Luxenberg is aware that
    many features of a standard philological presentation are
    missing. These he promises in the final study.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] In the
    Foreword, Luxenberg summarizes the cultural and linguistic
    importance of written Syriac for the Arabs and for the
    Qur’ān. At the time of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad, Arabic was not a written language.
    Syro-Aramaic or Syriac was the language of written
    communication in the Near East from the second to the seventh
    centuries A.D. Syriac, a dialect of Aramaic, was the language
    of Edessa, a city-state in upper Mesopotamia. While Edessa
    ceased to be a political entity, its language became the
    vehicle of Christianity and culture, spreading throughout Asia
    as far as Malabar and eastern China. Until the rise of the
    Qur’ān, Syriac was the medium of wider communication
    and cultural dissemination for Arameans, Arabs, and to a lesser
    extent Persians. It produced the richest literary expression in
    the Near East from the fourth century (Aphrahat and Ephraem)
    until it was replaced by Arabic in the seventh and eighth
    centuries. Of importance is that the Syriac – Aramaic
    literature and the cultural matrix in which that literature
    existed was almost exclusively Christian. Part of
    Luxenberg’s study shows that Syriac influence on those
    who created written Arabic was transmitted through a Christian
    medium, the influence of which was fundamental.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5]
    Luxenberg then gives an etymology of the word
    “Syriac,” and notes that the language is mentioned
    with importance in the earliest <hi rend="italic">hadīth</hi> literature
    which reports that Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad instructed
    his followers to know Syriac (as well as Hebrew). This can only
    be the case because these were the literary forerunners of
    written Arabic. Luxenberg conceived his study to test the
    following hypothesis: since written Syriac was the written
    language of the Arabs, and since it informed the cultural
    matrix of the Near East, much the same way that Akkadian did
    before it and Arabic after it, then it is very likely that
    Syriac exerted some influence on those who developed written
    Arabic. Luxenberg further proposes, that these Arabs were
    Christianized, and were participants in the Syriac Christian
    liturgy.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] Western
    scholars have since the nineteenth century been aware of the
    influence of foreign languages, particularly of the dialect of
    Aramaic called Syriac, on the vocabulary of the
    Qur’ān. Luxenberg assembles all of the pieces of
    this line of research into a systematic examination of the
    Arabic of the Qur’ān in order to provide a general
    solution to its many textual difficulties. The conclusions
    drawn about the source of the Qur’ān, its
    transmission history from Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad to
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān, and its thematic content rest on
    arguments drawn from evidence collected and examined through
    the tools of philological and text-critical methods. No part of
    the method rests on a blind acceptance of religious or
    traditional assumptions of any kind, especially on the part of
    the Arabian commentators. Until now, Western critical
    commentators of the first rank have not been critical enough in
    this regard and Luxenberg directly and indirectly through his
    conclusions proves that their trust was betrayed. Hence any
    argument that seeks to prove Luxenberg’s findings
    incorrect cannot assume that the earliest Arabian commentators
    understood correctly the grammar and lexicon of the Arabic of
    the Qur’ān. This is an important contribution of the
    study.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7]
    Luxenberg then presents the Islamic tradition about the early
    transmission history of the Qur’ān. According to
    that tradition, <hi rend="italic">khalifa</hi>
            <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān ibn
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Affan (A.D. 644-656) first assembled into a single
    book the written record of the utterances of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad (A.D. 570-632). The Qur’ān is the
    first book of the Arabic language of which scholars are aware.
    It is important because it is the basis for written Arabic, the
    language of a sophisticated Medieval civilization, and because
    for Muslims it is the source of all religious expression,
    theology, and law, and is held to be God’s revelation to
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad. For non-Muslims, it is an
    important literary artifact, and deserves to be studied from a
    historical as well as a philological perspective.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] It is
    the latter that Luxenberg follows. The text of the
    Qur’ān has been largely unexplored with any
    philological method. Western commentators have followed Islamic
    tradition rather than use the reference tools and techniques.
    Luxenberg gives a brief description of the findings from the
    important work on Qur’ānic philology in the West.
    Scholarship has been increasingly aware of the presence in the
    Qur’ān of foreign terms and references to foreign
    historical events and that Aramaic dialects contributed most of
    these. However, because western scholars maintained the
    technically outdated and unscientific approach of Islamic
    exegesis, the significance of these findings has had to wait
    until the present study.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Section
    two is little more than a statement that Luxenberg’s
    study is independent of both Arabian as well as Western
    research precisely because his method does not rely on the
    explanations of the Arabian commentators, but rather on Arabic
    and Syriac lexical tools as well as comparative Semitic
    linguistics. His chief source among the Arabian commentators is
    the earliest commentary on the Qur’ān, that of
    <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī.<note place="foot" xml:id="FN2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Abū Ja<hi rend="sup">c</hi>far Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad bin Jarīr a<hi rend="u">t</hi>-<hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī,
    <hi rend="italic">Jāmi<hi rend="sup">c</hi> al-bayān <hi rend="sup">c</hi>an
    ta’wīl al-Qur’ān</hi> (Cairo,
    3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> ed., 1968). 
         </p>
                </note>
            <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī had no Arabic dictionary that he could
    consult, and so he had to rely on oral tradition and on
    commentators closer to the time of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad whose lost works his citations in part
    preserve. The <hi rend="italic">Lisān</hi>, the most extensive lexicon of
    the Arabic language,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Abū l-Fa<hi rend="u">d</hi>l Jamāl
    ad-Dīn Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad bin Mukarram
    al-Ifriqī al-Mi<hi rend="u">s</hi>rī bin
    Man<hi rend="u">z</hi>ūr, <hi rend="italic">Lisān
    al-<hi rend="sup">c</hi>arab</hi> (Beirut, 1955). 
         </p>
                </note> the Western translations and commentaries
    of Bell,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Richard Bell, <hi rend="italic">The Qur’ān; Translated,
    with a critical rearrangement of the Surahs</hi>, vol. 1
    (Edinburgh, 1937), vol. 2 (Edinburgh, 1939). 
         </p>
                </note> Blachère,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Régis Blachère, <hi rend="italic">Le Coran (traduit
    de l’arabe)</hi> (Paris, 1957). 
         </p>
                </note> and Paret,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Rudi Paret, <hi rend="italic">Der Koran; Übersetzung</hi>
    (Stuttgart, Berlin, Cologne, Mainz, 2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed., 1982).
    
         </p>
                </note> the Syriac
    dictionaries of Payne Smith<note place="foot" xml:id="FN7" n="7">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             R. Payne Smith, ed., <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus Syriacus</hi>,
    vol. 1 (Oxford, 1879), vol. 2 (Oxford, 1901). 
         </p>
                </note> and Brockelmann,<note place="foot" xml:id="FN8" n="8">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Carl Brockelmann, <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Syriacum</hi> (Halle in
    Saxony, 1928). 
         </p>
                </note> and the
    <hi rend="italic">Vocabulaire Chaldéen – Arabique</hi> of
    Mannā<note place="foot" xml:id="FN9" n="9">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Jaques Eugène Mannā, <hi rend="italic">Vocabulaire
    Chaldéen – Arabique</hi> (Mossul, 1900); reprinted
    with new appendix by Raphael J. Bidawid (Beirut, 1975).
    
         </p>
                </note> are the other primary reference works.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] The
    use of these materials is placed in the service of the method
    in section three. Luxenberg states that the primary goal of the
    study was to clarify expressions that were unclear to the three
    Western commentators. The discovery of many aramaisms led
    Luxenberg to check these in passages that were supposedly not
    contentious according to the Western exegetes. The examination
    of these passages was all the more justified when the
    explanations of the Arabian commentators (which the Western
    scholars largely followed) did not at all fit the context. For
    example, <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī did not have any
    lexicographical tools and only occasionally cites a verse from
    pre-Qur’ānic Arabic poetry as support for his
    interpretation of a given expression. In such cases the margin
    of error is wide because the context for these pre-Islamic
    poems is often difficult to ascertain. Even so, in many
    instances the Western commentators accept these explanations
    uncritically.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Using his philological method Luxenberg attempts to establish
    the historical context for the Qur’ān in order to
    provide a systematic approach to solving text-critical
    problems. His base text is the canonical edition of the
    Qur’ān published in Cairo in 1923-24, taken without
    the vowel marks. The advantage of this edition over earlier
    ones is that it sought to base its readings on a comparison of
    earlier Arabic commentators. The most important feature of this
    work is that the redactors attempted to fix the diacritical
    points that distinguish between possible readings of a single
    letter. Luxenberg does in many cases emend these points, but
    does so following a clear and detailed method. When he has a
    clear choice between two variant readings, <hi rend="italic">lectio
    difficilior</hi> prevails. Only when the context of an
    expression is manifestly unclear, and the Arabian commentators
    have no plausible explanation, does Luxenberg explore a
    solution that involves changing one or more diacritical points
    in the Cairene edition.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Luxenberg clearly outlines the heuristic. Starting from those
    passages that are unclear to the Western commentators, the
    method runs as follows. First check if there is a plausible
    explanation in <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī that the
    Western commentators overlooked. If not, then check whether the
    <hi rend="italic">Lisān</hi> records a meaning unknown to <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī and his earlier sources. If this turns
    up nothing, check if the Arabic expression has a homonymous
    root in Syriac with a different meaning which fits the context.
    In many cases, Luxenberg found that the Syriac word with its
    meaning makes more sense. It is to be noted, that these first
    steps of the heuristic do not emend the consonantal text of the
    Cairene edition of the Qur’ān.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] If
    these steps do not avail, then see if changing one or more
    diacritical marks results in an Arabic expression that makes
    more sense. Luxenberg found that many cases are shown to be
    misreadings of one consonant for another. If not, then change
    the diacritical point(s) and then check if there is a
    homonymous Syriac root with a plausible meaning.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] If
    there is still no solution, check if the Arabic is a calque of
    a Syriac expression. Calques are of two kinds: morphological
    and semantic. A morphological calque is a borrowing that
    preserves the structure of the source word but uses the
    morphemes of the target language. For example, German
    <hi rend="italic">Fernsehen</hi> is just the morphemes <hi rend="italic">tele</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">visio</hi> of English “television” translated
    into their German equivalents. A semantic calque assigns the
    borrowed meaning to a word that did not have the meaning
    previously, but which is otherwise synonymous with the source
    word.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] In
    section four, Luxenberg presents the development of the Arabic
    script and its central importance to the transmission history
    of the Qur’ān. He demonstrates that there were
    originally only six letters to distinguish some twenty-six
    sounds. The letters were gradually distinguished by points
    written above or below each letter. The Arabic alphabet used in
    the Qur’ān began as a shorthand, a mnemonic device
    not intended as a complete key to the sounds of the language.
    Luxenberg concludes that the transmission of the text from
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad was not likely an oral
    transmission by memory, contrary to one dominant claim of
    Islamic tradition.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] That
    tradition preserves different stories about the oral
    transmission of the Qur’ān and Luxenberg assembles
    these in section five. According to Islamic tradition, the
    Qur’ān was transmitted in part by an uninterrupted
    chain of "readers," Arabic <hi rend="italic">qurrā’</hi>,
    contemporaries of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad such as ibn
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Abbas (d. 692) and maintained by such early
    authorities as Anas ibn Mālik (d. 709). Contradicting this
    is another tradition, that <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān obtained the
    "leaves" of the Qur’ān from Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad's widow Hafsa, and assembled them into a
    codex. The Islamic tradition is unable to pinpoint when the
    diacritical points were finally "fixed," a process that
    unfolded over three hundred years, according to
    Blachère. The reason for the difficulty in tracing the
    development of the Qur’ān before
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān is, as <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī points out, that <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān
    destroyed all manuscripts with variant readings of the
    consonantal text which disagreed with his final recension.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] In
    section six Luxenberg presents the Islamic tradition derived
    from Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad himself concerning the
    indeterminate nature of the Qur’ān's consonantal
    text, of which two stories are recorded by <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī. The gist of these is that
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad sanctioned any reading of the
    text that did not blatantly change a curse into a blessing or
    vice-versa. Luxenberg argues that these obviously later stories
    reflect what must be a faint recollection of the indeterminacy
    of the Arabic alphabet.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] In
    section seven, Luxenberg outlines how Islamic tradition
    resolved the doubts due to Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad's
    “flexibility” concerning the text that arose among
    the first commentators. In this section, Luxenberg applies his
    heuristic method on the Qur’ān to show that the
    Qur’ān itself gives evidence that the tradition of
    the seven readings, Arabic <hi rend="italic">sab<hi rend="sup">c</hi>at a<hi rend="u">h</hi>ruf</hi>, which were permitted to Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad out of recognition of the many dialects of
    Arabic, is closely connected with the seven vowel signs of
    Estrangeli, the writing system developed by speakers of East
    Syriac. This system uses dots above and below the letters,
    similar to the dots used in Arabic to distinguish consonants.
    <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī also knows of the tradition
    that there were five readings, which he suggests correspond to
    the five vowel signs of West Syriac. The vowel signs of the
    West Syriac system are the source of the three vowel signs used
    in Classical Arabic.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] The
    rest of the section draws on personal names of Biblical origin
    in the Qur’ān to demonstrate that the so-called
    Arabic <hi rend="italic">matres lectionis, alif, waw,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ya,</hi> must
    also be polyvalent. Luxenberg points out that Islamic tradition
    admits a reading of the <hi rend="italic">mater</hi> for long /a/ in certain
    instances as /e/ because this pronunciation was a peculiarity
    of the Arabic of Mecca. Luxenberg shows that the term
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>arf</hi>, “sign” must
    also carry a meaning synonymous to <hi rend="italic">qirā’at</hi>,
    "(way of) reading" and that this is not only supplying the
    vowels in an unvocalized text, but also supplying the
    diacritical points that distinguish consonants. It is only
    gradually that these diacritical points became fixed so that
    consonants came to have just one reading. This process of
    determining the value of each letter of the Qur’ān
    unfolded over some three hundred years. This is known from the
    oldest manuscripts of the Qur’ān which do not have
    the diacritical points distinguishing readings of a single
    consonant. By the time these became commonly used, Arabian
    commentators were no longer aware that many words were either
    straight Aramaic or were calques peculiar to Meccan Arabic.
    From this resulted the difficulties that the Qur’ān
    posed to even the earliest Arabian commentators.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20]
    Section eight briefly outlines the difficulties facing a
    critical translator. Luxenberg agrees with Paret's general
    assessment of the difficulties, which include many unclear
    words and expressions, contradictory explanations in the
    Arabian tradition, and lack of a <hi rend="italic">textus receptus</hi> with
    fixed diacritical points, such as for the Hebrew Bible.
    Moreover, even the earliest Islamic commentators are divided
    over many passages and offer sometimes over a dozen possible
    interpretations, many mutually exclusive and equally
    plausible.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21]
    Section nine discusses the proposition, which the
    Qur’ān itself asserts and which is a basic element
    of Islam, that the Qur’ān was revealed in Arabic. In
    particular, the proposition that the origin of the
    Qur’ān, the <hi rend="italic">umm kitāb</hi> (lit.
    “mother of [the] book”), is in heaven or with God
    and is the direct and immediate pre-image of the Arabic text
    presents the strongest dogmatic challenge to Luxenberg’s
    assertion that the Arabic of the Qur’ān is in large
    measure not Arabic at all, at least not in the sense the
    Arabian commentators understood it. The language of the
    Qur’ān is the Arabic dialect of the tribe of
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad, the Quraysh, who were located
    in Mecca. This does not rule out the possibility that this
    dialect was heavily influenced by Aramaic, and Syriac in
    particular. Luxenberg maintains that the Islamic tradition
    alludes to such an influence. <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī follows the tradition attributed to
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad that a scholar must seek wisdom
    "be it in China" and exhorts the philologists of the
    Qur’ān, the <hi rend="italic">ahl al-lisān</hi>, to seek sound
    philological evidence from wherever it may come in order that
    the Qur’ān be clearly explained to all. Luxenberg
    undertakes in the subsequent chapters to mine the wisdom of
    this advice.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22]
    Luxenberg proceeds in section ten to the heart of the matter:
    an analysis of the word “Qur’ān.” He
    sets out the argument that <hi rend="italic">qur’ān</hi> derives
    from the Syriac <hi rend="italic">qeryānā</hi>, a technical term from
    the Christian liturgy that means "lectionary," the fixed
    biblical readings used at the Divine Liturgy throughout the
    year. His claim rests on variations in the spelling of the word
    attested in early manuscripts. The word
    <hi rend="italic">qeryānā</hi> had been written without <hi rend="italic">hamza</hi>
    by Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad, according to one early
    witness and Luxenberg argues that this reflects a Syriac
    influence. According to Islamic tradition, Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad's dialect pronounced the <hi rend="italic">hamza</hi>, the
    glottal stop, "weak." Indeed, the arabophone Aramaic Christians
    of Syria and Mesopotamia pronounce the <hi rend="italic">hamza</hi> in the same
    way, approximately /y/. Furthermore, the Arabic-Syriac lexica
    which preserve several pre-Islamic variant readings of Arabic
    words, give for the Syriac word <hi rend="italic">qeryānā</hi> both
    <hi rend="italic">qur’ān</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">quryān</hi>.
    Luxenberg posits the development of the spelling of this word
    as follows: <hi rend="italic">qeryān</hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic">qurān</hi>, written
    without <hi rend="italic">alif</hi>, then <hi rend="italic">qurān</hi> written with
    <hi rend="italic">alif</hi>, and finally <hi rend="italic">qur’ān</hi>, with an
    intrusive <hi rend="italic">hamza</hi>. The commentators were no longer aware
    that <hi rend="italic">ya</hi> could represent /ā/, a use extensively
    attested in the writing of third-weak verbs. The rest of the
    section presents clarifications of other unclear passages where
    the obscurity arose from the same phenomenon, sometimes
    directly, and sometimes in conjunction with other ambiguities
    in the writing system, such as mispointing <hi rend="italic">ta</hi> for
    <hi rend="italic">ya</hi> and then applying the same derivation.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] The
    section concludes by demonstrating that the technical meaning
    of "lectionary" is preserved in the word
    <hi rend="italic">qur’ān</hi>. Most striking is the conclusion that
    the term <hi rend="italic">umm kitāb</hi>, an aramaism, must be a written
    source and that the Qur’ān was never intended to
    replace this written source. One might complain that the
    details of the argument for the reading of suras 12:1-2 and 3:7
    are squeezed into footnotes, but nevertheless the argument is
    clear. Luxenberg proves that the term <hi rend="italic">qur’ān</hi>
    itself is the key to unlocking the passages that have given
    commentators in and outside of the tradition frustration. If
    <hi rend="italic">quryān</hi> means “lectionary,” and if the
    text itself claims to be a clarification of an earlier text,
    then that earlier text must be written in another language. The
    only candidate is the Old and New Testament in Syriac, the
    Peshitta. Hence the influence of Aramaic on the Arabic of
    Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad has an identifiable, textual
    origin. At the very end of the work, Luxenberg makes a
    compelling argument that sura 108 is a close allusion to the
    Peshitta of 1 Peter 5:8-9. Indeed this sura, which is only
    three lines long, is one of the most difficult passages for the
    Arabian as well as the Western commentators. Luxenberg shows
    why: it is composed of transcriptions into Arabic writing of
    the Syriac New Testament text, i.e., there is almost no
    “Arabic” in the sura. These are
    “revealed” texts, and insofar as the
    Qur’ān contains quotations or paraphrases of them,
    the Qur’ān is also “revealed.”</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] Many
    dialects of Arabic existed at the time of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad. In the ten places where the
    Qur’ān claims to have been written in Arabic,
    Luxenberg shows first that these passages have grammatical
    forms which are difficult for the commentators and have varying
    interpretations among the translators. He notes that in sura
    41:44, the Arabic <hi rend="italic">fassala</hi> means “to divide,”
    but the context here requires "make distinct" or better
    "interpret." Nowhere else does the Arabic word have this
    meaning, and the Syriac-Arabic lexica do not give the one as a
    translation for the other; <hi rend="italic">tarjama</hi> (a direct borrowing
    from Syriac) is the usual Arabic word for "interpret." However,
    the Syriac <hi rend="italic">praš / parreš</hi> can mean both
    "divide" as well as "interpret" (like Hebrew
    <hi rend="italic">hibdīl</hi>; also this is an example of a
    “semantic calque” mentioned above). <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī too understands <hi rend="italic">fassala</hi> to be a
    synonym for <hi rend="italic">bayyana</hi> (sura 44:3), which also has the
    meaning "interpret." Sura 41:44 also clearly attests to a
    source for the Qur’ān that is written in a foreign
    language. Luxenberg, following <hi rend="u">T</hi>abarī, notes a corruption in the text of this
    verse that clearly shows that part of the Qur’ān has
    a non-Arabic source. His argument here is somewhat weak if not
    for the further evidence deduced from eleven other locations in
    the Qur’ān where Luxenberg consistently applies
    these and similar arguments to difficulties all of which center
    on the terms related to the revelation and language of the
    Qur’ān. These arguments leave little doubt, that
    Luxenberg has uncovered a key misunderstanding of these terms
    throughout the Qur’ān.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25] In
    section twelve Luxenberg demonstrates that not only the origin
    and language of the Qur’ān are different from what
    the commentators who wrote two hundred years after its
    inception claim it to be, but that several key passages contain
    words or idioms that were borrowed from Syriac into Arabic.
    From his analysis of sura 19:24 (in the so-called “Marian
    Sura”): "Then he called to her from beneath her:
    ‘Grieve not; thy Lord hath placed beneath thee a
    streamlet,’" he concludes that it should be read "He
    called to her immediately after her laying-down (to give
    birt<hi rend="u">h</hi> ‘Grieve not; thy Lord has
    made your laying-down legitimate.’" Luxenberg’s
    lengthy discussion of the complexities of this passage resolve
    grammatical difficulties in the Arabic in a way that fits the
    context: Jesus gives Mary the courage to face her relatives
    even with a child born out of wedlock. The section then
    presents lengthy arguments dealing with various lexical,
    morphological, syntactic and versification problems in sura
    11:116-117.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26]
    Section thirteen uncovers evidence of Aramaic morphology in the
    grammar of the Qur’ān. Instances of ungrammatical
    gender agreement (feminine subject or noun with a masculine
    verb or modifier) arose because Syriac feminine forms were
    misread as an Arabic masculine singular accusative predicate
    adjective or participle where the governing noun is a feminine
    subject. In Syriac, predicate adjectives and participles were
    in the absolute form (predicate form). A feminine singular
    Syriac form transcribed into Arabic is identical to a genuine
    Arabic masculine singular accusative form. This phenomenon is
    quite pervasive in the Qur’ān (e.g. sura 19:20, 23,
    28). The argument that many commentators put forward to explain
    these anomalies is that grammar was sacrificed to preserve the
    rhyme of a verse. Luxenberg shows the weakness of this argument
    by demonstrating that in many cases the rhyme is sacrificed to
    render a grammatical expression (e.g. suras 33:63 and 42:17).
    Moreover, in at least one case of anomalous syntax in sura
    19:23, the grammatically correct word order would have fit the
    rhyme. In places where a masculine form corresponds to a
    feminine one, Luxenberg realized that the copyist had deleted
    the “masculine accusative singular” ending on the
    predicate adjective, not realizing that the adjective was a
    Syriac feminine predicate adjective transcribed into Arabic.
    These Syriac predicative/absolute forms in the
    Qur’ān are supported by the fact that Arabic always
    borrowed Syriac nouns and adjectives in their absolute form and
    not the emphatic (“unbound” or
    “dictionary”) form; e.g. <hi rend="italic">allah</hi> &lt;
    <hi rend="italic">alāhā</hi>: absolute state <hi rend="italic">alāh</hi>;
    <hi rend="italic">qarīb</hi>, ”near” &lt;
    <hi rend="italic">qarībā</hi>: absolute state <hi rend="italic">qarīb</hi>.
    Luxenberg then demonstrates that the loss of the feminine
    ending in Qur’ānic Arabic derives from the same
    phenomenon. Many Arabic grammatical rules which the earliest
    Arabian grammarians first posed to explain these anomalies are
    shown to have been <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>, written by those who no
    longer understood the language in which it had been written. A
    similar fate befell the so-called <hi rend="italic">accusative of
    specification</hi>, which required the noun in the sequence
    number + noun to be in the accusative singular. Luxenberg
    demonstrates that the noun in every case is really a Syriac
    masculine plural noun; singular and plural masculine nouns in
    Syriac have the same consonantal spelling.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27] In
    that same section, one also finds a study of how Syriac roots
    were misread and altered by later commentators. In one case,
    the word <hi rend="italic">jaw</hi> (sura 16:79) misread “air,
    atmosphere” is from Syriac <hi rend="italic">gaw</hi>, which means both
    “insides, inner part” and can also be used as a
    preposition meaning “inside.” In sura 16:79
    Luxenberg demonstrates that the prepositional use makes more
    sense than the solution posed by the commentators. Classical
    Arabic grammar, which was created three hundred years after the
    Qur’ān, does not recall the prepositional meaning of
    the word. However, dialects of Arabic preserve the original
    Syriac prepositional use. So where sura 16:79 reads <hi rend="italic">fī
    jaw as-samā’</hi> “in(side) heaven”
    referring to birds held aloft and kept from falling down by
    God, the dialects agree: <hi rend="italic">fī jawwāt al-bet</hi>
    “inside the house” is perfectly good Arabic. The
    misreading of Qur’ānic Arabic <hi rend="italic">jaw</hi> as
    “air” has become part of the technical vocabulary
    of modern standard Arabic: “air mail,” “air
    force,” “airline,” and “weather
    report” all use <hi rend="italic">jaw</hi>. The imaginary meaning of the
    grammarians lives on.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28]
    Finally, Luxenberg shows that there are verb forms in Arabic
    that are conflations from two distinct Syriac roots. The
    argument is detailed and here it suffices to mention that the
    confusion is based on a pronunciation of East Syriac
    provenance. The meaning of the Arabic verb <hi rend="italic">saxxara</hi> at
    times corresponds to Syriac <hi rend="italic">šaxxar</hi> “to
    blame, use up” and at times to <hi rend="italic">šawxar</hi>
    “to keep back, hinder.” The confusion arose because
    Syriac <hi rend="italic">šawxar</hi> was pronounced in East Syriac and
    Mandaic as either <hi rend="italic">šāxar</hi> or
    <hi rend="italic">šaxxar</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29]
    Section fourteen briefly argues for misunderstood Arabic
    idioms, which are calques of Aramaic expressions. Luxenberg
    looks at sura 17:64 which Paret translates as “And rouse
    with your voice all those you can, and assemble against them
    with all of your hosts, with your cavalry and your infantry,
    share with them (as a partner) wealth and children and make
    them promises – but Satan promises them only deceitful
    promises” (p. 217). The strange combination of rousing
    and besieging indicates a misreading. In this case it is Arabic
    that is misread, Arabic that literally translates Syriac
    expressions. According to Luxenberg’s analysis this verse
    should read “Thus seduce with your voice whomsoever from
    among them you can, outsmart them with your trick and your
    lying and deception, and tempt them with possessions and
    children and make promises to them – indeed Satan
    promises them nothing but vain things!” (p. 220).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30]
    Harmonization of passages that are united by theme is another
    feature of the textual difficulty of the Qur’ān.
    Sections fifteen and sixteen examine how a misreading in one
    verse triggered sympathetic misreadings throughout the text
    based not on grammatical or lexical similarity but because the
    scattered verses alluded to a single concept. In section
    fifteen, Luxenberg treats the virgins of paradise and in
    section sixteen the youths of paradise. Sura 44:54 is the
    starting point for the discussion. Bell translates this as
    “We will join to them dark, wide-eyed (maidens).”
    The verb “join as in marriage” or “pair as in
    animals for copulation” is a classic misreading of
    <hi rend="italic">ze</hi> for <hi rend="italic">re</hi> and <hi rend="italic">jim</hi> for <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>a</hi>(both pairs distinguished only by a single
    dot), instead of <hi rend="italic">zawwaj</hi> it is <hi rend="italic">rawwa<hi rend="u">h</hi>
            </hi> “give rest, refresh,” the object
    of the verb being the blessed in paradise. The major conclusion
    of section fifteen is that the expression <hi rend="italic">hūr
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>īn</hi> means “white (grapes), jewels (of
    crystal)” and not “dark, wide-eyed (maidens)”
    (suras 44:54 and 52:20). Luxenberg first examines carefully
    each component of sura 44:54 and of sura 52:20. The
    Qur’ān mentions other kinds of fruits in paradise,
    namely, dates and pomegranates (sura 55:68) as well as grapes
    (sura 78:32). Grapes are also mentioned in the context of
    “earthy” gardens ten times. Since earlier
    scholarship knows that the Qur’ān uses the Syriac
    word for garden <hi rend="italic">ganta</hi> &gt; <hi rend="italic">janna</hi> for paradise,
    the grape then must be the fruit of paradise <hi rend="italic">par
    excellence</hi> (p. 234). Why, if that is so, is the grape only
    mentioned in connection with the “heavenly” garden
    once?</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31] To
    answer this, Luxenberg presents earlier scholarship, notably
    that of Tor Andrae and Edmund Beck, showing a connection
    between the images of the garden of paradise in the
    Qur’ān and in the hymns of Ephraem the Syrian
    entitled <hi rend="italic">On Paradise</hi>. Andrae remarked that
    <hi rend="italic">hūr</hi> was likely from the Syriac word for
    “white,” but his solution was to say that the
    Qur’ānic usage was somehow metaphorical. Neither he
    nor Beck considered that the Arabic “virgin” was a
    later misunderstanding on the part of the commentators.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32]
    Ephraem uses the term <hi rend="italic">gupnā</hi>, “vine,”
    grammatically feminine, with which <hi rend="italic">hūr</hi> agrees and
    from this Andrae concluded that it was a metaphor for
    “the virgins of paradise” in the Qur’ān.
    In suras 44:54 and 52:20, Luxenberg argues that instead of the
    singular <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>īn</hi> the plural
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>uyun</hi> should be read, referring to the grapes
    on the vine. Elsewhere the Qur’ān compares the
    grapes to “pearls,” and so they must be white
    grapes, which is not apparent from the text at first glance.
    Luxenberg then offers two variants of this expression. The
    first reading renders the phrase “white, crystal (clear
    grapes),” the second, and the one Luxenberg adopts, is
    “white (grapes), (like) jewels (of crystal).” The
    restored verse then reads “We will let them (the blessed
    in Paradise) be refreshed with white (grapes), (like) jewels
    (of crystal).”</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] Of
    the several related examples in sections 15.2 – 15.9,
    Luxenberg follows the virgins of paradise through the
    Qur’ān. In section 15.2, Luxenberg observes that
    <hi rend="italic">azwaj</hi>, “spouses,” also can mean
    “species, kinds” (suras 2:25, 3:15, and 4:57). The
    latter reading makes more sense “therein also are all
    kinds of pure (fruits).” Luxenberg links to the
    misunderstanding of sura 44:54 <hi rend="italic">zawwaj</hi>, “join,
    marry.” The misinterpretation of one verse spills over
    into the related thematic content of another. The other
    sections are also well-argued. Of special interest are the
    discussions in sections 15.5 – 15.6 of suras 55:56 and
    55:70, 72, 74, respectively, which state, referring to the
    virgins of paradise “whom deflowered before them has
    neither man nor <hi rend="italic">jinn</hi>.” Instead, these are the
    grapes of paradise “that neither man nor <hi rend="italic">jinn</hi> have
    defiled.” Luxenberg points out that sura 55:72 evidences
    another Qur’ānic parallel to Ephraem, who writes
    that the vines of paradise abound in “hanging
    grapes.”<note place="foot" xml:id="FN10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
             Luxenberg does not give the place in Ephraem
    but cites Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des heiligen Ephraem des Syrers
    Hymnen de Paradiso und contra Julianum</hi>, in Corpus
    Scriptorum Christianorum Orientalium (CSCO), Scriptores Syri t.
    78, vols. 174 [Syriac], t. 79, vol. 175 [German translation]
    (Louvain, 1957). The passage to which Luxenberg refers is Hymn
    VII, stanza 17. In fact, one finds the text in CSCO, vol. 174,
    p. 29. There are many similar passages where the fruits
    “stretch themselves out” to those in Paradise. See
    Sebastian Brock, tr. and commentary, <hi rend="italic">St. Ephrem the Syrian,
    Hymns on Paradise</hi> (Crestwood, N.Y.: St. Vladimir’s
    Seminary Press, 1998). 
         </p>
                </note>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34]
    Section sixteen follows this investigation as it points to a
    similar misreading of paradise’s grapes as <hi rend="italic">youths</hi>,
    Arabic <hi rend="italic">wildun</hi>. Sura 76:19 “Round amongst them go
    boys of perpetual youth, whom when one see, he thinks them
    pearls unstrung” (sura 16.1, citing Bell’s
    translation). <hi rend="italic">Wildun</hi> is a genuinely Arabic word, but it
    is used in a sense which is borrowed from Syriac
    <hi rend="italic">yaldā</hi>. Youths like pearls is somewhat suspicious,
    especially given that “pearls” are a metaphor for
    the grapes of paradise from the previous section. Luxenberg
    uncovered that Syriac has the expression <hi rend="italic">yaldā
    dagpettā</hi>, “child of the vine,” appearing
    in the Peshitta: Matthew 26:29, Mark 14:25, and Luke 22:18, in
    which Christ foreshadows his death and resurrection: “I
    will not drink of this child of the vine (<hi rend="italic">yaldā
    dagpettā</hi>) until the day when I drink it new in the
    kingdom of my Father.” Here it is the juice of the grape
    that is the “child.” Entries in the Arabic-Syriac
    lexica for each of <hi rend="italic">yaldā</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gpettā</hi>
    give in addition to “child” and “vine”
    “fruit” and “wine,” respectively.
    Luxenberg gives further evidence from suras 37:45, 43:71, and
    76:15 that Ephraem the Syrian’s depiction of the grapes
    of paradise is behind the original Qur’ānic
    text.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35]
    Section seventeen synthesizes the techniques and findings of
    the foregoing study and analyzes two complete suras: 108 and
    96. Luxenberg provides for each a complete commentary and
    translation. The thrust of sura 108 has already been presented
    above. The analysis of all nineteen verses of sura 96 spans
    twenty-two pages. Among the many solutions provided in this
    section is that the particle <hi rend="italic">’a</hi> which has stumped
    the commentators and the grammarians is really two different
    words: the Syriac word <hi rend="italic">’aw</hi> “or” and
    the Syriac <hi rend="italic">’ēn</hi> “if, when.”
    Omitting here the details of the argument, this sura is to be
    read as a call to participate in liturgical prayer and has the
    “character of a Christian-Syriac <hi rend="italic">prooemium</hi>, which
    in the later tradition was replaced by the <hi rend="italic">fati<hi rend="u">h</hi>a</hi> (from Syriac <hi rend="italic">ptāxā</hi>,
    ’opening’).” This is not just any liturgy,
    but the Divine Liturgy, the eucharistic commemoration, as
    Luxenberg reconstructs verses 17-19: “Should he [i.e.,
    the Slanderer] wish to call his idols, he will (thereby) call a
    [god who] passes away! You should not at all listen to him,
    (rather) perform (your) liturgy and receive the Eucharist
    (<hi rend="italic">wa-isjid wa iqtabar</hi>)” (p. 296). This is
    noteworthy, as this is the oldest sura according to Islamic
    tradition, and reveals its Christian-Syriac roots. In sura 5
    “The Repast” Luxenberg indicates that closely
    related eucharistic terminology as in sura 96 (the proof for
    which is omitted in this review) suggests that the verses in
    sura 5:114-115 refer to the Eucharistic liturgy (and not just
    the Last Supper). Further evidence for this reading comes from
    a piece of pre-Islamic poetry by the Christian Arab poet
    ‘Adi ibn Zayd which the <hi rend="italic">Kitāb
    al-aghānī</hi> of Abū l-Faraj
    al-Isfahānī (d. 967) preserved. Section eighteen, a
    brief, comprehensive summary, concludes the study.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P36"/>[36] The
    production of the book is overall of good quality. There are
    certain proofreading errors, including the mis-numbering of
    sections (e.g., pp. 237 and 239), and very few grammatical
    mistakes. The page layout is at times difficult to read. This
    is partly due to the nature of the study, which requires
    Arabic, Syriac, Mandaic, and Latin alphabets to share space
    with footnotes and inline quotations from the sources.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P37"/>[37] A
    work of this scope presented piece-meal necessarily lacks the
    cohesion and elegance of a full study. The implications of this
    method are nevertheless clear. Any future scientific study of
    the Qur’ān will necessarily have to take this method
    into consideration. Even if scholars disagree with the
    conclusions, the philological method is robust. It has
    established a discipline that is substantially different from
    the exegetical traditions of the Arabian and Western
    commentators. Luxenberg has called into question the view of
    the Qur’ān as a “pure” text, one free of
    the theological and philological difficulties that plague the
    transmission histories of other texts, e.g., the Hebrew Bible
    and its versions.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P38"/>[38] A
    central question that this investigation raises is the
    motivation of <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān in preparing his
    redaction of the Qur’ān. Luxenberg presents the two
    <hi rend="italic">hadīth</hi> traditions recounting how
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān came to possess the first manuscript.
    If Luxenberg’s analysis is even in broad outline correct,
    the content of the Qur’ān was substantially
    different at the time of Mu<hi rend="u">h</hi>ammad and
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Uthmān’s redaction played a part in the
    misreading of key passages. Were these misreadings intentional
    or not? The misreadings in general alter the Qur’ān
    from a book that is more or less harmonious with the New
    Testament and Syriac Christian liturgy and literature to one
    that is distinct, of independent origin.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P39"/>[39] It
    is hoped that an English translation of this work will soon
    appear. Despite the sober revolution this book will no doubt
    create, one should not be naïve to think that all
    Islamicists in the West, many of whom are presently engaged in
    massive damage control, will immediately take up and respond to
    the scholarly challenges posed by any work of this kind.
    However, just as Christianity faced the challenges of
    nineteenth and twentieth century biblical and liturgical
    scholarship, so too will serious scholars of Islam, both East
    and West, benefit from the discipline Luxenberg has
    launched.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N1PRPhenixHorn1">Notes</head>
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>