<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Gabriel of Qatar's Commentary on the Liturgy</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Sebastian P.</forename>
                  <surname>Brock</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>July 2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/ /hv6n2brock</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Sebastian P. BROCK</author>
                  <title level="a">Gabriel of Qatar's Commentary on the Liturgy</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Gabriel of Beth Qatraye</term>
               <term>Commentary</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
    
         <p>The Commentary on the Liturgy by Gabriel of
    Beth Qatraye (early seventh century) is preserved in a single
    thirteenth-century manuscript. A short introduction draws
    attention to the interest of the manuscript itself (as well as
    its contents), and to previous studies of the Commentary. In
    order to give a fuller indication of its contents, an English
    translation of the chapter headings is given, and this is
    followed by a translation of the chapter on the Eucharistic
    Liturgy (Memra V, chapter 2). At the end, the Syriac text of
    chapter 2 of Memra V is also given.</p>
         <lb/>
    
         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock3">The Unique Manuscript</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    unique witness to the important Commentary on the Liturgy by
    the early seventh-century author, Gabriel bar Lipeh of Qatar,
    is a thirteenth-century manuscript in the British Library, Or.
    3336. The opening of the text is lost, and a few folios are
    missing later on. Although this manuscript received a short
    description in Margoliouth's <hi rend="italic">Descriptive List of Syriac and
    Karshuni MSS. in the British Museum acquired since
    1873</hi>,<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> it was not until 1966 that it received any
    serious attention. In that year S.H. Jammo published a
    useful—though still brief—description of its
    contents.<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> In the course of his article Jammo made two
    important observations: the date accorded to Gabriel of Qatar
    by A. Scher and A. Baumstark (late seventh century) cannot be
    correct, since Gabriel makes mention (f.109a) of Shubhalmaran,
    metropolitan of Karka d-Beth Slokh as still alive; this means
    that Gabriel must belong to the early decades of the seventh
    century. Jammo went on to identify the author with the scribe
    of British Library Add.14471, written at Nisibis by a Gabriel
    of Qatar and dated 615; this, however, seems unlikely, for
    reasons I have given elsewhere.<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> This earlier date is
    particularly important, since it means that Gabriel was writing
    before the liturgical reforms of the Patriarch
    Isho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>yahb III (649-659). Jammo's second
    observation concerned the date of the manuscript: this had been
    given as AG 1579 = AD 1268 by Margoliouth, but as Jammo
    observes, the manuscript is damaged at this point and most of
    the third digit is missing. Jammo rightly points out that the
    date could equally be AG 1549 = AD 1238. Although this is
    correct, there is in fact a further possibility: all that
    remains of the third digit is [-]<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">yn</hi>,
    which means that the number might have been
    <hi rend="italic">tesh<hi rend="sup">c</hi>in</hi> (90), as well as
    <hi rend="italic">shab<hi rend="sup">c</hi>in</hi> (70) or <hi rend="italic">arb<hi rend="sup">c</hi>in</hi>
    (40); in other words, the later date of AG 1599 = AD 1288. (The
    month is given as July, and the day as the last Friday of that
    month).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2]
    Margoliouth gives no indication of where the manuscript was
    written, and Jammo simply states that the manuscript was
    written at the Monastery of Deba at the foot of Mount Kola.
    This turns out to be a little misleading, for what the (rather
    damaged) colophon in fact states is: "This book ... was
    completed and finished in the holy monastery, the place of rest
    for humility, Tabor's abode, Sion's Upper Room, the fragrant
    shrine [of] the holy Mar Hnanya, Mar
    Hnanisho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>, Mar Bassima, and Mar Habbib, known
    as the (monastery) of the Bear (<hi rend="italic">debba</hi>), situated ... on
    the edge of the resting place of Noah and his children when
    [they] came out of the Ark (<hi rend="italic">qibuta</hi>), it being on the
    slopes of the mountain of the Ark (KWL' = <hi rend="italic">kewila</hi>)". This
    happens to be very interesting information, supplementing some
    exiguous other sources on the monastery. The ninth-century
    <hi rend="italic">Ktaba d</hi>-<hi rend="italic">nakputa</hi> (Liber Castitatis) by
    Isho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>dnah<ref target="#FN4">4</ref> mentions (in section 52) the
    monastic foundation of the otherwise little known Mar Habbib in
    the vicinity of a village called Kfar Tuta in the region of
    mount Qardu (where, according to the Peshitta, Noah's Ark came
    to rest, rather than on Ararat). In his next section
    Isho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>dnah goes on to tell of Mar Bassima, who
    while in secular life in royal service<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> was told by a
    Zoroastrian magian that he would become a monk. This indeed
    took place, and after spending time in various different
    monasteries, he ended up in that built by Habbib, and in due
    course he enlarged it. In the eighth century the monastery had,
    for a while, as its abbot the famous monastic author Joseph the
    Seer (Hazzaya).<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> After that date, as Fiey puts it, "on n'entend
    plus parler du couvent. On ignore sa position exacte en
    Qardu".<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> Our manuscript thus provides clear evidence, not
    only that two further names (both otherwise unknown) were
    associated with the monastery, but also that it was still
    flourishing in the thirteenth century.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock4">The Contents</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The work
    consists of five Memre of uneven length, and each is divided up
    into chapters. In his article Jammo listed the topics covered
    by the five Memre, and for the fifth he mentioned the topics
    dealt with in each chapter. Subsequently, in the course of his
    useful monograph <hi rend="italic">La structure de la messe
    chaldéenne</hi>
            <ref target="#FN8">8</ref> he provided a Latin translation of the
    chapter in Memra 5 which constitutes a commentary on the
    Eucharistic liturgy. An English translation of the same
    section, made by Father Placid Podipara, was first published in
    India in 1974, and then reprinted by Father G. Vavanikunnel,
    <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">Interpretation on the Holy
    Qurbana</hi>, in 1977. Since a full listing of the chapter
    headings of each of the five Memre has not yet been made
    available, an English translation of these is given below.
    Similarly, since Podipara's English translation is not easily
    accessible, I have also provided a new English translation
    (deliberately rather literal and without annotation) of this
    important section, as well as the text of its Syriac original.
    For convenience of future reference, I have broken the text up
    into short sections.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] In his
    article of 1966 Jammo already pointed to certain aspects of
    particular interest in this part of the Commentary, and he
    makes some comparisons with some of the other East Syriac
    liturgical commentaries; in particular he rightly observes that
    the published Commentary by Abraham bar Lipeh<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> is nothing but an
    abbreviation of Gabriel's work (what the relationship between
    these two men was, both bar Lipeh, remains a puzzle). In order
    to highlight the passages found in Abraham, I have italicized
    these in the translation. A full-scale investigation of the
    relationship of Gabriel's chapter on the Eucharistic liturgy
    with the other commentaries would be of considerable interest,
    but this is a task which must wait for the future. Here it must
    suffice simply to note that Gabriel makes use (in sections
    43-44) of the early anonymous Commentary which has proved
    influential in all three Syriac ecclesial traditions,<ref target="#FN10">10</ref> and
    that, while Ps.George of Arbela shows little contact with
    Gabriel, Abdisho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>, in his <hi rend="italic">Tukkas
    Dine,</hi>
            <ref target="#FN11">11</ref> does draw on him.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] There
    is, however, one other significant matter which should be
    mentioned. In the discussion of the attitude of the Church of
    the East towards figurative images and icons, attention has
    already been drawn by scholars to the important evidence of
    Abraham bar Lipeh's commentary, where the presence of an icon
    of Christ on the altar is considered essential at the time of
    the consecration.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref> Abraham's source is (as one would expect)
    Gabriel's commentary, where the relevant passage will be found
    in sections 45 and 46. In this connection it is worth drawing
    attention to another reference to the liturgical importance of
    icons, to be found in an unpublished set of 23 liturgical
    questions put to Isho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>barnun, in Vatican
    Borg. Syr. 81. Question 10 (f.371b), concerns the case of a
    priest who, in an emergency, has to baptize his own child when
    there is no one else apart from the mother—his
    wife—available to "receive" the child (that is, act as
    godparent). Isho<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>barnun's solution to this
    dilemma is to say that the child should be placed on an icon
    instead, the person portrayed thus acting as godparent.
    Specific reference is made here to an "icon of our Lord"
    (<hi rend="italic">yuqneh d-Maran</hi>) if the infant is a boy, and an "icon of
    the Blessed" (Mary), if it is a girl. Later on in the questions
    there is a passing reference to "icons of the saints" (Question
    21, f.373b).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    remainder of Gabriel's Commentary remains largely unexploited,
    though Jammo has provided a description of his comments on
    Ramsha,<ref target="#FN14">14</ref> and I have given a translation of his section
    on the Trisagion (<hi rend="italic">Qaddisha</hi>; ff.23a-26b) as a
    contribution to a (forthcoming) Festschrift in honour of Fr.
    Emmanuel Thelly, the compiler of the recently-published
    Syriac-English-Malayalam Dictionary that is based on Audo's
    <hi rend="italic">Simta d-leshana suryaya</hi>. I hope to return to some other
    aspects of particular interest on a later occasion. In the
    meantime, mention might be made of the presence of several
    patristic quotations; thus Gabriel quotes from Basil's Letter
    to Gregory (f.95a),<ref target="#FN15">15</ref> Gregory of Nazianzus' Invective against
    Julian (f.96a), Evagrius (ff.96b-97a, 218a),<ref target="#FN16">16</ref> Narsai (f.59b)
    and (not surprisingly) the "Interpreter", that is, Theodore of
    Mopsuestia (ff.123b, 160b, 170b etc.). Much more surprising,
    however, is the presence of a long and unattributed extract
    (ff.107b-108b) from Sergius of Resh<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>aina's
    Discourse on the spiritual life, which prefaces the first
    Syriac translation (probably by Sergius) of the Dionysian
    Corpus.<ref target="#FN17">17</ref> There are also references to Aristotle's
    Categories and to Pythagoras (ff.88b, 144a-b).</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock5">Translations<ref target="#FN18">18</ref>
         </head>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock6">Chapter Headings</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7]
    <hi rend="bold">Memra 1</hi>: On the ordering of the Office of
    Ramsha on weekdays.<lb/>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>&lt;Opening lost&gt;</item>
            <item>Why do we begin from the Old [Testament] in our services
      and crown them with the new <hi rend="italic">teshb<hi rend="u">h</hi>ata</hi>? [f.3b]</item>
            <item>Why do we change the <hi rend="italic">qala</hi> before the
      <hi rend="italic">marmyatha</hi> come to an end, and then we say the Glory
      and have the <hi rend="italic">suyyaka</hi>? [f.5b]</item>
            <item>&lt;Opening lost&gt;</item>
            <item>Why do we bring out a light at this point, and kindle
      from it the lamps on the menorah that is placed in front of
      the sanctuary? [f.7a]</item>
            <item>What is the reason why we draw the curtain along with the
      utterance of "Peace be with us"? [f.9a]</item>
            <item>Why do we burn incense at the <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u Mara</hi>?
      f.10b]</item>
            <item>Why do we say the <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u Mara</hi> at this point, and
      what its words mean? [f.11a]</item>
            <item>Why do we say two separate <hi rend="italic">shurraye</hi> at every
      Ramsha, and why we say "O Lord, I have called on you" in the
      middle? [f.15a]</item>
            <item>What the ordering of the petition and the
      proclamation/litany that follow it mean for us, and why we
      say them? [f.19a]</item>
            <item>How, and what is the reason for this <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi>
      "Holy", and why we say it continually? [f.22b]</item>
            <item>Why, when the service of Ramsha is completed with the
      <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi> "Holy", we add an
      <hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">onitha</hi> and a section from the
      Beatitudes? [f.26b]</item>
            <item>&lt;Opening lost&gt;</item>
            <item>Why, on Friday which is a weekday, do its <hi rend="italic">shurraye</hi>
      go round not twice, but three times? [f.29b]</item>
            <item>What is the reason for the sevenfold cycle (?) of the
      <hi rend="italic">shurraye</hi> on Sundays? [f.32a]</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8]
    <hi rend="bold">Memra 2</hi>: On the ordering of the Office of
    Sapra on weekdays. List of chapters. [f.35a]</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>What is the common purpose of the rites for the Office of
      Sapra? [f.36a]</item>
            <item>What benefits do we have from knowledge of these
      orderings? [f.40b]</item>
            <item>Why are we instructed to pray and to praise God at the
      time of Sapra? [f.44a]</item>
            <item>With what aim is the psalm(ody) of Sapra arranged?
      [f.46b]</item>
            <item>What is the ordering of the second psalm? [f.49a]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering of the third psalm instruct us?
      [f.51a]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering of the fourth psalm indicate to
      us? [f.53a]</item>
            <item>Why do we serve these <hi rend="italic">shurraye</hi> from the Old
      (Testament) at Sapra before the <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u Mara</hi>?
      [f.58b]</item>
            <item>Why do we complete the first two psalms, but not the
      third; and why do we attach five others to the fourth?
      [f.60b]</item>
            <item>Why do we say the <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u Mara</hi> after these psalms?
      [f.63a]</item>
            <item>What is the reason why we say the psalm "Have mercy on
      me, O God" (Ps 51) after the <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u Mara</hi>?
      [f.65b]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering here of the petition, and
      proclamation (litany) after it, indicate to us? [70a]</item>
            <item>What is the reason that prevents the Solitaries from
      saying the petition and following proclamation at Sapra?
      [f.73a]</item>
            <item>What purpose does the ordering of "To You be praise"
      have, and why do we say it at the crowning/climax of our
      Office? [f.77b]</item>
            <item>Why do we say the <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi> "Holy" after this
      <hi rend="italic">teshbo<hi rend="u">h</hi>ta</hi>? [f.82b]</item>
            <item>What is the reason why the Fathers arranged that we
      should give thanks and praise to God seven times, by night
      and day? [f.83b]</item>
            <item>Why do we serve three <hi rend="italic">shubbahe</hi> during the Hours of
      daytime, but at Compline four, and at Lilya nine? [f.89b]
      Admonition concerning this topic [f.100a]</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9]
    <hi rend="bold">Memra 3</hi>: On the ordering of the Office of
    Ramsha and of the three Sessions that are served at Lilya of
    Sunday. List of chapters. [102a]</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>On the special honour of the day of holy Sunday.
      [f.102b]</item>
            <item>Why the orderings of the Office of Ramsha are not changed
      in the way that the orderings of the Office of Sapra on the
      same day are changed? [f.105b]</item>
            <item>What is the reason for the ordering of the first Session
      which we serve at Lilya of Sunday? [f.111a]</item>
            <item>Why do we sound the great <hi rend="italic">naqosha</hi> (semantron) in
      the middle of Lilya, and begin once again to sing praise?
      [f.114a]</item>
            <item>Why do we sound the <hi rend="italic">naqosha</hi> again at the last
      Session, and open the door of the sanctuary; and why do we
      say the <hi rend="italic">Qale d-Shahra</hi>? [f.115b]</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    <hi rend="bold">Memra 4</hi>: On the ordering of the Office of
    Sapra on Sunday. List of chapters. [f.120b]</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>The <hi rend="italic">protheoria</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">memra</hi>. [f.121a]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering of the <hi rend="italic">naqosha</hi> at Sapra on
      Sunday instruct us? [f.122b]</item>
            <item>For what reason, at Sapra on Sunday, do we first serve
      four separate psalms, but we do not attach other psalms to
      the fourth one, as we do on weekdays? [f.124a]</item>
            <item>What do we understand about the sequence of the four
      psalms of the fifth <hi rend="italic">shuraya</hi>; and why do we not say
      "Praise the Lord with a new song" (Ps. 149)? [f.128a]</item>
            <item>Why, at Sapra on Sunday, do we say an
      <hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">onitha</hi> instead of <hi rend="italic">Lak(h)u
      Mara</hi>; and why do we not say the Petition and
      Proclamation? [f.132b]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering of the two new
      <hi rend="italic">teshb<hi rend="u">h</hi>ata</hi> joined to one another
      instruct us; and why do we then attach to them a third, that
      of Hnanya (Ananias) and companions? [f.136a]</item>
            <item>What opinion do we have of the ordering of "Glory to God
      in the heights"? [f.162b]</item>
            <item>Why, after this <hi rend="italic">teshbo<hi rend="u">h</hi>ta</hi>,
      do we say the <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi> "Holy" in a raised and distinct
      voice/melody? [f.173a]</item>
            <item>Why do we say <hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">onyatha</hi> of the
      Martyrs, and not of the Apostles, in particular on Sunday;
      and why do the Solitaries say them every day? [f.176b]</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    <hi rend="bold">Memra 5</hi>: On the ordering of the Office of the
    Mysteries. List of chapters. [f.182b]</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>Why do we constantly perform the Office of the Mysteries?
      [f.183b]</item>
            <item>What does each one of the orderings of the Office of the
      Mysteries instruct us? [f.186b]</item>
            <item>Why do the Solitaries not draw the curtain at the time of
      the epiclesis in the way that the clergy in the world do?
      [f.211b]</item>
            <item>Why do we light lamps during the daylight at the time of
      our Office, while we take care that the (lamp) of the
      sanctuary does not go out? [f.215a]</item>
            <item>What does the ordering of the Solitaries instruct us, who
      reside in their cells during the whole week, but on Sunday
      they gather together and take part in the Office and in the
      Mysteries, and in the Table? [f.218b]</item>
            <item>From when did the tonsure begin, and what is the reason
      for it? [f.223b]</item>
            <item>Why do the Solitaries shave their head but allow their
      beards to grow; and what advantages do they gain from this?
      [f.225a]</item>
            <item>An admonition concerning virtuous conduct, in accordance
      with the common aim of the whole book. [f.227b]</item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock7">Memra 5, Chapter 2 (On the Eucharistic
    Liturgy)</head>
         <p>(Italics indicate passages taken up by Abraham bar
    Lipeh)</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    [186b] What each of the components in the service of the
    Mysteries signifies to us.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>In this service of the Holy Mysteries, too, our blessed
      Fathers have had as their aim briefly and cursorily to
      provide [187a] a reminder of God's entire dispensation that
      was fulfilled in the world through Christ, beginning from his
      fleshly birth and travelling on, step by step, to his death,
      resurrection and ascension. They depicted for us, as it were
      as an image, each one of the things that were performed, for
      the confirmation of our faith, the growth of our hope, and
      the increase of our love towards him.</item>
            <item>We begin, therefore, with the commencement of this
      service.</item>
            <item>The fact that <hi rend="italic">we serve one</hi> marmitha <hi rend="italic">from the
      Psalms</hi> of the blessed David <hi rend="italic">signifies</hi> this:
      <hi rend="italic">that the Lord Jesus Christ Son of God is one; he was born
      of the</hi> holy <hi rend="italic">Virgin</hi> who was descended from the seed
      of David. In his divinity he was born of the Father, beyond
      all times, without limit and without beginning; [187b] and at
      the end of times, in his humanity, <hi rend="italic">Christ was born in the
      flesh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">while the Old Testament still held
      sway</hi>.<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact</hi> that this <hi rend="italic">marmitha</hi> is arranged <hi rend="italic">out
      of three psalms is because the name Christ</hi> [mshiha]
      <hi rend="italic">makes known</hi> the Father <hi rend="italic">who anointed him, the Son
      who was anointed, and the Holy Spirit who fulfilled the role
      of the oil</hi> [mesh<hi rend="u">h</hi>a].<lb/>
      Or, another explanation: just as three psalms constitute one
      <hi rend="italic">marmitha</hi>, so too the Man [<hi rend="italic">barnasheh</hi>] of our
      Lord is perfect in body, perfect in soul, and perfect in
      mind, just like all human beings who share his nature. He was
      not body without soul, according to the opinion of Arius and
      Eunomius, nor was he body and soul without mind, according to
      the precept [188a] of Apollinarius.<lb/>
      Or, the triple psalms indicate the threefold decade of years
      during which Christ fulfilled all the observances of the
      threefold laws in the Old Testament, that is, the natural
      law, the law that was commanded, and the written law.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that we attach a</hi> hullala <hi rend="italic">to every
      verse (</hi>pethgama<hi rend="italic">) is an indication</hi> of the
      utterances of praise <hi rend="italic">of the heavenly powers who, at the
      birth of Christ, appeared to the shepherds, giving praise</hi>
      and saying "Glory to God in the heights" (Luke 2:14)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that, before the</hi> marmitha <hi rend="italic">ends, we
      change the chant with the two verses (signifies) the change
      that John the Baptist introduced to the Law through
      baptism</hi> of forgiveness of sins.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that</hi> after these things <hi rend="italic">we glorify
      Father, Son and Holy Spirit is a demonstration of</hi> [188b]
      <hi rend="italic">the revealing of</hi> the Trinity of holy <hi rend="italic">Persons</hi>
      (qnome) <hi rend="italic">who were made known</hi> to rational beings <hi rend="italic">at
      the baptism of our Lord</hi>; for when our Lord was baptized
      the Spirit in the bodily form of a dove tabernacled
      (<hi rend="italic">aggen)</hi> over his head, and the Father called out from
      on high "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased"
      (Matt. 3:17 and par.)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The <hi rend="sup">
                     <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                  </hi>
               </hi>onitha <hi rend="italic">of the chancel
      (</hi>qenke<hi rend="italic">) is a symbol (</hi>raz<hi rend="italic">) of the praises of</hi>
      the heavenly hosts who, on seeing these things, raised up new
      songs of praise to the Lord of all.<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Or, it is a symbol of the (utterance of) praise of
      John</hi>, who cried out saying, "This is the Lamb of God; he
      takes away the sin of the world". (John 1:29)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The coming out of the cross</hi> from the sanctuary is
      <hi rend="italic">a symbol of Jesus' going out to the wilderness</hi> and his
      fight with Satan.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The ascent of the cross</hi> to <hi rend="italic">the Bema</hi>
      accompanied by the deacons and priests <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of
      Jesus'</hi> frequent <hi rend="italic">ascents</hi> to Jerusalem accompanied
      [189a] by his twelve disciples and the seventy.</item>
            <item>The <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi> "<hi rend="italic">To you, Lord</hi> (Lak(h)u Mara)"
      <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of the confession of the Apostles</hi>
      concerning him, spoken by Simon, representing them all, "You
      are the Christ, the Son of God" (Matt. 16:17).</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The two lights accompanying the cross are a symbol of
      the light of the two Testaments</hi> from which Christ
      supported the words of his teaching, as when he said "Such
      and such was said to those of old, but I tell you such and
      such". (cp Matt. 5:21, 27, 33).</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fragrant</hi> (d-besme) <hi rend="italic">incense is a symbol of
      the delight (</hi>bussama<hi rend="italic">) that is to come</hi>, which our
      Lord promised to those who believe in him and keep his
      commandments.</item>
            <item>The <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi> "<hi rend="italic">Holy</hi>..." <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of the
      sanctification</hi> (of Christ) <hi rend="italic">by the angels</hi> who
      accompanied him during his entire dispensation, just as the
      blessed Matthew said, "The angels approached and were
      ministering to him". (Matt. 4:11)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Law and the Prophets that are read are a symbol of
      the demonstrations that our Lord adduced</hi> for the
      confirmation of his teaching, taken <hi rend="italic">from Moses and</hi> all
      <hi rend="italic">the Prophets</hi>, such as when he was seen saying to the
      Jews, "Examine the Scriptures in which you hope that you have
      eternal life: they will testify concerning me". (John
      5:39)<lb/>
      And again, "Do you imagine that I am accusing you before the
      Father? There is one who accuses you, Moses, whom you hold to
      be true. If you had believed in Moses, you would have been
      believing in me; for Moses wrote concerning me. And if you do
      not believe his writings, how will you believe in my words?"
      (John 5:45-47)<lb/>
      And again, increasing his rebuke, he was saying to them,
      "None of you keeps the Law". Thus, when he was given the Book
      of Isaiah [190a] the Prophet to read, he read the section
      "The Spirit of the Lord is upon me; for this reason the Lord
      has anointed me" etc. (Luke 4:18) After the reading he said
      to them, "Today this Scripture which you have heard has been
      fulfilled". (Luke 4:21) And when they further argued against
      him, he said to them, "Well did the prophet Isaiah prophesy
      and say 'This people honours me with their lips, but their
      heart is greatly distant from me, and in vain do they fear
      me, teaching doctrines that belong to the ordinances of human
      beings'". (Matt. 15:7)<lb/>
      And again, when they asked him to show them a sign from
      heaven, he said, "An evil and adulterous generation seeks for
      a sign, but no sign will be given to it, apart from the sign
      of Jonah the prophet: for just as Jonah was in the fish's
      belly for three days and three nights, so the Son of Man will
      be in the heart [190b] of the earth for three days and three
      nights". (Matt. 12:39-40)<lb/>
      In the same manner, when he was prophesying concerning the
      devastation of Jerusalem, his disciples asked him, "When will
      these things happen?" (Matt.24:3) He said in answer, "When
      you see that unclean sign spoken of by Daniel the prophet".
      (Matt. 24:15)<lb/>
      Our Lord used to adduce many demonstrations to establish his
      teaching. It is for this reason that the Law and the Prophets
      are read first.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Acts</hi> of the Apostles <hi rend="italic">are read along with
      the Old Testament</hi>: firstly, as a <hi rend="italic">demonstration</hi> of
      the harmony <hi rend="italic">of the two Testaments</hi>. And secondly, as an
      indication of what was done by our Lord before he suffered,
      for the Old Testament still held sway, [191a] and the
      apostles were living as Jews. Our Lord sent them to all the
      towns of Israel, saying to them, "Do not go to the region of
      the gentiles, and do not enter the town of the Samaritans. Go
      rather to the sheep who have been lost from the House of
      Israel, and tell them, Repent, the Kingdom of Heaven has come
      close to you". (Matt. 10:5-7)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The sitting down of the priests on the Bema</hi> at the
      time of the Readings is <hi rend="italic">for a demonstration of what our
      Lord said</hi> to his Apostles, "You who have left everything
      and followed me, <hi rend="italic">when the Son of Man comes in his glory,
      you too shall sit</hi> on twelve thrones and judge the twelve
      tribes of Israel". (Matt. 19:28)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Their rising up from sitting</hi>: (this) points to
      <hi rend="italic">the assurance of the Apostles' minds</hi> at our Lord's
      words. [192a]</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The</hi> estatyona <hi rend="italic">before the Apostle</hi>: <hi rend="italic">a
      symbol of the praises of the people concerning John who</hi>,
      after he appeared, <hi rend="italic">was preaching repentance</hi> and the
      forgiveness of sins; and <hi rend="italic">he was prophesying concerning</hi>
      the closeness of <hi rend="italic">the Kingdom of Heaven</hi>.</item>
            <item>The reading from the <hi rend="italic">Apostle</hi>: <hi rend="italic">a symbol of
      John's exalted words</hi> when he spoke to the crowds
      concerning our Saviour, such as "He who has come from above,
      is above all" (John 3:31), along with the rest of such
      passages; and "<hi rend="italic">I am not the Christ, but the one sent
      before him</hi>". (John 3:28)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That a deacon reads the Apostle and not a priest is
      because John was in the role of a deacon/minister</hi> before
      our Saviour, <hi rend="italic">and not in the role of a presbyter, a priest
      of the New Testament</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The psalmody (</hi>zummara<hi rend="italic">) before the Gospel: a
      symbol</hi> of the songs <hi rend="italic">of praise</hi> of the disciples
      <hi rend="italic">and children who were crying out saying, "Hosanna</hi>
      [192a] to the son of David" etc. (Matt. 21:9).</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The silk vestment that the priest</hi> carrying the
      Gospel <hi rend="italic">is wrapped in</hi>: (this is) <hi rend="italic">because he stands
      in the role of our Lord who was wrapped in a robe of
      glory</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The coming forth of the Gospel, and the Cross with it:
      a symbol of the humanity of our Lord which existed in body
      and soul. The Cross is a symbol of the body which was
      crucified, and the Gospel a symbol of the soul in which there
      is rationality</hi>.</item>
            <item>That the Gospel goes forth <hi rend="italic">with a procession of the
      deacons is a symbol of the procession with which our Lord
      entered Jerusalem,</hi> riding on a colt.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The reading of the Gospel: a demonstration of our
      Lord's reply to the Scribes and Pharisees</hi> who were
      smitten with envy, and they said to him, "Do you not hear
      what these people are saying? Rebuke them, so that they do
      not praise you as God". Whereas our Lord answered and said to
      them, "If these keep quiet, the stones will cry out" etc. And
      this is the end of the matter. (Matt. 21:16, Luke
      19:39-40)</item>
            <item>[192b] The reading of the Gospel is a symbol of all the
      words which our Lord spoke to the Jews before he
      suffered.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Cross which is fixed above the staff</hi> is a
      symbol <hi rend="italic">of what our Lord said as he indicated by what
      death</hi> the Son of Man would be raised up, and (how)
      everyone who believes in him will not be ashamed, but have
      eternal life.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Lights at that moment are a symbol of what our
      Lord told</hi> his Apostles, "<hi rend="italic">You are the light of the
      world"</hi> (Matt. 5:14); and again, "<hi rend="italic">Let your light thus
      shine out before people</hi> so that they may see your good
      works and praise your Father who is in heaven". (Matt.
      5:16)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that there are two Lights, not one, is
      because he did not say this just to the Apostles</hi>, all of
      whom were from the single people of Israel, <hi rend="italic">but also (he
      said it) concerning those who</hi> from the gentiles <hi rend="italic">were
      converted at their hands</hi>, as the words he spoke when he
      prayed testify, [193a] "Not only for these do I ask, but also
      for those who believe through their words". (John 17:20)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The</hi> (<hi rend="italic">sweet</hi>) <hi rend="italic">incense</hi> at this moment
      <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of the sweetness of our Lord's words</hi>; what
      he said indicates: "Come unto me, all you who are weary and
      carrying loads, and I will give you rest (Matt. 11:28); for
      my yoke is kind (<hi rend="italic">bassim</hi>) and my load is light". (Matt.
      11:30) And again, "Learn from me that I am restful and humble
      in my heart, and you will find rest for yourselves". (Matt.
      11:29)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The</hi> turgama after the Gospel <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of the
      teaching uttered by</hi> Jesus <hi rend="italic">before he suffered</hi>.</item>
            <item>The supplication and <hi rend="italic">proclamation</hi>: as a
      demonstration of his saying "<hi rend="italic">Be wakeful and pray</hi> so
      that you do not enter into temptation" (Matt. 26:41)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The prayer of the</hi> syamida <hi rend="italic">which the person who
      fills the role of Christ prays is a symbol of the prayer that
      he prayed [193b] over his disciples before he suffered</hi>:
      "Holy <hi rend="italic">Father</hi>, <hi rend="italic">keep them by your name</hi> that you
      have given me, so that they may be one, just as we are one"
      (John 17:11), and the remainder of the words that he uttered
      in prayer before he was arrested by the Jews.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Cross and the Gospel</hi> on the Throne that is
      <hi rend="italic">on the Bema</hi>: <hi rend="italic">a symbol of the sitting of Jesus among
      his disciples</hi> as he taught the crowds in Jerusalem.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The taking up of the Cross along with the Gospel from
      the Throne</hi>, and the descent from the Bema: <hi rend="italic">a symbol of
      the arrest of Jesus by the crucifiers, and his departure from
      Jerusalem to the place where he was crucified</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that a priest carries the Gospel: a symbol of
      the attachment of John the Evangelist who accompanied Jesus
      up to the crucifixion</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The carrying of the Cross by a deacon:[194a] a symbol
      of the carrying of the Cross by Simon of Cyrene who was
      coming from the field</hi>. (Matt. 27:32 and par.)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that the Cross and the Gospel come down from
      the Bema without any procession</hi> and unaccompanied by
      <hi rend="italic">priests and deacons: because when Jesus was arrested and
      led off to be crucified, all his disciples abandoned him and
      fled</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The raising of the Cross at the entrance of the
      sanctuary door: a symbol of the crucifixion of Jesus on the
      wood</hi> (of the Cross).</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The separation of the Gospel from the Cross</hi>, and
      its being placed <hi rend="italic">on the other side: a symbol of the
      separation of his soul from his body and its going to
      Paradise</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">The fact that, when the Cross and Gospel are
          placed by the sanctuary door</hi>, the deacons <hi rend="italic">say</hi>
          "<hi rend="italic">Let whoever has not received</hi> baptism [194b]
          depart": <hi rend="italic">a symbol which (the Church) depicts
          (indicating) that when the soul of Jesus separated
          from</hi> his <hi rend="italic">body and entered Paradise, the soul of
          the (Good) Thief accompanying it</hi> (cp Luke 23:43),
          <hi rend="italic">all the souls of the righteous from Adam up till that
          moment, entered after them into Paradise</hi>, which is a
          staging post for the Kingdom of Heaven; <hi rend="italic">whereas all
          the souls of sinners are held back and prohibited from
          entering.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">At this moment the Church depicts a type by which
          she portrays the crucifixion of Jesus on the Wood</hi> and
          <hi rend="italic">the separation &lt;of his soul</hi>&gt; (from his body)
          <hi rend="italic">and its entry into Paradise</hi>; by dividing off and
          <hi rend="italic">expelling those who are not worthy to participate in
          his living and saving body</hi>, (the Church) <hi rend="italic">hints
          that in the same way</hi> the <hi rend="italic">souls of sinners have
          been held back and prohibited from entering</hi> that holy
          place of Paradise <hi rend="italic">along with</hi> [195a] <hi rend="italic">the souls
          of the righteous</hi>. It is as if the divine intimation
          was saying to them, "Let everyone depart who does not
          repent of his sins like the Thief, and for whom his
          repentance has not filled the place of baptism, and let
          him not enter Paradise. And <hi rend="italic">everyone who from this
          moment onwards is not going to receive the mark</hi>
          (rushma) of Salvation in the <hi rend="italic">baptism</hi> that Jesus
          has handed down to his Church, let him go back and <hi rend="italic">not
          enter that holy place</hi>; <hi rend="italic">just as</hi> Jesus <hi rend="italic">said
          beforehand</hi>: '<hi rend="italic">Whoever is not born of water and the
          Spirit</hi> shall not enter the Kingdom of heaven'". (John
          3:5) <hi rend="italic">Thus in the case of everyone who does not
          sanctify his body</hi> and soul and <hi rend="italic">receive the gift of
          the Mysteries in purity, his soul will go (and join) the
          sinners, and not enter Paradise</hi>.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item>"<hi rend="italic">Depart</hi>, <hi rend="italic">catechumens</hi>
      (shamo<hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi>e)", etc. [195b]<hi rend="italic">(This is) like
      the divine intimation bidding the angels there to preserve
      those (souls) mentioned (earlier)</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">From this point onwards the Church depicts</hi> a type
      of <hi rend="italic">the burial of Christ by the setting out of the bread
      and wine</hi> that are placed <hi rend="italic">on the altar, for the altar
      is considered as (taking) the place of the tomb, and the veil
      over the bread and wine as (taking) the place of the stone
      which was placed above the entrance of the tomb</hi>. (cp
      Matt. 28:2 and par.)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The deacons who stand on either side: a symbol of the
      angels who were seen in the tomb, one by his pillow, the
      other at his feet</hi>. (cp John 20:12)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Cross and the Gospel that are placed on the altar,
      and above them the icon of our Lord</hi>, amidst which the
      awesome Mysteries are consecrated: <hi rend="italic">these fulfil the place
      of the person of our Lord who</hi>, [196a] when he handed down
      these Holy Mysteries to his disciples did not cut some of his
      own body to give them to eat, nor did he put some of his own
      blood in a cup to give them to drink—this could not
      possibly happen!; rather, he blessed bread and wine, broke
      and gave to them saying, "This is my body and this is my
      blood; take, eat and drink of it, all of you. And thus should
      you be doing whenever you are gathered in remembrance of me".
      (cp Matt. 26:26-7 and par.; 1 Cor. 11:23-6)</item>
            <item>The fact that he said "This is my body", and "This is my
      blood", and did not say "a type of my body and my blood", was
      so that the matter of the Holy Mysteries should not be
      thought of as ordinary. [196b] For this reason, in the
      consecration of the Mysteries the holy Church depicts the
      type of that moment when our Lord handed down this Mystery to
      his disciples: instead of the person of our Lord, she places
      the Cross and the Gospel on the altar, and instead of the
      bread and wine which he gave, she sets out bread and wine.
      <hi rend="italic">Accordingly it is not at all permitted for the Holy
      Mysteries to be consecrated without the proximity of the
      Cross, the Gospel and the icon of our Lord</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The <hi rend="sup">
                     <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                  </hi>
               </hi>Onitha <hi rend="italic">of the</hi>
      Raze<hi rend="italic">: a symbol of the ineffable songs of praise which the
      holy angels and the souls of the righteous raised up at the
      time when the souls entered Paradise along with the soul of
      our Lord</hi>.<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Alternatively: a symbol of the songs of praise of the
      angels</hi> and saints <hi rend="italic">at the time of the Passion of our
      Lord</hi>, <hi rend="italic">when they saw that the earth quaked, the rocks
      were rent apart, the sun [197a] was darkened</hi>, and the
      curtain of the Temple was torn, and the dead who had arisen.
      (Matt. 27:45, 51-2)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that at this time the priests are seated on
      the Bema</hi> is because, <hi rend="italic">at the death of Jesus, all the
      Apostles were sitting in Jerusalem, in hiding for fear of the
      Jews</hi>, with their minds dazed as they pondered on the
      death of their Master.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Their washing their hands at this time: a symbol of
      the washing away from their hearts of resentment</hi>
      (Abraham: against the Jews) and doubt over the love of their
      Lord.<lb/>
      Alternatively: a symbol of the washing of the Jews.<lb/>
      Again, because they are on the point of entering the
      sanctuary in order to complete and perfect the service of the
      awesome Mysteries, they do well to indicate, by the washing
      of their hands, the washing away from their hearts of
      resentment and enmity; just as our Lord himself [197b] said,
      "When you get up to pray, leave behind anything you have
      against anyone". (Mark 11:25) And in another place he said,
      "Do you wash the interior—that is, the heart—from
      which issue forth evil thoughts which make a person unclean".
      (cp Matt. 15:19-20) Just as the blessed David said, "I have
      washed my hands in purity and have gone around your altar".
      (Ps. 26:5(6))</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that when the priests go down from the Bema
      the deacons come out of the sanctuary and do obeisance to
      them, and give way for them to enter (the sanctuary) in front
      of them: this instructs that when the Jews crucified Christ,
      the priesthood (Abraham: and kingdom) was taken from them;
      and the Levites left the sanctuary while there entered the
      company of Simon, who did not carry out their ministry with
      the sacrifice of animals, [198a] but with the living
      sacrifice of the Son of God,</hi> concerning whom the blessed
      Melkizedek, in the distant past and many generations ago, had
      indicated beforehand. (cp Gen. 14:20; Heb. 5:6,
      7:10-11).</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that the deacons</hi> meet <hi rend="italic">the priests and
      enter the sanctuary after</hi> them <hi rend="italic">is a demonstration
      of</hi> what has happened: that <hi rend="italic">those</hi> of the priests
      and Levites <hi rend="italic">who believed in Christ</hi> and were converted
      <hi rend="italic">used to hold the Apostles in great honour, like disciples
      their teachers, showing reverence to them and showing respect
      to their words</hi>; just like (other) people who were
      converted through them and received baptism from them, they
      also received ordination of priesthood from them. Rightly are
      they numbered after the apostles, in accordance with the will
      of the Spirit who (thus) assigned them.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that,[198b] when the priests enter the
      sanctuary, before everything else they say the Creed laid
      down by our Fathers. This indicates that everyone who does
      not correctly believe in the Holy Trinity and the
      Dispensation effected in Christ, is alien to the truth, and
      deprived of delight with our Lord</hi> Christ who was
      sacrificed for the salvation of the world.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that</hi> when the Creed has finished the
      herald (= deacon) <hi rend="italic">says</hi>, "<hi rend="italic">Pray for the memory</hi> of
      our Fathers the bishops" <hi rend="italic">is a demonstration of the
      spiritual love</hi> which bids us to honour and pray <hi rend="italic">for
      our Fathers</hi> who have laboured, toiled and struggled for
      the true faith, and for its sake have accepted all kinds of
      tortures and deaths.</item>
            <item>The (words) "Let us also pray for the priests and
      deacons": because they too have toiled [199a] and been
      diligent in the divine ministry, and they have instructed and
      baptized. And "Let us remember, along with these, the
      celibate young men and women", for they too, by their
      virtuous way of life, have benefited the entire community.
      Thus <hi rend="italic">we also pray for the remainder of the faithful, who
      are to the Church like sons and daughters, in order to show
      that the fullness of spiritual love is preserved in the
      Church</hi>.</item>
            <item>The fact that we remember the prophets, apostles, martyrs
      and confessors is because we take refuge in their prayers so
      that we may be held worthy to carry out fittingly this
      awesome divine service.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Up to here the Church depicts, through her types, the
      Mystery/symbol of the death and burial of Christ. From now on
      the priest approaches to depict the type of the
      Resurrection</hi> through the recital [199b] of the holy words
      from his mouth, and by the sign (<hi rend="italic">rushma</hi>) of the cross
      which is in his hand. <hi rend="italic">For just as our Lord</hi> Jesus
      <hi rend="italic">Christ, when he transmitted these Mysteries, blessed, gave
      thanks as said</hi> (these words), <hi rend="italic">so the Church, in
      accordance with his bidding, separates out a single priest to
      be the one who blesses and gives thanks, in the likeness of
      Christ our Lord. Through the recital, he indicates that he is
      uttering the words of our Lord</hi>, (saying) "This is my body
      which is broken for you for the forgiveness of sins". (1 Cor.
      11:24) <hi rend="italic">After the priest's recital, blessing the bread and
      the wine, through the grace of the Holy Spirit which
      overshadows, they become henceforth the Body and Blood of
      Christ—not by nature, but by faith and effectiveness.
      It is not that Christ has two bodies, one in heaven and one
      on earth; rather, [200a] just as a king and his statue/image
      do not constitute two kings. Nor does the humanity which has
      been taken from us constitute two sons, but a single Son of
      God who has been united to the humanity that (comes) from us.
      Thus this Body along with that one in heaven constitute the
      single Body of Christ</hi>. Accordingly, it is necessary for
      the priest to complete this awesome service in fear and with
      great attention, realizing that he is standing there at that
      moment instead of Christ, as he blesses and gives
      thanks.</item>
            <item>Now at this time the priest prays the first prayer. In it
      is confession and supplication for himself; he prays and
      supplicates that he may be held worthy to carry out his
      priestly action fittingly.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The first Peace which the priest gives [200b] to the
      people is a prayer of the priesthood where</hi> he <hi rend="italic">prays
      for the people that there may remain</hi> with him, and beside
      him, <hi rend="italic">that peace which Christ left behind before he
      died</hi>, saying "<hi rend="italic">My peace I leave to you</hi>". (John
      14:27)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">After the people respond to the priest "May you have
      peace with the spirit of priesthood which you have received",
      then the herald bids the people "Give the peace to one
      another in the love of Christ"; that is to say, "Show in
      action your peace with one another, and root out from your
      hearts resentment</hi> and enmity<hi rend="italic">, so that you may become
      worthy to receive the life-giving Mysteries</hi>, and be
      forgiven your sins". (cp Matt. 6:14<hi rend="italic">) For with this peace
      we fulfil the words of our Lord, "Forgive</hi>, so that <hi rend="italic">you
      may be forgiven</hi>", and again, "When you offer up your
      offering on the altar [201a] and there remember that your
      brother holds some resentment against you, leave your
      offering there on the altar", and the rest. (Matt.
      5:23-4)</item>
            <item>The fact that at this point they <hi rend="italic">read the Book of the
      Living and the Dead is for a demonstration that the Mysteries
      of our salvation have been performed on behalf of the living
      and the dead, and together, the living and the dead are in
      need of what is carried out by us in a mystical
      fashion</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That a single priest offers the</hi> sacrifice: as <hi rend="italic">a
      symbol of the one High Priest who was sacrificed</hi> for the
      salvation of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> race.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The priests and deacons who stand in the sanctuary
      (are) a demonstration that the holy angels are close by when
      the Mystery of our salvation is performed</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That the herald cries out</hi> and says "<hi rend="italic">Stand well
      and be attentive</hi> to what is being done: (this) is <hi rend="italic">an
      instruction of the priesthood</hi> who prepare the entire
      [201b] people so that <hi rend="italic">everyone stands</hi> with great
      attention <hi rend="italic">before God at that awesome</hi> and dread
      <hi rend="italic">time</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The incense at this point: a symbol of the aromatic
      spices with which the body of our Saviour was
      embalmed</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That the priest inclines himself three times and
      recites the holy words</hi> of the offering of the oblation:
      <hi rend="italic">a symbol of the three days during which the humanity of
      our Lord was under the authority of death</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that he recites the entire section quietly,
      but at the end raises his voice so that the people can
      hear</hi>: first, because it is <hi rend="italic">a Mystery that is being
      performed, and it is not appropriate that all the people
      should know of it; and secondly, so that the words, on being
      heard, should not be learnt by laymen, women and children,
      with the result that the divine worlds are held to be
      ordinary and (so) despised</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that [202a] he raises his voice at the end
      (is) so that, along with the priest, the people should
      participate</hi> with the response "Amen".</item>
            <item>The fact that, at the moment of the epiclesis [lit.
      hovering] <hi rend="italic">the herald cries out</hi> and says "<hi rend="italic">In your
      minds</hi> pray; <hi rend="italic">in stillness</hi> and fear be standing":
      <hi rend="italic">in order to teach us that at this moment full of awe it is
      not appropriate that we should utter our prayers in an
      audible voice, but rather, in stillness, within the
      heart</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that the entire people prostrate, along with
      the priest, at the time of the epiclesis [lit. hovering]
      corresponds to our supplicating, together with the priest,
      that the grace of the Holy Spirit should come and perfect and
      complete the Holy Mysteries. Again, in honour of the coming
      of Grace</hi> we supplicate and <hi rend="italic">prostrate</hi> in stillness
      and awe.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact [202b] that when the priest invokes the
      Spirit and she hovers he joins the Body to the Blood, and the
      Blood to the Body: a symbol of the returning of the soul
      of</hi> our Lord <hi rend="italic">within his body, and his resurrection from
      the dead</hi>. For the priest resurrects the Body symbolically
      through the agency of the Spirit.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that, after the tabernacling of Grace, the
      priest does not make the sign of the cross again over the
      Mysteries (is) because the Mysteries have been completed
      by</hi> the dissolution <hi rend="italic">of death</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that at this point we remove the incense from
      the altar (is) because corruptibility, which was the reason
      for the embalming, is dissolved</hi>.</item>
            <item> 
        <list type="ordered">
                  <item>After these things the herald cries out and says
          "<hi rend="italic">Let us all with fear</hi> and honour approach the
          Mystery of the honoured Body and Blood of our Saviour"
          etc. Through this proclamation the priesthood <hi rend="italic">teaches
          us concerning the exalted character and the greatness of
          the Mystery; and that we should not [203a] henceforth
          look on the bread and wine in accordance with their
          natural disposition, but as the Body and Blood of
          Christ</hi>, who in his human <hi rend="italic">qnoma</hi> is body and
          soul, like everyone, because of the conjunction with God
          the Word who shared everything with him apart from his
          (divine) nature; (God) granted that he should have life
          in his <hi rend="italic">qnoma</hi>, just as our Lord said "Just as the
          Father has life in his <hi rend="italic">qnoma</hi>, so likewise did he
          grant to the Son to have life in his <hi rend="italic">qnoma"</hi>. (John
          5:26). For it is clear that what he said here about the
          Father was said because of the weakness of the listeners,
          for it was not the case that the Father gave to his
          eternal Son to have life in his <hi rend="italic">qnoma</hi>, as is the
          supposition of the heretics, but (he did so) to the Man
          who (derives) from us, who, because of his union with God
          the Word, has inherited a name that is more honourable
          than [203b] all names, etc., (cp Heb.1:4) that is, the
          Son of God, as the angel said to his Bearer, "He shall be
          called Son of the Most High", (Luke 1:32) that is, the
          Man who possesses body and blood, whose type he
          transmitted to the Church; just as, again, our Lord said,
          "The Spirit gives life, the body profits nothing".(John
          6:63) For the body of our Lord Christ does not possess of
          its own (human) nature New Life, and was going to give
          (this) to others too; rather, through the grace of the
          Holy Spirit which was given to him (sc. the Man) as a
          result of his resurrection from the dead, and by the
          perfect conjunction with the divine Nature, he was raised
          up, and became the gatherer of immortality to others,
          just as he said "Just as I am alive because of my Father,
          so whoever eats me will also live because of me". (John
          6:54) Accordingly, with awe [204a] and great attention we
          ought to approach this Mystery, and not in an ordinary
          fashion.</item>
                  <item>For just as (in the case of) the blessing with which
          God blessed Adam and Eve, saying "Be fruitful and
          multiply, and fill the earth", (Gen. 1:28) it travels
          through all generations up till eternity, without being
          held back, so too with that blessing with which our Lord
          blessed the bread and the wine, calling them his Body and
          Blood, it travels through all generations up to eternity,
          without being held back.</item>
                  <item>Again, just as it is an act of great wickedness that
          someone should say that Adam is not the image of God when
          God (himself) called him his image (Gen. 1:26), so (too)
          it is an act of great wickedness that someone should say
          of the Mysteries that they are not the Body and Blood of
          Christ, after (Christ) himself has said [204b] "This is
          my Body, and this is my Blood".</item>
                  <item>For even though by their nature they are bread and
          wine, but we, by faith, ought to look upon them as the
          Body and Blood of Christ, just as we were instructed by
          Christ. And whenever we take them in our hands we ought
          thus to think that we are embracing and kissing our
          Saviour himself, as we mingle his Body in our body, and
          mix his Blood in our blood. Consequently it is
          appropriate that we approach them with awe and honour,
          seeing that they convey two types, of things past and
          things to come: for they teach us about the closeness we
          shall have to Christ in the world to come; for he, again,
          arms us against suffering and death, since through these
          our salvation has been accomplished. For the blessed Paul
          said, [205a] "Whenever you eat this Bread and drink this
          Cup, you recall the death of our Lord, until his coming
          (again)". (1 Cor. 11:26) For if, by participating in the
          Mysteries we make a commemoration of the suffering and
          death, according to the words of the Apostle, (Christ)
          did well to transmit to us, along with the Body, also the
          Blood, so that by the Body we might learn about the
          suffering, in that suffering affects the body, and
          through the Blood, (we might learn) the strength of the
          suffering, in that the suffering causes blood to be shed.
          And from this we learn that, through the suffering and
          death (of Christ) we have been held worthy of this entire
          gift, in order that we might have expectation of
          resurrection and delight with Christ in eternal
          life.</item>
                  <item>Besides teaching us how we should approach the Holy
          Mysteries in awe [205b] and with honour, at the same time
          the sense of the words of this proclamation also puts to
          shame the dogmas of the heretics who proclaim that this
          (sc. the <hi rend="italic">karozutha</hi>) is concerning (?) the
          reception (of Communion)—about which they say that
          we are saved by the death of God—with the result
          that they have removed this proclamation from their
          churches, since they cannot (bear to) hear what is said
          in it, (namely) that for our sakes the Only Begotten God
          the Word took from human beings a mortal body and a
          rational soul endowed with intelligence, and immortal;
          and after the entire dispensation on our behalf the
          Firstfruits of our nature was tested on the cross, arose
          from the dead, and was raised to heaven.</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">At the end of this proclamation we say "Lord, forgive
      the sins</hi> and wrongdoings <hi rend="italic">of your servants</hi>",
      <hi rend="italic">seeing that we are in this world of mortality,[206a] and
      it is not possible that we should not do wrong, as</hi> we
      learn from <hi rend="italic">what has been said "There is no one who does
      not sin</hi>". (cp Eccl. 7:20)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">After these things we say the prayer of "Our Father
      who is in heaven</hi>". It is right we should say this prayer
      at this point: for, <hi rend="italic">because we are depicting the Mystery
      of the death and the resurrection by which we become children
      of God, it is good that we now call God "Our Father". Just as
      our Lord said, "You shall not call (anyone) father on
      earth</hi>", (Matt. 23:9) and as the blessed Paul said, "Just
      as Jesus Christ has risen from the dead in the glory of his
      Father, so too we shall walk in New Life", (Rom. 6:4) in that
      henceforth we become, in faith, children of God, just as he
      again said, "We call God 'Father, our Father'". (Rom.
      8:15)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The Peace which the priest gives at this [206b] moment
      is a symbol of that peace which our Lord gave to the women
      and to his disciples</hi> after he had arisen from the
      dead.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">After</hi> these things <hi rend="italic">the priest says</hi> "<hi rend="italic">What
      is holy is fitting for the holy, in harmony": we do not
      presume to speak about this matter which the Interpreter
      expounded</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">We crown this service by means of thanksgiving, and we
      say "One holy Father", indicating through this that the Holy
      Trinity is not a numerical Trinity where one precedes two,
      and two (precedes) three, but (a case of) one, one,
      one.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">We provide a seal with "Praise to the Father and to
      the Son and to the Holy Spirit, for eternal ages, amen". By
      this we indicate that the cause of all our benefits is that
      worshipful and glorious Nature which is confessed (as)
      Father, Son and Holy Spirit</hi>, [207a] to whom is due glory
      and honour, thanksgiving and worship, not only now but to
      eternal ages, amen.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">We say these things at this point in remembrance of
      what our Lord said to his Apostles</hi> after he arose from
      the dead, that "everything has been transmitted to me" etc.,
      (Matt. 11:27) "<hi rend="italic">Go out, therefore, make disciples of all
      the nations; baptise them in the name of the Father, Son and
      Holy Spirit".</hi> (Matt. 28:19)</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The fact that we say "Fearful are You", and the
      Response (<hi rend="sup">
                     <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
                  </hi>
               </hi>onaya<hi rend="italic">) is a symbol of the
      praises</hi> and ineffable hullale <hi rend="italic">with which all the
      heavenly hosts give praise for the dispensation that has been
      effected in Christ.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">That the consecrator is the first to receive the
      Sacrament (</hi>qudsha<hi rend="italic">) is a symbol of what (occurred with)
      Jesus, the High Priest, for the priest stands in his role;
      for (Christ), through the sacrifice of himself first, through
      the Holy Spirit, [207b] received the nourishment of
      immortality; and then he was capable of giving it to
      others.</hi> For this reason, it was not in an ordinary way,
      without the Spirit, the divine Nature in him, that he took
      and gave to himself, just as it is said that he also raised
      himself, in that he was also God; and it was not because he
      was Man that he raised himself, as he intimated by what he
      said, "This commandment I have received from my Father".
      (John 10:18) <hi rend="italic">Therefore</hi> (the priest who celebrates)
      <hi rend="italic">should, without restraint, be bold to receive the
      Sacrament without anyone else, for he stands in the role of
      the life-giving Spirit. Now the consecrator gives to others
      as a demonstration of what will happen as a result of our
      Lord at the (final) resurrection, for he will give us all
      that future immortality.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Our partaking of the Holy Mysteries is a symbol of our
      participation that we shall have with him in the Kingdom
      [208a] of Heaven</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">The</hi> teshbo<hi rend="u">h</hi>ta <hi rend="italic">beginning
      "Our Lord Jesus, revered Sovereign</hi>", which we say at the
      end of the service of the Mysteries, <hi rend="italic">is a symbol of (the
      praise) that will occur in the world to come from all
      rational beings, for we praise and exalt as heavenly King the
      one in whom the entire fullness of divinity willed to dwell,
      and through his mediation we worship the Trinity</hi>.</item>
            <item>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>The "Seal of Prayer" and the signing <hi rend="italic">of the cross
          by the priest over the people (is) in remembrance of that
          blessing with which our Lord blessed his Apostles at the
          time he was raised up to heaven</hi>, just as the blessed
          Luke said, "It happened that while he was blessing them
          that he was separated from them and he ascended to
          heaven". (Luke 24:51)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="italic">Again</hi>, the blessings with which <hi rend="italic">the priest
          blesses the people as he stands on the threshold of the
          sanctuary door is [208b] a symbol of the tabernacling of
          the grace of the Holy Spirit over the apostles after our
          Lord had ascended to heaven</hi>, just as he himself said,
          "I tell you the truth, that it is better for you that I
          should go; for if I do not go, the Paraclete will not
          come to you. Whereas, if I go, I will send him to you".
          (John 16:7) This was fulfilled with the apostles on the
          day of Pentecost, as Luke wrote in Acts, "There appeared
          to them tongues divided like fire, and they settled on
          each one of them and they were all filled with the Holy
          Spirit". (Acts 2:3)</item>
               </list>
            </item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Also the Peace that we give one another after
      receiving the Mysteries is a symbol of the holy union by
      which we are united there to one another, as limbs, and we
      are all joined to the Head of the Church [209a] and the
      Firstborn from the dead, (Col. 1:18) our Lord Jesus
      Christ</hi>.</item>
            <item>Understand, O discerning reader, and see how, from the
      reading of the Gospel until the end of this service, nothing
      of the ancient psalmody is said, and realize that it is not
      right that there should be said on feasts those two Psalms
      which are said in the monasteries of solitaries when the
      brethren finish in the sanctuary, since these do not belong
      to the former (liturgical) arrangements, but they have come
      in recently; and testimony to their recent character are the
      churches where they are not said. But if there should be a
      church with this custom, having learnt it from solitaries who
      are ancient(?) or close by, they [ ] accepting it without
      investigation [ ] and all sorts of <hi rend="italic">teshbhatha</hi> and
      <hi rend="italic">qanone</hi> [209b] and (liturgical) arrangements. On what
      understanding the solitaries make use of these two psalms I
      have no idea. But one should realize this, that formerly the
      psalms from the Old Testament were arranged so as to be used
      as a demonstration of the prior character of the Old
      Testament, preceding in time the New Testament; accordingly
      as a result we culminate all our services with new poetic
      texts, so as to demonstrate that the New Testament has
      fulfilled and set the seal on the Old Testament, following
      the declaration of the blessed Paul, who says, "Christ is the
      end of the Law", (Rom 10:4) and as our Saviour said, "The Law
      and the Prophets have prophesied up to the time of John; from
      then on the Kingdom of Heaven is necessarily [210a] in
      force". (Luke 16:16) Both these things we depict in the
      arrangements for the church services; if that were not so,
      why is it that in all the services, after the
      <hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">onitha</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">qanona</hi>,
      <hi rend="italic">teshbo<hi rend="u">h</hi>ta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">karozutha</hi>,
      or "Holy...", we do not utter anything further from the Old
      Testament. And if we observe this in all the other services,
      how much more ought we to observe this in the service of the
      Mysteries, which is the seal of all the other services. For
      it is in this service that we depict the type of the Passion
      and death and resurrection and ascension, and the gift of the
      Spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ who fulfilled the Old
      Testament and gave the New. Manifestly in this service we
      ought to observe the (rule) that after we have finished
      [210b] the service, we do not say anything from the Old
      Testament. Otherwise, after receiving the Mysteries, the
      participation in which points to the participation we shall
      have with Christ in the world to come, then, at the very
      moment when we depict the type of that holy union, we are
      returning to say a psalm from the Old Testament—which
      depicts the type of this world: by doing so we indicate that
      we concur with the infantile mentality of the Jews, and that
      of the heretic Apollinarius who transmitted that, after the
      resurrection we would again be eating and drinking, and once
      again living in the way of life of the Old Testament. This is
      something that is absurd [211a] for us to accept, seeing that
      it is the opposite to the words which our Lord spoke: "Human
      beings will be like angels, because they have become children
      of the Resurrection". (Luke 20:36)</item>
            <item>Along with these things, I urge those who are going to
      encounter this book not to attach blame to me if they find
      anything I have said which does not agree with the view of
      others, for it is the sequence of the arrangements that
      forces me to act thus; otherwise, the sequential order of the
      wording and meaning would be confused and muddled. For every
      explanation that does not have a sequential ordering that
      fits the order and sequence (<hi rend="italic">akolouthia</hi>) of the words,
      then the commentator misses the aim of the meaning and he
      will not be accepted by discerning readers, as the blessed
      [211b] Interpreter declared when he spoke on this matter on
      many occasions. I have not thought it necessary to set these
      out here, so as not to burden the discourse by reason of the
      expansive and drawn-out nature of the universal Teacher's
      words.</item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock8">Text</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Since the Syriac text of this important section of Gabriel's
    Commentary has not yet been published, I give it here.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref> In
    copying Gabriel's work the scribe of Or. 3336 has made a number
    of small errors, and these have been corrected in the text
    printed below, though in every case the manuscript's reading is
    given in the apparatus.</p>
         <p> </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText01.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText02.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText03.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText04.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText05.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText06.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText07.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText08.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText09.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText10.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText11.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText12.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText13.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText14.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText15.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText16.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText17.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText18.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText19.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText20.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText21.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText22.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText23.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText24.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="698px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText25.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="420px"
                     height="678px"/>
            <lb/>
            <graphic url="HV6N2BrockText26.gif"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/gif"
                     width="422px"
                     height="436px"/>
         </p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock9">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> (London, 1899), 15.<ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> "Gabriel Qatraya et son commentaire sur la liturgie
    chaldéenne"<hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 32
    (1966), 39-52. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> "Syriac writers from Beth Qatraye," <hi rend="italic">Aram</hi>
    11-12 (1999-2000), 85-96, esp. 89-92. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> Ed. J.B. Chabot, <hi rend="italic">Le Livre de la Chasteté
    composé par Jesusdenah</hi> (Rome 1896). <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> By ‘king’ either Sasanid shah or Muslim
    Caliph could be intended. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> Liber Castitatis, section 125. <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> J-M.Fiey, <hi rend="italic">Nisibe</hi>, <hi rend="italic">metropole syriaque
    orientale</hi> (CSCO Subsidia 54; 1977), 219.<ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Analecta</hi> 207, 1979,
    29-48. <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> R.H. Connolly, <hi rend="italic">Anonymi auctoris Expositio
    Officiorum Ecclesiae Georgio Arbelensi vulgo ascripta. Accedit
    Abrahae Bar Lipeh Interpretation Officiorum, II</hi> (CSCO
    Scr.Syri 29, 1913), 171-80. <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> Reedited, with English translation, in my
    "An early Syriac Commentary on the Liturgy", <hi rend="italic">Journal of
    Theological Studies</hi> NS 37 (1986), 387-403. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> Latin translation in J-M.Vosté,
    <hi rend="italic">Ordo iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum ... a Mar
    Abdiso<hi rend="sup">
                  <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
               </hi> metropolita Nisibis et Armeniae
    latine interpretatus</hi> (Fonti, II.xv; Rome, 1940), 93-103. I
    hope to publish an English translation of this section in the
    near future. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> As does Iohannan bar
    Zo<hi rend="sup">
               <hi rend="italic">c</hi>
            </hi>bi, according to Jammo, "Gabriel Qatraya
    et son commentaire," 45. <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> J. Dauvillier, "Quelques témoignages
    littéraires et archéologiques sur la
    présence et sur le culte des Images dans
    l’Ancienne Eglise Chaldéenne," <hi rend="italic">L’Orient
    Syrien</hi> 1 (1956), 297-304, esp. 297; K. Parry, ‘Images
    in the Church of the East’, in J.F. Coakley and K. Parry
    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Church of the East:</hi> (= <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the
    John Rylands Library</hi> 78:3 (1996)), 143-62. <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> "L’Office du soir chaldéen au
    temps de Gabriel Qatraya," <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien</hi> 12
    (1967), 187-210.<ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> An edition of the Syriac translation of this
    letter is in preparation. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> This is from <hi rend="italic">Kephalaia Gnostica</hi>
    IV.25. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> Ed. P. Sherwood, ‘<hi rend="italic">Mimro</hi> de
    Serge de Reshaina sur la vie spirituelle’,
    <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Syrien</hi> 5 (1960), 433-59; 6 (1961),
    95-115, 121-56; sections 35-39 are quoted (= <hi rend="italic">L’Orient
    Syrien</hi> 5, (1060), 456, and 6 (1961), 96). There is also a
    quotation attributed to Dionysius on f.49ab. <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> For the liturgical technical terms, see the
    glossary in J. Mateos, <hi rend="italic">Lelya-Sapra: Essai
    d’interprétation des matines
    chaldéennes</hi> (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 156,
    1979), 485-502. <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> I take the opportunity to thank Fr. Robert
    Matheus for kindly lending me a photographic copy of the
    manuscript. <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif"
                        rend="img"
                        mimeType="image/gif"
                        width="15px"
                        height="15px"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Brock10">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Brock, S.P. "An early Syriac
    Commentary on the Liturgy," <hi rend="italic">Journal of Theological
    Studies</hi> NS 37 (1986), 387-403.</p>
         <p>— "Syriac writers from Beth
    Qatraye," <hi rend="italic">Aram</hi> 11-12 (1999-2000), 85-96.</p>
         <p>Chabot, J.B. <hi rend="italic">Le Livre de la
    Chasteté composé par Jesusdenah</hi> (Rome,
    1896).</p>
         <p>Dauvillier, J. "Quelques
    témoignages littéraires et archéologiques
    sur la présence et sur le culte des Images dans
    l'Ancienne Eglise Chaldéenne," <hi rend="italic">L'Orient Syrien</hi> 1
    (1956), 297-304.</p>
         <p>Fiey, J-M. <hi rend="italic">Nisibe, metropole
    syriaque orientale</hi> (CSCO Subsidia 54, 1977).</p>
         <p>Jammo, S.H. "Gabriel Qatraya et son
    commentaire sur la liturgie chaldéenne," <hi rend="italic">Orientalia
    Christiana Periodica</hi> 32 (1966), 39-52.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">La structure de la messe
    chaldéenne</hi>, Orientalia Christiana Analecta 207,
    1979.</p>
         <p>— "L'Office du soir
    chaldéen au temps de Gabriel Qatraya," <hi rend="italic">L'Orient
    Syrien</hi> 12 (1967), 187-210.</p>
         <p>Parry, K. "Images in the Church of
    the East," in J.F. Coakley and K. Parry (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Church
    of the East:</hi> (= <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the John Rylands Library</hi>
    78:3 (1996)), 143-62.</p>
         <p>Margoliouth, G. <hi rend="italic">Descriptive List
    of Syriac and Karshuni MSS. in the British Museum Acquired
    Since 1873</hi>, (London: Longmans &amp; Co., 1899).</p>
         <p>Mateos, J. <hi rend="italic">Lelya-Sapra: Essai
    d'interprétation des matines chaldéennes</hi>
    (Orientalia Christiana Analecta 156, 1979).</p>
         <p>Sherwood, P. (ed.) "Mimro de Serge
    de Reshaina sur la vie spirituelle," <hi rend="italic">L'Orient Syrien</hi> 5
    (1960), 433-59; 6 (1961), 95-115, 121-56.</p>
         <p>Vosté, J-M. <hi rend="italic">Ordo
    iudiciorum ecclesiasticorum ... a Mar Abdiso<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
    metropolita Nisibis et Armeniae latine interpretatus</hi>
    (Fonti, II.xv; Rome, 1940).</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
