<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Daniel Caner, Wandering, Begging Monks: Spiritual Authority and the Promotion of Monasticism in Late Antiquity. The Transformation of the Classical Heritage 33. University of California Press: Berkeley, 2002. Pp. xv + 325. Cloth, $65.00</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Robert A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kitchen</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Knox-Metropolitan United Church</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv6n2prkitchen</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Robert A. KITCHEN</author>
                  <title level="a">Daniel Caner, Wandering, Begging Monks: Spiritual Authority and the Promotion of Monasticism in Late Antiquity. The Transformation of the Classical Heritage 33. University of California Press: Berkeley, 2002. Pp. xv + 325. Cloth, $65.00</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol6/HV6N2PRKitchen.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="order" n="10"/>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Monasticism</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="review">
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    choice of topic for Daniel Caner's doctoral dissertation was an
    ingenuous and fortunate one. Working under Susanna Elm at the
    University of California at Berkeley, Caner approaches the
    social and religious history of all those wandering, begging
    monks and ascetics in Late Antiquity that everyone knows about,
    yet always manages to consign to simple condemnation or
    glorification - or push further out from investigation to the
    margins of ambiguity and neglect.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Towards
    these famous and infamous ascetics Caner's perspective is
    positive and sympathetic, without ignoring historical witnesses
    on either side of the controversies. He prefers to see the
    peripatetic ascetics as presenting another option to the form
    fourth- and fifth-century monasticism and asceticism took, to
    which there was considerable opposition as well as popular
    enthusiasm. Absorbing the rhetoric, Caner discerns not only the
    genuine historical cause and effect, but also the voices of
    religious and social authority and standing of the various
    authors. The benefit for the reader is to be able listen, for
    once unfettered, to the tales and controversies of monks who
    neither stayed still nor worked.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    historical narratives oscillate between several dichotomies
    (perhaps similar to the function of Walter Brueggemann's
    bipolar themes for Old Testament theology):</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Wandering, begging</hi> are understood by many as the
      consequences of the abandonment of <hi rend="italic">stillness,
      labor</hi>;</item>
            <item>
               <hi rend="italic">Akribeia</hi> (strict, scrupulous ascetic discipline)
      is fueled by desire for the imitation of Christ, while
      <hi rend="italic">argia</hi> (idleness) is the consequence of no
      discipline;</item>
            <item>Caner emphasizes that the real assessment of wandering
      ascetics was due to <hi rend="italic">behavioral criteria</hi>, rather than
      the <hi rend="italic">doctrinal criteria</hi> used by church leaders to
      condemn these same groups and individuals;</item>
            <item>The <hi rend="italic">apostolic mandate</hi> for engaging in this
      particular form of asceticism is presented as a neglected
      motive by Caner, in contrast to the assumption that most
      heretics modeled their behavior after that of a <hi rend="italic">heretical
      mentor</hi>.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    critical mass of this study resides in the Messalian
    controversy with Alexander the Sleepless (fl. 420s) as the
    object lesson and exemplar of how the issues were handled and
    interpreted. Caner includes as an appendix the first English
    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Life of Alexander Akoimētos</hi> from
    a solitary manuscript.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Caner
    takes a fresh look at a number of significant texts dealing
    with wandering, begging monks. From the perspective of this
    journal, it is gratifying to see that Syriac texts and history
    are being included as primary sources by non-Syriac specialists
    in cross-cultural studies of Late Antiquity.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In
    particular, Caner analyzes the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Liber
    Graduum</hi>) for its outlook on wandering, begging ascetics, a
    source he sees providing an alternative window through which to
    interpret primarily Greek ascetic phenomena.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] In the
    Introduction and first chapter, "Wandering in the Desert and
    the Virtues of Manual Labor," Caner sets the stage before us of
    the historical attitudes towards wandering, begging ascetics.
    The Coptic <hi rend="italic">Life of Phif</hi>, a fourth century wandering
    Egyptian monk, goes against the grain of Athanasius' <hi rend="italic">Life of
    Antony</hi> which established the agenda for most of fourth- and
    fifth-century monasticism, that of
    <hi rend="italic">xeniteia</hi>—voluntary (and settled in one place)
    alienation from material and social means of support. Wandering
    monks were variously suspected of avoiding manual labor or
    being possessed by demons.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Evagrius
    Ponticus added theory to the attitudes, warning that monks who
    wander will "practice false sayings" and create social
    disturbances. Moreover, such unsettled monks were particularly
    susceptible to <hi rend="italic">akēdia</hi>, or a desperate kind of bored
    depression and despondency.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Other
    characters, such as Abba Bessarion, would concoct an edifying
    tale to win the admiration and charity of his hosts, and then
    move on. Eventually, many came to perceive that the propensity
    to wander from place to place also suggested a refusal to
    submit to an elder's authority.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    Chapter 2, "Apostolic Wanderers of Third-Century Syria,"
    primarily treats Syriac materials, although Caner begins with
    the observations of Greek historian Sozomen. The latter
    identifies the first Syrian monks as <hi rend="italic">boskoi</hi> or
    "grazers," homeless people who ceaselessly praised God as they
    wandered the mountain regions, consuming neither bread nor meat
    nor wine.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Aphrahat and Ephrem, mid-fourth-century Syriac writers, witness
    to the establishment of communities of ascetics who patterned
    their life after Jesus, the <hi rend="italic">Ihīdāyā</hi> or
    "Only Begotten/Solitary One." These male and female clusters
    were known as the <hi rend="italic">Bnay/Bnāt Qyāmā</hi>,
    Sons/Daughters of the Covenant, "a living icon of Paradise
    restored" in the phrase of Sidney Griffith. These ascetics
    based their lifestyle on apostolic precedent rather than on the
    example of Antony, and that meant active engagement with the
    world they had renounced rather than permanent social
    withdrawal. To exhibit "demonstrative piety" (Fergus Millar)
    was considered an apostolic imperative.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Several texts provide evidence of this strategy, especially
    <hi rend="italic">The Acts of Thomas</hi>, in which Thomas is depicted in
    homeless poverty adopted in imitation of Jesus. Repeatedly,
    Thomas is called a "stranger" (<hi rend="italic">xenos</hi> in Greek;
    <hi rend="italic">aksnāyā</hi> in Syriac). After a while, it is
    difficult to distinguish the character of Thomas from Jesus,
    spurring the readers of the <hi rend="italic">Acts</hi> to imitate Thomas and
    Christ in the apostolic way of life.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    <hi rend="italic">Parrhēsia</hi>, the bold self-confidence needed to
    confront people of higher social station or office with freedom
    of speech, was a gift of the Hebrew prophets that was available
    to all Christians and especially ascetics if they imitated
    Jesus. Thomas, who challenged kings and nobility with his
    Christian ascetic agenda, is the model of
    <hi rend="italic">parrhēsia</hi>-filled speech and actions.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] A
    different witness is the third century Pseudo-Clementine
    <hi rend="italic">Letters to Virgins</hi>, extant in Syriac, which has little
    to do with virgins. Instead, it is a manual written to instruct
    wandering Christian ascetics how to conduct themselves
    appropriately and effectively in the towns and villages along
    their itinerary. The <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> proscribe that only a few
    in the traveling company should be allowed to speak publicly
    and then "with Jesus' gentleness and humility." Already, the
    author of the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> was observing that many want to
    talk for their own gain, "trafficking in iniquity in the name
    of Christ."</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of the Twelve Apostles</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Didache</hi>
    offered caution from the other side of the highway, enabling
    Christians in these towns, villages, and churches to
    distinguish the true charismatic wandering figures from the
    false ones. Begging for money or wanting to stay longer than
    two days were the negative red lights. Such persons who refused
    to work the <hi rend="italic">Didache</hi> labeled "Christmongers."</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Chapter Three, "In Support of "'People Who Pray': Apostolic
    Monasticism and the Messalian Controversy," as well as Chapter
    Four, treat the historical moments of controversy that brought
    the issues of wandering, begging monks to center stage.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    During this period the nebulous group of Messalians (Syriac -
    People Who Pray) were classified as heretics with specific
    doctrines attributed to them by church authorities and
    councils. Caner understands this activity as the result of an
    ecclesiastical process aimed at defining, consolidating, and
    homogenizing different forms of Christian life, marginalizing
    along the way any disturbing or competing "other." But since
    the alleged Messalian practices were derived from the Gospels
    rather than particular Messalian leaders, what was supposed to
    be uniquely Messalian could be found all over the empire
    wherever Christian ascetics turned to the Gospels for direction
    as they developed new forms of monasticism and asceticism.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18]
    Epiphanius of Salamis included Messalians in his catalogue of
    heresies, the <hi rend="italic">Panarion</hi>, and his profile would provide
    the general definition of Messalianism from the 370s onward.
    Wandering, cohabitation of males and females, total
    renunciation of material possessions, irregular prayer and
    fasting, literal identification with spiritual exemplars and
    <hi rend="italic">argia</hi>—refusal to work and consequent
    begging—were the primary sins.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] The
    ecumenical council at Ephesus in 431 condemned all Messalians,
    Euchites or Enthusiasts, and anathematized an <hi rend="italic">Asceticon</hi>,
    reputedly the Messalian manual. There have long been questions
    whether such a book existed. John of Damascus (eighth century)
    cited 18 sections from the so-called <hi rend="italic">Asceticon</hi> in his
    <hi rend="italic">On Heresies</hi>, but these citations have been shown to be
    excerpted from the spiritual homilies of Pseudo-Macarius.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] Into
    the fray Caner introduces the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>, a
    collection of 30 homilies written anonymously, most likely in
    northern Mesopotamia in the mid-fourth-century. Caner
    underlines the work's stark vision of ascetic poverty and frank
    discussion of what this means in actual practice. It is a book
    that presses the apostolic imperatives, at times echoes
    so-called Messalian traits, yet does not fit or accept the
    heretical patterns.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] The
    spiritual elite of the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>, the Perfect Ones,
    were "apostolic vagrants." The author urges them to imitate the
    deranged "fools of the world" who treat themselves with
    contempt by moving around in rags, without any home or
    possessions, eating whatever comes their way. They must not
    work if they intend to recapture the angelic freedom that had
    characterized Adam before his Fall—before he had to
    work.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] Once
    the Perfect can completely emulate the apostles, they are able
    to receive the Paraclete and be perfected, and then undertake
    an apostolic mission back towards the society they had
    renounced. According to the author of the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>,
    these ministries entitled the Perfect to material support from
    the Upright.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23]
    Caner enlists Augustine's <hi rend="italic">On the Work of Monks</hi> (written
    401) to show that while the label Messalian was not used, the
    assumption that dedication to an ascetic life strictly
    evangelical and apostolic in character includes a dependence
    upon and entitlement to material support from other Christians
    had spread to diverse regions.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24]
    Chapter Four, "Apostle and Heretic: The Controversial Career of
    Alexander the Sleepless," investigates the person who along
    with Adelphius of Edessa was identified as one of the
    arch-Messalian heretics. Caner resorts to the condemnations of
    the council at Antioch in 426, Ephesus in 431, and the treatise
    <hi rend="italic">On Voluntary Poverty</hi> by Nilus of Ancyra; along with the
    naturally sympathetic <hi rend="italic">Life of Alexander
    Akoimētos</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25]
    Alexander led a band of a hundred or so monks from place to
    place, where they would engage themselves seemingly in
    continual—even combative—prayer and psalm-singing
    in the public venues. Well-organized around the clock singing
    evoked the "sleepless" epithet. The band refused to work
    (interpreted as <hi rend="italic">argia</hi> by detractors) and would
    aggressively assert their right to support from the churches
    and populace. Alexander's prayers and psalms would frequently
    be diatribes against the legitimacy and authority of church and
    civil leaders. Consequently, Alexander and company were
    attacked and then evicted by government and ecclesiastical
    forces from Antioch and later Constantinople. The doctrinal
    heresies by which Alexander would be indicted were irrelevant,
    tacked on later as intellectual justification for the
    condemnation of his behavior.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26]
    Alexander's biographer presents a quite different picture,
    though never denying his hero's rough treatment in the big
    cities. The authorities were genuinely corrupt and insincere,
    so Alexander's challenges were appropriate. The prime concern
    of Alexander was <hi rend="italic">akribeia</hi>, which meant for him truly
    living by the letter of the Scriptures. The biographer
    emphasizes that Alexander is best characterized not by his
    sleepless regimen of prayer, but by his uncompromising standard
    of ascetic poverty.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27]
    Caner inserts observations from the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>, for
    he sees that the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi> "provides the most
    striking parallels for Alexander's way of life." Both expressed
    concern that monks were being held back from Perfection by
    being lured into performing "righteous labor"—work that
    is meant for the Upright ones. The author of the <hi rend="italic">Book of
    Steps</hi> indicates that the Evil One is the source of this
    distraction, attempting to make the Perfect fall from Jesus'
    major commandment, "Do not be anxious even about yourself."</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28]
    There is a difference in manner between Alexander and the
    <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi> in how one publicly addresses people of
    authority. Alexander was full of <hi rend="italic">parrhēsia</hi>, that
    bold self-confidence handy in speaking to social superiors, and
    he used it liberally, if not caustically. The author, however,
    advises his charges to use caution and to assess how they
    should address each person. "If we owe honor [to someone]
    greater than us, let us not give him teaching so he might find
    fault and say, 'Are you teaching me?'"</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29] The
    author did not allow his Perfect to work, but felt that part of
    their duty was to teach other Christians to "see" the afflicted
    and give to those in need. Alexander too was inclined to
    admonish the rich to relieve the poor and gave whatever surplus
    his band received to the destitute poor.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30] The
    author of the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi> is on the same page with
    Alexander in the assumption that the problems of the Perfect
    issued largely from the envy of other clergy. The author
    believes that his wandering Perfect transcend geographical and
    institutional boundaries, and should be able to conduct their
    ministry everywhere with no intention of undermining local
    clergy. Still, many local clergy were challenged and were vocal
    and sometimes violent in their opposition to the Perfect.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31]
    Chapter Five, "Hypocrites and Pseudomonks: Beggars, Bishops,
    and Ascetic Teachers in Cities of the Early Fifth Century,"
    turns about face toward the less attractive aspects of
    wandering, begging monks and the manner in which their behavior
    challenged established ecclesiastical authorities. The focus
    shifts to the dichotomy of begging/labor, more precisely, to
    the means of physical support.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32]
    Again the problem is <hi rend="italic">argia</hi>, but now the microscope is
    aimed as much upon the regular clergy and hierarchy, whether
    the nature of their vocation and sources of their funding were
    legitimate, as on the irregular monks. The opposition of John
    Chrysostom and Nilus of Ancyra to these "ascetic idlers" is
    tempered by their efforts to defend their own spiritual
    labors—particularly teaching and writing—and their
    own support from wealthy aristocrats. John Chrysostom's
    campaign for financial integrity in the churches, clergy, and
    nascent monastic communities of Constantinople stepped on the
    toes of popular holy men, especially a certain Isaac, who
    relied upon alliances with wealthy benefactors for ongoing
    support. John's own support for his spiritual labors was not
    above criticism.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] From
    these ambiguities developed the notion that manual labor
    provided a source of income for monks that encouraged
    self-sufficiency and honesty, a notion that helped distinguish
    Christian monasticism from other ancient philosophies.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34]
    Chapter Six, "Monastic Patronage and the Two Churches of
    Constantinople," examines the conflicted politics of spiritual
    authority in fifth-century Constantinople.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35] The
    fourth canon of the Council of Chalcedon responded to the
    battles between bishop and charismatic monks by not only
    forbidding monks to wander or establish monasteries in cities,
    but by placing their vocations clearly under the authority of
    the bishop. Motivation for this canon had come the hard way:
    the power play exerted by the archimandrite Dalmatius ended in
    the deposition of the bishop Nestorius, similar to the scenario
    thirty years previously with Isaac and John Chrysostom; and not
    quite twenty years later, Dalmatius' successor, Eutyches, was
    accused of heresy and then excommunicated, but was able to
    exert considerable patronal leverage in temporarily reversing
    his condemnation at the infamous Robber Council at Ephesus in
    449. Once again, the current bishop of Constantinople, Flavian,
    was the loser of his see and of his life. With the death of the
    emperor Theodosius, the tide turned against Eutyches who was
    re-condemned at Chalcedon. The Council did not provide a
    conflict-free solution, but the church and the monasteries were
    now united, and never again did an Isaac, Dalmatius, or
    Eutyches arise to wreak havoc.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P36"/>[36]
    Caner concludes with an appropriate "Epilogue," looking at the
    retrospectives of writers in the sixth century and beyond. John
    Climacus does not talk about work very much, but no wandering
    is allowed. The legislation of the council of Persian bishops
    at Seleucia-Ctesiphon took a dim view of pretend-ascetics
    wandering into urban areas, and encouraged them if they were
    authentic to return to properly isolated locations.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P37"/>[37] The
    apostolic impulse, Caner observes, could not be legislated out
    of existence, and later would thrive in orthodox traditions
    with the <hi rend="italic">saloi</hi> or "Fools for Christ." The Syriac
    <hi rend="italic">Legend of the Man of God of Edessa</hi> provides the extreme
    of anonymity to the imitation of Christ among the poor, while
    Theodoret of Cyrrhus' biography of Simeon Stylites points us
    literally skyward to the consummate holy man, perfectly stable,
    yet totally dependent on his admirers below.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P38"/>[38]
    Caner has written in an entertaining and engaging style and
    packed this monograph fully and comprehensively with the
    details and impressions of what was the dilemma of Christian
    asceticism in the third-fifth centuries. Caner takes the reader
    a lot of places, and it is gratifying to see the significant
    role of Syriac-speaking asceticism being given its proper and
    measured place in the history.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P39"/>[39] The
    translation of Alexander the Sleepless flows easily and is well
    annotated. The bibliography and index are more than ample and
    useful. The footnotes throughout the monograph are
    comprehensive. Full Greek and Latin citations are provided. If
    there is a second edition, hopefully full Syriac citations will
    be included!</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>