<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">North American Syriac Symposium IV, 9-13 July 2003</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Eugene</forename>
                  <surname>Aydin</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Princeton Theological Seminary</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/conferenceReport/hv6n2craydin</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Eugene AYDIN</author>
                  <title level="a">North American Syriac Symposium IV, 9-13 July 2003</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol6/HV6N2CRAydin.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    Fourth North American Syriac Symposium on Syriac Studies was
    held at Princeton Theological Seminary, Princeton, New Jersey
    from July 9 through 12, 2003. It was co-sponsored by Princeton
    Theological Seminary, Princeton University, The Institute for
    Advanced Study, and Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Its
    theme was "Syriac Christianity: Culture at the Crossroads". The
    Symposium also included the Fourth International Forum on
    Syriac Computing.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] More
    than hundred scholars, researchers and interested individuals
    attended the Symposium. The participants came from the USA,
    Canada, Europe, Australia and the Middle East, and included
    some of the prominent scholars in the field of Syriac Studies.
    In addition to experienced and distinguished experts in the
    field, there were a number of graduate, postgraduate students
    and researchers, some of whom were making their first public
    presentations of their research.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] A total
    of 46 papers were presented at the Symposium including those of
    the International Forum on Syriac Computing. The topics of
    these papers were diverse. The proceedings will be published
    either in <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> Journal or in a separate volume in book
    form.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    Symposium was opened with a program of sacred music from the
    Christian Middle East and India held at Miller Chapel of the
    Seminary on Wednesday evening and performed by two church
    choirs and individuals from the following Syriac traditions:
    the Syrian Orthodox Church, the Assyrian Church of the East,
    the Orthodox Church in India and Syro-Malabar Church. This was
    a remarkable musical feast which provided the audience with a
    foretaste of both Eastern and Western Syriac musical
    traditions. The music program and a number of the key-note
    lectures were streamed alive on the internet for the public to
    hear and enjoy. These have been recorded and will be archived
    on the <ref target="http://www.bethmardutho.org/">Beth Mardutho</ref>
    website.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] In
    addition to many papers read at the symposium there were four
    remarkable plenary lectures presented by the following scholars
    in their field. The first opening plenary address was given by
    Professor John Healey on the "The Edessan Milieu and the Birth
    of Syriac". The second keynote address was delivered by Dr.
    Robert Hoyland on "Language and Identity: Arabic vs. Syriac".
    The third was presented by Professor Herman Teule on the Syrian
    Renaissance (1026-1318)". The fourth and the concluding one was
    delivered by Professor Amir Harrak on "Commemorating Church
    History during the Ottoman Period: Syriac Monumental
    Inscriptions from the Assyrian Heartland in Mesopotamia".</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    proceedings concluded with a banquet at Prospect House of
    Princeton University which was also attended by friends and
    supporters of Beth Mardutho. At the banquet, Professor Sidney
    Griffith was presented with a <hi rend="italic">Festschrift</hi> in honor of
    his many contributions to Syriac and Christian Arabic studies
    as well as to Muslim-Christian Dialogue. On this occasion, Dr.
    Shawqi Talia delivered a felicitation and recited a poem in
    <hi rend="italic">Suret</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Swadaya</hi>), or the East Syriac vernacular,
    along with an English translation, in honor of Fr. Sidney
    Griffith and his many scholarly achievements. Also, Dr. George
    Kiraz, informed the audience about Beth Mardutho: The Syriac
    Institute, highlighting its work and mission in the field of
    Syriac Studies. He also gave an account of their important
    projects and welcomed the help and support of scholars and
    public alike in accomplishing the important mission undertaken
    by Beth Mardutho for bringing Syriac Studies to the third
    millennium.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Another
    noteworthy feature of the symposium was the excellent
    exhibition of Syriac manuscripts and liturgical furnishings
    displayed at Speer and Luce library of Princeton Seminary. The
    Speer library exhibits included three displays: The first,
    under the title "Scattered Pearls" included Syriac manuscripts
    and liturgical furnishings from the Syrian Orthodox tradition
    on loan from the Syrian Orthodox Archdiocese of the Eastern
    United States, thanks to the generosity of Archbishop Mor Cyril
    Aphrem Karim. The second entitled "From Manuscript to Printed
    Book" covered a number of manuscripts, rare early printed
    books, and printing paraphernalia, on loan from the personal
    collection of Dr. George Kiraz. The third bearing the title
    "Physicians and teachers: American Presbyterian Mission in
    Urmia, Iran" contained a display of books and photographs
    illustrative of the history of the American Protestant Mission
    at Urmia, Persia (Iran). The Luce library exhibit however, with
    its dramatic title: "'Saved from the Pillage and Devastation of
    the War': Manuscripts from the Mission Library in Urmia, Iran"
    had on display a collection of Syriac manuscripts, which
    address Biblical, liturgical, devotional, theological,
    philosophical and scientific subjects. Most of these
    manuscripts that once belonged to the Mission Library of Urmia
    in Iran came to Princeton Seminary via the Board of Missions in
    New York in 1931. The exhibition will remain open until the
    first week of October.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] The
    Fourth North American Syriac Symposium was indeed a success. It
    was both enjoyable and a memorable conference for all, thanks
    to its convener Professor Kathleen McVey and all those who
    contributed to it in different ways. This was the first Syriac
    Symposium to feature live internet streaming of the plenary
    sessions, thanks to the outstanding efforts of the media
    personnel at the Princeton Theological Seminary. The next North
    American Syriac Symposium will be held at the University of
    Toronto in Canada in the year 2007, followed by Duke University
    in North Carolina, USA in 2011.</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>