<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">François Graffin, S.J. (1905-2002)</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Bernard</forename>
                  <surname>Outtier</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Bibliothèque du Caucase</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv6n2outtier</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Bernard OUTTIER</author>
                  <title level="a">François Graffin, S.J. (1905-2002)</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol6/HV6N2Outtier.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Obituary</term>
               <term>Fr. Francois Graffin</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Father
    François Graffin was an outstanding figure in the world
    of French oriental studies and of Syriac studies in particular.
    His gentle energy allowed him to work for many years in order
    to make known the field which had become dear to him: the
    theology of those who wrote in the Syriac language, especially
    of the poets.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Born in
    the West of France, in the <hi rend="italic">Département de la
    Sarthe</hi>, on January 1, 1905, he always remained attached to
    his family and to his native village, to which he used to
    return every year.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] He
    received a solid education in the <hi rend="italic">Collège
    Sainte-Croix</hi> of Le Mans, with the Jesuit Fathers, and
    subsequently he himself joined the Society of Jesus.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] However,
    the fate of Father Graffin was to be determined by the work of
    his uncle, Monseigneur René Graffin (1858-1941), editor
    of the <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Syriaca</hi>, which was soon expanded into
    the <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi>, enabling the inclusion of
    texts in the other languages of Eastern Christianity.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5]
    François Graffin loved to tell the humorous tale of how
    he was appointed his uncle's successor by Pope Pius XI, to whom
    his uncle submitted every year the new installments of the
    <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi>. In 1931, the Pope suggested that
    the work should be entrusted to a religious order, which would
    guarantee its continuity. "I have been educated by the
    Jesuits," was Monseigneur Graffin's reply, "and I have a nephew
    who is a Jesuit." - "Well then, take him!"</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] Ten
    years later, after additional studies in Paris, François
    Graffin succeeded his uncle as editor of the <hi rend="italic">Patrologia
    Orientalis</hi>. He himself became a specialist in the Syriac
    language, which he taught at the <hi rend="italic">Institut catholique</hi> in
    Paris from 1951 to 1975.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] His
    interest remained focused on theology. In 1957, he published
    one of the "bases" of the "Lamp of the Sanctuary" (a major work
    by Gregory Abu 'l-Faraj Barhebraeus), devoted to theology
    (<hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi>, XXVII, fasc. 4).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Father
    Graffin was a faithful man in the fullest sense of the word. He
    took care to complete the work left unfinished by his teachers,
    a heavy task to which he gave priority over his own work. He
    thus brought to completion the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Cathedral
    homilies</hi> of Severus - no less than six fascicules of the
    <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> - and subsequently of the
    <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes decem de Uno e sancta Trinitate incorporato
    et passo</hi> by Philoxenus of Mabbog (four fascicules).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] For
    fourteen years he was deeply involved in bringing these works
    to completion and it was only in 1984 that he published
    anonymous Syriac homilies, based on a sixth-century manuscript,
    and then co-authored the publication of the <hi rend="italic">Letter on the
    Three Degrees of Monastic Life</hi> by Joseph Hazzaya.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] In
    fifty years of intense activity, François Graffin
    supervised the publication of fifty fascicules of the
    <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi>, thirty-two of which deal with
    Syriac texts.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] He
    was also in charge of the publication of the last volume of the
    <hi rend="italic">Revue de l'Orient Chrétien</hi>, and he was
    considering resuming the publication of this journal after the
    death of Monseigneur Khouri-Sarkis (1968) and the termination
    of <hi rend="italic">L'Orient syrien</hi>, the journal to which he had
    contributed regularly, from its third issue onwards, and of
    which he had become vice-director.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    However, a different solution was adopted, which consisted in
    the merger with the journal <hi rend="italic">Melto</hi> and the creation of
    <hi rend="italic">Parole de l'Orient</hi>. François Graffin was
    particularly pleased with this solution, which highlighted the
    special relations which he had developed with his Eastern
    students, in this case those of the Maronite University of
    Kaslik, in Lebanon. He was a member of the editorial committee
    of this recreated journal and published in it several
    articles.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] Of
    course, he was in love with Saint Ephrem, and because he also
    loved the beauty of French, he contributed to two volumes with
    translations of hymns which appeared in the collection
    <hi rend="italic">Sources chrétiennes</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Always speaking with the rigor and the clarity of a teacher, he
    remained humble, amiable in all circumstances, and
    generous.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] The
    impulse that he was able to give to Syriac studies in France
    resonates far beyond, in space as well as in time!</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] A
    printed bibliography of François Graffin, up to 1975,
    can be found in volume 6-7 (1975-1976) of <hi rend="italic">Parole de
    l'Orient</hi>, which was offered to honor him on the occasion of
    his seventieth birthday. On the web, see: <ref target="http://www.jesuites.com/bibliographie/auteurs/graffin.htm">http://www.jesuites.com/bibliographie/auteurs/graffin.htm</ref>.</p>
         <p>[Translated from French by L. Van Rompay]</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>