<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Public Lectures of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname/>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>January 2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/conferenceAnnouncement/hv6n1fccsss</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author/>
                  <title level="a">Public Lectures of the Canadian Society for Syriac Studies</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Conferences</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    Canadian Society for Syriac Studies will be holding the
    following Public Lectures:</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">22 January 2003</hi>. Professor John Corbett, University
    of Toronto. <hi rend="italic">They Do Not Take Wives, or Build, or Work the
    Ground: Ascetic Life in the Early Syriac Christian
    Tradition</hi>. The search for Perfection in the ascetic life is
    central to the Book of Steps. Robert Murray has demonstrated
    that the primary rationale for the ascetic life in the Syriac
    tradition draws on the theme of Holy War in the Hebrew Bible
    and related materials in the Gospel tradition. I will attempt
    to demonstrate that the same theme provides a fundamental
    symbolic structure for the ascetic vocation in the Book of
    Steps.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">12 March 2003</hi>. Professor Kathleen McVey, Princeton
    Theological Seminary. <hi rend="italic">Returning to the Womb and the Breast:
    Images of Joy in Ephrem's Hymns on Paradise</hi>. The paper is
    an exploration of Ephrem's invocation of the bliss of infancy
    to describe life in paradise.  It will begin with a
    presentation of these themes especially as seen in the Paradise
    Hymns 9-11. Next will be a brief effort to contextualize these
    notions in relation to Near East Wisdom literature,
    Jewish-Christianity and Stoic allegory. Finally I will ponder
    the uniqueness of Ephrem's vision and its value for
    contemporary theology.</p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="bold">9 April 2003</hi>. Dr. Jan van Ginkel, Leiden University.
    <hi rend="italic">A Monk, Missionary and Martyr Who Also Wrote History: John
    of Ephesus, a Syrian Orthodox Historian in Sixth Century
    Byzantium</hi>. John of Ephesus was an imperial missionary and a
    "Monophysite" bishop who died as a convicted "heretic". He
    wrote the excellent Lives of Eastern Saints as well as Church
    History both in the Syriac language. Being a member of Syrian
    Orthodox Church, his views differed from the Greek and
    Chalcedonian ones. But John also differed from later Syriac
    authors, in that he wrote contemporary events with no idea of
    how these would unfold, whereas later writers looked at the
    same events as "past" history. We will present the man, career
    and literary activities, and then focus on his perception of
    6th century ecclesiastical and political events and on how this
    perception may influence our own understanding of the same
    events.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] For information,
    contact the Society at csss@chass.utoronto.ca, Tel.
    416/978-3184, Fax. 416/978-3305,
    www.chass.utoronto.ca/~csss.</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
