<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Doctrina Addai as a Paradigm of Christian Thought in Edessa in the Fifth Century</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Sidney H.</forename>
                  <surname>Griffith</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Institute of Christian Oriental Research</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>July 2003</date>
            <idno>Vol. 6, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/ /hv6n2griffith</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Sidney H. GRIFFITH</author>
                  <title level="a">The Doctrina Addai as a Paradigm of Christian Thought in Edessa in the Fifth Century</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date>2003</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="6">6</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Addai</term>
               <term>Edessa</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->     <!--
  <h1>Abstract</h1>
  <p class="Abstract"> </p>
  <br />
-->

         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith2">1. Prolegomena</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Perhaps
    in the waning years of the fourth century, but more probably in
    the first decades of the fifth century, as we will argue below,
    a now anonymous writer working in Edessa, and using the city's
    archives, as he claims, put together a remarkable narrative
    which he called <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai the Apostle</hi>
    (<hi rend="italic">malpānùtâ d'Aday shlî<hi rend="u">h</hi>â</hi>).<ref target="#FN1">1</ref>  At the end of the work the
    author says that he used records written by the scribe
    Labûbna, the son of Senaq, the son of Abshadar, as his
    source, and that <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān, the royal
    archivist, had testified to their accuracy.<ref target="#FN2">2</ref>  In his work
    the author undertook not only to tell the story of the coming
    of Christianity to Edessa, and to demonstrate its apostolic
    origins, but, perhaps even more importantly for his own
    purposes, he provided a profile of the doctrine that he
    represented as the Christian kerygma originally preached in
    Edessa.  One may see in this enterprise an apologetic, and
    perhaps even a polemical agenda, pertinent to the author's own
    time and place.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>, as this work has come to be known among
    modern scholars, has attracted an enormous amount of academic
    attention, from the late nineteenth century when the text was
    first published, until now.  Therefore, to study it, and
    to recall the history of scholarship associated with it, is to
    remind oneself of the historiography not particularly of the
    author's time, but to become aware of the concerns over the
    last century of the most prominent western scholars of
    Syriac.  Because of their work, one is now in a position
    to change the point of view somewhat, and to examine the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> not so much with an interest in its more
    intriguing historical components, but from the perspective of
    the integral narrative, with a view to discerning, if we can,
    the purposes and concerns of its now unknown author.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith3">2. The Literary Profile of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] For most
    commentators the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> is primarily associated
    with the legend of King Abgar V, 'the Black', (4 B.C. - 7 A.D.
    &amp; 13 A.D. - 50 A.D.) of Edessa, who is said to have sent
    envoys to Palestine with a letter for Jesus at the time of his
    passion, asking him to come to Edessa to heal the king of an
    illness.  According to the story, Jesus then responded
    with a message of his own in which he promised to send a
    disciple to Edessa after his ascension into heaven, to heal
    Abgar and to preach the Gospel in his kingdom.<ref target="#FN3">3</ref>  This much
    the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> has in common with a report included
    by Eusebius of Caesarea (260-339) in his Ecclesiastical
    History.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref>  As a result, much of the scholarly
    discussion of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi> has focused on a comparison
    of the two narratives, and speculations about their common
    source in a Syriac document kept in the archives of Edessa,
    from where both Eusebius and the author of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi>
    say their information ultimately comes.<ref target="#FN5">5</ref>  But the fact
    is that the account of the correspondence between Jesus and
    King Abgar is a relatively small part of the actual narrative
    in the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi>.  Nevertheless, scholars have
    persisted in viewing it as the heart of the piece, around which
    later accretions have accumulated.  In part, one suspects
    that the persistence of this view has been the result of a
    scholarly preoccupation, since the days of Walter Bauer, with
    the modern question about the actual origins of Christianity in
    Edessa.<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> Scholars before the time of Bauer, who wrote the
    first edition of his book in 1934, had already set this agenda
    in the late nineteenth century; they were interested
    principally in the account of the Abgar/Jesus correspondence
    and in the story of the image of Christ, which the Syriac text
    says was painted by <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān, the
    archivist who, according to the narrative, accompanied Abgar's
    emissaries to Palestine.<ref target="#FN7">7</ref>  While the author of the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi>, as we have it in its fullest form, was himself
    certainly interested in these issues too, one hopes to be able
    to show that his intention in composing his work was to use
    these traditions, together with several others current in the
    Syriac-speaking milieu of his day, to make an altogether
    different point about Edessan Christianity.  The thesis
    defended here is that the author wanted to put forward a
    paradigm of normative Edessan Christianity, supported by the
    local ecclesiastical and historical lore, which he hoped would
    play an authoritative role in the largely Christological
    controversies of his own day.  On this reading, the most
    important part of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> appears then not to
    be the Abgar legend itself, with its several sub-plots, but the
    textually longer, narratively more central accounts of Addai's
    sermons and speeches, which are presented as accomplishing the
    delivery of the Christian kerygma in Edessa in the first
    instance.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] The
    outline which one finds at the beginning of the work in the St.
    Petersburg manuscript is the best one to follow in constructing
    a table of contents.  It begins abruptly, listing the
    three main moments of the narrative:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>when Abgar, the king, the son of Ma'nû, the king,
      sent the letter to Jerusalem, to our Lord;</item>
            <item>when Addai, the apostle, came to Edessa/Urhāy, and
      what he said in the announcement of his kerygma;</item>
            <item>the instructions he gave when he was leaving this world,
      to those who had received the hand of the priesthood from
      him.<ref target="#FN8">8</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5]
    Following the third moment of the narrative, the account of
    Addai's instructions to his Edessene followers, the author
    provides a brief, concluding recital of developments in the
    church of Edessa after the time of Addai.  Finally, at the
    very end, there is the notice about Labûbna, the king's
    scribe (<hi rend="italic">sāprâ dmalkâ</hi>), "the one writing
    down these things of Addai, the apostle," and <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān, the king's trustworthy archivist
    (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>abûlārâ
    sharîrâ dmalkâ</hi>), who "set down the hand
    of witness."<ref target="#FN9">9</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith4">A. When Abgar sent the letter</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    Syriac narrative explains that in the year 343 of the Greeks,
    or 31-32 A.D., in the reign of Emperor Tiberius (14-37 A.D.),
    King Abgar sent two of his nobles, plus his archivist
    (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">t</hi>abûlārâ</hi> /
    <hi rend="italic">tabularius</hi>), <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān, to the
    Roman governor in Eleutheropolis in Palestine on routine
    business.  On their way back home they had taken the road
    to Jerusalem when they encountered crowds of people going to
    the city to see the Messiah.  They joined them. 
    <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān wrote down everything they
    saw, including the notice that the Jews were plotting what to
    do to him, "seeing that some of the multitude of their people
    were acknowledging him."<ref target="#FN10">10</ref>  When this report was given
    to Abgar, he is the one who makes the first of a number of
    Christological statements that appear in the text.  He
    says, "These powers are not of men but of God.  For there
    is no one who can revivify the dead, except God alone."<ref target="#FN11">11</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Abgar
    decides to send a letter to Jesus by the hand of <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān.  The text explains that the king
    took this action rather than to go to Jerusalem himself, lest
    he precipitate an international incident by trespassing into
    the territory of the Romans.  The letter arrives in
    Jerusalem and is read to Jesus on the 12th of Nisan, in the
    house of Gamaliel.  In the letter Abgar asks Jesus to come
    to Edessa, where the king will give him refuge from the Jews,
    so that he might also cure Abgar of an illness.  Again,
    there is a Christological statement; the king says, "When I
    heard of the great wonders which you do, I decided either that
    you are God, in that you have come down from heaven and have
    done these things, or that you are the Son of God because you
    are doing all these things."<ref target="#FN12">12</ref>  In reply, Jesus sends the
    message that after his ascension he will send one of his
    disciples to heal Abgar, to convert his people, and to bless
    his city.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Finally,
    as the encounter between Abgar's emissaries and Jesus
    concludes, <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān paints a portrait
    of him and brings it back to Abgar, who enshrines it in one of
    his palaces.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith5">B. When Addai Came to Edessa</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9]
    According to the narrative, after Jesus' ascension into heaven,
    Judas Thomas sent Addai, "one of the seventy-two apostles to
    Abgar."<ref target="#FN14">14</ref>  When Addai arrived, "he dwelt in the
    house of Tobia, the son of Tobia the Jew, who was from
    Palestine."<ref target="#FN15">15</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] Once
    Addai was recognized in Edessa, by the miracles he performed,
    as the man whom Jesus promised to send, he was introduced to
    Abgar.  In virtue of the miracles performed, the king
    expressed his own faith.  But first he reiterates to Addai
    his reason for not himself traveling to Palestine to see
    Jesus.  He says, "because that kingdom belongs to the
    Romans I have respect for the covenant of peace which was
    established by me as by my forefathers with our lord Caesar
    Tiberius."<ref target="#FN16">16</ref>  Then, when Addai speaks of Christ's
    economy of salvation, Abgar replies, "Indeed, I believe in him
    and in his Father."<ref target="#FN17">17</ref>  The king then invites Addai to
    teach.  The apostle asks for a general assembly of all the
    people, at which, he says,</p>
         <quote>
      [I will proclaim to you] how and why he diminished himself,
      abased his exalted divinity by the body which he took, was
      crucified, went down to the house of the dead, broke through
      the barrier which had never been broken through before and
      gave life to the dead by being himself killed.  He
      descended alone, but ascended with many to his glorious
      Father, with whom he was from eternity in one exalted
      godhead.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Addai then delivers two addresses, which, for convenience, I
    designate as: the catechizing of Abgar; and the address to the
    people of Edessa.  Because of the easy availability of the
    text, we may here, in outline fashion, simply call attention to
    the highlights of these addresses.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith6">i. The Catechizing of Abgar</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Addai tells the story of Protonike and the discovery of the
    true cross in Jerusalem.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref>  There are several important
    elements to highlight in the narrative, from the perspective of
    the literary outline of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> as a
    whole:</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Addai tells the story as an example of what has been done
      for people "like you", who "believed in the Messiah, that he
      is the Son of the living God."<ref target="#FN20">20</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Protonike is the wife of Claudius; she was converted in
      Rome by Simon, who worked signs and miracles in Jesus'
      name.  She joined "with those who were followers of
      Simon, and held him in great honor."<ref target="#FN21">21</ref>
            </item>
            <item>When Protonike came to Jerusalem, she met Jacob, "who was
      made administrator (<hi rend="italic">mdabbrānâ</hi>) and prefect
      (<hi rend="italic">pāqûdâ</hi>) in the church built for us
      there," and "she received him with great joy, just as she had
      Simon Kepha."<ref target="#FN22">22</ref>
            </item>
            <item>"Show me Golgotha where the Messiah was crucified, the
      wood of his cross on which he was hung by the Jews, and the
      grave where he was laid."<ref target="#FN23">23</ref>  They are under the
      control of the Jews, who will not let the Christians have
      access to them.  "They persecute us that we not preach
      or proclaim in the name of the Messiah.  Often also they
      confine us in prison."<ref target="#FN24">24</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Three crosses produced; death of Protonike's daughter;
      revived when wood of the third cross touches her.  As
      for Protonike, "She glorified the Messiah and believed
      concerning him, that he is the Son of the living
      God."<ref target="#FN25">25</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Protonike gave the cross to Jacob; commanded that "an
      especially great edifice be built over Golgotha where he was
      crucified and over the tomb where he was laid."<ref target="#FN26">26</ref>
            </item>
            <item>The crowd of Jews and Pagans who had been happy and
      cheerful at the beginning of this affair became very sad at
      the end of it.</item>
            <item>Back in Rome, "When Caesar heard of it, he commanded all
      the Jews to leave the country of Italy. ... She also gave a
      recital of this matter before Simon Kepha."<ref target="#FN27">27</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith7">ii. Address to the People of Edessa</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Abgar instructs Addai to address all the people, "that they
    might know that the Son of God is God."<ref target="#FN28">28</ref>  The people
    are summoned, with their leaders, who are named.  There
    are three sections in the address which one may summarize under
    the headings: Christology; personal testimony; and an
    exhortation against paganism.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith8">a. Christology</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Addai begins his address with the affirmation that "I am a
    disciple of Jesus the Messiah ... the son of God."<ref target="#FN29">29</ref> 
    He goes on to speak of how Jesus "abased the greatness of his
    exalted divinity, he who had been with his Father from the
    beginning."<ref target="#FN30">30</ref> A little further on he says of the Messiah
    that "although his appearance was human, his power, intellect,
    and authority were divine as he himself said to us."<ref target="#FN31">31</ref> 
    Addai's Christology then leads to his profession of Trinitarian
    faith:</p>
         <quote>
      We herald and proclaim this Jesus the Messiah, we glorify his
      Father with him, and we extol and worship the Spirit of his
      divinity, because thus we were commanded by him to baptize
      and purge those who believe in the name of the Father and the
      Son and the Holy Spirit.<ref target="#FN32">32</ref>
            <lb/>
         </quote>
         <p>Addai claims that this faith fulfills the Israelite
    prophecies of old, and he claims that "if I speak that which is
    not written in the Prophets, the Jews who are among you and who
    hear me will not receive it."<ref target="#FN33">33</ref>  In a very telling
    phrase, Addai then says that the faith that he preaches is:
    "that God was crucified for all people."<ref target="#FN34">34</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith9">b. Personal Testimony</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    Addai aligns himself with the apostles, who knew only "the
    language of the Hebrews," but who now announce Christ in all
    languages.  And he says, "I am from Paneas, from the place
    where the Jordan river flows forth."<ref target="#FN35">35</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith10">c. Exhortation against Paganism</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Addai's attack against paganism is fairly standard.  God,
    who is Christ, is the "Lord of created things." He "was before
    worlds and creations, whose nature is incomprehensible being
    invisible, who is sanctified with his Father in high places
    above, since he is Lord and God from eternity."<ref target="#FN36">36</ref>  He "is
    the God of the Jews who crucified him."<ref target="#FN37">37</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    Addai recalls the blessing for Edessa that was contained in
    Jesus' message to Abgar: "Because you have thus believed in me,
    may the city in which you dwell be blessed and may the enemy
    never prevail over it."  A little further along he says,
    "You are a blessed land according to the will of the Lord
    Messiah."<ref target="#FN38">38</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] At
    the end of the address, the people and Abgar and his nobles all
    profess their faith.  The king bids Addai to build a
    church.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith11">C. Addai's Instructions for the Church in
    Edessa</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] In
    this final section of the work, the author sets out Addai's
    arrangements for the church in Edessa, and his inauguration of
    a local hierarchy.  He describes Abgar's message to
    Emperor Tiberius, and Addai's arrangements for the
    evangelization of Assyria, as well as how it came about, after
    Addai's death, that the hierarchy of Edessa became suffragan to
    Antioch, and ultimately to be in communion with the see of
    Rome.</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>The consolidation of Christianity involved the conversion
      of the pagans, and "even the Jews who were learned in the Law
      and the Prophets, who traded in silk, submitted and became
      followers and confessed that the Messiah is the Son of the
      living God."<ref target="#FN39">39</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Addai selected Aggai, Palut, Abshelama, and Barsamya as
      his associates in ministry.</item>
            <item>"Every day many people would gather to come for the
      prayer of the liturgy (<hi rend="italic">l<hi rend="u">s</hi>lûtâ dteshmeshtâ</hi>) and for
      the Old Covenant and the New of the Diatessaron."<ref target="#FN40">40</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Orientals in the disguise of merchants came over into the
      territory of the Romans in order to see the signs which Addai
      was doing.  Abgar wrote to Narses, King of the
      Assyrians, about Addai's mission.<ref target="#FN41">41</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Abgar wrote a letter to Tiberius against the Jews for
      their role in the death of Jesus.  Tiberius answers,
      denouncing Pilate, promising punitive action, declaring the
      Jews should have worshipped Jesus, commending Abgar for
      having done well.  Aristides, Tiberius' ambassador in
      Osrohoene reports to the emperor, who orders the execution of
      some Jewish leaders.</item>
            <item>When Addai ages, Aggai is appointed in his place as
      administrator and prefect (<hi rend="italic">mdabbrānâ
      wpāqûdâ</hi>)<ref target="#FN42">42</ref> of the church in Edessa,
      Palut, a deacon, becomes a presbyter, and Abshelama, a
      scribe, becomes deacon.</item>
            <item>Addai's farewell discourse to the hierarchs: "make the
      path and road smooth in a rough place, between the crucifying
      Jews and the erring pagans;" "Beware, therefore, of the
      crucifiers and do not be friends with them, lest you be
      responsible with those whose hands are full of the blood of
      the Messiah."  "Beware of the Pagans."  "Do not be
      investigators into secret things nor inquisitors of hidden
      things."  "Do not be respecters of persons."<ref target="#FN43">43</ref>  About the scriptures:<lb/>
               <quote>
          As for the Law and the Prophets and the Gospel, which you
          read daily before the people, and the Letters of Paul,
          which Simon Peter sent to us from the city of Rome, and
          the Acts of the Twelve Apostles, which John the son of
          Zebedee sent to us from Ephesus, read these books in the
          churches of the Messiah.  Do not again read along
          with these any other since no longer is there any other
          in which the truth you possess is written.<ref target="#FN44">44</ref>
               </quote>
            </item>
            <item>Response of Aggai, Palut, and Abshelama: "We will flee
      from the worship of things made and created which our fathers
      worshiped.  Moreover, we will not take part with the
      crucifying Jews."<ref target="#FN45">45</ref>
            </item>
            <item>Death of Addai.</item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith12">D. Developments after the time of Addai</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20]</p>
         <list type="unordered">
            <item>Burial of Addai "in a great sepulchre of adorned
      sculpture."  Yearly memorial.</item>
            <item>Aggai made priests and leaders in all the district of
      Mesopotamia.</item>
            <item>Rebellious son of Abgar breaks Aggai's legs for refusing
      request.</item>
            <item>"Because he died speedily and rapidly at the breaking of
      his legs he was unable to lay his hand upon Palut. 
      Palut himself went to Antioch and received ordination to the
      priesthood from Serapion, Bishop of Antioch.  Serapion
      himself, Bishop of Antioch, had also received ordination from
      Zephyrinus, Bishop of the city of Rome from the succession of
      ordination to the priesthood of Simon Peter who received it
      from our Lord, and who had been Bishop there in Rome
      twenty-five years in the days of Caesar who reigned there
      thirteen years."<ref target="#FN46">46</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith13">3. The Narrative Themes of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] The
    topical outline of the full text of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina</hi>, as we
    have it in the St. Petersburg manuscript, highlights a number
    of important themes which in the ensemble may be taken to
    compose a historical and creedal view of the faith in early
    Christian Edessa as the author of the work intended to
    represent it, and as he supposed it to have been.  
    Furthermore, taking one's cue from the prominence in the text
    of Addai's speeches, it seems clear that from the author's
    point of view they make up the center-piece of the
    composition.  On this understanding, the Abgar story and
    its several features, while contributing important historical
    details, nevertheless functions primarily as a framework story
    for the main narrative.  It provides a readily
    recognizable, literary and legendary Sitz im Leben for the
    speeches and their themes, and at the same time it makes
    certain claims for historical legitimacy which would have been
    readily recognized by the work's intended audience.<ref target="#FN47">47</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22] The
    major themes in the speeches may the most easily be reviewed
    under the following headings: the Roman connection, the program
    of church order, the adversaries of record, the Christological
    profile, and the moral imperatives that are commended.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith14">A. The Roman Connection</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] The
    'Roman connection' is a theme that will not escape even the
    most casual reader of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>.  It has
    both civil and ecclesiastical dimensions.  From the civil
    perspective, the King Abgar of the narrative is portrayed as
    serving in the capacity of a client king under the rule of the
    Roman emperor Tiberius, and his associate and successor,
    Claudius.  This motif appears both in the frame story, and
    in the Protonike legend, featured as part of Addai's
    catechizing of Abgar.<ref target="#FN48">48</ref>  It also appears in the story of the
    exchange of letters between King Abgar and Emperor Tiberius
    about the punishment of the Jews for Christ's
    crucifixion.<ref target="#FN49">49</ref>  While these narrative components of the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> present a number of chronological and
    historical difficulties for the modern scholar, it nevertheless
    clearly seems to be the original author's intention to point to
    Edessa's continuing political loyalty to the <hi rend="italic">imperium
    romanum</hi> from the earliest times.  In this connection
    one recalls the ever present challenge of the Persian threat in
    the Aramean environs of Edessa. This circumstance is evoked in
    the narrative by the mention of Narses/Narsai, "king of the
    Assyrians," whose subjects are said to have come into the
    territory of the Romans "to see the signs which Addai was
    working;" according to the story, the king asked Abgar for a
    report, and the Edessan king sent him a written account of
    them, at which the 'Assyrian' was amazed.<ref target="#FN50">50</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] On
    the hypothesis that the author's real, political interest here
    is to assert Edessa's historical loyalty to Rome, continuing up
    to his own day, during the reign of the eastern emperor
    Theodosius II (408-450), as will be suggested below, one
    notices a number of anachronistic features in the telling,
    which may point more closely to his own time, when the capital
    of the eastern empire was actually in 'New Rome',
    Constantinople.  One notices, for example, that
    Narses/Narsai, the 'Assyrian' king mentioned in the text,
    actually reigned in the third century and was not a
    contemporary of either Tiberius or Claudius.  
    Furthermore, in connection with what the text says about the
    relationship between Tiberius and Claudius, one notices that
    the author's assumption that a Caesar is subordinate to an
    Augustus reflects the usages of a later time, not those of the
    first century of the empire.  What is even more pertinent
    in connection with the text's mention of Tiberius' allusion to
    "the war with the Spaniards, who have rebelled against
    me,"<ref target="#FN51">51</ref> is that after the Spanish wars under Augustus,
    there was no serious imperial fighting in Spain until the
    Goths, Suevi and Vandals invaded the peninsula in 409. 
    Therefore, one might conclude on these grounds that what the
    text says about Claudius should indicate a date subsequent to
    the future, western emperor Constantius' operations against the
    Visigoths in Spain between 414 and 416, the next campaigns in
    Spain that the ancient historians mention after the time of
    Augustus.<ref target="#FN52">52</ref>  When one puts this observation together
    with the fact that the first mention of Spanish rebels in the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> occurs in the account of the Protonike
    legend, a Syriac calque on the story of the empress Helena's
    finding of the true cross, and it is further taken into account
    that Helena's story first circulated in Greek only in the
    latter years of the fourth century,<ref target="#FN53">53</ref> it suggests that the full
    form of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> could not have been composed
    until well after the beginning of the fifth century.<ref target="#FN54">54</ref> 
    As will appear below, this dating for the text accords well
    with what will be suggested below, on other grounds, as the
    most likely time for the production of the integral work. 
    But the point to be made at this juncture is simply that the
    historically anachronistic features of the narrative can well
    be seen to be in the service of a political ideology, namely
    loyalty to the <hi rend="italic">imperium romanum</hi>, as pertinent a concern
    for an Edessan writer in the first half of the fifth century as
    at any earlier, or later time until the Islamic conquest
    removed both the Persian threat and Byzantine suzerainty from
    Aramean territory in the seventh century.  The details are
    not in themselves what the author intends to claim
    historically, although he was no doubt convinced of their
    veracity.  Rather, one might reasonably conclude that his
    overriding intention was to cite them in support of the main
    historical, political claim of his work, that Edessa had an
    impressive record of loyalty to the <hi rend="italic">imperium romanum</hi>, in
    an area where this loyalty was not without serious political
    and cultural challenge, and that its continuation in his own
    time was to her ultimate benefit.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25]
    Political loyalty to the <hi rend="italic">imperium romanum</hi> had not only a
    civic, but also an ecclesiastical dimension in the author's
    view.  In the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> one notices this
    dimension in several contexts: in the Protonike story, in
    Addai's farewell address to the hierarchs who are chosen for
    ecclesiastical service in Edessa, and in the final section of
    the work, dealing with developments after the time of
    Addai.  In the Protonike story this dimension is to be
    seen in Protonike's relationship with Simon Peter in
    Rome.  In the first place, the text says, "She became a
    believer in, and a worshipper of our Lord the Messiah, giving
    Him glory with those who were followers of Simon, whom she held
    in great honor."<ref target="#FN55">55</ref>  Then, on her return from Jerusalem,
    "She related the things which had happened to Claudius Caesar.
    ... She also told Simon Peter that which had happened."<ref target="#FN56">56</ref> 
    In other words, what one might call the Eusebian relationship
    between bishop and royalty is exemplified in the account of the
    queen's behavior toward the caesar and the apostle in Rome.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26] In
    his exhortation to Aggai, Palut and Abshelama, Addai also
    speaks of Simon Peter in Rome.  He mentions "the Letters
    of Paul, which Simon Peter sent to us from the city of
    Rome."<ref target="#FN57">57</ref>  In context, the author of the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> is only insisting on the apostolic origin
    of the canon of the scriptures as it was promoted in Edessa in
    his own day.  Nevertheless, the Roman connection, so
    prominent in other parts of the text, is also in evidence
    here.  At another place in the same address, Addai
    likewise gives advice about the appropriate behavior of the
    hierarchs toward the civil authorities.  He says:</p>
         <quote>
      As to rulers and judges who have attained to this faith, love
      them, though you should be no respecter of persons in
      anything.  But if they go astray, rebuke them justly
      that you might demonstrate the boldness of your integrity and
      that they might amend their ways so as not again to be
      directed by their own will.<ref target="#FN58">58</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27]
    Again, one notices in the text the assumption of a relationship
    between civil and ecclesiastical officials of a character that
    the wistful ecclesiology of Eusebius of Caesarea in Palestine
    (c. 260 - c. 340) would commend.<ref target="#FN59">59</ref>  The same model is
    behind the often quoted passage from the last section of the
    work, devoted to the account of developments after the time of
    Addai.  When one of Abgar's rebellious sons is said to
    have killed Aggai, the text goes on to say:</p>
         <quote>
      Because he died speedily and rapidly at the breaking of his
      legs he was unable to lay his hand upon Palut. Palut himself
      went to Antioch and received ordination to the priesthood
      from Serapion, Bishop of Antioch. Serapion himself, Bishop of
      Antioch, had also received ordination from Zephyrinus, Bishop
      of the city of Rome from the succession of ordination to the
      priest-hood of Simon Peter who received it from our Lord, and
      who had been Bishop there in Rome twenty-five years in the
      days of Caesar who reigned there thirteen years.<ref target="#FN60">60</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28] In
    addition to the clear appeal to the fourth-century
    ecclesiological idea of the unbroken episcopal succession from
    the time of the apostles, of which more will be said below,
    this passage also presumes the early Byzantine, and the
    Ephraemian, view of the dual royal and episcopal governance of
    a city, in terms of its civic and spiritual interests, complete
    with a case of royal coveting of episcopal wealth.  What
    is more, the particulars of the chain of ordinations, as Walter
    Bauer showed so long ago, anachronistically presume the usages
    of the author's day, rather than any earlier practice.<ref target="#FN61">61</ref> 
    Once again, the reader's perception is that the historical
    details in the narrative are subservient to the author's larger
    purpose, to commend the ideal of a harmonious relationship
    between Edessa's hierarchy, duly claimed to be apostolic in
    origin, and the civil authority, appropriately aligned under
    the Roman emperor.  It reflects nothing so much as an
    anachronistic retrojection into the early Christian period of
    Edessa's history, of the political and ecclesiological ideas of
    the kind articulated in Syriac by Ephraem the Syrian in the
    second half of the fourth century, complete with the
    paradigmatic role of Peter.<ref target="#FN62">62</ref>  It is hard to avoid the
    conclusion that the author of the full form of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi> composed a work, into which he incorporated earlier
    legendary traditions, for the purpose of making a historical
    and doctrinal claim in his own day.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29] The
    earlier legendary traditions, like the story of the Abgar/Jesus
    correspondence, the account of how Edessa acquired a famous
    image of Christ, the veneration of which was becoming
    increasingly popular in the fifth century, and the claim of
    apostolic succession for her hierarchy, all went together to
    supply the credentials for the authenticity of Edessa's
    historical epithet, "the Blessed City (<hi rend="italic">mdintâ
    mbarrabtâ</hi>)," a title which the author of the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> suggests was due to Christ's own prayer
    for the city, included in his letter to King Abgar, "As for
    your city, may it be blessed and may no enemy ever again rule
    over it."<ref target="#FN63">63</ref>  In his work, for reasons pertinent to
    the conditions of his own time, and by means of the themes that
    he highlights, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> proposes
    a paradigm of Christian thought which he anachronistically
    represents as corresponding to the city's ancient faith, in
    reward for which she first received the promise of the Lord's
    blessing.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith15">B. Church Order</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30] The
    elements of church order highlighted in the narrative, which
    seem to have been included to testify to Edessa's
    ecclesiastical legitimacy in the church of the Roman empire,
    are the aforementioned participation in the apostolic
    succession, signified by the tradition of the laying-on of
    hands reaching back to Simon Peter, the espousal of Nicene
    faith by a constant affirmation in the narrative of the
    divinity of Jesus Christ as the Son of God the Father,
    warranted by miracles, and the firm affirmation of the full
    canon of the Old and the New Testaments.<ref target="#FN64">64</ref>  The profile
    of 'orthodoxy' which these standards demarcate is entirely
    conformable with that one espoused by Ephraem the Syrian in
    Nisibis and Edessa in the second half of the fourth
    century.<ref target="#FN65">65</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31] In
    connection with the author's concern for the text of the
    scriptures being read at the liturgy in Edessa, one notices
    especially the following report about the services in the
    church Addai is said to have built at the bidding of King
    Abgar.  The text says, "Every day many people used to
    assemble to come to the prayer of the liturgy and to the Old
    Testament and the New [Testament] of the Diatessaron."<ref target="#FN66">66</ref> 
    It is the mention of the Diatessaron that catches one's
    attention in the present context.  In the first half of
    the fifth century, particularly during the reign of Bishop
    Rabbula of Edessa (411/2-435), a campaign was waged in the city
    to ban the reading of the Diatessaron and to replace it with
    the Peshitta version of the Gospels.<ref target="#FN67">67</ref>  The author
    of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> anachronistically represents the
    reading of the Diatessaron in the liturgy as dating from the
    time of Addai and the establishment of Christianity in
    Edessa.  Therefore, it is hard to avoid the conclusion
    that in this connection he is taking a position in the
    controversy about the Diatessaron, alleging its historical
    authority, at the very time of his writing.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith16">C. The Adversaries of Record</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32] Even
    the hurried review of the contents of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    that we have been able to include in the present article makes
    it clear that in the narrative as a whole, but particularly in
    the sermons and speeches of Addai, the Jews and Pagans are
    major adversaries.  These were the perennial, literary
    adversaries of the Christian preachers in Late Antiquity, never
    more so than in the fourth and fifth centuries.  They were
    also the common adversaries of writers in all the language
    communities of the Christians at the time, and, as such, the
    stereotypical charges lodged against them often lacked more
    specific definition.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] Nebo
    and Bel are the pagan gods most frequently mentioned in the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>, and they were indeed "the main gods of
    Edessa,"<ref target="#FN68">68</ref> against whose cult the Christian writers of
    the fourth and fifth centuries inveighed the most
    insistently.  The text also mentions other deities
    worshipped in Edessa and in neighboring, Syriac-speaking
    locales.  In his general instruction to the people of the
    city, Addai said:</p>
         <quote>
      I see that this city is filled with paganism which is<lb/>
      contrary to God.  Who is this [man-] made idol<lb/>
      Nebo which you worship, and Bel which you honor?<lb/>
      Behold there are those among you who worship Bath<lb/>
      Nical, like the inhabitants of Haran your neighbors,<lb/>
      and Taratha, like the inhabitants of Mabug, and the<lb/>
      Eagle, like the Arabs, and the sun and the moon, like<lb/>
      the rest of the inhabitants of Haran who are like
      you.<ref target="#FN69">69</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34] What
    is striking in this portrait of pagan religion at Edessa is its
    local accuracy; it also calls attention to the continuing
    appeal of what one might call the 'Persian tilt' in Edessan
    politics, in that the indigenous cults may be thought to have
    favored the Persian suzerainty under which they had flourished
    before the establishment of Christianity in the city under
    Roman auspices, as the author of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    wanted to claim.<ref target="#FN70">70</ref> In the fourth and early fifth centuries
    these cults were still exercising both their religious and
    their political influence.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35] From
    a local perspective, the group of non-Christian, or
    semi-Christian adversaries over whose claims the author seems
    most interested to prevail were the Manichaeans. 
    Professor Han J.W. Drijvers has already amply shown this
    dimension of the work.<ref target="#FN71">71</ref>  It remains only to say that
    the concern to refute the claims of the Manichaeans in Edessa
    and its environs fits well with the polemical agenda of Ephraem
    in the late fourth century and with the continuing efforts to
    institutionalize his ecclesiastical program in the first half
    of the fifth century.<ref target="#FN72">72</ref>  Nevertheless, it is important also
    to take notice of the fact that the author of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi>, consistent with his purpose to present his own
    position as that of the first preachers of Christianity in
    Edessa, does not actually name the adversaries of record
    against whom the upholders of imperial orthodoxy in the
    Syriac-speaking milieu in his own day argued strenuously,
    namely, Marcion, Bar Day<hi rend="u">s</hi>ān, and
    Mani.  This is the case in spite of the clearly
    anachronistic, anti-Manichaean character of the legendary
    claims made in the narrative about the origins of Christianity
    in Edessa and about the relationship between Addai and Abgar,
    so reminiscent, according to Prof. Drijvers, of the
    relationship between Mani and the Persian king, Shapùr I
    (241-272).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P36"/>[36] The
    one group against whom the author vigorously polemicizes by
    name throughout the work are the Jews.  On the one hand he
    seems anxious to acknowledge a Jewish connection for the
    earliest Christianity in Edessa; Addai first dwelt in Edessa
    with Tobia, "the son of Tobia the Jew, who was from
    Palestine,"<ref target="#FN73">73</ref> and as a result of Addai's ministry, the text
    says, "Even the Jews who were learned in the Law and the
    Prophets, who traded in silk, submitted and became followers
    and confessed that the Messiah is the Son of the living
    God."<ref target="#FN74">74</ref>  On the other hand, throughout the
    narrative the Jews are called 'Crucifiers'
    (<hi rend="italic">zaqôpê</hi>), and the reader is reminded that
    Christ "is the God of the Jews who crucified him."<ref target="#FN75">75</ref> 
    In his farewell address to the hierarchs who would succeed him
    Addai says, "Beware, therefore, of the crucifiers and do not be
    friends with them, lest you be responsible with those whose
    hands are full of the blood of the Messiah."<ref target="#FN76">76</ref>  Notice is
    taken of the action of the Roman emperor against the Jews,
    credited to the intervention of King Abgar with Emperor
    Tiberius by letter, "since he could not pass over into a
    country of the Romans to enter Palestine and kill the Jews,
    because they crucified the Messiah."<ref target="#FN77">77</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P37"/>[37]
    There is an anachronistic quality to this pronounced
    anti-Jewishness and concern about the involvement of Christians
    with Jews; it's terms are reminiscent of the <hi rend="italic">Adversus
    Judaeos</hi> dimension of the works of many writers of the
    fourth and fifth centuries, such as Cyril of Alexandria (c. 375
    - 444), John Chrysostom (c. 347-407) in Antioch, or Ephraem the
    Syrian (306-373) in Nisibis and in Edessa.<ref target="#FN78">78</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P38"/>[38] The
    text of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> does not anachronistically
    name any particular Christian adversaries or well known
    heresiarchs from a later time.  Nevertheless, the
    doctrinal positions adopted throughout the work, as will be
    mentioned below, make it abundantly clear that the author
    intends to claim that Edessa's historical faith should
    logically exclude the Christological doctrines of those who
    would in any way discount the full divinity of Christ.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith17">D. The Christological Profile</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P39"/>[39]
    Throughout the outline of the contents of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi> given above, care has been taken to quote the
    sentences and phrases in which the author set down the terms of
    the confession of faith in Christ that he represents as
    characterizing the historical faith of the kingdom of
    Edessa.  Perhaps the single most important place in the
    narrative to study the Christological profile of the whole
    document is in the section dealing with Addai's address to the
    people of Edessa.  Here the Nicene character of the faith
    is evident in such phrases as the one which expresses King
    Abgar's wish that many of his own people will come to know
    that, "the son of God is God."<ref target="#FN79">79</ref>  But in this
    connection the most striking sentence of all is surely the one
    Addai utters in his address to characterize "the faith which we
    preach, that God was crucified for all people."<ref target="#FN80">80</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P40"/>[40] It
    would be difficult not to recognize in the phrase, "God was
    crucified for all people," a representation of the Christology
    of those whom their adversaries, after the time of the council
    of Chalcedon (451), would polemically label
    'Monophysites'.  To put it forward as the historical faith
    of Edessa suggests that the author of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    was interested in propounding the Christological view
    associated with the teaching of Cyril of Alexandria (d. 444) in
    the context of the controversies of his own day.  In
    Edessan history, the period when the city's ecclesiastical
    establishment notably wavered between the Christologies of
    Antioch and Alexandria, but prior to when the Roman imperial
    authority proposed a definitive solution to the controversy,
    was the time of the reign of Bishop Rabbula (d. 436).<ref target="#FN81">81</ref> 
    Once again, what must seem an anachronism in the text suggests
    the era to which it is plausible to date the composition of the
    full form of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith18">E. The Moral Imperatives</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P41"/>[41] A
    noticeable theme in the narrative of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    is a pronounced concern for the proper use of wealth, or
    rather, the renunciation of it by Addai and his
    disciples.  This concern surfaces at the very beginning of
    Addai's relationship with Abgar, when the king gave orders for
    silver and gold to be given to the apostle.  Addai says,
    "how can we receive anything which is not ours?  Now
    behold we have left that which is ours as we were commanded by
    our Lord that we should be without purses and without
    wallets."<ref target="#FN82">82</ref>  Nevertheless, the text is careful to
    point out that Abgar made large monetary gifts to support the
    building of the church in Edessa and the ministries of Addai
    and his disciples.<ref target="#FN83">83</ref>  In his address to his disciples,
    Addai reminded them that they should have no other occupation
    than the service of the Lord, and that they should not "love
    the profits of this world."<ref target="#FN84">84</ref>  But the narrative reports
    that in their ministries, in addition to their faithfulness to
    their ecclesiastical duties, the disciples "made visitations of
    alms to the sick and to the well according to Addai's teaching
    to them."<ref target="#FN85">85</ref>  At the end of Addai's life, the king
    sent him rich garments for his burial clothes, but Addai sent
    back the message: "During my life I took nothing from you; I
    will not deny in myself the word of the Messiah who said to me,
    'Take nothing from any man, and acquire nothing in this
    world.'"<ref target="#FN86">86</ref>  Finally, the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    leaves the following portrait of Addai and his followers:</p>
         <quote>
      He did not take silver or gold from any man.  The<lb/>
      gifts of princes came no where near him.  For in<lb/>
      place of gold and silver, he enriched Christ's church<lb/>
      with the souls of the believers.  The whole status
      of<lb/>
      the men and women was: they were splendidly chaste,<lb/>
      they were pure and holy, they were living singly and<lb/>
      chastely, without defilement, splendidly [engaged] in<lb/>
      the watchfulness of the liturgy, in taking on the
      burden<lb/>
      of the poor, in visiting the sick.<ref target="#FN87">87</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P42"/>[42] This
    passage reflects the ideal view of church life as it was
    normally put forward in the fourth and fifth centuries in the
    Syriac-speaking milieux.  In particular, it echoes the
    ascetical language so prominent in the works of the classical
    writers, such as Aphrahat and Ephraem,<ref target="#FN88">88</ref> as well as the
    emphasis on the care of the poor and the sick, evident in
    certain hagiographical texts of the fifth century.<ref target="#FN89">89</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P43"/>[43] In
    addition to the maintenance of the poor and the sick, the one
    expenditure of wealth of which the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    clearly approves is the building of churches.  In the
    account of the Protonike legend a favorable mention is made of
    the "especially great edifice" that the queen gave orders to be
    built over Golgotha and Christ's tomb in Jerusalem.<ref target="#FN90">90</ref> 
    And in Edessa, there is the church which Addai built with
    Abgar's support.  In this connection, the text suggests
    that this accomplishment was only the beginning of a church
    building campaign that reached well beyond the confines of the
    city.  It says:</p>
         <quote>
      Some years after the Apostle Addai had built the<lb/>
      church in Edessa, had provided it with everything<lb/>
      suitable for it, and had made many disciples from<lb/>
      the city's populace, he built churches in other<lb/>
      districts as well, both far and near.  He adorned<lb/>
      and embellished them, set up deacons and presbyters<lb/>
      in them taught those who were to read the scriptures<lb/>
      in them, and taught the orders of the ministry<lb/>
      within and without.<ref target="#FN91">91</ref>
         </quote>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith19">History and Historiography in Late Antique
    Edessa</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P44"/>[44] As
    is abundantly clear from the bibliographical references
    included in the footnotes to the present study, from the late
    nineteenth century and throughout the twentieth century,
    virtually every historian of note who has had the occasion to
    be concerned with Syrian Christianity has also tried his hand
    with one or another of the problems associated with the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>.  But few have considered the
    integral work in its fullest form.  It has been the
    purpose of the present essay to review the composition it its
    literary integrity.  In the light of the review, a number
    of conclusions suggest themselves.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P45"/>[45] It
    seems clear that Addai's addresses and instructions are at the
    heart of the narrative.  Although Addai himself, along
    with a number of the other <hi rend="italic">dramatis personae</hi> are put
    forward as historical characters, it appears that the author
    expected his intended audience to recognize their names and to
    know their stories from the general fund of local, Edessan,
    historical lore.  The historical claims he puts forward in
    particular, therefore, are not immediately the historical
    details of the narrative, which he takes for granted, but the
    larger theological and political themes one finds developed
    throughout the work.  They are the themes discussed above:
    the Roman and Jerusalem connections; the apostolic tradition;
    the adversaries of record; the Christological profile; the
    moral imperative, especially the concern for evangelical
    poverty.  As we have seen, these themes are clearly put
    forward anachronistically from the perspective of what could
    have been the case at the time of the evangelization of
    Edessa.  The period that in the ensemble they most
    immediately suggest is the first third of the fifth century,
    and perhaps, more specifically, the time of Bishop Rabbula (d.
    436).  For many of the same reasons alleged here, in a
    recent study, Prof. Han J.W. Drijvers concludes that the bishop
    himself was responsible for the work.  He declares
    straightforwardly, "The final version of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi> probably is due to bishop Rabbula."<ref target="#FN92">92</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P46"/>[46] The
    major conclusion to which the present writer comes is that the
    <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> in its fullest form is an integral work,
    with a definite set of ideas to commend, in the service of a
    line of thinking that is at once political and religious, civil
    and ecclesiastical.  The author puts it forward, not
    without apologetical and polemical intent, as a paradigm of
    right thinking for the Edessan milieu; he rightly calls it
    'teaching' or 'doctrine' (<hi rend="italic">malpānûtâ</hi>),
    and not 'history' (<hi rend="italic">tash'îtâ</hi>).  He
    represents the several themes of the work as the component
    parts of an Edessan profile of the Christian faith that in his
    opinion goes back to the origins of Christianity in that
    city.  For this purpose he utilizes pre-existing material,
    including the locally well known stories of Abgar and
    Protonike, finally alleging that the whole work, including
    Addai's sermons and instructions, have all along been preserved
    in Edessa's royal archive, in a copy written by the legendary
    scribe, Labûbna, and vouched for by the legendary
    archivist, <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān.<ref target="#FN93">93</ref>  A modern
    reader may think of it as an historical novel composed to
    promote Bishop Rabbula's agenda for the 'Church of the Empire'
    in Edessa, maybe even supposing that it is an instance of
    "fiction as history", to borrow Prof. Glen Bowersock's
    felicitous phrase, from the title of his own study of some
    earlier, not entirely dissimilar material from other, late
    antique language communities.<ref target="#FN94">94</ref>  But the conviction
    remains that the author himself of the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>
    intended to write the Gospel truth.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV6N2Griffith20">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> The text was first published and translated into
    English by George Phillips, <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Addai, the
    Apostle, Now First Edited in a Complete Form in the Original
    Syriac</hi> (London: Trübner &amp; Co., 1876).  It is
    now also available, in Phillips’ edition, but with a new
    English version , in George Howard (trans.), <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of
    Addai</hi> (SBL Texts and Translations, 16, Early Christian
    Literature Series, 4; Chico, CA: Scholars Press, 1981). 
    For further information about the text and its manuscript
    witnesses, see A. Desreumaux, “La Doctrine
    d’Addaï; essai de classement des témoins
    syriaques et grecs,”  <hi rend="italic">Augustinianum</hi> 23
    (1983), pp. 181-186.  See also Alain Desreumaux,
    <hi rend="italic">Histoire du roi Abgar et de Jésus</hi> (Paris:
    Brepols, 1993).<ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    lii-liii; 105-107.  In this and all succeeding citations
    of the text, the first set of numerals (Roman) indicates the
    pages of Phillips’ edition of the Syriac text, numbered
    by Syriac characters, as reprinted by Howard; the second set of
    numerals (Arabic) indicates the differently numbered pages of
    Howard’s translation. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> For an overview of the scholarly <hi rend="italic">status
    quaestionis</hi> see H.J.W. Drijvers, “The Abgar
    Legend,” in Wilhelm Schneemelcher (ed.), <hi rend="italic">New Testament
    Apocrypha</hi> (rev. ed.; R. McL. Wilson (trans.); Louisville:
    Westminster / John Knox Press, 1991), pp. 492-499. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">The Ecclesiastical History</hi>, I, 13.
    <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> For a discussion of this issue, and a review of the
    pertinent scholarship, see Sebastian Brock, “Eusebius and
    Syriac Christianity,” in Harold W. Attridge &amp; Gohei
    Hata (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Eusebius, Christianity, and Judaism</hi>
    (Detroit: Wayne State University Press, 1992), pp. 212-234.
    <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> See Walter Bauer, <hi rend="italic">Orthodoxy and Heresy in
    Earliest Christianity</hi> (2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> ed., R.A. Kraft &amp;
    G. Kroedel (trans.); Philadelphia: Fortress Press, 1971), pp.
    1-43. <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> See, e.g., L.-J. Tixeront, <hi rend="italic">Les origins de
    l’église d’Édesse et la
    légende d’Abgar; étude critique suivie de
    deux textes orientaux inédits</hi> (Paris: Maisonneuve,
    1888); Ernst von Dobschütz, <hi rend="italic">Christusbilder;
    Untersuchungen zur christlichen Legende</hi> (Leipzig: Hinrichs,
    1899); <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, “Der Briefwechsel zwischen Abgar und
    Jesus,” <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche
    Theologie</hi> 43 (1900), pp. 422-486. <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. i &amp;
    3. <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. liii
    &amp; 107.  Labûbna was mentioned earlier in the
    narrative, among the nobles of the city, on pp. xviii &amp;
    37.  <hi rend="u">H</hi>annān, the archivist,
    has a prominent part in the legend of King Abgar’s
    embassy to Jesus. <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. ii
    &amp; 5. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    iii &amp; 7. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    iii-iv; 7-9. <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> While this report has been the subject of
    much scholarly discussion, to pursue it here would be beside
    the point.  See now Han J.W. Drijvers, “The Image of
    Edessa in the Syriac Tradition,” in H.L. Kessler &amp; G.
    Wolf (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Holy Face and the Paradox of
    Representation</hi> (Villa Spelman Colloquia, Florence, 1996,
    vol. 6; Bologna: Nuova Alfa, 1998), pp. 13-31. <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. v
    &amp; 11.  See Luke 10:1, where, in many ancient MSS the
    number 72 appears, while modern Bibles often mention only 70,
    following other MSS.  Throughout the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina
    Addai</hi>, Addai is called <hi rend="italic">shlî<hi rend="u">h</hi>â</hi>, ‘the apostle’.  The
    term is not used in its technical sense, refering to the twelve
    apostles, and Paul, but in the etymological use of 'envoy' or
    'messenger.' <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. v
    &amp; 11. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. vi
    &amp; 13.  Presumably the arrangement which allowed Edessa
    to live under Roman hegemony between the years 212/213 and
    242/243 is here being projected back to the time of King Abgar
    V.  See Millar, <hi rend="italic">Roman Near East</hi>, pp. 472-481.
    <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    vii &amp; 15. <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    viii &amp; 17. <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> See S. Heid, "Zur frühen Protonike- und
    Kyriakoslegendt," <hi rend="italic">Analecta Bollandiana</hi> 109 (1991), pp.
    73-108; Jan Willem Drijvers, <hi rend="italic">Helena Augusta: The Mother of
    Constantine the Great and her Finding of the True Cross</hi>
    (Leiden: Brill, 1992); <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, “ The Protonike
    Legend and the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi>,” <hi rend="italic">Studia
    Patristica</hi> 33 (1996), pp. 517-523; <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, “The
    Protonike Legend, the <hi rend="italic">Doctrina Addai</hi> and Bishop Rabbula
    of Edessa,”  <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 51 (1997),
    pp. 288-315; <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, “Promoting Jerusalem: Cyril and
    the True Cross,” in Jan Willem Drijvers &amp; John W.
    Watt, (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Portraits of Spiritual Authority: Religious
    Power in Early Christianity, Byzantium and the Christian
    Orient</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1999), pp. 79-95.  See also Han
    J.W. Drijvers &amp; Jan Willem Drijvers, <hi rend="italic">The Finding of the
    True Cross; the Judas Kyriakos Legend in Syriac</hi> (CSCO, vol.
    565, Subs. 93; Louvain: Peeters, 1997). <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. x
    &amp; 21. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef21">21</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. x
    &amp; 21. <ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef22">22</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xi
    &amp; 23. <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef23">23</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xi
    &amp; 23. <ref target="#FNRef23">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef24">24</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xi
    &amp; 23. <ref target="#FNRef24">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef25">25</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xv
    &amp; 31. <ref target="#FNRef25">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef26">26</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xv
    &amp; 31. <ref target="#FNRef26">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef27">27</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvi &amp; 33. <ref target="#FNRef27">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef28">28</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvii &amp; 35. <ref target="#FNRef28">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef29">29</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvix &amp; 39. <ref target="#FNRef29">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef30">30</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvix &amp; 39. <ref target="#FNRef30">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef31">31</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xx
    &amp; 41. <ref target="#FNRef31">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef32">32</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xx
    &amp; 41. <ref target="#FNRef32">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef33">33</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xx
    &amp; 41. <ref target="#FNRef33">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef34">34</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxi &amp; 43. <ref target="#FNRef34">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef35">35</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxi &amp; 43. <ref target="#FNRef35">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef36">36</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxv &amp; 51. <ref target="#FNRef36">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef37">37</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxix &amp; 59. <ref target="#FNRef37">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef38">38</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxx &amp; 61.  See also <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>, pp. iv &amp; 9.
    <ref target="#FNRef38">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef39">39</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxiv &amp; 69. <ref target="#FNRef39">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef40">40</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxvi &amp; 73. <ref target="#FNRef40">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef41">41</ref> The text makes it clear that this Assyria is
    outside of the territory of the Romans (<hi rend="italic">bêt
    rhômāyyê</hi>), while the author calls its
    inhabitants ‘orientals’ (<hi rend="italic">madn.<hi rend="u">h</hi>āyyê</hi>).  See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The
    Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. 74 &amp; 75.  It seems probable
    therefore that the Assyria of which he speaks is in the
    territory under Persian hegemony, which may or may not be the
    province of Adiabene.  See Millar, <hi rend="italic">The Roman Near
    East</hi>, pp. 100-101.  In any event, the Narses/Narsai
    named here is most likely to be the Persian king who in the
    year 294 succeeded to the throne of Bahrâm III.  See
    Desreumaux, <hi rend="italic">Histoire du roi Abgar</hi>, p. 98, n. 155 &amp;
    p. 126. <ref target="#FNRef41">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef42">42</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xl
    &amp; 81. <ref target="#FNRef42">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef43">43</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xli &amp; 83 – xlv &amp; 91. <ref target="#FNRef43">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef44">44</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xlvi &amp; 93. <ref target="#FNRef44">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef45">45</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xlvii &amp; 95 – xlviii &amp; 97. <ref target="#FNRef45">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef46">46</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    lii &amp; 105.  Howard notes that contrary to
    Cureton’s text, Phillips’ text speaks of Zephyrinus
    as Bishop of the City of Antioch.  See <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
    110, n. 42. <ref target="#FNRef46">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef47">47</ref> On the varying uses of the Abgar story in
    Syriac historiography see L. van Rompay, “Jacob of Edessa
    and the Early History of Edessa,” in G.J. Reinink &amp;
    A.C. Klugkist (eds.), <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan: Studies on Continuity
    and Change in Syriac Christianity in Honour of Professor Han
    J.W. Drijvers</hi> (Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta, 89; Leuven:
    Uitgeverij Peeters en Departement Oosterse Studies, 1999), esp.
    pp. 279-281. <ref target="#FNRef47">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef48">48</ref> See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>,
    pp. i &amp; 3, vi &amp; 13, x &amp; 21, xvi &amp; 33, xxxviii
    – xxxix &amp; 77-79. <ref target="#FNRef48">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef49">49</ref> See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>,
    pp. xxxvii &amp; 75 – xl &amp; 81. <ref target="#FNRef49">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef50">50</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxvii &amp; 75.  See n. 56 above. <ref target="#FNRef50">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef51">51</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. x
    &amp; 21, xxxviii &amp; 77. <ref target="#FNRef51">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef52">52</ref> See the Spanish campaign in the fifth
    century mentioned in Paulus Orosius, <hi rend="italic">Orose, Histoires
    (Contre les Païens)</hi> (Marie-Pierre Arnaud-Lindet, ed.
    &amp; trans.; Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 1991), vol. III, pp.
    123-127; Hydatius, The Chronicle of Hydatius <hi rend="italic">and the</hi>
    Consularia Constantinopolitana: <hi rend="italic">Two Contemporary Accounts of
    the Final Years of the Roman Empire</hi> (R.W. Burgess, ed.
    &amp; trans.; Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1993), pp. 79-91.
    <ref target="#FNRef52">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef53">53</ref> See the studies cited in n. 34 above.
    <ref target="#FNRef53">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef54">54</ref> The author wishes to thank Prof. Timothy D.
    Barnes for calling these historical observations to his
    attention. <ref target="#FNRef54">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef55">55</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. x
    &amp; 21.  My own translation of this passage accepts the
    textual correction suggested in Howard, p. 117, i.e.,
    <hi rend="italic">mshabb<hi rend="u">h</hi>â</hi> for
    <hi rend="italic">mshî<hi rend="u">h</hi>â.</hi>
            <ref target="#FNRef55">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef56">56</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvi &amp; 33. <ref target="#FNRef56">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef57">57</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xlvi &amp; 93.  In the same passage he also speaks of
    “the Acts of the Twelve Apostles, which John the son of
    Zebedee sent to us from Ephesus.” <ref target="#FNRef57">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef58">58</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xlv – xlvi &amp; 91 – 93. <ref target="#FNRef58">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef59">59</ref> See T.D. Barnes, <hi rend="italic">Constantine and
    Eusebius</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press,
    1981). <ref target="#FNRef59">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef60">60</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    lii &amp; 105.  See also n. 61 above. <ref target="#FNRef60">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef61">61</ref> See Bauer, <hi rend="italic">Orthodoxy and Heresy</hi>, pp.
    17-20. <ref target="#FNRef61">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef62">62</ref> In this connection see the following studies
    by Sidney H. Griffith, “Ephraem, the Deacon of Edessa,
    and the Church of the Empire,” in T. Halton &amp; J.
    Williman, (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Diakonia: Essays in Honor of Robert T.
    Meyer</hi>(Washington, D.C.: CUA Press, 1986), pp. 22-52;
    “Ephraem the Syrian’s Hymns ‘Against
    Julian’: Meditations on History and Imperial
    Power,” <hi rend="italic">Vigiliae Christianae</hi> 41 (1987), p.
    238-266; “Setting Right the Church of Syria: Saint
    Ephraem’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns against Heresies</hi>,” in Wm.E.
    Klingshirn &amp; Mark Vessey (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Limits of Ancient
    Christianity: Essays on Late Antique Thought and Culture in
    Honor of R.A. Markus</hi> (Ann Arbor: The University of Michigan
    Press, 1999), pp. 97-114. <ref target="#FNRef62">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef63">63</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. iv
    &amp; 9. <ref target="#FNRef63">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef64">64</ref> See the passage quoted above at n. 59.
    <ref target="#FNRef64">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef65">65</ref> See Sidney H. Griffith, “The Marks of
    the ‘True Church’ according to Ephraem’s
    <hi rend="italic">Hymns Against Heresies</hi>,” in Reinink &amp;
    Klugkist, <hi rend="italic">After Bardaisan</hi>, pp. 125-140. <ref target="#FNRef65">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef66">66</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. 72
    &amp; 73. <ref target="#FNRef66">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef67">67</ref> See M. Black, “Rabbula of Edessa and
    the Peshitta,” <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the John Rylands
    Library</hi> 33 (1951), pp. 203-210. <ref target="#FNRef67">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef68">68</ref> H.J.W. Drijvers, <hi rend="italic">Cults and Beliefs at
    Edessa</hi> (Leiden: Brill, 1980), p. 40. <ref target="#FNRef68">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef69">69</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxiv &amp; 49. <ref target="#FNRef69">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef70">70</ref> For the associations of these cults see
    Drijvers, <hi rend="italic">Cults and Beliefs</hi>, pp. 40-75. <ref target="#FNRef70">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef71">71</ref> See in particular Drijvers, “The Abgar
    Legend,” and Han J.W. Drijvers, “Facts and Problems
    in Early Syriac-Speaking Christianity,” <hi rend="italic">The Second
    Century</hi> 2 (1982), pp. 157-175. <ref target="#FNRef71">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef72">72</ref> See Sidney H. Griffith, “The
    ‘Thorn among the Tares’: Mani and Manichaeism in
    the Works of St. Ephraem the Syrian,” in M.F. Wiles and
    E.J. Yarnold (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> (vol. XXXV;
    Leuven: Peeters, 2001), pp. 403-435 in press. <ref target="#FNRef72">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef73">73</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. v
    &amp; 11. <ref target="#FNRef73">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef74">74</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxiv &amp; 69. <ref target="#FNRef74">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef75">75</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxix &amp; 59. <ref target="#FNRef75">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef76">76</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xliii &amp; 87. <ref target="#FNRef76">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef77">77</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxvii &amp; 75.  See also <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. pp. xxxviii &amp;
    77 – xxxix &amp; 79. <ref target="#FNRef77">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef78">78</ref> See Robert L. Wilken, <hi rend="italic">Judaism and the
    Early Christian Mind: a Study of Cyril of Alexandria’s
    Exegesis and Theology</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press,
    1971); <hi rend="italic">idem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">John Chrysostom and the Jews: Rhetoric
    and Reality in the Late Fourth Century</hi> (Berkeley:
    University of California Press, 1983).  There is as yet no
    satisfactory study of Ephraem and the Jews.  Look for the
    forthcoming doctoral dissertation of Tina Shepherdson at Duke
    University. <ref target="#FNRef78">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef79">79</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xvii &amp; 35. <ref target="#FNRef79">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef80">80</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxi &amp; 43. <ref target="#FNRef80">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef81">81</ref> See Georg Günter Blum, <hi rend="italic">Rabbula von
    Edessa; der Christ, der Bischof, der Theologe</hi> (CSCO, vol.
    300, Subs. 34; Louvain: Secrétariat du Corpus SCO,
    1969); Han J.W. Drijvers, “Rabbula, Bishop of Edessa:
    Spiritual Authority and Secular Power,” in J.W. Drijvers
    &amp; J.W. Watt, <hi rend="italic">Portraits of Spiritual Authority</hi>, pp.
    130-154.  See also the study of the Syriac <hi rend="italic">vita</hi> of
    Rabbula by G.W. Bowersock, “The Syriac Life of Rabbula
    and Syrian Hellenism,” in Tomas Hägg &amp; Philip
    Rousseau, <hi rend="italic">Greek Biography and Panegyric in Late
    Antiquity</hi> (Berkeley: University of California Press, 2000),
    pp. 255-271.<ref target="#FNRef81">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef82">82</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    viii &amp; 17. <ref target="#FNRef82">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef83">83</ref> See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>,
    pp. xxxii &amp; 65. <ref target="#FNRef83">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef84">84</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxvi &amp; 73. <ref target="#FNRef84">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef85">85</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xxxvi &amp; 73. <ref target="#FNRef85">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef86">86</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    xlviii &amp; 97. <ref target="#FNRef86">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef87">87</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. l
    &amp; 101.  The translation given here differs
    considerably in nuance from Howard’s. <ref target="#FNRef87">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef88">88</ref> See Sidney H. Griffith, “Asceticism in
    the Church of Syria: the Hermeneutics of Early Syrian
    Monasticism,” in Vincent L. Wimbush &amp; Richard
    Valantasis (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Asceticism</hi> (New York: Oxford
    University Press, 1995), pp. 220-245. <ref target="#FNRef88">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef89">89</ref> See Han J.W. Drijvers, “The Man of God
    of Edessa, Bishop Rabbula, and the Urban Poor: Church and
    Society in the Fifth Century,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early
    Christian Studies</hi> 4 (1996), pp. 235-248. <ref target="#FNRef89">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef90">90</ref> See Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>,
    pp. xv &amp; 31. <ref target="#FNRef90">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef91">91</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp. xl
    &amp; 81. <ref target="#FNRef91">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef92">92</ref> H.J.W. Drijvers, “The Image of
    Edessa,” pp. 15-16. <ref target="#FNRef92">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef93">93</ref> Howard, <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of Addai</hi>, pp.
    liii &amp; 107. <ref target="#FNRef93">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef94">94</ref> G.W. Bowersock, <hi rend="italic">Fiction as History: Nero
    to Julian</hi>  (Sather Classical Lectures, vol. 58;
    Berkeley: University of California Press, 1994). <ref target="#FNRef94">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <!--
  _______<br />
  <h1>Bibliography</h1>
  <p id="B1" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B2" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B3" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B4" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B5" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B6" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B7" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B8" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B9" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B10" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B11" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B12" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B13" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B14" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B15" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B16" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B17" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B18" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B19" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B20" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B21" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B22" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B23" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B24" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B25" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B26" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B27" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B28" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B29" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B30" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B31" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B32" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B33" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B34" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B35" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B36" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B37" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B38" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B39" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B40" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B41" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B42" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B43" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B44" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B45" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B46" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B47" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B48" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B49" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B50" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B51" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B52" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B53" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B54" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B55" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B56" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B57" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B58" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B59" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B60" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B61" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B62" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B63" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B64" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B65" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B66" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B67" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B68" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B69" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B70" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B71" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B72" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B73" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B74" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B75" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B76" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B77" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B78" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B79" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B80" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B81" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B82" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B83" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B84" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B85" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B86" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B87" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B88" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B89" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B90" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B91" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B92" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B93" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B94" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B95" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B96" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B97" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B98" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B99" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B100" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B101" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B102" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B103" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B104" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B105" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B106" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B107" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B108" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B109" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B110" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B111" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B112" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B113" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B114" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B115" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B116" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B117" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B118" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B119" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B120" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B121" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B122" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B123" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B124" class="biblio"> </p>
  <p id="B125" class="biblio"> </p>
  -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>