<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mar Raphael Bidawid (1922-2003)</title>
            <author>
               <name>George A. Kiraz</name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 7, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.org/Vol7No1</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>George A. Kiraz</author>
                  <title level="a">Mar Raphael Bidawid (1922-2003)</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="7">7</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-26-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <!-- #BeginEditable "PubTypeLabel" -->
         <p rend="pubtype">OBITUARY</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Title" -->
    
         <!-- #EndEditable -->     <!-- #BeginEditable "Author" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Address" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->     <hi style="float:right;margin:5px 0 5px 15px;background-color: #fff;padding:5px;border-top:1px solid #555;border-right:2px solid #999;border-bottom:2px solid #999;border-left:1px solid #555;">
            <graphic url="HV7N1OBBidawid_Img01.jpg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
         </hi>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P1"/>[1] On the
    morning of July 7, 2003, Mar Raphael Bidawid, Patriarch of the
    Chaldean Church passed away in Beirut, Lebanon. The 81-year old
    Patriarch had been suffering for a few months from an acute
    health problem. The news of his death was first announced to
    the Syriac studies community two days later during the opening
    session of the North American Syriac Symposium in Princeton,
    NJ. The gathered scholars recalled Mar Raphael's various
    scholarly contributions.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P2"/>[2] Raphael
    Yousif Warda was born on April 17, 1922 in Mosul, Iraq. His
    parents enrolled him at the very young age of 11 in the
    Chaldean seminary. Shortly thereafter, in 1936, he was sent to
    Rome where he studied for 10 years. He was ordained a priest in
    1944 and received his doctorate in 1946. The following year Fr.
    Raphael went back to Iraq where he served as a priest in the
    Chaldean Church. In 1957, he was consecrated bishop for the
    Amadia district, and in 1966 he was transferred to Beirut,
    Lebanon.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P3"/>[3] On May
    21, 1989, Mar Raphael succeeded Mar Paulos Chekho II to the
    Patriarchate of the Chaldean Church, and received the Pallium
    from Pope John Paul II on November 9 of the same year. Mar
    Raphael was instrumental in the ecumenical movement, especially
    with relations with the Assyrian Church of the East. During his
    Patriarchate, he established Babylon College which became an
    instrumental educational institution for the Chaldean
    Church.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P4"/>[4] Mar
    Raphael has been succeeded by Mar Emmanuel Delly at a Synod of
    the Chaldean bishops in the Vatican on December 2-3, 2003.</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
