<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Session on Syriac Lexicography, International Meeting of the Society of Biblical Literature Groningen, The Netherlands July 25-28, 2004.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Ilaria</forename>
                  <surname>Ramelli</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2004</date>
            <idno>Vol. 7, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv7n2crramelli</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Ilaria Ramelli</author>
                  <title level="a">Session on Syriac Lexicography, International Meeting of the Society of Biblical Literature Groningen, The Netherlands July 25-28, 2004.</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="7">7</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Syriac Bible</term>
               <term>Lexicography</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    program of the International Syriac Language Project (ISLP)
    held during the 2004 SBL International Meeting in Groningen
    took place on July 27, 2004 and was characterized by important
    contributions in the field of Syriac linguistics and
    lexicography. The morning session was chaired by Wido van
    Peursen of Leiden University; the afternoon session was chaired
    by Peter Williams of the University of Aberdeen.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli1">Index of Paper Abstracts</head>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.1">George Kiraz, "Lexica and Grammar in the
      Syriac Tradition."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.2">Peter Williams, "The Semantics of the
      Epistles of the Peshitta: The Case of
      alpha-privatives."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.3">A.D. Forbes, "Distributionally-Inferred
      Word- and Form-Classes in the Hebrew Lexicon."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.4">Terry Falla, "International Syriac
      Language Project (ISLP) Report: Aims, Publications, and
      Projects."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.5">Janet W. Dyk, "Considerations of Form and
      Function in the Treatment of the Passive
      Participle."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.6">Andreas Juckel, "Towards an Analytical
      Concordance of the Harklean Version"</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.7">Michael Sokoloff, "An English Translation
      and Revised Edition of C. Brockelmann's Lexicon
      Syriacum."</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="#S1.8">Wido van Peursen and Terry Falla, "The
      Particles gyr and dyn in Classical Syriac: Syntactic and
      Semantic Aspects"</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
         <lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli2">Lexica and Grammar in the Syriac Tradition</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli3">George A. Kiraz, Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    first paper of the morning session was delivered by George A.
    Kiraz (Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute) and dealt with
    <hi rend="italic">Lexica and Grammar in the Late Syriac Tradition</hi>. It
    offered a selected but detailed survey of the history of Syriac
    lexicography and grammar, in which particular attention was
    paid to three works written by Syriac lexicographers and
    philologists of the nineteenth century: Touma Oddo's
    Syriac-Syriac lexicon, Awgen Manna's Syriac-Arabic lexicon, and
    Clemis Joseph David's grammar, and the most extensive one
    written after that by Bar Hebraeus. Many examples were given of
    the dependence of David's work on Arabic grammatical criteria
    and of its normative approach to the language. The aim of the
    paper was also to see whether and how the methodologies used in
    such early works can be employed in modern Syriac
    lexicography.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli4">The Semantics of the Epistles of the Peshitta:
    The Case of alpha-privatives</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli5">Peter A. Williams, University of Aberdeen</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Peter A.
    Williams, of the University of Aberdeen, spoke about <hi rend="italic">The
    Semantics of the Epistles of the Peshitta: The Case of
    alpha-privatives</hi>. He showed how some aspects of the meaning
    of Syriac words can be inferred by text-internal bases, also in
    the light of a diachronic study of the language and of
    translation techniques from Greek, a synthetical language, to
    Syriac, a more analytical one. The example most closely
    considered was that of the various Syriac renderings of Greek
    alpha-privatives in the Peshitta translation of the New
    Testament Epistles: some of such words are transliterated in
    Syriac, others are translated with a negative form (negative
    particle + adjective or noun etc.), or with a positive one;
    sometimes it is absolutely unpredictable whether a negative or
    a positive pattern will be used. Particular problems arise in
    the case of Greek double negatives, given the necessity of
    avoiding two negative particles in Syriac, and of 'negative +
    positive(s)' sequences which generally give rise to word order
    disturbances in Syriac (positive[s] + negative at the end),
    where the negative particle must be placed in the last syntagm,
    so that it becomes impossible to refer it to the other terms of
    the series. From such considerations, it is evident that
    translation literature played a formative role in Syriac
    semantics.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli6">Distributionally-Inferred Word- and Form-Classes
    in the Hebrew Lexicon</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli7">A.D. Forbes, University of California, Berkeley</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] A.D.
    Forbes, of the University of California, Berkeley, presented a
    paper on <hi rend="italic">Distributionally-Inferred Word- and Form-Classes in
    the Hebrew Lexicon</hi>. He illustrated how to infer word- and
    form- classes in the masoretic text of the Bible on the basis
    of geometrical and hierarchical techniques from statistical
    pattern recognition. In particular he showed the importance of
    word categories or classes, and investigated which of them can
    be appropriate, how they ought to be assigned, what
    complications arise in the case of Biblical Hebrew (where we
    face orthographical variation, agglutination, and missing
    punctuation), how computational systems can help to infer a
    taxonomy, and how to derive word classes from word contexts and
    form classes from form contexts. Several dendrograms, plots and
    ideographical schemata helped much to clarify the exposition.
    As the author observed, the resulting groupings of words and
    forms are rather satisfactory, but also exhibit some oddities
    that need to be either explained away or eliminated. Since it
    is necessary to derive insights from limited data that cannot
    be increased, the suggestion and the resolution has been to
    implement ways of treating and intrepreting these data.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli8">International Syriac Language Project (ISLP)
    Report: Aims, Publications, and Projects</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli9">Terry Falla, University of Melbourne</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The last
    paper delivered in the morning was a short communication by
    Terry Falla, from the University of Melbourne: <hi rend="italic">International
    Syriac Language Project (ISLP) Report: Aims, Publications, and
    Projects</hi>. It presented the present and future work of the
    ISLP, which coordinated the first full day session on Syriac
    lexicography at the 2003 SBL International Meeting in
    Cambridge. Among many other things, the scholar observed that
    much Syriac literature has not yet been lexicalized and that
    plenty of work is still to be done, e.g. the preparation of a
    Syriac-English lexicon, a Syriac New Testament thesaurus, etc.
    Of course, nowadays many tasks can be achieved thanks to the
    new digital and computing tools that linguists and
    lexicographers can employ. Volumes on Syriac lexicography and
    related matters will be published by Gorgias Press, as well as
    the papers presented at the meeting sessions, and important
    studies have been announced: they will be written by Sebastian
    Brock, George Kiraz, Terry Falla, etc. The volumes will belong
    to a specific series.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli10">Considerations of Form and Function in the
    Treatment of the Passive Participle</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli11">Janet W. Dyk, Vrije University of Amsterdam</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In the
    afternoon session, Janet W. Dyk (Vrije University of Amsterdam)
    expounded some <hi rend="italic">Considerations of Form and Function in the
    Treatment of the Passive Participle</hi>. Attention was focused
    on the classification of the participles as verbal forms: the
    author showed that their character of verbs, attributes, nouns,
    or even adverbs, usually depends on the contexts in which they
    are found: if they govern elements (i.e., complements)
    verbally, they are verbs, either subordinate, if alone, or main
    verbs, if joined to the form "to be", etc. Thus, the question
    arose where to put them in the construction of a lexicon: the
    scholar suggested that they ought to be set under their
    respective verbs, and, if they are placed as separate entries,
    in any case there should be the indication of the verbs they
    belong to, so that the link may not be missed.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli12">Towards an Analytical Concordance of the Harklean
    Version</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli13">Andreas Juckel, Institute of New Testament Textual
    Research</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The
    second paper of the afternoon was delivered by Andreas Juckel,
    of the Institute of New Testament Textual Research: <hi rend="italic">Towards
    an Analytical Concordance of the Harklean Version</hi>. It dealt
    with the latest Syriac version of the New Testament-more an
    adaptation than a translation-prepared by Thomas of Harqel,
    Syriac-Orthodox bishop of Mabbug, in A.D. 615-616. The main
    characteristic of this translation is that it disregards the
    rules of Syriac and prefers a 'mirror translation' of the Greek
    text; this makes it particularly useful for those who concern
    themselves with textual criticism of the Greek New Testament,
    thanks to the possibility of a retroversion too. Recent
    scolarship could even reconstruct the Greek NT manuscript(s)
    used for this translation, which, together with the existence
    of reliable Harklean editions and the consistency of lexical
    and translational features in it, induces the preparation of an
    analytical concordance of this version. The paper also
    illustrated the cultural context in which the Harklean version
    arose, its fortune among the Miaphysites, and how it employed
    the Greek versions of Origen's Hexapla in a kind of comparative
    translation, and offered many examples of translations from
    Thomas' work, including hapax legomena, transliterations of
    Greek words, the various renderings of Greek compounds, and the
    development of transliterations of proper Greek names from
    Thomas to the Massora and later documents.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli14">An English Translation and Revised Edition of C.
    Brockelmann's Lexicon Syriacum</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli15">Michael Sokoloff, of the Bar Ilan University</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Michael
    Sokoloff, of the Bar Ilan University (Ramat Gan, Israel),
    illustrated the enormous and precious work that he is
    preparing: <hi rend="italic">An English Translation and Revised Edition of C.
    Brockelmann's Lexicon Syriacum</hi>. Brockelmann, an Arabist who
    worked really very much, and at a rather high level indeed,
    published the first edition of his lexicon (Edinburgh-Berlin
    1895) when he was 27, and the second edition (Halle 1928) is
    still used, in absence of better tools, together with the
    <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire syriaque-français</hi> by L. Costaz
    (Beirut 1963: it is also a Syriac-English and Syriac-Arabic
    dictionary). Prof. Sokoloff expounded the main intentions of
    his project:</p>
         <p>1. To translate the dictionary from Latin into English
    (there were some English glosses in the first edition and some
    German ones in the second).</p>
         <p>2. To update the etymologies, making corrections when
    Brockelmann made mistakes, and filling the gaps (e.g.,
    loanwords cited from Akkadian that are either incorrect or
    non-existent, considering that when Brockelmann was working no
    Akkadian dictionary was available; for the Persian loanwords,
    Brockelmann did not consider the Middle Persian dialects; the
    various Jewish Aramaic dialects are not distinguished; no
    cognates from Jewish Babylonian Aramaic or the middle Eastern
    dialects are mentioned, etc.).</p>
         <p>3 &amp;4. To correct and update the references to text
    editions and secondary literature, also revising the
    abbreviations system.</p>
         <p>5. To reorder the dictionary entries in strict alphabetical
    order, while in Brockelmann's lexicon they are not always
    listed in that way; moreover, the most useful <hi rend="italic">Index
    Latino-Syriacum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Index analyticus</hi>, both present
    in Brockelmann's first edition, disappeared in the second
    one.</p>
         <p>Brockelmann's work is regarded to be the most authoritative
    and accurate dictionary of Syriac: its translated and revised
    edition will be extremely useful for all those who deal with
    Semitic languages, Aramaic studies, and Eastern
    Christianity.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli16">The Particles gyr and dyn in Classical Syriac:
    Syntactic and Semantic Aspects</head>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2CRRamelli17">Wido van Peursen, Peshitta Institute, Leiden and Terry
    Falla, University of Melbourne</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] The last
    paper, presented by Wido van Peursen (Peshitta Institute,
    Leiden University) and Terry Falla, dealt with <hi rend="italic">The Particles
    gyr and dyn in Classical Syriac: Syntactic and Semantic
    Aspects</hi>. The first problem tackled was that of the
    classification of <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> as parts of the
    speech: rather than seeing them as adverbs or conjunctions
    since they occur together with true conjunctions, the authors
    prefer to consider them as 'connective particles'. From the
    syntactical point of view, van Peursen demonstrated that the
    position of <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> in a clause can be
    described more precisely than simply "after the first word": in
    fact, they are often found after two or more initial words too.
    It is better to state that they usually occur after the first
    syntactical 'atom', though there are some exceptions
    (<hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> found even inside an atom). It
    is opportune to notice that other elements too, such as the
    enclitic pronouns or <hi rend="italic">l</hi>- + suffix, tend to assume the
    second position inside the clause, and when these elements
    occur all together at the beginning of a phrase, they appear in
    the following order: enclitic pronoun, <hi rend="italic">l</hi>- + suffix,
    gyr/dyn. Sometimes the two connective particles are placed
    immediately after the conjunction, like in Greek <hi rend="italic">ei
    gar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ei de</hi>.</p>
         <p>Just the connection to Greek <hi rend="italic">gar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de</hi>
    often lead to the erroneous assumption that <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> are equivalent of the first two also from the
    semantic and functional point of view, as shown by Falla on the
    basis of a systematical synopsis of the Greek and Syriac
    couples of particles in the Gospel and the Pastoral Epistles.
    It results that <hi rend="italic">gar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de</hi> are not always
    translated respectively by <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi>, and,
    on the other hand, <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> do not always
    translate <hi rend="italic">gar</hi> or <hi rend="italic">de</hi>. For instance, in the
    Peshitta Gospels <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> translates <hi rend="italic">de</hi>, to be
    sure, but also <hi rend="italic">kai</hi>, <hi rend="italic">oun</hi>, <hi rend="italic">alla</hi>,
    <hi rend="italic">gar</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mentoi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">plên</hi>,
    <hi rend="italic">hoti</hi>, <hi rend="italic">te</hi>, etc. Conversely, in the Peshitta
    Epistles to Timothy and Titus, Greek <hi rend="italic">de</hi> is rendered by
    <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi>, but also by <hi rend="italic">w</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi>, etc., or
    even has no correnspondence at all in the Peshitta Pastoral
    Epistles. The Peshitta translators seem to have been well aware
    of the various semantic values of <hi rend="italic">gyr</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi>; furthermore, the translations appear different in
    the single parts of the Peshitta version. <hi rend="italic">Gyr</hi> can
    assume at least the following meanings: so, because, so that,
    then, for, you see, well, indeed, certainly; for example;
    <hi rend="italic">dyn</hi> can assume at least the following ones, marking
    the beginning of a new sentence: but, and, so, that is,
    nevertheless, and yet, however.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] The
    ISLP has begun to produce very good fruits; all those
    interested in Syriac topics will hope that it continues to do
    this and to develop its plans and achieve its objectives-which
    seems very likely indeed.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>