<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Pearl of Virginity: Death as the Reward of Asceticism in Mēmrā 191 of Jacob of Serug</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Robert A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kitchen</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2004</date>
            <idno>Vol. 7, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv7n2kitchen</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Robert A. Kitchen</author>
                  <title level="a">The Pearl of Virginity: Death as the Reward of Asceticism in Mēmrā 191 of Jacob of Serug</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="7">7</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Jacob</term>
               <term>Serug</term>
               <term>Sarugh</term>
               <term>memra</term>
               <term>pearl</term>
               <term>asceticism</term>
               <term>virginity</term>
               <term>death</term>
               <term>bat qyama</term>
               <term>daughter of the Covenant</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>Jacob of Serug’s
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, “On the <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā</hi>, a pure virgin, who departs from this
    world,” appears to be a funeral oration written on the
    death of a consecrated “daughter of the
    Covenant.”  Jacob counsels those mourning that death
    is not the end, but the entrance into the angelic realm, the
    reward for a life of asceticism, virginity, and devotion to
    Jesus, the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>, her betrothed.  The
    metaphor of the pearl applied to her virginity illustrates how
    she has ascended out of the iniquity of the world/sea to the
    glory of heaven through the power of her virginity and
    asceticism.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->

         <lb/>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Jacob of
    Serug, the Flute of the Holy Spirit, played seemingly
    innumerable tunes in dodecasyllabic meter, 763 verse homilies
    by one count. His poetic <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> did not
    pretend to an historical dimension, as did some of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi>. Best known for
    his long Biblical expositions, Jacob also explored ascetical
    themes frequently. This is the second paper examining
    several of these ascetical <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> attempting
    to reconstruct Jacob's theology of asceticism.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2]
    <hi rend="italic">Mēmrā</hi> 191 in Paul Bedjan’s
    edition<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> allows us to hear Jacob’s voice a
    little more intimately. Not that this voice is absent from
    700-odd other <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi>, but here we have a good
    idea of the occasion and environment to which his words were
    addressed. The title is “Concerning the
    <hi rend="italic">bat</hi>
            <ref target="#FN3">3</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">qyāmā</hi>, the pure virgin who
    departs from this world.” It is a funeral oration,
    addressed to the mourners of an exceptional, but anonymous,
    consecrated virgin.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] That the
    setting is funereal becomes clearer upon examining a later
    document published recently by Sebastian P. Brock: the
    “Order for the burial of <hi rend="italic">bnāt
    qyāmā</hi>, or the burial of nuns
    (<hi rend="italic">dayrāyātā</hi>) existing in a single
    manuscript copied by a priest Joseph, presumably in Tur Abdin
    in 1980.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref> Brock notes that the term <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā</hi> in modern times often refers to the wife
    or widow of a priest. Whether the <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā</hi> had to be celibate, a virgin, still needs
    to be examined. Lucas van Rompay has drawn attention to
    the modifier “the pure virgin” in Jacob of
    Serug’s title, which may indicate that the two statuses
    are not equivalent. The use of the modern term
    “nun”—a female monk—as a translation of
    <hi rend="italic">bat qyāmā</hi> may be too restrictive.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] With
    such a late document, there is no way to determine whether the
    original liturgy is preserved out of which context Jacob
    wrote. Jacob clearly is referring to a virgin <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā,</hi> so that the use of such a liturgy for
    wives and widows of priests may be a development and adaptation
    or simply a reflection of the broad definition of the
    <hi rend="italic">bnāt qyāmā</hi>. There is little
    indication that the modern liturgy is not derived from one
    intended for virgins. While Jacob does not directly follow
    the sequence of the liturgy, there are echoes of the
    terminology and themes of the liturgy embedded in his
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā.</hi>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5]
    Unfortunately, the only place the technical term <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā</hi> appears is in the title,<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> and Jacob tells us
    little to add to the profile of the <hi rend="italic">bnāt
    qyāmā</hi>. That a <hi rend="italic">bat qyāmā</hi>
    would be normally a virgin is no revelation, so we have to
    listen a little more attentively to Jacob’s
    characterization.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] Bedjan
    utilizes a single manuscript, British Library Add.
    14608,<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> of 7th or 8th century provenance, that
    contains a series of 14 <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> by Jacob (ff.
    3a-69a). These <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> bear the common
    thread and theme of death—funeral sermons for youth, a
    priest, a meditation on death, and on the end of the
    world. This cycle is enclosed by metrical discourses by
    Isaac of Antioch on the plague in the days of King David (ff.
    1-3a); a <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> by Ephrem on the
    departed/dead (69a-72a); and five more discourses of Isaac of
    Antioch on the death of youths, the evils of the world, life in
    the time of plague, and on the rich of the world
    (72b-96b). A single leaf from a <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>
    by Jacob, probably entitled “On the Resurrection”
    (f. 97), adds a theological punctuation to the contents of the
    manuscript.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Our
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, 11th in the series (40b-48a),<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> has
    the title as listed in Bedjan’s edition. Consisting
    of 319 lines,<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> it is of medium length for Jacob’s
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi>. The sense units are two-line
    couplets of 12 syllables each, and the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>
    is divided into 10 sections of varying lengths.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2Kitchen2">Mēmrā 191: Concerning the <hi rend="italic">bat
    qyāmā</hi>
         </head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Section
    1. (821:4-822:8) Jacob declares immediately that this
    occasion of a funeral is not tragic, but a time of celebration
    and accomplishment. “Admirable is the departure when
    it adorns itself gloriously/It is without suffering for whoever
    lives prudently.:: Beloved is death when righteousness
    accompanies it/It does not sadden him when it enshrouds a
    person of God.::” (821:4-7) Aiming to dispel the
    reputed power and finality of death, Jacob transforms it into
    an anticipated entry into the kingdom of heaven.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Jacob
    establishes the metaphors that permeate the rest of the
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>: the world is depicted as the
    sea,<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> the traditional realm of chaos, in which
    many evils churn like the waves. Death is a haven, a
    sheltered cove, in which one finds protection from the
    tumultuous waves and storms.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10]
    Alluding to the spices, oils, and flowers used to prepare the
    body for burial, Jacob speaks of the sweet, but unnatural smell
    all these foreign substances emit. “The supposed
    fragrance from roots and from flowers/a foolish person smears
    on, but he is not praised by wise ones.:: They know that
    the good smell is not his own/but that of the oil that he is
    anxious to acquire through his
    licentiousness.” (821:16-19) The righteousness
    of a person is like the smell of choice oil that is a true
    natural odor of the person, far more pleasing to the wise and
    discerning ones who surround her.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Section 2. (822:9-824:8) Jacob explains his reordering of
    the sequence of authentic life. “The day of death is
    better than the day of birth/Every discerning person looks
    forward to death so that he may be victorious in it.::”
    (822:9-10) When one is born, the mighty and evil are equal
    with the weak and good—the proverbial clean
    slate. But at death, one’s labor and valor are now
    known, and for the good ones, “the beauty of their crowns
    shines” (822:14).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12]
    Worldly possession is not equivalent to glory, for as everyone
    knows you can’t take the former with you at
    death. However, glory does accompany whoever acquires
    it. There are different rules in play.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    Section 3. (824:9-825:17) Jacob turns his attention directly to
    the deceased. “The virgin who departed from within the
    world to God/the day of her death was not controlled by
    lamentations and weeping.::” (824:9-10)</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Death ruins the hopes of those who become betrothed to others
    in the world. No wonder, because when people love this
    untrue, inauthentic world, they are disturbed and unsettled at
    the thought of death and separation. Not so for the
    virgin, Jacob declares, for she has betrothed herself to the
    “faith of the Cross” (825:2)—an expression
    utilized several times in the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> as a
    synonym for Christ. A banquet is prepared for her in the
    other world; she is a bride in the realm of death.<ref target="#FN10">10</ref> Yet this is not the realm of despair, and
    anyone who weeps for her should be ashamed. There she will
    receive the dowries of her betrothed, along with the ring that
    his body and blood gave her. She leaps for joy in the
    glory of her husband.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15]
    Section 4. (825:18-826:15) Because the virgin despised
    transient rewards in this world the bridegroom rewards her in
    the other world.<ref target="#FN11">11</ref>  The watchers
    (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="italic">ayrē</hi>) or angels are
    rejoicing, for they witness that she despised intercourse on
    account of her love for the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>, the Only Begotten.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Section 5. (826:16-829:6) The longest section fills out the
    nature of this relationship.  The virgin made a covenant
    (<hi rend="italic">qyāmā</hi>) with the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi> who died for her sake,
    and she wore on her forehead a sign of mourning, a rag of
    passions (<hi rend="italic">’ūrqa<hi rend="sup">c</hi>tā d<hi rend="u">h</hi>ashē</hi>), as do all the wise pure
    maidens. Wearing black garments—the darkness of the
    crucifixion and night—was a sign of the covenant
    (<hi rend="italic">qyāmā</hi>) of virgins who have betrothed
    themselves to the “faith of the Cross.”
    (827:7-8)  “And like that day that became dark in
    the crucifixion/She became dark so that she might also become
    light through the Son in the new world.::”
    (827:15-16)</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] Upon
    her departure/death she is able to finally see her betrothed in
    whose name she had resided, and then her mourning subsided and
    she put on the crown of glory and the garment of
    light. She felt no pain in her death and spoke to one of
    her mourners that she had escaped the evil world and had
    reached the serene place.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18]
    Jacob revives the imagery of the world as the tumultuous sea.
    The virgin ascended from the snares/nets of the world/sea, the
    serpent whispering to her and laying traps for her, but she did
    not become weak or listen.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref> The <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi> guarded her steps from
    the murderer, and she crossed over the sea of evil passions and
    death became a haven of rest from the waves.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19]
    Sections 6.-7. (829:7-830:10 &amp; 830:11-831:14) The next
    two sections both deal with the reception of the virgin by the
    watchers or angels into their company. They rejoice in the
    pearl (<hi rend="italic">margānītā</hi>) that the virgin
    brings to the royal bridegroom as a wedding gift. All the
    heavenly host welcome her into their midst when the bridegroom
    introduces her after she has defeated Satan through
    virginity.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] The
    angels marveled at her virginity because her accomplishments
    were similar to theirs. They perceived their own virginity
    existing in an earthly being, and now she is like a relative or
    neighbor to them, living ‘without
    suffering/passion’ (<hi rend="italic">lā <hi rend="u">h</hi>ashshā</hi>) (831:14) in their ranks
    forever.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21]
    Section 8. (831:15-833:6) Jacob expresses his own laments
    and fears to the virgin. Your death is not like my
    death. I am afraid to die. Yet Jacob knows the Lord
    leads and guides her.  “Death is bitter and sweet is
    the smell of glory/but now I have both tastes from
    you.:: When the bitterness of death wafts up to me from
    your departure/may the sweet smell of your virginity perfume
    and enclose me” (832:10-13).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22]
    Finally, he has recognized the effect of her
    asceticism. “Resurrection renders death null and
    void/and therefore, there is no way to bring your virginity to
    naught” (833:3-4). Virginity is not just an earthly
    trait; it is the status of the angels, and so is eternal in
    nature.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23]
    Section 9. (833:7-834:19) The penultimate section is an
    exhortation to those attending the funeral, probably many who
    are <hi rend="italic">bnāt qyāmā</hi>, that they may imitate
    the departed’s example and so share her reward.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] When
    her pearl is honored in the treasury of the king, it will bring
    benefit to all who rejoice with her. The king guards the
    good people who have died like treasures in a living storehouse
    full of light. Like the virgin, righteous people pass from
    struggle and fear in this world at their death to the wedding
    feast of the king. Death is a place of comfort to the wise
    virgins who are full of light and have oil for their lamps
    (Matthew 25:1-13).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25]
    Section 10. (834:20-836:5) In this concluding
    section, Jacob spells out the metaphor of the pearl of
    virginity. Deep in the dark sea, no one knows about the
    qualities of the pearl until it brought to the surface to
    light. In this way, “the pearl depicts a type of
    virginity<ref target="#FN14">14</ref>/for the sea is the world and as long as the
    pearl is in [the sea] its beauty is unknown”
    (835:12-13). While in the evil world, the beauty of this
    woman’s virginity is hidden, although the angels are
    joyously aware of it.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26] Two
    trajectories are presented. At death the virgin ascended
    from the world/sea and brought up with her the pearl just as a
    diver might do from the darkness of the deep dark sea. Then in
    reverse, death descends after her and makes her ascend to the
    high places. Death has lost its sting and is now the agent
    who brings the righteous to eternal life.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2Kitchen3">The Asceticism of Death</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27]
    Alas, the funeral is over and we do not know as much as we
    would like about the <hi rend="italic">bnāt
    qyāmā</hi>. However, Jacob has told us a great
    deal about the context and nature of asceticism along the
    way.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28]
    Asceticism as a form of death to this world finds the metaphor
    fully realized in Jacob’s
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>. Death is an act of grace-full
    asceticism. As such, it is both an act of personal
    effort—the virgin ascends from the world with the pearl
    and attains the goal of death; and as the
    reward—grace—when death descends to fetch
    her. In several instances in the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>,
    death is personified as the benevolent agent of eternal
    life.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29] The
    only ascetical discipline mentioned in the
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> is virginity
    (<hi rend="italic">btūlūtā</hi>). This is the
    renunciation of sexual intercourse, which is specifically
    mentioned, but also implied is the renunciation of the various
    evils of this world.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30]
    Physical, earthly virginity is a mirror image of the nature of
    the angelic life. The angels are said to rejoice greatly over
    our <hi rend="italic">bat qyāmā</hi> because her virginity is so
    similar to theirs in heaven (Luke 20:34-36). After
    physical death, she is received into their company. Does
    she become literally an angel in substance? Jacob does not
    venture there, though I am not sure anyone has figured out the
    precise dimensions of angelic life.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31]
    Nevertheless, she lives with the angels
    eternally. “They exult in her and she rejoices with
    them with their crowns/She lives <hi rend="italic">without
    suffering/passion</hi> (<hi rend="italic">lā <hi rend="u">h</hi>ashshā</hi>) forever among their
    ranks.::” (831:13-14) The expression
    “<hi rend="italic">lā <hi rend="u">h</hi>ashshā</hi>” is not the fuller term
    <hi rend="italic">lā <hi rend="u">h</hi>āshōshūtā</hi>—the Syriac
    equivalent of <hi rend="italic">apatheia</hi>—but it must reflect the
    same state of mind and soul. Certainly, to possess
    <hi rend="italic">apatheia</hi> on earth is to anticipate the angelic status.
    Our virgin now enjoys this blessed state eternally in the realm
    of the Resurrection.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32] The
    famous pearl of great price (Matthew 13:45-46) for which the
    merchant in the parable sold all he possessed to buy it ties
    together the entire <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>. The pearl is
    her virginity that she brings up from the dark sea of the evil
    world, avoiding and eluding all the nets intended to entrap her
    and her pearl, to present finally as a wedding gift—her
    dowry—to her betrothed, Jesus the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] By
    Jacob’s funeral exhortations to the mourners, it is
    apparent how important the concept of betrothal was to the
    <hi rend="italic">bnāt qyāmā</hi>. Virginity is, after
    all, an act of renunciation, of not engaging in a certain
    activity. The <hi rend="italic">bnāt qyāmā</hi> actively
    engage themselves in betrothal to the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>. Wearing black
    clothes and the rag of passions on their foreheads are the
    signs of their allegiance to the crucified Christ, as well as
    anticipation of that day when they will be united to their
    betrothed. Indeed, Jacob plays on the word
    <hi rend="italic">qyāmā</hi> several times to indicate that this
    betrothal to the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi> is the content of their
    covenant. “She made a covenant with the
    <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi> who
    died for her sake/for she clings to him, there shall be no
    other for her.::” (826:15-16)</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34] Once
    the bride meets the bridegroom after death, he receives her
    into all he has, places the crown of eternal light upon her
    (825:20), and shares the wedding feast with her. While
    Jacob is not explicit, could there now be a type of union with
    the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>—“so they are
    no longer two, but one flesh” (Matthew 19:6)?</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P35"/>[35]
    Virginity as simple renunciation of sexual intercourse is not
    mature asceticism. The <hi rend="italic">bnāt qyāmā</hi>
    utilize their virginity as signs of their betrothal to the Only
    Begotten, an ascetical discipline that awaits fulfillment in
    the next world, the place of death that contains the reward of
    eternal union with the <hi rend="italic">Ī<hi rend="u">h</hi>īdāyā</hi>. Virginity is a
    manner of death in the natural world, a negation of the cycle
    of sexual relations and continuation of human life. This
    turning upside down of human patterns results in another
    reversal in the next world in which the virgin becomes
    perfectly alive in the realm of death.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2Kitchen4">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> R. A. Kitchen, "A Practical Theology of Asceticism
    in Jacob of Serug's <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> on the Solitary
    Ones," presented at North American Patristics Society, Chicago,
    May 2002. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Homiliae Selectae</hi>, vol. 5 (Paris, 1910),
    edit. Paul Bedjan. <hi rend="italic">Mēmrā</hi> 191: 821-836.
    <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> The feminine form of ‘<hi rend="italic">bar</hi>’ is
    written ‘<hi rend="italic">bart</hi>’; however, the
    <hi rend="italic">rēsh</hi> is usually elided, resulting in the
    pronunciation ‘<hi rend="italic">bat</hi>’, which will be the
    transliterated form used in the remainder of the article.
    <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> Sebastian P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">Burial Service for
    Nuns</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Mōrān ’Eth’ō</hi> 4;
    Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute,
    1992). <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> The same phenomenon occurs in an Armenian
    translation of one of Ephrem’s hymns (number 46 in
    <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> 30.1, 214-217), translated into
    English by Robert Murray, “‘A marriage for all
    eternity’: the consecration of a Syrian bride of
    Christ,” <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review</hi> 11
    (1989) 65-69. Murray believes that the hymn refers to a
    <hi rend="italic">bat qyāmā</hi>, but the term or its Armenian
    counterpart does not appear in the text. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> William Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts
    in the British Museum</hi>, Vol II (London, 1882), p. 733,
    DCCLXVI. Also cf. Arthur Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Handschriftliche
    Überlieferung der</hi> Mēmrē<hi rend="italic">-Dichtung des
    Ja'qob von Serug</hi>
            <hi rend="u">,</hi> vol. 1
    (<hi rend="italic">CSCO</hi> 344; Subsidia 39; Louvain, 1973) 52. <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> cf. Arthur Vööbus, <hi rend="italic">Handschriftliche
    Überlieferung der</hi> Mēmrē<hi rend="italic">-Dichtung des
    Ja'qob von Serug</hi>, vol. 2 (<hi rend="italic">CSCO</hi> 345; Subsidia 40;
    Louvain, 1973) 12. Vööbus has mistakenly dittoed the
    fourth <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, adding one more to
    Wright’s list. <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> 822:6 is a single line unit. <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> Cf. <hi rend="italic">Burial Service for Nuns</hi>, First
    Service, 7 [Syriac text: 6:1-2]<lb/>
         </p>
         <quote>
      “It is he who has granted you<lb/>
      to pass over the sea of sins (<hi rend="italic">yamā da<hi rend="u">ht</hi>āhē</hi>) in purity.” <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Burial Service</hi>, First Service, 7
    [Syriac, 6:5-7]</p>
         <quote>
      “The Royal Son has prepared for you<lb/>
      the bridal chamber (<hi rend="italic">gnūnā d<hi rend="u">h</hi>atnā</hi>) on high;<lb/>
      enter it, sister, and find joy,<lb/>
      give thanks to him who has held you worthy to behold
      him.” <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Burial Service</hi>, Third Service, part
    Seven: Madrasha, 35 [Syriac, 34:17-22]</p>
         <quote>
      “The virgin who rejected<lb/>
      the marriage crown which is subject to corruption<lb/>
      has gained the bridal chamber of the just<lb/>
      which the children of light yearn for.” <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Burial Service</hi>, Second Service, 29
    [Syriac, 28:3-4]</p>
         <quote>
      (addressed to Satan)<lb/>
      “Cunningly and clearly<lb/>
      you laid your snares (<hi rend="italic">pa<hi rend="u">h</hi>ē</hi>)<lb/>
      in order to make humanity captive.” <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Burial Service</hi>, First Service, 11
    [Syriac, 10:7-8]</p>
         <quote>
      “Lead her by the hand of the peaceful<lb/>
      angels to the blessed abodes of<lb/>
      your saints.”<ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> Ephrem utilizes the pearl as metaphor/type
    in a series of the Hymns on Faith, commonly known as “The
    Pearl.” Ephrem describes the origins of the pearl in
    the sea, being given birth by a virgin mother in the bosom of
    the sea who ‘knew her not.’  The pearl is then
    addressed as “the exact type of the Only Begotten”
    (Hymn 82.5). J. B. Morris, translator &amp; J. Gwynn,
    editor, <hi rend="italic">Selections translated into English from the Hymns
    and Homilies of Ephraim the Syrian and from the Demonstrations
    of Aphrahat, the Persian Sage</hi> (Oxford, 1898).</p>
         <p>Cf. also Edward G. Mathews, Jr., “St. Ephrem, Madrase
    on Faith, 81-85: Hymns on the Pearl, I-V,” <hi rend="italic">St.
    Vladimir’s Theological Quarterly</hi> 38 (1994)
    45-72.</p>
         <p>Mathews offers a different translation of 82.5:</p>
         <quote>
      “Our Lord had siblings, yet He was without
      siblings<lb/>
      for He is the Unique One, O singular one,<lb/>
      a great mystery whose unique type<lb/>
      you are. On a king’s crown<lb/>
      you have brothers as well as sisters.”
    </quote>
         <p>Robert Murray notes that the pearl is seen as the symbol
    (<hi rend="italic">rāzā</hi>) of virginity, as well as a title of
    Christ. Cf. Robert Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church and Kingdom: A
    Study in Early Syriac Tradition</hi> (Cambridge, 1975) 148,
    359. <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV7N2Kitchen5">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Sebastian P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">Burial
    Service for Nuns</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Mōrān
    ’Eth’ō</hi> 4; Kottayam, India: St. Ephrem
    Ecumenical Research Institute, 1992).</p>
         <p>Jacob of Serug, <hi rend="italic">Homiliae
    Selectae</hi>, vol. 5 (Paris, 1910), edit. Paul Bedjan.</p>
         <p>Edward G. Mathews, Jr., “St.
    Ephrem, Madrase on Faith, 81-85: Hymns on the Pearl,
    I-V,” <hi rend="italic">St. Vladimir’s Theological Quarterly</hi>
    38 (1994) 45-72.</p>
         <p>J.B. Morris, translator &amp; J.
    Gwynn, editor, <hi rend="italic">Selections translated into English from the
    Hymns and Homilies of Ephraim the Syrian and from the
    Demonstrations of Aphrahat, the Persian Sage</hi> (Oxford,
    1898).</p>
         <p>Robert Murray, <hi rend="italic">Symbols of Church
    and Kingdom: A Study in Early Syriac Tradition</hi> (Cambridge,
    1975).</p>
         <p>—, “‘A marriage for
    all eternity’: the consecration of a Syrian bride of
    Christ,” <hi rend="italic">Sobornost/Eastern Churches Review</hi> 11
    (1989) 65-69.</p>
         <p>Arthur Vööbus,
    <hi rend="italic">Handschriftliche Überlieferung der</hi>
    Mēmrē<hi rend="italic">-Dichtung des Ja'qob von Serug</hi>, vol. 1
    &amp; 2 (<hi rend="italic">CSCO</hi> 344-345; Subsidia 39-40; Louvain,
    1973).</p>
         <p>William Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of
    Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum</hi>, Vol II (London,
    1882).</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>