<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Mallpânâ dilan Suryâyâ Ephrem in the Works of Philoxenus of Mabbog: Respect and Distance†</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename>
                  <surname>Rompay</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName>Duke University</orgName>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 7, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/ /hv7n1vanrompay</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Lucas Van Rompay</author>
                  <title level="a">Mallpânâ dilan Suryâyâ Ephrem in the Works of Philoxenus of Mabbog: Respect and Distance†</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="7">7</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass/>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
         <!-- #BeginEditable "PubTypeLabel" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Title" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Author" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Address" -->
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
         <!-- #BeginEditable "Content" -->

         <p>This paper focuses on two theological works
    by Philoxenus of Mabbog (d. 523) in which the author considers
    Ephrem’s theological views. One is an early work, the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against Habbib</hi> (482-484); the other
    is the <hi rend="italic">Letter to the monks of Senoun</hi>, which may be
    dated to 521. In the early work, quotations from Ephrem’s
    work occupy a prominent position, but in the later work only a
    very few quotations are found and the author criticizes the
    imprecision of Ephrem’s language. This change in attitude
    between the earlier and the later work is symptomatic of the
    transition through which Syriac Christianity passed around the
    year 500. Syriac theological thought was reconfigured along the
    lines of Greek patristic theology and the legacy of Ephrem,
    “our Syrian teacher,” caused some
    discomfort.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] By
    expressing their preference for the term
    “Miaphysite” to characterize their Christological
    teaching, the Oriental Orthodox Churches of the
    anti-Chalcedonian tradition emphasize their indebtedness to
    Cyril of Alexandria, whose formula “one nature (<hi rend="italic">mia
    physis</hi>) of God the Word having become flesh” is
    indeed the cornerstone of their theological tradition.<ref target="#FN2">2</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] It is
    well known that Cyril’s works started being translated
    into Syriac during, or in the aftermath of, the Nestorian
    controversy, in the thirties of the fifth century. The
    mainstream Syrian anti-Chalcedonians did not follow
    Eutyches’ understanding of the “one nature”
    in Christ as overwhelmingly divine, but always interpreted
    Cyril’s Christology as doing full justice to both
    Christ’s godhead and manhood.<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> However, in spite of this
    duality, they firmly rejected any idea of division, or conjoint
    existence of divinity and humanity in Christ after the union.
    The Council of Chalcedon (451), therefore, with its two-nature
    formula, was unacceptable to them. They saw it as the betrayal
    of Cyril’s ideas and as the resurgence of
    Nestorius’ fundamental error, condemned at the Council of
    Ephesus (431).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    Philoxenus, since 485 bishop of Mabbog, halfway between Aleppo
    and Edessa, belonged to the first generation of Syrian
    theologians and church leaders who devoted all their energy to
    formulating a response to Dyophysitism of both the Nestorian
    and the Chalcedonian types. Elaborating upon Cyril’s
    Christology and taking the expression of John 1:14 (“the
    Word became flesh”) as his starting-point, he developed a
    theology which focuses on “God <hi rend="italic">becoming</hi>
    man”—becoming, without change in the divine
    unchangeability, without losing anything of what He previously
    was. If we take the expression “becoming”
    seriously, Philoxenus argues, and do not reduce it—as
    Nestorius did—to “indwelling,” the outcome of
    the process can be one entity only, not two.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] This
    theological program Philoxenus defended consistently and
    relentlessly for more than forty years, between 480 and 523.
    Here it is my aim not to study any specific aspect of this
    theology, but rather to ask the question to what extent
    Philoxenus relates his theology—for himself as well as
    for his readers – to the earlier Syriac heritage, in
    particular the works of Ephrem. As is well known, both
    adherents and opponents of the Council of Chalcedon tried to
    strengthen their case by claiming that their teaching was in
    full agreement with the established tradition of the
    Church.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref> Along with other anti-Chalcedonian authors,
    writing in Greek or in Syriac, Philoxenus was delving in
    earlier works in order to find support for his views and to
    underpin his resistance to Chalcedon with authoritative texts
    from the Fathers. Who were these Fathers and how prominent was
    Ephrem among them?</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] There
    can be no doubt that Philoxenus was intimately familiar with
    Ephrem’s works. Ephrem’s ideas had a decisive
    influence on his theology; Ephrem’s images and language
    resonate in many of his writings.<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> And yet, certain passages in
    Philoxenus’ œuvre prove that his relationship to
    Ephrem’s heritage was not always an easy one. In the
    following, I would like to examine evidence from the very
    beginning of Philoxenus’ career, in the early eighties of
    the fifth century, and to compare it with data taken from one
    of his last writings, datable to 521. This will show us that in
    these forty years a remarkable shift took place. Whereas for
    the young Philoxenus Ephrem was indeed a much respected
    theological authority, in his old age Philoxenus appears to
    have become much more critical of him. We will be focusing on
    two of Philoxenus’ major writings, the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against Habbib</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Letter to
    the monks of Senoun</hi>.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N1VanRompay3">The <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against Habbib</hi>
    (between 482 and 484)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] We first
    have to turn to an extensive theological composition, known as
    the <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against Habbib</hi>.<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> Like Philoxenus,
    Habbib was an influential monk in Mesopotamia, using his pen to
    defend his theological views. Philoxenus regards him as a
    Nestorian. Habbib was the author of an exposition
    (<hi rend="italic">Mamllâ</hi>), which largely consisted of a
    refutation of an earlier dogmatic letter by Philoxenus, sent to
    the monks in Mesopotamia. Philoxenus replied to Habbib’s
    <hi rend="italic">Mamllâ</hi> first with a short refutation and later
    on with a very thorough analysis and refutation in the
    above-mentioned <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi>, which are ten in
    number. The <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi>, or
    “Treatises,” preserved in two sixth-century
    manuscripts, include at the end a number of appendixes—in
    all likelihood to be traced back to Philoxenus himself—in
    which extracts from the three other works (Philoxenus’
    letter, Habbib’s <hi rend="italic">Mamllâ</hi>, and
    Philoxenus’ short refutation) are incorporated. The main
    piece among the appendixes, however, is a Florilegium of two
    hundred and twenty-seven patristic quotations, having as its
    title: <hi rend="italic">Sahdwâtâ men ktâbê
    d-’abâhâtâ</hi>, “Testimonies
    from the writings of the Fathers.” The
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> were published in various
    installments in <hi rend="italic">Patrologia Orientalis</hi> between 1920 and
    1982, begun by Maurice Brière<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> and after
    Brière’s death continued by François
    Graffin,<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> accompanied first with a Latin and later with a
    French translation. The Florilegium is in the 1982 issue.
    André de Halleux provided an analysis of the whole work
    in his 1963 monograph on Philoxenus,<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> while François Graffin
    studied the Florilegium in his contribution to the first
    <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum</hi>, held in Rome in 1972.<ref target="#FN10">10</ref>
    Sebastian Brock briefly discussed the Florilegium and pointed
    out its importance in 1997.<ref target="#FN11">11</ref> The Christology of the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> was studied in great detail by Luise
    Abramowski in a 2002 publication.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] The ten
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> themselves consist of theological
    explanation, mostly in direct reaction to points which Habbib
    had made. They only rarely refer to patristic authors, or do so
    in a very general way. Heretics are more frequently referred to
    by name. Sharing the same Syriac Mesopotamian background, both
    Philoxenus and Habbib occasionally accuse each other of being a
    follower of Bardaisan or Mani. At one point, Philoxenus reacts
    with indignation when Habbib attributes the idea of “the
    Most Highest becoming a baby” (<hi rend="italic">hwâ
    <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Ellâyâ <hi rend="sup">c</hi>ulâ</hi>) to
    Bardaisan and argues that it belongs to “the truthful
    teachers” (<hi rend="italic">mallpânê
    šarrirê</hi>) and above all to the “saintly
    and blessed” Ephrem.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] Let us
    turn to the Florilegium. This is divided into five thematic
    sections, a division which is explained and justified by the
    author. The five sections (A to E) as well as the names of the
    authors quoted and the number of passages attributed to each of
    them are shown in the following overview.<ref target="#FN14">14</ref>
         </p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>“The hypostasis of the Son, one from the Trinity,
      God the Word, descended from heaven and hypostatically
      dwelled in the Virgin.”<lb/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">1-27</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrem</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">28-32</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">John Chrysostom</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">33-44</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">45-46</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyril of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>      <lb/>
            </item>
            <item>“The One who dwelled in the Virgin hypostatically
      took his body from her (<hi rend="italic">’etgaššam
      mennâh</hi>) hypostatically without
      change.”<lb/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">47-54</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">John Chrysostom</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(8)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">55-61</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrem</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">62-65</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Athanasius of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atticus of Constantinople</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Athanasius of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">69-70</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basil of Caesarea</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">71-77</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyril of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <lb/>
            </item>
            <item>“Just as God became body, He also was born. The
      Virgin therefore is rightly called ‘Mother of
      God’, because she gave birth to the one hypostasis of
      God having become body (<hi rend="italic">
                  <hi rend="u">h</hi>ad
      qnomâ d-’Alâhâ
      da-mgaššam</hi>).”<lb/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">78-80</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gregory of Nazianzus</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">81-85</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">John Chrysostom</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">86-87</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">88-89</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Athanasius of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">90-91</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atticus of Constantinople</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theophilus of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alexander of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basil of Caesarea</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">95-101</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrem</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(7)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">102-103</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyril of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table> 
      </item>
            <item>“There is not the one and the other, neither are
      there the properties of the one and the properties of the
      other. The one hypostasis of God having become man cannot be
      counted as two, but He is the one God-Word having become man
      without change.”<lb/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">104-106</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Athanasius of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">107-109</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basil of Caesarea</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(3)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">110-132</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrem</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(23)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">133-137</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">John Chrysostom</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">138-142</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">143-148</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyril of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">149-152</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gregory of Nazianzus</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(4)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <lb/>
            </item>
            <item>“The suffering and the death may rightfully be
      ascribed to God. Being by nature God and Son, He was exposed
      to all human experiences except sin. God suffered and God
      died.”<lb/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">153-193</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ephrem</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(41)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">194-202</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">John Chrysostom</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">203-211</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Athanasius of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">213-218</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Basil of Caesarea</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eusebius of Emesa</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+1)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">220-221</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gregory of Nazianzus</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(2)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">222-227</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyril of Alexandria</cell>
                     <cell rowspan="1" colspan="1">(6)</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Of the
    authors quoted,<ref target="#FN15">15</ref> one wrote in Syriac, nine originally wrote in
    Greek. But the number of quotations from Ephrem fully
    compensates for this imbalance: 105, nearly half of the total
    number! Ephrem thus becomes by far the most quoted author, the
    first author from whom Philoxenus wanted to find support for
    his theological views.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] For
    a number of quotations Philoxenus provides the title of the
    work and exceptionally even the section. Several titles
    correspond to the names under which Ephrem’s works are
    commonly known and which are still used in modern scholarship.
    Thus we find: the <hi rend="italic">Madrâshê</hi> on the Church
    (a title which also covers our <hi rend="italic">Madrâshê</hi> on
    Virginity), the <hi rend="italic">Madrâshê</hi> on the Nativity,
    the <hi rend="italic">Madrâshê</hi> on Faith, the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> on Nicomedia, the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> on Faith,<ref target="#FN16">16</ref> the volume on the
    <hi rend="italic">Nisibene Martyrs</hi> (the one quotation attributed to this
    work does not figure in the <hi rend="italic">Carmina Nisibena</hi>, whereas
    three other quotations, given without attribution, are from
    this work), the <hi rend="italic">Madrâshê</hi> on Julian
    Sâbâ. The prose work known to us as “Sermon
    on our Lord” is quoted with its beginning words. For
    other quotations no title of the work is given. This is true
    for quotations from the hymns on the Resurrection, on
    Virginity, on the Fast, on Unleavened Bread, and against
    Heresies. In addition to these well-known works, most of which
    have been edited and fully documented in Beck’s
    editions,<ref target="#FN17">17</ref> there are fifteen quotations from works which
    nowadays are considered dubious and can be found only in the
    nineteenth-century edition by Lamy.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref> Moreover, in
    Graffin’s edition and translation twenty-seven quotations
    remained unidentified. Four of them subsequently were
    identified by Sebastian Brock.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref> This means that about one
    quarter of the quotations remain unaccounted for. A number of
    them may belong to works by Ephrem which have not survived. The
    four quotations from the <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> on
    Nicomedia constitute an interesting case. These
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> have survived not in the Syriac
    original, but in an early Armenian translation. Our four
    fragments are among the very few witnesses of the original
    text.<ref target="#FN20">20</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Wherever verification is possible, the text of the quotations
    in the Florilegium turns out to be identical, or nearly
    identical, to the text of Beck’s editions, which are
    often based on sixth-century manuscripts. When there are
    variant readings, these can occasionally be found in
    Beck’s apparatus, and are, thus, well attested in the
    Syriac manuscript tradition. To one significant variant I will
    turn shortly. There can be no doubt that the quotations were
    carefully selected and copied from written texts.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] Let
    us take a brief look at the other authors. The most unexpected
    name is that of Eusebius of Emesa, an author who is extremely
    rare in dogmatic Florilegia. He is represented with
    thirty-three fragments and therefore is the second most
    frequently quoted author! It is difficult to imagine what made
    him so attractive in Philoxenus’ eyes. Very little of his
    work has survived in Greek or in Syriac and his name was
    surrounded with the taint of Arianism. Might it be that one of
    the reasons why Philoxenus—who most certainly did not see
    him as an Arian!—chose him was that he was a Syrian, born
    in Edessa and a contemporary of Ephrem, though writing in
    Greek? With the combination of Ephrem and Eusebius we would
    have the two faces of Syriac culture, one expressing itself in
    Syriac and the other in Greek, joining in the orthodox
    faith!<ref target="#FN21">21</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] All
    the Greek authors in the Florilegium, Eusebius included, are of
    course presented in Syriac translation. There is reason to
    believe that the redactor of the Florilegium did not produce
    the Syriac translations himself, but was relying on existent
    translations. This can be proven for the extracts from
    Athanasius’ <hi rend="italic">Letter to Epictetus</hi>, which fully
    conform with the Syriac translation published by R.W.
    Thomson.<ref target="#FN22">22</ref> In the case of Eusebius of Emesa, the
    fragments quoted in the Florilegium are not known from
    elsewhere. We do not know anything about their origin and
    translation into Syriac, even though there seems to be no
    reason to question their authenticity.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] All
    the quotations were selected as witnesses to Philoxenus’
    theology of God’s descent, his becoming man from the
    Virgin, of the Virgin’s status as Mother of God, of the
    singleness, not the duality of the Son, and of God’s
    suffering, crucifixion, and death. In general the point is
    clear and convincing, although the sometimes very short
    extracts leave one a bit uncertain about the meaning of the
    fragment in its broader context. Modern readers cannot escape
    the impression that we are reading Ephrem through the lens of
    late-fifth century theology, that Ephrem’s texts are
    being recontextualized within Philoxenus’ theology.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] A
    different problem we encounter in fragment no. 19, from
    Ephrem’s Hymns on the Resurrection (I,7). The quotation
    runs as follows: “The Word of the Father came from his
    bosom and became a body in another bosom ….” Now,
    “became a body” (<hi rend="italic">wa-hwât
    pagrâ</hi>) perfectly expresses Philoxenus’ idea of
    God becoming man. However, in Ephrem’s text as edited by
    Beck, one reads: “clothed itself with a body”
    (<hi rend="italic">w-lebšat pagrâ</hi>),<ref target="#FN23">23</ref> an expression
    which is frequently found in Ephrem and is more problematic
    from the viewpoint of Philoxenus’ Christology. We do not
    know whether Philoxenus himself changed Ephrem’s
    text—there is no evidence for that in any of the other
    fragments and in fact there is one other fragment in the
    Florilegium which does have the expression <hi rend="italic">lbeš
    pagrâ</hi> (no. 111, unidentified). However, this case
    shows us that Syrian theologians of the end of the fifth
    century did occasionally have problems in their attempt to
    readjust the earlier heritage to the theological discourse of
    the day.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Philoxenus’ problems with the expression <hi rend="italic">lbeš
    pagrâ/besrâ</hi> are discussed in another work
    which he wrote about twenty years after the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against Habbib</hi>, his Commentary on
    the prologue of the Gospel of John, written around 505 and
    preserved in an early-sixth-century manuscript. Here, on
    several occasions, Philoxenus criticizes the imprecision of the
    existing Syriac New Testament translation. Focusing on the
    Epistle to the Hebrews which in chapter 5, verse 7 has the
    expression: “... in the days of his flesh ...”
    (<graphic url="HV7N1VanRompay_Gr.jpg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>, rendered in the Peshitta
    as <hi rend="italic">kad besrâ lbiš (h)wâ</hi>
    “while he was clothed with the flesh”), Philoxenus
    writes about the translators:<ref target="#FN24">24</ref>
         </p>
         <p>And rather than to Paul, they adhered to the
    (ideas) of Nestorius, who laid the body upon the Word as a
    garment on anyone’s body and in the likeness of purple on
    the body of kings, so that it would be thought of as something
    foreign, outside the (Word) itself, just as each vestment is
    foreign and distinct from the one who wears it.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17] The
    expression “clothing himself with the body, or with the
    flesh,” in Philoxenus’ view, suggests Nestorian
    duality and therefore can no longer serve to express the
    Incarnation. Even if in his commentary on John’s
    prologue, he does not explicitly mention Ephrem, he must have
    realized that the same expression often occurs in the beloved
    Syrian poet.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N1VanRompay4">The <hi rend="italic">Letter to the Monks of Senoun</hi>
    (521)</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] When
    Philoxenus wrote the commentary on John’s prologue, he
    was metropolitan bishop of the city of Mabbog, a position which
    he had held since 485. He was instrumental in improving the
    situation of the Syrian anti-Chalcedonians under the emperor
    Anastasius, and above all, in the deposition of the
    Chalcedonian patriarch of Antioch, Flavian, in 512 and his
    replacement by the anti-Chalcedonian Severus. The triumph of
    the anti-Chalcedonians and their control of the patriarchate of
    Antioch lasted for six years only. Following the Chalcedonian
    restoration under Justin I in 518, most anti-Chalcedonian
    bishops were expelled from their sees and went into exile.
    Philoxenus ended up in the Thracian city of Philippoupolis
    (present-day Plovdiv in Bulgaria). Embittered by the reports of
    defection of his former clergy and many laypeople in Syria, he
    wrote a treatise in 521, in which he defended his theological
    views and attacked the Dyophysites, Nestorians and
    Chalcedonians alike, with the same vigor as in his earlier
    works. The treatise, preserved in two sixth-century
    manuscripts, has the form of a letter of encouragement
    addressed to the monks of Senoun, a monastery in the vicinity
    of Mabbog, who in these troubled times had remained faithful to
    the cause of orthodoxy.<ref target="#FN25">25</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19] In
    the list of heretics,<ref target="#FN26">26</ref> the name of Nestorius is now followed
    explicitly by the Council of Chalcedon and the Tome of Leo. The
    views of these Dyophysites are exposed and refuted at length.
    Following this negative presentation, the author turns to the
    “blessed Fathers” to prove his point that
    “the one who was crucified for us” was indeed
    God.<ref target="#FN27">27</ref> From here onwards, the treatise is centered on
    a Florilegium. Quoting passages from the Fathers, combining
    them and commenting on them, the author unfolds his Miaphysite
    understanding of the Incarnation. Formally speaking, this
    Florilegium is quite different from the one attached to the
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> against Habbib, since we have much
    more than a pure list of quotations. But the author’s
    intention is the same: finding approval and support for his
    theology in the earlier Fathers. We may distinguish two
    sections here.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] The
    first section contains the names of Gregory of Nazianzus, Basil
    of Caesarea, Gregory of Nyssa, and Athanasius. Three of these
    authors (except Gregory of Nyssa) also occur in the earlier
    Florilegium and for each of these three several quotations are
    given. Only in one quotation is there overlap with the earlier
    Florilegium.<ref target="#FN28">28</ref> After these four names, the author turns to
    Ephrem with these words:<ref target="#FN29">29</ref>
         </p>
         <p>And next, the blessed Ephrem, our Syrian
    teacher (<hi rend="italic">mallpânâ dilan
    Suryâyâ</hi>), he also understood (it) according to
    these (ideas)...</p>
         <p>Then follow two quotations from “On
    Reprehension” (a work now mostly regarded as spurious).
    The two brief quotations also occur in the earlier
    Florilegium.<ref target="#FN30">30</ref> After these quotations, rather than providing
    commentary as he did for the other authors, Philoxenus breaks
    off the short Ephrem section with the following laconic
    statement.<ref target="#FN31">31</ref>
         </p>
         <p>And since it befits you more than (it befits)
    us to remember what has been said by this saint, I leave the
    rest to your effort.</p>
         <p>What follows is a conclusion not to the Ephrem section, but
    to quotations of the five authors taken together, without any
    special mention of Ephrem.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P21"/>[21] This
    is indeed a very telling passage! By using the expression
    “our Syrian teacher,” Philoxenus creates an
    opposition between the previous authors (the two Gregories,
    Basil, and Athanasius), all originally writing in Greek, and
    the Syrian Ephrem. Ephrem does not take the lead, as he did in
    Philoxenus’ earlier Florilegium, but is added at the very
    end. In addition, Philoxenus creates an opposition between
    himself and the monks, making clear that Ephrem belongs to the
    monks. He “leaves the rest to their effort,” i.e.,
    the further comments on the Ephrem passages as well as the
    search for, and study of, other passages. In short, having
    declared that Ephrem indeed is orthodox, he dismissively tells
    the monks to look for the evidence themselves!</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P22"/>[22]
    Philoxenus then moves to the next section of the treatise, in
    which he wants to prove, with the help of the Fathers, that it
    is not permitted to speak of two natures after the Incarnation.
    The authorities quoted are: Gregory Thaumaturgus, Julius of
    Rome (in both cases we are dealing with pseudepigraphical works
    belonging to Apollinaris of Laodicea), Athanasius of Alexandria
    (again Pseudo-Athanasius), Cyril of Alexandria, Basil of
    Caesarea, and again Cyril, “who in every respect walked
    on the path of the saintly Fathers, his predecessors, and did
    not turn aside from the royal road on which they had traveled,
    neither to the right nor to the left.”<ref target="#FN32">32</ref> The position of
    the Cyril quotations, their number and length, along with
    Philoxenus’ elaborate introductions and comments make it
    clear that <hi rend="italic">he</hi> definitely is the yardstick of
    orthodoxy, against whom all the others should be judged.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P23"/>[23] Now,
    for the second time in the treatise, again at the point where a
    section is coming to a close, Philoxenus brings Ephrem onto the
    stage:<ref target="#FN33">33</ref>
         </p>
         <p>That also Blessed Ephrem—the one whom I
    already quoted once at an earlier stage, the one from whose
    books, I guess, you possess more than (from those) of the other
    Fathers, while you also have the habit of reading in them a
    great deal—(that he) agrees with the (opinions) of the
    rest of the Fathers, also with regard to the question of one
    nature having become man, becomes particularly clear from his
    own words. For he somewhere wrote as follows: “One from
    the height, and the other from the depth, He mingled the
    natures like pigments and the image became God-man
    (<hi rend="italic">’Alâh
    barnâš</hi>).”<ref target="#FN34">34</ref>
         </p>
         <p>Philoxenus observes that “height” stands for the
    divinity and “depth” for the humanity and that
    there is no question of two natures.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P24"/>[24] Here
    again, Ephrem is quoted only at the end of the list of the
    Fathers whom he is allowed to join obediently. The passage in
    question does not provide clear support for the Miaphysite
    cause and needs quite some laborious explanation.<ref target="#FN35">35</ref> One
    wonders whether Philoxenus himself selected it or whether
    perhaps the monks submitted it to him, wanting to know how
    Ephrem’s poetical description of the Incarnation could be
    reconciled with the new theology.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P25"/>[25] As a
    matter of fact, Philoxenus explains that Ephrem’s choice
    of the verb “He mingled” is infelicitous and does
    not exactly express what he believed.<ref target="#FN36">36</ref> God forbid that
    Ephrem would have thought that the natures were mingled like
    water and wine, loosing in this process their specific and
    distinct characteristics! “He mingled” should be
    understood here as “He united.”<ref target="#FN37">37</ref> The use of the
    wrong verb, Philoxenus goes on, is due to the lack of precision
    in “our Syriac language,” which—particularly
    with regard to the Incarnation—does not have the same
    rigor that is found with the Greeks. This is true not only for
    the use of the verb “He mingled,” but also for
    another odd expression found in the same verse: “(and the
    image became) God-man” (<hi rend="italic">’Alâh
    barnâš</hi>), where expressions using the verbs
    “to be incarnated” (<hi rend="italic">’etbassar</hi>) and
    “to be inhumanized”
    (<hi rend="italic">’etbarnaš</hi>),<ref target="#FN38">38</ref> would have been more
    appropriate. It is too bad that Ephrem did not use them!
    However, his orthodoxy cannot be questioned, for in an obvious
    attempt to prevent the reader from making a distinction between
    God and man, he wisely omitted the conjunction
    “and,” writing “God-man” rather than
    “God-and-man.”<ref target="#FN39">39</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P26"/>[26]
    Philoxenus then returns to the imprecision of the language of
    the Syriac New Testament<ref target="#FN40">40</ref>—a problem which he already
    addressed in the commentary on the prologue of John. The Syriac
    translators did not care about preserving the rigor of the
    terms used in Greek and wrote down whatever they liked or what
    they thought was common in Syriac, thus missing an opportunity
    to introduce exact Syriac terms, which subsequently would have
    become of common use. Perhaps they believed that it befitted
    Syriac always to remain a poor language and not to make
    progress through an increase of knowledge. Blessed Ephrem had
    this same attitude with regard to the union of the two natures
    when he wrote “they were mingled” instead of
    “they were united” and again, when he wrote
    “and the image became God-man” instead of
    “(God) was incarnated and inhumanized.”<ref target="#FN41">41</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P27"/>[27]
    Isn’t this a very strong criticism of the Syrian Church
    Father who forty years earlier provided the large majority of
    the quotations supporting the Miaphysite theology? He now seems
    to have lost his position as a theological mentor. Although his
    basic orthodoxy is not questioned, the imprecision of his
    language and his alleged carelessness make him unfit to be used
    in theological discussions. The monks in the monasteries,
    steeped in Ephrem’s works from the liturgy as well as
    from their private reading, are now told to turn to Cyril and
    to the Greek Fathers for rigorous instruction into the
    mysteries of the Incarnation!</p>
         <head xml:id="HV7N1VanRompay5">The larger context</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P28"/>[28] The
    question arises whether this loss of interest in Ephrem as a
    spokesman in the Christological controversy may be seen as part
    of a broader phenomenon. There can be no doubt that in the
    early sixth century Ephrem was extremely popular. The
    recipients of Philoxenus’ letter to Senoun may be quoted
    as proof! And from roughly the same period—or slightly
    earlier—we have Jacob of Serug’s
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrâ</hi> on Ephrem, “the great master
    of teaching” and “the crown of the entire
    Aramaeandom.”<ref target="#FN42">42</ref> We also should bear in mind that the
    sixth century saw the production of a number of important
    Ephrem codices, which up to the present day constitute the main
    basis for our study of the authentic Ephrem. But what about his
    use in theological writings?</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P29"/>[29]
    Severus of Antioch, the main anti-Chalcedonian leader and
    theologian in the first half of the sixth century hardly ever
    mentions Ephrem in his numerous works.<ref target="#FN43">43</ref> These were
    written in Greek, but soon translated into Syriac, and Severus
    continuously interacted with the Syriac world, both during his
    patriarchate (512-518) and after his expulsion, when from Egypt
    he kept in close contact with the Syrian cities and
    monasteries, until his death in 538.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P30"/>[30] One
    of Severus’ theological writings is a refutation of a
    work by John the Grammarian, written in defense of the Council
    of Chalcedon, shortly before 518. Severus responded to this
    work in the early years of his exile, exactly the period when
    Philoxenus wrote to the monks of Senoun. John’s work must
    have included a Florilegium containing one or more quotations
    from Ephrem, in Greek translation. In one case Severus
    straightforwardly rejects the testimony, because the work in
    question, “On the pearl,” he argues, was a forgery.
    Severus had searched for it in the Syriac original, in
    Mesopotamia and as far as Edessa, where Ephrem had taught, but
    it was completely unknown.<ref target="#FN44">44</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P31"/>[31]
    Other quotations—apparently among those that were also
    included in the Grammarian’s Florilegium—might be
    reliable, but Severus’ reaction again is evasive.<ref target="#FN45">45</ref>
         </p>
         <p>I could have adduced, in order to demonstrate
    the truth, many quotations from other
    <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê</hi> (by Ephrem), which have been
    received and circulate in the Greek language. But it seemed to
    me audacious and incautious to provide for the demonstration of
    the divine teachings (passages from) those (quotations) which
    the one who happened to find (them) offered arbitrarily and
    haphazardly and differently at different times. For even one
    single ill-placed word may turn a correct statement into
    blasphemy.</p>
         <p>Although Severus does not refer to the imprecision of
    Ephrem’s language, he has his own reasons to regard the
    Ephrem texts as largely unreliable and of no use in the
    Christological discussions. At the same time, he fully agrees
    with Philoxenus in accepting Ephrem’s orthodoxy:
    “Of course I admit that the saintly Ephrem was a wise
    teacher among the Syrians!”<ref target="#FN46">46</ref> and he assumes that Basil
    had Ephrem in mind when, in very positive terms, he quoted
    “a Syrian man” in his second homily on the
    Hexaemeron—a further proof of Ephrem’s
    orthodoxy.<ref target="#FN47">47</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P32"/>[32]
    Christological statements in the Life of John of Tella, written
    by a certain Elijah shortly after 542,<ref target="#FN48">48</ref> are always based
    on Cyril of Alexandria. There is never any reference to Ephrem.
    The theological writings of the Syrian-Orthodox Church from the
    middle and the second half of the sixth century, many of which
    are concerned with internal theological controversies, do not
    refer to Ephrem. Ephrem’s name also is absent from the
    major collection of anti-Dyophysite and anti-Chalcedonian
    writings and extracts contained in the mid-sixth-century Syriac
    manuscript London, British Library, Add. 12,156.<ref target="#FN49">49</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P33"/>[33] We
    have to assume, therefore, that different processes were at
    work in the sixth century, when Syriac Christianity was on in
    its way to creating its own church structures, based on the
    rejection of Chalcedon, and eventually leading to an
    independent church. On the one hand, the early Syriac heritage,
    with Ephrem as its most illustrious representative, continued
    to have a decisive role in shaping the Syriac Christian
    identity in its liturgical and spiritual dimension. On the
    other hand, the theology of Syrian-Orthodox Christianity was
    increasingly determined by the writings of the mainstream
    theologians of the imperial church: Athanasius, the
    Cappadocians, and above all Cyril of Alexandria. Of course,
    since the Syriac translations of these authors had been fully
    incorporated into Syriac literary tradition, the opposition
    between Syriac and Greek had long become neutralized. But, as
    we have seen in the writings of Philoxenus of Mabbog, in the
    controversy over Nestorianism and Chalcedonianism the
    categories and concepts of early Syriac theology gradually
    proved insufficient and in need of replacement.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P34"/>[34]
    However, Ephrem’s name did not completely disappear from
    the Syrian-Orthodox theological tradition. As a matter of fact,
    after his absence—or loss of prominence—in the
    sixth century, he seems to re-emerge in the Syrian-Orthodox
    theological Florilegia of the seventh century and
    beyond.<ref target="#FN50">50</ref> Extracts from his works are now found among
    those of the major Greek fathers (Cyril of Alexandria and
    Severus of Antioch being most prominent among them) as well as
    the Syrians, Philoxenus and Jacob of Sarug. These extracts, not
    very numerous nor very substantial, may be seen as evidence of
    a certain rehabilitation of Ephrem in the theological canon of
    the Syrian-Orthodox Church.<ref target="#FN51">51</ref>
         </p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV7N1VanRompay6">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef0">†</ref> In memory of André de Halleux
    († 1994) and François Graffin († 2003).
    <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> This is a slightly reworked version of a paper
    presented at the North American Syriac Symposium IV (Princeton,
    NJ, July 9-12, 2003). An earlier draft was read by
    Françoise Petit (Louvain-la-Neuve), Joel Marcus (Duke
    University), and Bas ter Haar Romeny (Leiden). Their useful
    comments and suggestions as well as the observations of the two
    anonymous <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> reviewers should be gratefully
    acknowledged. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> For the use of this formula (which was not created
    by Cyril), see the references in G.W.H. Lampe, <hi rend="italic">A Patristic
    Greek Lexicon</hi>, Fourth impression (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
    1976), 1500b-1501b. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> It is for this reason that the term
    “Monophysite” was seen as particularly
    inappropriate. See, e.g., V.C. Samuel, <hi rend="italic">The Council of
    Chalcedon Re-examined.</hi> Indian Theological Library 8
    (Madras, 1977), xxi and <hi rend="italic">passim.</hi>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> Compare Marcel Richard, “Les
    florilèges diphysites du V<hi rend="sup">e</hi> et du
    VI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle,” in <hi rend="italic">Das Konzil von
    Chalkedon, Geschichte un Gegenwart</hi>, A. Grillmeier and H.
    Bacht, eds., I (Würzburg: Echter-Verlag, 1951), 721-748.
    <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> Edmund Beck, “Philoxenos und
    Ephräm,” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 46 (1962),
    61-76; André de Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène de Mabbog.
    Sa vie, ses écrits, sa théologie</hi> (Louvain:
    Imprimerie Orientaliste, 1963), esp. 318, with note 30; Roberta
    C. Chesnut, <hi rend="italic">Three Monophysite Christologies. Severus of
    Antioch, Philoxenus of Mabbug, and Jacob of Sarug</hi> (London:
    Oxford University Press, 1976), 2. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> Another title under which the work is known since
    the day of Assemanus is: “De uno ex Trinitate incarnato
    et passo Dissertationes X.” <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> M. Brière, <hi rend="italic">Sancti Philoxeni episcopi
    Mabbugensis dissertationes decem de Uno e sancta Trinitate
    incorporato et passo. Dissertatio I<hi rend="sup">a</hi> et
    II<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 15,4 (Paris, 1920).
    <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> M. Brière† and F. Graffin, <hi rend="italic">Sancti
    Philoxeni episcopi Mabbugensis dissertationes decem de Uno e
    sancta Trinitate incorporato et passo</hi>, II.
    <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 4<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,
    5<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 38,3 (Turnhout:
    Brepols, 1977); III. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes 6<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,
    7<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 8<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 39,4
    (Turnhout: Brepols, 1979); IV. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes
    9<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 10<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 40,2
    (Turnhout: Brepols, 1980); V. <hi rend="italic">Appendices</hi>: I.
    <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi>; II. <hi rend="italic">Refutatio</hi>; III. <hi rend="italic">Epistula
    dogmatica</hi>; IV. <hi rend="italic">Florilegium.</hi> Patrologia Orientalis
    41,1 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1982). <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> De Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène</hi> [1963],
    225-238. In a later article the same author focused on
    Habbib’s treatise: “Le <hi rend="italic">Mamlelâ</hi> de
    «Habbîb» contre Aksenâyâ. Aspects
    textuels d’une polémique christologique dans
    l’Église syriaque de la première
    génération post-chalcédonienne,” in
    <hi rend="italic">After Chalcedon. Studies in Theology and Church History
    Offered to Professor Albert Van Roey for his Seventieth
    Birthday</hi>, C. Laga, J.A. Munitiz, and L. Van Rompay, eds.,
    Orientalia Lovaniensia Analecta 18 (Louvain: Departement
    Oriëntalistiek &amp; Peeters, 1985), 67-82. <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> François Graffin, “Le
    florilège patristique de Philoxène de
    Mabbog,” in <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum 1972.</hi> Orientalia
    Christiana Analecta 197 (Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium
    Studiorum, 1974), 267-290. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> Sebastian Brock, “The Transmission of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi> in the Syriac Liturgical
    Tradition,” in <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 23, Elizabeth
    A. Livingstone, ed. (Louvain: Peeters, 1997), 490-505. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> Luise Abramowski, “Aus dem Streit um
    das „Unus ex trinitate passus“: Der Protest des
    Habib gegen die Epistula dogmatica des Philoxenus an die
    Mönche,” in <hi rend="italic">Jesus der Christus im Glauben der
    Kirche</hi>, Band 2/3. <hi rend="italic">Die Kirchen von Jerusalem und
    Antiochien nach 451 bis 600</hi>, Theresia Hainthaler, ed.
    (Freiburg i.B.: Herder, 2002), 570-647. The Florilegium is not
    included in this study. <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> M. Brière and F. Graffin, II,
    582[112]. For a nuanced analysis of this passage, see
    Abramowski, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, 595-596 (compare also 598).
    <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> The section headings given below are my own
    summaries of the fuller descriptions provided by Philoxenus (or
    by the redactor of the whole dossier?) at the end of the
    Florilegium (Graffin’s edition, 124[124]-126[126]). For
    different summaries, see De Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène</hi>
    [1963], 227, and Graffin, “Le florilège,”
    269. <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> The question whether Philoxenus is solely
    responsible for the creation of the Florilegium and whether he
    (or the unknown redactor) used preexisting collections of
    fragments (see De Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène</hi> [1963],
    323-324, with note 28) does not detract from the fact that the
    Florilegium as it exists must fully reflect his ideas. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> This quotation (no. 159) had not been
    identified by the editor. It consists of <hi rend="italic">Sermon on
    Faith</hi> III,349-352 and 359-360 (CSCO 212 / Syr. 88, 30).
    <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> For an overview of the editions of
    Ephrem’s works, see Sebastian Brock, <hi rend="italic">Saint Ephrem.
    Hymns on Paradise</hi> (Crestwood, New York: St.
    Vladimir’s Seminary Press, 1990), 230-233. <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> Thomas J. Lamy, <hi rend="italic">Sancti Ephraem Syri
    Hymni et Sermones</hi>, 4 vol. (Malines, 1882-1902). <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> Brock, “The Transmission,” 492,
    note 6. The first quotation (no. 116 or § 147) is taken
    from the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Church</hi> 13,23 (CSCO 198 / Syr.
    84, 34); the second quotation (no. 159 or § 200), from the
    third <hi rend="italic">Sermon on Faith</hi>, is mentioned in note 16 –
    the last two lines, not identified by Brock, are verses
    359-360; the third quotation (no. 163 or § 204) is from
    <hi rend="italic">Sermo</hi> I, iii, 349-352 (CSCO 305 / Syr. 130, 55 –
    the last word of this quotation in Graffin’s edition
    should be read as <hi rend="italic">l-<hi rend="sup">c</hi>ln’</hi>, i.e.,
    <hi rend="italic">l-<hi rend="sup">c</hi>allânê</hi>); the fourth
    quotation (no. 173 or § 214) is from the <hi rend="italic">Hymns on
    Fast</hi>, 5,6, lines 3-6 (CSCO 246 / Syr. 106, 14). <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> See Charles Renoux, <hi rend="italic">Éphrem de
    Nisibe. Mêmrê sur Nicomédie.</hi> Patrologia
    Orientalis 37,2-3 (Turnhout : Brepols, 1975), XIV. The
    four fragments are as follows: no. 4 (without title) =
    X,153-156 (for the second Syriac form <hi rend="italic">dalli</hi>, the
    Armenian rather suggests the reading <hi rend="italic">dallyan</hi> “He
    rescued us”); no. 5 (“From the eleventh
    Mêmrâ”) = XI,141-144 and 147-150; no. 157
    (“From the Mêmrâ on Nicomedia”) =
    I,9-12; no. 158 (without title) = X,369-382. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef21">21</ref> For a first presentation and edition of the
    fragments attributed to Eusebius, see É. M. Buytaert,
    <hi rend="italic">L’héritage littéraire
    d’Eusèbe d’Émèse. Étude
    critique et historique. Textes.</hi> Bibliothèque du
    Muséon 24 (Louvain, 1949), 30-31, 31*-37* (Syriac text),
    69*-74* (Latin translation). For a general survey of
    Eusebius’ theology, based on the homilies preserved in
    Latin as well as on Syriac fragments of the Philoxenian
    Florilegium, see M.F. Wiles, “The Theology of Eusebius of
    Emesa,” in <hi rend="italic">Papers Presented to the Tenth
    International Conference on Patristic Studies Held in Oxford
    1987</hi>, E.A. Livingstone, ed.. Studia Patristica 19
    (Louvain: Peeters, 1989), 267-280. <ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef22">22</ref> R.W. Thomson, <hi rend="italic">Athanasiana Syriaca</hi>,
    I,1. <hi rend="italic">De Incarnatione</hi>, 2. <hi rend="italic">Epistula ad
    Epictetum</hi>. CSCO 257-258 / Syr. 114-115 (Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1965). <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef23">23</ref> Ed. Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem
    des Syrers Paschahymnen (De Azymis, De Crucifixione, De
    Resurrectione).</hi> CSCO 248-249 / Syr. 108-109 (Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1964), 79,16-17 (text) and
    74,1-2 (German translation). <ref target="#FNRef23">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef24">24</ref> Ed. André de Halleux<hi rend="italic">,
    Philoxène de Mabbog. Commentaire du prologue johannique
    (Ms. Brit. Mus. Add. 14,534)</hi>. CSCO, 380-381 / Syr. 165-166
    (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1977), 53,24-29
    (text); 53,10-15 (French translation). See also Sebastian
    Brock, “Clothing Metaphors as a Means of Theological
    Expression in Syriac Tradition,” in <hi rend="italic">Typus, Symbol,
    Allegorie bei den östlichen Vätern und ihren
    Parallelen im Mittelalter</hi>, Margot Schmidt, ed..,
    Eichstätter Beiträge 4 (Regensburg, 1982), 15-18.
    <ref target="#FNRef24">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef25">25</ref> Ed. and French translation: André de
    Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène de Mabbog. Lettre aux moines de
    Senoun.</hi> CSCO 231-232 / Syr. 98-99 (Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1963). <ref target="#FNRef25">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef26">26</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 10,23-11,19. <ref target="#FNRef26">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef27">27</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 32,23-26. <ref target="#FNRef27">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef28">28</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 33,3-5 = ed. Graffin,
    120[120], no. 220. The wording is slightly different. <ref target="#FNRef28">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef29">29</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 35,24-25. <ref target="#FNRef29">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef30">30</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 35,25-27 and 35,27-36,1 =
    ed. Graffin, 108[108], nos. 160 and 161. The demarcation of the
    quotations is different so that, even though the wording of the
    overlapping parts is identical, the later quotations cannot
    simply have been taken from the earlier work. <ref target="#FNRef30">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef31">31</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 36,1-3. <ref target="#FNRef31">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef32">32</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 47,3-6. Compare 45,6-8.
    <ref target="#FNRef32">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef33">33</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 49,7-14. <ref target="#FNRef33">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef34">34</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">On the Nativity</hi>, 8,2. Ed. and
    German translation: Edmund Beck, <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des
    Syrers Hymnen De Nativitae (Epiphania)</hi>. CSCO 186-187 /
    Syr. 82-83 (Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1959), 59
    (text) and 51 (translation). My translation of the Ephrem
    quotation is taken from Kathleen McVey, <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the Syrian.
    Hymns</hi>. The Classics of Western Spirituality (New York
    &amp; Mahwah: Paulist Press, 1989), 119; only at the end I have
    translated “and the image became God-man” (McVey:
    “and an image came into being: the God-man”),
    because I think this translation is more in line with how
    Philoxenus interpreted the verse. <ref target="#FNRef34">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef35">35</ref> Cf. De Halleux, <hi rend="italic">Philoxène</hi>
    [1963], 324, note 30. <ref target="#FNRef35">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef36">36</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 51,6-24. <ref target="#FNRef36">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef37">37</ref> In the <hi rend="italic">Mêmrê against
    Habbib</hi> Philoxenus already discussed the problematic
    Christological use of the term “mixture”
    (<hi rend="italic">muzzâgâ</hi>), which according to him was
    found “in all the writings of our Fathers, both in the
    Aramaic and in the Greek (writings), except in (the writings
    of) a few who were prevented (from using it) by their
    conscience or if there are those others who childishly
    refrained from (using) it, in order not to give an opportunity
    (read <hi rend="italic">ma<hi rend="sup">cc</hi>lânutâ</hi> instead of
    <hi rend="italic">m<hi rend="sup">c</hi>allyutâ</hi>?) to the heretics.”
    Here Philoxenus argues that the term is acceptable, because
    mixture may occur without alteration (e.g. the word mingled
    with the voice): ed. Brière &amp; Graffin, III,
    690[150]-698[158]. <ref target="#FNRef37">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef38">38</ref> For these Syriac neologisms created by, or
    at the instigation of, Philoxenus himself, see A. de Halleux,
    “La philoxénienne du symbole,” in
    <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum</hi> 1976. Orientalia Christiana
    Analecta 205 (Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium Studiorum,
    1978), 295-315. <ref target="#FNRef38">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef39">39</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 53,17-22. <ref target="#FNRef39">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef40">40</ref> Ed. De Halleux, 54,23-55,11. <ref target="#FNRef40">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef41">41</ref> Among fifth- and sixth-century writers the
    criticism of imprecise language and terminology in the earlier
    theologians is not unique. Here, however, this criticism is
    coupled to the distinction Greek-Syriac. <ref target="#FNRef41">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef42">42</ref> Ed. Joseph Amar, <hi rend="italic">A Metrical Homily on
    Holy Mar Ephrem by Mar Jacob of Serugh</hi>. Patrologia
    Orientalis 47,1 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1995). The phrases quoted
    are on p. 24 (3) and 64 (155). In modern scholarship
    Jacob’s Christology is generally seen as closer to Ephrem
    than Philoxenus’ Christology is, and above all as more
    irenic. See Tanios Bou Mansour, “Die Christologie des
    Jakob von Sarug” and “Die Christologie des
    Philoxenus von Mabbug,” in <hi rend="italic">Jesus der Christus im
    Glauben der Kirche</hi>, 2/3, 449-569 – esp. 567:
    “Die Theologie des Philoxenus löst sich noch mehr
    als die des Jakob von Sarug von der syrischen Tradition mit
    ihrem Höhepunkt in Ephraem …”; Theresia
    Hainthaler, “Rückblick und Ausblick,”
    <hi rend="italic">ibidem</hi>, 654-659. <ref target="#FNRef42">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef43">43</ref> For Severus and Ephrem, see already Graffin,
    “Le florilège,” 279-280. <ref target="#FNRef43">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef44">44</ref> Ed. Iosephus Lebon, <hi rend="italic">Severi Antiocheni
    Liber contra impium Grammaticum. Orationis tertiae pars
    posterior</hi>. CSCO 101-102 / Syr. 50-51 (Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO 1952), 243,14-26 (text);
    179,11-21 (Latin translation). See also Marcel Richard,
    <hi rend="italic">Iohannis Caesariensis Presbyteri et Grammatici Opera quae
    supersunt</hi>. Corpus Christianorum, Series Graeca 1
    (Turnhout: Brepols &amp; Louvain: University Press, 1977),
    43-44 (no. 109). The work in question, attributed to Ephrem,
    from which John the Grammarian had quoted, appears to exist in
    Greek, see Mauritius Geerard, <hi rend="italic">Clavis Patrum Graecorum</hi>,
    II (Turnhout: Brepols, 1974), no. 3949, and André de
    Halleux, “Saint Éphrem le Syrien,” <hi rend="italic">Revue
    théologique de Louvain</hi> 14 (1983), 339. <ref target="#FNRef44">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef45">45</ref> Ed. Lebon, 243,27-244,7 (text); 179,22-29
    (Latin translation). <ref target="#FNRef45">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef46">46</ref> Ed. Lebon, 244,21-22 (text); 180,8-9 (Latin
    translation). <ref target="#FNRef46">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef47">47</ref> Ed. Lebon, 244,23-28 (text); 180,9-13 (Latin
    translation). See Lucas Van Rompay, “L’informateur
    syrien de Basile de Césarée. À propos de
    Genèse 1,2,” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana
    Periodica</hi> 58 (1992), 245-251. <ref target="#FNRef47">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef48">48</ref> Ed. and Latin translation: E.W. Brooks,
    <hi rend="italic">Vitae virorum apud Monophysitas celeberrimorum</hi>, I.
    CSCO, 7-8 / Syr. 7-8 (Paris, 1907), 29-95 (text); 21-60
    (translation). <ref target="#FNRef48">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef49">49</ref> W. Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac
    Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year
    1838</hi>, II (London, 1871), 639-649. <ref target="#FNRef49">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef50">50</ref> Some examples of 7th-8th-century manuscripts
    containing Florilegia which include Ephrem are: Brit. Libr.
    Add. 17,214 (Wright, <hi rend="italic">Catalogue</hi>, II, 915-917), Add.
    14,529 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 917-921), Add. 12,155 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
    921-955), and 14,532 (955-967). For the importance of these
    Florilegia for the study of the transmission of Ephrem’s
    works, see Brock, “The Transmission,” 494, note 12.
    <ref target="#FNRef50">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef51">51</ref> The list of authorities represented in these
    Florilegia, comes very close to what Jacob of Edessa, at the
    end of the seventh and the beginning of the eighth century, saw
    as the assembly of orthodox teachers. See Lucas Van Rompay,
    “Past and Present Perceptions of Syriac Literary
    Tradition,” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</hi>
    3/1 (January 2000), par. 11-23. <ref target="#FNRef51">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV7N1VanRompay7">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Abramowski, Luise. “Aus dem
    Streit um das „Unus ex trinitate passus“: Der
    Protest des Habib gegen die Epistula dogmatica des Philoxenus
    an die Mönche.” In <hi rend="italic">Jesus der Christus im Glauben
    der Kirche.</hi> Band 2/3. <hi rend="italic">Die Kirchen von Jerusalem und
    Antiochien nach 451 bis 600</hi>, Theresia Hainthaler, ed.
    Freiburg i.B.: Herder, 2002. 570-647.</p>
         <p>Amar, Joseph. <hi rend="italic">A Metrical Homily
    on Holy Mar Ephrem by Mar Jacob of Serugh</hi>. Patrologia
    Orientalis 47,1. Turnhout: Brepols, 1995.</p>
         <p>Beck, Edmund. <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen
    Ephraem des Syrers Hymnen De Nativitae (Epiphania)</hi>. CSCO
    186-187 / Syr. 82-83. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO,
    1959.</p>
         <p>— “Philoxenos und
    Ephräm.” <hi rend="italic">Oriens Christianus</hi> 46 (1962):
    61-76.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Des Heiligen Ephraem des
    Syrers Paschahymnen (De Azymis, De Crucifixione, De
    Resurrectione).</hi> CSCO 248-249 / Syr. 108-109. Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1964.</p>
         <p>Bou Manour, Tanios. “Die
    Christologie des Jakob von Sarug” and “Die
    Christologie des Philoxenus von Mabbug.” In <hi rend="italic">Jesus der
    Christus im Glauben der Kirche.</hi> Band 2/3. <hi rend="italic">Die Kirchen
    von Jerusalem und Antiochien nach 451 bis 600</hi>, Theresia
    Hainthaler, ed. Freiburg i.B.: Herder, 2002. 449-569.</p>
         <p>Brière, M. <hi rend="italic">Sancti
    Philoxeni episcopi Mabbugensis dissertationes decem de Uno e
    sancta Trinitate incorporato et passo. Dissertatio
    I<hi rend="sup">a</hi> et II<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis
    15,4. Paris, 1920.</p>
         <p>Brière, M. and F. Graffin,
    <hi rend="italic">Sancti Philoxeni episcopi Mabbugensis dissertationes decem
    de Uno e sancta Trinitate incorporato et passo.</hi> II.
    <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes 3<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 4<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,
    5<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 38,3. Turnhout:
    Brepols, 1977. III. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes 6<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,
    7<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, 8<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 39,4.
    Turnhout: Brepols, 1979. IV. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes 9<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,
    10<hi rend="sup">a</hi>
            </hi>. Patrologia Orientalis 40,2. Turnhout:
    Brepols, 1980. V. <hi rend="italic">Appendices</hi>: I. <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi>;
    II. <hi rend="italic">Refutatio</hi>; III. <hi rend="italic">Epistuladogmatica</hi>; IV.
    <hi rend="italic">Florilegium.</hi> Patrologia Orientalis 41,1. Turnhout:
    Brepols, 1982.</p>
         <p>Brock, Sebastian. “Clothing
    Metaphors as a Means of Theological Expression in Syriac
    Tradition.” In <hi rend="italic">Typus, Symbol, Allegorie bei den
    östlichen Vätern und ihren Parallelen im
    Mittelalter</hi>, Margot Schmidt, ed., Eichstätter
    Beiträge 4. Regensburg, 1982. 11-40.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Saint Ephrem. Hymns on
    Paradise.</hi> Crestwood, New York: St. Vladimir’s
    Seminary Press, 1990.</p>
         <p>— “The Transmission of
    Ephrem’s <hi rend="italic">Madrashe</hi> in the Syriac Liturgical
    Tradition.” In <hi rend="italic">Studia Patristica</hi> 23, Elizabeth
    A. Livingstone, ed., Louvain: Peeters, 1997. 490-505.</p>
         <p>Brooks, E.W. <hi rend="italic">Vitae virorum apud
    Monophysitas celeberrimorum</hi>, I. CSCO, 7-8 / Syr. 7-8.
    Paris, 1907.</p>
         <p>Buytaert, É. M.
    <hi rend="italic">L’héritage littéraire
    d’Eusèbe d’Émèse. Étude
    critique et historique. Textes.</hi> Bibliothèque du
    Muséon 24. Louvain, 1949.</p>
         <p>Chesnut, Roberta C. <hi rend="italic">Three
    Monophysite Christologies. Severus of Antioch, Philoxenus of
    Mabbug, and Jacob of Sarug.</hi> London: Oxford University
    Press, 1976.</p>
         <p>De Halleux, André.
    <hi rend="italic">Philoxène de Mabbog. Sa vie, ses écrits, sa
    théologie.</hi> Louvain: Imprimerie Orientaliste,
    1963.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Philoxène de
    Mabbog. Lettre aux moines de Senoun.</hi> CSCO 231-232 / Syr.
    98-99. Louvain: Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1963.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Philoxène de
    Mabbog. Commentaire du prologue johannique (Ms. Brit. Mus. Add.
    14,534)</hi>. CSCO, 380-381 / Syr. 165-166. Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1977.</p>
         <p>— “La
    philoxénienne du symbole.” In <hi rend="italic">Symposium
    Syriacum</hi> 1976. Orientalia Christiana Analecta 205. Rome:
    Pont. Institutum Orientalium Studiorum, 1978. 295-315.</p>
         <p>— “Saint Éphrem
    le Syrien.” <hi rend="italic">Revue théologique de Louvain</hi>
    14 (1983): 328-355.</p>
         <p>— “Le
    <hi rend="italic">Mamlelâ</hi> de «Habbīb» contre
    Aksenâyâ. Aspects textuels d’une
    polémique christologique dans l’Église
    syriaque de la première génération
    post-chalcédonienne.” In <hi rend="italic">After Chalcedon.
    Studies in Theology and Church History Offered to Professor
    Albert Van Roey for his Seventieth Birthday</hi>, C. Laga, J.A.
    Munitiz, and L. Van Rompay, eds., Orientalia Lovaniensia
    Analecta 18. Louvain: Departement Oriëntalistiek &amp;
    Peeters, 1985. 67-82. </p>
         <p>Geerard, Mauritius. <hi rend="italic">Clavis
    Patrum Graecorum.</hi> II. Turnhout: Brepols, 1974.</p>
         <p>Graffin, François. “Le
    florilège patristique de Philoxène de
    Mabbog.” In <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum 1972.</hi> Orientalia
    Christiana Analecta 197. Rome: Pont. Institutum Orientalium
    Studiorum, 1974. 267-290.</p>
         <p>Hainthaler, Theresia. <hi rend="italic">Jesus der
    Christus im Glauben der Kirche.</hi> Band 2/3. <hi rend="italic">Die Kirchen
    von Jerusalem und Antiochien nach 451 bis 600</hi>. Freiburg
    i.B.: Herder, 2002.</p>
         <p>Lampe, G.W.H.  <hi rend="italic">A Patristic
    Greek Lexicon</hi>, Fourth impression. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
    1976.</p>
         <p>Lamy, Thomas J. <hi rend="italic">Sancti Ephraem
    Syri Hymni et Sermones.</hi> 4 vol. Malines, 1882-1902.</p>
         <p>Lebon, I. <hi rend="italic">Severi Antiocheni
    Liber contra impium Grammaticum. Orationis tertiae pars
    posterior</hi>. CSCO 101-102 / Syr. 50-51. Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1952.</p>
         <p>McVey, Kathleen. <hi rend="italic">Ephrem the
    Syrian. Hymns</hi>. The Classics of Western Spirituality. New
    York &amp; Mahwah: Paulist Press, 1989.</p>
         <p>Renoux, Charles. <hi rend="italic">Éphrem
    de Nisibe. Mēmrē sur Nicomédie.</hi>
    Patrologia Orientalis 37,2-3. Turnhout : Brepols,
    1975.</p>
         <p>Richard, Marcel. “Les
    florilèges diphysites du V<hi rend="sup">e</hi> et du
    VI<hi rend="sup">e</hi> siècle.” In <hi rend="italic">Das Konzil von
    Chalkedon, Geschichte un Gegenwart.</hi> A. Grillmeier and H.
    Bacht, eds. I. Würzburg: Echter-Verlag, 1951. 721-748.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Iohannis Caesariensis
    Presbyteri et Grammatici Opera quae supersunt</hi>. Corpus
    Christianorum, Series Graeca 1. Turnhout: Brepols &amp;
    Louvain: University Press, 1977).</p>
         <p>Samuel, V.C. <hi rend="italic">The Council of
    Chalcedon Re-examined.</hi> Indian Theological Library 8.
    Madras, 1977.</p>
         <p>Thomson, R.W. <hi rend="italic">Athanasiana
    Syriaca.</hi> I,1. <hi rend="italic">De Incarnatione</hi>, 2. <hi rend="italic">Epistula ad
    Epictetum</hi>. CSCO 257-258 / Syr. 114-115. Louvain:
    Secrétariat du CorpusSCO, 1965.</p>
         <p>Van Rompay, Lucas.
    “L’informateur syrien de Basile de
    Césarée. À propos de Genèse
    1,2.” <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Periodica</hi> 58 (1992):
    245-251.</p>
         <p>— “Past and Present
    Perceptions of Syriac Literary Tradition.” <hi rend="italic">Hugoye:
    Journal of Syriac Studies</hi> 3/1 (January 2000) [ <ref target="http://syrcom.cua.edu/Hugoye/">http://www.bethmardutho.org/Hugoye/</ref>
    ].</p>
         <p>Wiles, M.F. “The Theology of
    Eusebius of Emesa.” In <hi rend="italic">Papers Presented to the Tenth
    International Conference on Patristic Studies Held in Oxford
    1987</hi>, E.A. Livingstone, ed. Studia Patristica 19. Louvain:
    Peeters, 1989. 267-280.</p>
         <p>Wright, W. <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Syriac
    Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year
    1838.</hi> II. London, 1871.</p>
         <!-- #EndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>