<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Digitization of Syriac Books and Other Holdings at The Catholic University of America</title>
            <author>
               <name>Monica J. Blanchard</name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.org/Vol8No1</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Monica J. Blanchard</author>
                  <title level="a">Digitization of Syriac Books and Other Holdings at The Catholic University of America</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-26-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P1"/>[1] This
    past year The Catholic University of America Libraries, in
    cooperation with Beth Mardutho/The Syriac Institute and Brigham
    Young University's Institute for the Study and Preservation of
    Ancient Religious Texts (ISPART), digitized some of the Syriac
    materials (books, manuscripts, maps, photographs, and other
    documents) at CUA. This was part of Beth Mardutho's larger
    venture to establish an Internet digital library of e-books for
    Syriac studies: eBeth Arké: the Syriac Digital Library. It also
    was part of a related venture for a Web-based Eastern Christian
    Reference Library by Brigham Young University.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P2"/>[2] Between
    March and August 2004 the CUA team scanned 669 Syriac
    materials, for a total of 85,389 images, including 53,745 tiff
    images in black &amp; white, greyscale, and color, as well as
    31,644 color jpeg images. Scanned materials include 17th-early
    20th century liturgical, theological, historical, and
    hagiographical works, as well as grammars and dictionaries.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P3"/>[3] The
    groundwork for the CUA Syriac digital project began in June 20,
    2001 when representatives of CUA, BYU, and Beth Mardutho met to
    discuss digital library initiatives. I was asked to serve as
    the local CUA project manager. There were two initial stumbling
    blocks. The university's Syriac collections are extensive, but
    they are largely uncataloged and not easily accessible. Also,
    Mullen Library, which houses the Syriac collections, was
    scheduled for a major building renovation. Project office space
    was not available.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P4"/>[4] The
    first task of the CUA Syriac Digital Project was to make a
    bibliographic survey of the Syriac collections. Fr. Matthew
    Streett, a doctoral candidate in Biblical Studies at CUA, was
    appointed Project Bibliographer. He compiled a 400 page online
    bibliography of Syriac materials in the Semitics/ICOR library
    (035 Mullen), the main repository for CUA's Syriac holdings.
    This bibliography became an important selection tool and
    finding aid.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P5"/>[5] In
    January 2004 space suddenly became available in Mullen Library.
    Beth Mardutho and BYU rearranged their scanning priorities to
    take advantage of a five month window of opportunity
    (March-August, 2004) for the Syriac Digital Project. The first
    Beth Mardutho imaging workstation began operation at CUA on
    March 6, followed on March 22 by the BYU imaging workstation,
    and on April 24 by a second Beth Mardutho imaging workstation.
    The Project shut down on August 15, when renovation work
    resumed in the building.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P6"/>[6] Beth
    Mardutho and BYU provided the equipment, the initial training,
    and the funds for staff hired at CUA. CUA provided local
    project management, office space, and the Syriac resources.</p>
         <p rend="n">
            <anchor xml:id="P7"/>[7] A staff
    of 15 technicians was assembled from the CUA Libraries, the
    School of Library and Information Science, and from graduate
    academic departments and programs with an interest in Syriac
    (Semitics, Early Christian Studies, Biblical Studies, Medieval
    and Byzantine Studies. Volunteers from the Syriac Church
    communities also helped. Technicians with Syriac and Arabic
    language skills entered metadata information in Arabic and
    Syriac into the Beth Mardutho metadata database; they also
    dealt with pagination and bibliographic issues in these
    languages. Technicians with library skills worked with fragile
    and valuable materials requiring special handling. All the
    student technicians had good computer skills and an eye for
    detail—these proved to be the most important job assets. Two of
    the technicians, Jonathan Loopstra (for Beth Mardutho) and
    Diana Jill Kirby (for BYU), served as quality assurance heads.
    Both had previous quality assurance experience. The CUA team
    established work flow patterns and scanning procedures for the
    project. The team also prepared basic operations manuals which
    may be helpful for other institutions participating in eBeth
    Arké.</p>
         <p rend="n"> </p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
