<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Jacob of Edessa's version of Exodus 1 and 28†</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Alison</forename>
                  <surname>Salvesen</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2005</date>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv8n1salvesen</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Alison Salvesen</author>
                  <title level="a">Jacob of Edessa's version of Exodus 1 and 28†</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Jacob of Edessa</term>
               <term>Bible</term>
               <term>Peshitta</term>
               <term>Syrohexapla</term>
               <term>Pentateuch</term>
               <term>Exodus</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>At the end of the seventh century and into
    the beginning of the eighth, the Syriac Orthodox scholar Jacob
    of Edessa produced his own Syriac version of the Old Testament.
    According to the colophons of the extant manuscripts, this was
    explicitly a combination of the Syriac and Greek textual
    traditions. This is in fact borne out by a close study of
    Jacob's versions of Samuel, Genesis and Exodus. However, it is
    less obvious what criteria Jacob used for the inclusion or
    exclusion of the different strands available to him, including
    the Peshitta, the Syrohexapla, and different recensions of the
    Septuagint. This paper examines two very different passages in
    the book of Exodus from the unpublished manuscript of Jacob's
    version of the Pentateuch.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>



         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->


         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] By the
    end of the seventh century the Greek tradition of Scripture was
    well known among the Syriac churches, and in the West, it was
    particularly influential. The "separated" gospels in the Old
    Syriac and Peshitta forms had of course first been translated
    from Greek. The Philoxenian and Harklean versions of the New
    Testament were revisions of the Syriac to reflect the Greek
    original text more closely. In contrast, the Peshitta Old
    Testament had been translated from Hebrew (and Aramaic), but
    the loss of the knowledge of Hebrew in the Syriac Church
    coupled with the dominance of the LXX in the Greek-speaking
    world, meant that revisions of the Old Testament were made
    towards the Greek, not the Hebrew. Thus there may be traces of
    a Philoxenian version of the Old Testament,<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> but much more
    importantly there is the Syrohexapla, translated in 615-17 by
    Paul of Tella at the Ennaton in Egypt, from Origen's revised
    text of the LXX in the Hexapla.<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> The Syrohexapla attained real
    importance in the Syriac churches, and readings from it were
    cited even in the Church of the East by the commentators of the
    eight and ninth centuries, such as Isho'dad of Merv.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Driving
    this production of Syriac scriptural versions reflecting the
    Greek texts was the great influence of Greek Christianity in
    the spheres of politics, theology and general culture.This
    influence also resulted in an enormous number of translations
    of commentaries and exegetical works from Greek into
    Syriac.<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> The obvious problem withbible commentaries
    translated from Greek was the type of biblical text they cited:
    adjusting the citations to the Peshitta form, as the first
    translations did, often meant that they did not match the
    author's exegesis which was based on the LXX text. Reproducing
    in Syriac the LXX form of the original Greek commentary meant
    presenting the reader with a bible quotation to which they were
    unaccustomed, and thus the interpretation would be less
    convincing.<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> However, the increasing use of Scripture
    revisions towards the Greek by such versions as the Philoxenian
    and Syrohexapla no doubt made Syriac readers more familiar with
    the Greek tradition of Scripture, and to some degree they must
    have accepted certain Greek readings alongside those of the
    Peshitta.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    Nevertheless, there is also evidence that Greek aroused mixed
    feelings among Syrians loyal to their native traditions and
    bible versions. Notably, although the monks of Eusebona had
    fetched Jacob of Edessa from Kaisum in order to revive the
    teaching of Greek Scripture, he was attacked by some of the
    brothers who hated "the Greeks", and this is how he ended up at
    Tel 'Ada, where he produced his revision of the Old
    Testament.<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> Given this hostility in certain quarters, and
    the existence of the Philoxenian and Syrohexapla versions, why
    did Jacob want to produce yet another version of the Old
    Testament that, according to some colophons was revised
    according to the Syriac and Greek traditions? For instance, the
    colophon at the end of 1 Samuel<ref target="#FN8">8</ref> says that the First Book of
    Kingdoms was "corrected from the different traditions, namely
    from that of the Syrians and those of the Greeks." Since it is
    in the singular, the tradition of the Syrians can only refer to
    the Peshitta and not the Syrohexapla, which may even be
    included among "those of the Greeks," perhaps alongside the
    Lucianic recension whose influence is clear in Jacob's version
    of Samuel.<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> However, the wording of the colophon at the end
    of Numbers differs slightly: "It was corrected from the two
    traditions, from that of the Syrians and from that [note the
    singular] of the Greeks."<ref target="#FN10">10</ref> Perhaps the Syrohexapla and the
    LXX texts were regarded as co-terminous in this case, or
    perhaps the writer was being imprecise. The date and place of
    the version given by each manuscript is the same, 1016 AG, i.e.
    705 CE, in the monastery of Tel 'Ada.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Though
    small portions of the surviving manuscripts of Jacob's biblical
    version were already being reproduced and studied more than two
    centuries ago,<ref target="#FN11">11</ref> there is much work still to be done. At
    present the most work has been done on Jacob's version of
    Samuel, for which there is a detailed study and also an edition
    of the text.<ref target="#FN12">12</ref> A particular desideratum would be a complete
    edition of Jacob's version of the Pentateuch. This is preserved
    in a single manuscript, Bibliothèque Nationale Paris 26.
    Until someone is able to take on such a large project, it may
    be legitimate to take soundings of the individual
    books.<ref target="#FN13">13</ref> Jacob's version of Genesis has already
    received a limited amount of attention, but the rest of Jacob's
    Pentateuch has been largely passed over.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    biblical book of Exodus includes quite disparate material,
    covering narrative, legal prescriptions, and the description of
    the Tabernacle. I have chosen two different passages for
    analysis. The first example, taken from the story of the
    bondage of the Israelites in chapter 1, is illustrative of
    Jacob's general approach elsewhere (it can hardly be termed a
    method).</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Salvesen2">Exod 1.8 -21 (folios 108 col. a-109 col. a)</head>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV8N1Salvesen_01.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="670px" height="918px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6]
    <hi rend="italic">Italics</hi> indicate the use of identical Syriac wording
    to that in the Syrohexapla; <hi rend="bold">bold</hi> font
    indicates material that has been translated directly from LXX.
    Plain type indicates close proximity to the Peshitta text.</p>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>But a new king arose over Egypt, who did not know
      Joseph.</item>
            <item>He said to his people, "Look, the people of the children
      of Israel are more numerous and stronger than us."</item>
            <item>"<hi rend="italic">Come, therefore</hi>, let us act wisely towards
      them, <hi rend="italic">lest they increase, and whenever</hi> war befalls
      us they also be joined to our enemies, <hi rend="italic">and when they make
      war on us they leave our land</hi>."<ref target="#FN14">14</ref>
            </item>
            <item>They appointed evil ruling <hi rend="italic">officers</hi> over them,
      to enslave and <hi rend="italic">humiliate</hi> them <hi rend="italic">with works</hi>
      and <hi rend="bold">treat them badly</hi> (=LXX ίνα
      κακώσώσιν).
      They built <hi rend="italic">fortified cities</hi> for Pharaoh, Pithom,
      Ra'amsis <hi rend="italic">and On, which is</hi> 
               <hi rend="bold">Beth
      Shemesh</hi> (=LXX ήλίου
      πόλις).<ref target="#FN15">15</ref>
            </item>
            <item>As much as they enslaved and <hi rend="italic">humbled</hi> them, thus
      <hi rend="italic">they grew stronger</hi>, <hi rend="italic">and to such a degree they
      were increasing</hi> that <hi rend="italic">the Egyptians</hi> wearied of
      the children of Israel.</item>
            <item>The Egyptians were <hi rend="italic">oppressing</hi> and enslaving the
      children of Israel with cruelty.<ref target="#FN16">16</ref>
            </item>
            <item>They <hi rend="bold">embittered</hi> (= LXX
      κατωδύνων) their
      lives with hard labour, with clay and with bricks and with
      all types of agricultural work, with every slavery with which
      they enslaved them <hi rend="bold">by force</hi> (= LXX
      μετά βίας).</item>
            <item>The king of Egypt said to the midwives of the Hebrews,
      <hi rend="bold">of whom the name of one was Zephora</hi> (= LXX
      <graphic url="HV8N1Salvesen_04.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="244px" height="20px"/>)
      and the name of the other was Pu'a,<ref target="#FN17">17</ref>
            </item>
            <item>He said to them, "<hi rend="italic">Whenever</hi> you are assisting the
      Hebrew women to give birth, you see when they kneel <hi rend="italic">to
      give birth</hi>, and if it is a male, kill him, and if it is
      a female, preserve her."</item>
            <item>The midwives feared God, and they did not do as the king
      of the Egyptians commanded them. They saved the
      <hi rend="italic">males</hi>.</item>
            <item>The king summoned the midwives and said to them, "Why
      have you done this <hi rend="italic">deed</hi> and kept alive the
      <hi rend="italic">male</hi> children?"</item>
            <item>The midwives said to Pharaoh, "Not as the Egyptian women
      are the Hebrew women, because they are lively.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref> Before the
      midwives <hi rend="italic">come in</hi> to them, they give birth."</item>
            <item>God treated the midwives well because they did this
      <hi rend="italic">deed</hi>, and the people increased and grew very strong
      indeed.</item>
            <item>It happened that since the midwives feared God, he made
      houses for them/they made houses for themselves.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Compared
    with the situation in other passages in Jacob's versions of
    Samuel, Genesis and Exodus, much of the additional material
    Jacob uses seems to be from the Syrohexapla rather than
    translated directly from LXX as is often the case elsewhere,
    for instance in Samuel.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref> Jacob has effectively expanded
    the story recounted in the Peshitta, while preserving the
    Peshitta's wordplay on 'midwives', 'keeping alive', and
    'lively'. The latter is a feature only partly present in the
    Hebrew and not at all in the LXX and Syh versions (it is
    actually an inner-Aramaic feature found only in the Peshitta
    and Targums). Aside from that, the reason for Jacob's
    alterations to his base text of the Peshitta is not clear His
    approach seems rather casual, in fact, and probably was. In
    this particular passage his aim seems to be to include as much
    information as possible from the two traditions, Greek and
    Syriac, in order to fill out and expand the account. There
    seems to be no more scientific explanation (in the modern
    text-critical sense) for changing this particular passage than
    the one of expanding and including more material in the
    account.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] We might
    have expected Jacob to explain or defend his version somewhere.
    However, nowhere in Jacob's work is there an explicit comment
    from Jacob on what his general criteria are for choosing some
    readings and not others from the Greek, or Syrohexapla, and
    whether they replace or only expand on what the Peshitta
    provides. The colophons mentioned above are too vague in the
    information they provide about his working methods.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] One
    feature of Jacob's version in both Samuel and the Pentateuch is
    the provision of marginal notes that give an alternative
    reading from the other tradition than the one included in his
    main text. There are also several scholia in both manuscripts
    that elucidate specific names or problems in the text. Thus in
    the course of Exodus 28 there is an extensive scholion that
    sheds some light on Jacob's procedure in one particular
    passage. It occurs between verses 30 and 31, and occupies most
    of the top half of a page before the text of the chapter
    resumes. The subject of the scholion is the high priest's
    breastpiece and ephod, and it immediately follows the passage
    in Jacob's version that deals with these very items. The
    purpose of the scholion is to draw attention to the confusion
    that has arisen in the text (i.e. that of the Peshitta)
    concerning the proper terminology for the items called
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> and <hi rend="italic">perisa.</hi> The scholion is positioned
    between Jacob's version of Exod 28.30 and 28.31, at the top of
    folio 164, and occupying over one third of the page. Thus it is
    a prominent and deliberate note that the scribe has written
    before continuing on with the biblical text. Perhaps the
    scholion appeared in the autograph of the manuscript, or
    perhaps it was added from a collection of Jacob's scholia that
    was circulating separately.</p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV8N1Salvesen_02.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="670px" height="834px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] "One
    should know that many have erred not a little over these terms
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> and <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>, being unaware of what a
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> is and what a <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> is. While
    sometimes they call '<hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>' the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> of
    the judgments that is borne on the priest's breast and contains
    the twelve gems, at other times they use the term
    '<hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>' for the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> with which the
    priest covered (<hi rend="italic">kabben</hi>) his shoulders, and in which
    were the two emeralds on both his shoulders at the front, and
    to which was also bound the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> of judgments of the
    twelve gems.</p>
         <p>This <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> is called by the Hebrews an
    <hi rend="italic">ephod</hi>, but by the Greeks 'word of judgments', and in
    Greek is pronounced '<hi rend="italic">logion</hi>'. On it was placed the
    Revelation or Sign, and Truth [i.e.
    δήλωσις and
    άλήθεια], which are
    written 'Light and Perfection' by the Syrians. Therefore, from
    that term pronounced '<hi rend="italic">ephod</hi>' by the Hebrews, the
    Syrians call it sometimes '<hi rend="italic">ephodo</hi> and at other times
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>. In the book of Kingdoms, when David says to
    Abiathar the priest, 'Bring me the <hi rend="italic">ephod</hi> (i.e. the
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>)',<ref target="#FN20">20</ref> the priest had two items to bear, the
    <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> that was attached to
    it, and it is unknown which of them David referred to as
    <hi rend="italic">ephod/pedtho</hi>. For it seems that he called the
    combination of the two an <hi rend="italic">ephod/pedtho</hi>. But here, in
    this book of Exodus, where God commands Moses to make both of
    them, namely the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>, and
    the words of the account of each of them are known, an
    unfortunate and perplexing confusion has been created by this
    term <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> which was set down instead of the term
    <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>, since it [the <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>] is the name
    indicating the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> of judgment, being called
    <hi rend="italic">logion</hi> i.e.'Word', the item on which was placed the
    Sign and Truth.'"</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11]
    Though the scholion is hardly remarkable in itself, Jacob may
    be punning on the Syriac words for "error", "making a mistake"
    and "ephod" (note that he retained the word play in Exodus
    chapter 1). Jacob gives the Hebrew, Greek and correct Syriac
    words for the breast-piece, and the Greek and Syriac words for
    the Urim and Thummim, and refers to the passage in 1 Sam 23.9
    where David asks Abiathar to bring the ephod to him.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] As
    might be expected, Jacob's version of the biblical passage that
    immediately preceded this scholion accords completely with
    Jacob's definition of the correct usage of the terms
    <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">kebinta.</hi> Jacob's version also
    diverges from the confusing terminology of the Peshitta, which
    uses <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> and <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>usoyo</hi>
    for the same item, and he rejects the Syrohexapla's use of
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>.</p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV8N1Salvesen_03.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif" width="670px" height="719px"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13]
    (Underlining indicates material that is unparalleled in
    existing witnesses to the Peshitta, Syrohexapla or LXX, and
    thus is apparently unique to Jacob's version in that particular
    place.)</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Salvesen3">Exod 28.22-30</head>
         <list type="ordered">
            <item>You shall make upon the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>
               <ref target="#FN21">21</ref> paired
      chains, braided work of pure gold.</item>
            <item>You shall make for the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>
               <ref target="#FN22">22</ref> two clasps of
      pure gold and <hi rend="u">you shall bind</hi> the two
      clasps to the two sides of the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>.</item>
            <item>You shall lay the two braids of gold in the two clasps on
      the two sides of the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>.</item>
            <item>and the two ends of the two braids you shall tie to the
      two settings. <hi rend="u">You shall fasten</hi> them on
      the shoulders of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>,<ref target="#FN23">23</ref> opposite its
      face <hi rend="u">in front.</hi>
            </item>
            <item>You shall make two clasps of gold and place them on the
      two sides of the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>, on the edge that is
      opposite the edge of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>, inside.</item>
            <item>You shall make two clasps of gold and place them on the
      two shoulders of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> beneath, squarely [=
      Syh] opposite its face, opposite its seam above the
      girdle<ref target="#FN24">24</ref> of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>.</item>
            <item>He shall attach the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> by its links, to the
      links of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> by a blue thread, to be over
      the girdle of the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>, lest the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>
      move and come apart [= Syh] from the <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>.</item>
            <item>Aaron shall bear the names of the children of Israel in
      the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> of the judgments upon his breast, when he
      enters the place of [= Syh] the sanctuary, as a memorial
      before God continually.</item>
            <item>And you shall place upon the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> of
      judgements the Revelation and the Truth [= Syh]<ref target="#FN25">25</ref> ,
      and they shall be on Aaron's breast whenever he enters the
      place of (= Syh) the sanctuary before the Lord. And Aaron
      shall bear the <hi rend="u">iniquity</hi> of the
      children of Israel on his breast, when he enters before the
      Lord always [= Syh].</item>
         </list>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14]
    Ultimately, while preserving the Peshitta as a base text, Jacob
    uses the Greek LXX as a guide to the items, rendering
    λόγιον as <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> and
    έπωμίς as <hi rend="italic">kebinta.</hi> It
    should be noted that Exod 28.23-28 does not appear in the Old
    Greek (meaning the oldest stratum of the Septuagint) of Exodus,
    since the original Greek form was probably translated from a
    Hebrew Vorlage that was shorter than the one behind the present
    Hebrew Masoretic Text. These particular verses were added to
    the church's LXX by Origen from a later translation, probably
    that of "Theodotion", in order to represent what appeared in
    the current Hebrew text.<ref target="#FN26">26</ref> They appear in the Syrohexapla,
    because it was translated from Origen's LXX text, but there
    they are marked by a series of asterisks in the right hand
    margin to indicate that they had been added in by him.<ref target="#FN27">27</ref> Jacob
    would have understood only that Origen had corrected the LXX
    against the Hebrew text, and that therefore he should include
    those passages. Jacob omits (or never knew) the material that
    appears as vv. 24, 25/(29) in Wevers' edition.<ref target="#FN28">28</ref> These verses
    also appear in Lagarde's text of the Syrohexapla and are marked
    with the obelus, but in the Midyat manuscript of the
    Syrohexapla (SyhT) they occur unmarked He may have left it out
    deliberately because it was obelized by Origen as not being in
    the Hebrew, but this cannot be proved.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] The
    Peshitta, on the other hand, follows MT very closely, but is
    inconsistent with its use of equivalents for Hebrew
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>oshen.</hi> It uses <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi>
    for <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>oshen</hi> in
    vv.22,28<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, 29, 30, but <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">h</hi>usaya</hi> in vv.23<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, 24, 26. It is such
    confusion in the Peshitta that Jacob was primarily setting out
    to correct or adjust in this particular passage, with the help
    of the Greek tradition. We have confirmation of this in the
    scholion appended to this section in ch.28. His aims here are
    therefore in contrast to his procedure in the first passage
    from Exodus chapter 1, where the motive seemed to be solely to
    expand on what the Peshitta provided, using material from the
    Greek directly or via the Syrohexapla.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16]
    Looking at the passage in more detail, Jacob has made several
    minor alterations, such as changing the imperative verbs to the
    second person singular indicative of the Greek and Syrohexapla.
    He has also changed the Hebraistic verbs
    δώσεις and <hi rend="italic">hab</hi>,
    adapted them to the context and replaced them with his own
    words 'bind' and 'tie'. The phrase "And Aaron shall bear the
    <hi rend="italic">iniquity</hi> of the children of Israel on his breast" in
    the last verse is very curious. The use of 'iniquity'
    (<hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>awla</hi>) is unprecedented in the Peshitta,
    Syrohexapla and LXX at this point. All three witnesses have
    'judgment' or 'judgements'. The reading is very clear in the
    manuscript of Jacob's version. Scribal error through
    association with another similar passage has to be ruled out,
    since there is to be no other place in the Bible, in Syriac or
    Greek, that has quite this combination of words—
    especially with <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>awlo</hi>—that could lead
    a scribe to make an unconscious error. One can only conclude
    that it is deliberate, and that Jacob extrapolated the idea of
    iniquity from the idea of judgement. It is not unknown for
    Jacob to add his own glosses to the biblical text, but this is
    probably the most striking instance I have come across in his
    version of Genesis or Exodus.<ref target="#FN29">29</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    Overall, the structure and most of the terminology in these
    verses, apart from that concerning the <hi rend="italic">perisa</hi> and
    <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>, remain recognisably those of the Peshitta. The
    passage reflects more care and attention than Jacob often gives
    to the text of his own version. It is notable that there are
    several, rather briefer, scholia in the manuscript on other
    items in the Tabernacle account such as the hangings of the
    court of the Tabernacle,<ref target="#FN30">30</ref> the order of the gems on the high
    priest's breast piece,<ref target="#FN31">31</ref> the turban,<ref target="#FN32">32</ref> the
    settings,<ref target="#FN33">33</ref> how much 20 oboloi are worth.<ref target="#FN34">34</ref> In Jacob's
    version of Samuel he rewrote 1 Samuel 21 very carefully: this
    passage about David asking for the shewbread from the priest at
    Nob also concerns priestly activity,<ref target="#FN35">35</ref> and it is
    tempting to speculate that Jacob was rather interested in
    vestments and rules for the sanctuary. It should go without
    saying that in his scholia in Exodus Jacob is only concerned
    with the sense of passage and what all these items were: there
    is no attempt to use typology or allegory, and his approach is
    solidly historical and literal.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Salvesen4">Conclusion</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] In
    contrast to the findings of Goshen Gottstein and Baars, who
    believed that Jacob's version was an eclectic combination of
    the Peshitta and Syrohexapla,<ref target="#FN36">36</ref> it is very clear in these
    two passages from, Exodus that whether Jacob was expanding a
    particular passage or correcting details, Jacob's text base was
    certainly the Peshitta. Furthermore, he preferred to add to the
    Peshitta base text rather than make major changes, unless it
    was inadequate or confusing. Importantly, it also appears that
    on the whole he avoided depending too much on the Syrohexapla,
    preferring to make his own renderings of words directly from
    the Greek.<ref target="#FN37">37</ref> Perhaps Jacob thought the kind of text he had
    created would appeal to those who disliked the Syriac style of
    the Syrohexapla and the way in which it completely ignored the
    wording of the Peshitta. Maybe Jacob's version also enabled its
    readers to connect with Greek exegesis without abandoning their
    native Syriac scripture. The result of Jacob's work was or
    create a kind of hybrid that amplified and clarified both the
    Peshitta <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Greek texts of Scripture, and from a
    purely exegetical viewpoint it could even be considered to be
    superior to either tradition on its own.</p>
         <p>_______<lb/>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Salvesen5">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef0">†</ref> An earlier version of this paper was
    presented at the IX Symposium Syriacum in Kaslik, Lebanon,
    September 2004. <ref target="#FNRef0">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> I am grateful to the Peshitta Institute, Leiden,
    for lending me a microfilm of this manuscript,
    Bibliothèque Nationale 26. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> Notably in the margin of the eighth century
    Ambrosian Syro-Hexapla to Isa 9.6 (A.M. Ceriani, <hi rend="italic">Monumenta
    sacra et profana ex codicibus praesertim bibliothecae
    Ambrosianae tom. VII. Codex Syro-hexaplaris Ambrosianus,
    photolithographice editus</hi> (Milan: J.B. Pogliani, 1874),
    folio 176r. For another, anonymous, revision based on the
    Greek, see S.P. Brock, "Mingana Syr. 628: A folio from a
    revision of the Peshitta Song of Songs" (<hi rend="italic">JSS</hi> 40
    [1995]), 39-56. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> See A.G. Salvesen, "Hexaplaric Sources in
    Isho‘dad of Merv", in <hi rend="italic">The Book of Genesis in Jewish
    and Oriental Christian Interpretation</hi>, ed. J. Frishman and
    L. Van Rompay. TEG 5 (Louvain: Peeters, 1997), 229-53. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> See S.P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac
    Tradition</hi>. SEERI Correspondence Course (SCC) on Syrian
    Christian Heritage I (Kottayam, Kerala: SEERI, 1988), 20-23.
    However, perhaps the statement on the version of Jacob of
    Edessa, that Jacob "undertook another translation from Greek,
    but also keeping some elements from the Peshitta" should now be
    nuanced, at least with regard to the versions of Genesis,
    Exodus and Samuel.<ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> On the increasing prestige of Greek learning among
    Syriac-speakers, see S.P. Brock, "Towards a history of Syriac
    translation technique", <hi rend="italic">III Symposium Syriacum</hi>, ed. R.
    Lavenant. OCA 221. (Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum
    Orientalium, 1983), 4-5, and idem, "From Antagonism to
    Assimilation: Syriac Attitudes to Greek Learning" in <hi rend="italic">East
    of Byzantium: Syria and Armenia in the formative period.
    Dumbarton Oaks Symposium 1980</hi>, eds. Nina G. Garsoïan,
    Thomas F. Mathews, and Robert W. Thomson (Washington, D.C.:
    Dumbarton Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies, Trustees for
    Harvard University, 1982) 17-34.<ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> S.P. Brock, "From Antagonism to Assimilation:
    Syriac Attitudes to Greek Learning" in <hi rend="italic">East of Byzantium:
    Syria and Armenia in the formative period. Dumbarton Oaks
    Symposium 1980</hi>, eds. Nina G. Garsoïan, Thomas F.
    Mathews, and Robert W. Thomson (Washington, D.C.: Dumbarton
    Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies, Trustees for Harvard
    University, 1982) 18.<ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">Gregorii Barhebraei Chronicon
    Ecclesiasticum</hi>, ed. J.B. Abbeloos and T.J. Lamy (Louvain:
    Peeters, 1872) I, cols. 291-3.<ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> A.G. Salvesen, <hi rend="italic">The Books of Jacob in the Syriac
    Version of Jacob of Edessa</hi>. MPIL 10 (Leiden: E.J. Brill,
    1999): edition p.90 and translation p.67.<ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> R.J. Saley, <hi rend="italic">The Samuel Manuscript of Jacob of
    Edessa. A Study in Its Underlying Textual Traditions</hi>. MPIL
    9 (Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1998), 19-38.<ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> Bibliothèque Nationale 26, folio
    339.<ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> J.D. Michaelis, <hi rend="italic">Orientalische und
    exegetische Bibliothek</hi> 18 (1782) 180-183 [Gen 49.2-11]; C.
    Bugati, <hi rend="italic">Daniel secundum editionem LXX. interpretum ex
    tetraplis desumptum</hi> (Milan, 1788), xi-xvi, 150-151,
    157-158 [Gen 11.1-9; Gen 49.2-11; Dan 1.1-6; Dan 9.24-27; Sus
    1-6] (reprinted in J.B. Eichhorn, <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine
    Bibliothek</hi> 2 [1789] 270-293); A.M. Ceriani, Monumenta
    sacra et profana II/1 (Milan, 1863), x-xii [Gen 4.8-16; Gen
    5.21- 6.1]; A.M. Ceriani, <hi rend="italic">Monumenta sacra et profana</hi>,
    V/1 (Milan, 1868) 8-12; 21-23; 25-38 [Isa 28.1-21; 45.7-16;
    46.2-49.25]; L'Abbé Martin, "L'Hexaméron de
    Jacques d'Édesse" (<hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique</hi>
    (8ème sér.) 11 [1888] 155-219; 401-90; A. Hjelt,
    <hi rend="italic">Études sur l'Hexaméron de Jacques d'Edesse,
    notamment sur ses notions géographiques contenues dans
    le 3ième traité</hi> (Helsingfors: J.C.
    Frenckell, 1892) [Gen 1.9-10]; M. Ugolini, "Il Ms. Vat. Sir. 5
    e la recensione del V.T. di Giacomo d'Edessa" (<hi rend="italic">OrChr</hi> 2
    [1902]), 412-413 [Ezek 7.1-13]; M.H. Gottstein, "Neue
    Syrohexaplafragmente" (<hi rend="italic">Biblica</hi> 37 [1956]) 162-183 [1
    Sam 7.5-12; 20.1-23, 35-42; 2 Sam 7.1-17; 21.1-7; 23.13-17]; W.
    Baars, "Ein neugefundenes Bruchstück aus der syrischen
    Bibelrevision des Jakob von Edessa" (<hi rend="italic">Vetus Testamentum</hi>
    18 [1968]), 548-554 [Wis 2.12-24].<ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> M.H. Gottstein, "Neue
    Syrohexaplafragmente"(<hi rend="italic">Biblica</hi> 37 [1956]), 175-183,
    R.J. Saley, <hi rend="italic">The Samuel Manuscript of Jacob of Edessa. A
    Study in Its Underlying Textual Traditions</hi>. MPIL 9
    (Leiden:E.J. Brill, 1998), and A.G. Salvesen, <hi rend="italic">The Books of
    Jacob in the Syriac Version of Jacob of Edessa</hi>. MPIL 10
    (Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1999).<ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> Sylvestre de Sacy, "Notice d'un manuscrit
    syriaque, contenant les livres de Moïse", <hi rend="italic">Notices et
    extraits des manuscrits de la Bibliothèque
    Nationale</hi>, vol. IV (Paris 1798-99) 648-668. For a
    description of the manuscript, see the catalogue of H.
    Zotenberg, <hi rend="italic">Manuscrits orientaux. Catalogues des manuscrits
    syriaques et sabéens (mandaïtes) de la
    Bibliothéque Nationale</hi> (Paris 1874) 10. See also
    A.G. Salvesen, "The Genesis Texts of Jacob of Edessa: a Study
    in Variety" [forthcoming]. <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> Margin: "and fight us and go up from the
    land" = Peshitta.<ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Margin: "Heliopolis" = Syh.<ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> Margin: "by force" = Syh. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> The order of names is in accordance with the
    Greek tradition, and also to the Peshitta MS 5b1.<ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> Jacob preserves the wordplay of the
    Peshitta, "midwives", "keep alive" and "lively", which is lost
    in Greek and thus in Syh also.<ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> R.J. Saley, <hi rend="italic">The Samuel Manuscript of
    Jacob of Edessa. A Study in Its Underlying Textual
    Traditions</hi>. MPIL 9 (Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1998), 19-38,
    118-22.<ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> Jacob's own version of this phrase in 1 Sam
    23.9 (as also 23.6) uses the word <hi rend="italic">'ephod</hi>. However, he
    uses <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi> in 1 Sam 22.18 "priests bearing the linen
    ephod", and <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi> to describe the location of
    Goliath's sword, hidden behind the ephod (1 Sam 21.10). At 2
    Sam 6.14 Jacob has <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi>es<hi rend="u">t</hi>la</hi>, perhaps because David was not a priest.
    <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef21">21</ref> The same word appears in the Peshitta of
    this verse. LXX has λόγιον
    and Syh <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>. The underlying Hebrew word is
    <hi rend="italic"><!--<u>-->h<!--</u>-->oshen</hi>, NRSV "breast piece".<ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef22">22</ref> Here and in the next two occurrences in this
    verse the Peshitta uses the term <hi rend="italic"><!--<u>-->h<!--</u>-->usaya</hi>, which
    is most confusing. Jacob, Syh and LXX all maintain their
    equivalents from the previous verse. <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef23">23</ref> The Peshitta uses the term <hi rend="italic">pedtho</hi>
    in each case where Jacob employs Syh's <hi rend="italic">kebinta</hi>, which
    itself follows LXX έπωμίς.
    <ref target="#FNRef23">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef24">24</ref> 
            <hi rend="italic">hemyana</hi>: the word is the same in
    the Peshitta. LXX has
    μηχάνωμα and Syh
    <hi rend="italic">methaqnutha</hi>. The Hebrew word is <hi rend="italic">hesheb</hi>,
    translated as "decorated band" in NRSV.<ref target="#FNRef24">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef25">25</ref> I.e. the Urim and Thummim.<ref target="#FNRef25">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef26">26</ref> J.W. Wevers, <hi rend="italic">Text History of the Greek
    Exodus</hi> MSU XXI (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp;
    Ruprecht, 1992), 9, 125; K. G. O'Connell, <hi rend="italic">The Theodotionic
    Revision of the Book of Exodus: a contribution to the study of
    the early history of the transmission of the Old Testament in
    Greek</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1972);
    cf. also D. Fraenkel, "Die Quellen der asterisierten
    Zusätze im zweiten Tabernakelbericht Exod 35-40," in
    <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Septuaginta- Robert Hanhart zu Ehren aus
    Anlaß seines 65. Geburtstages</hi>. eds. D. Fraenkel,
    U.Quast, and J.W. Wevers. MSU XX (Göttingen: Vandenhoeck
    &amp; Ruprecht, 1990), 140-86. <ref target="#FNRef26">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef27">27</ref> SyhT misplaces the asterisks so that they
    run beside vv.24-29.<ref target="#FNRef27">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef28">28</ref> J.W. Wevers, with U. Quast, <hi rend="italic">Septuaginta.
    Vetus Testamentum Graecum auctoritate Academiae Scientiarum
    Gottingensis editum, II, I. Exodus</hi>.(Göttingen:
    Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 1991), 320.<ref target="#FNRef28">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef29">29</ref> The nearest similar expressions in a
    comparable context occur in Lev 22.16 "they shall bear upon
    them the iniquity and sins", and Num 18.1 "bear the iniquity of
    the sanctuary... bear the iniquity of your priesthood", also
    Ezek 4.5,6 "you shall bear the iniquity of the house of
    Israel". But it is hard to see how these passages could have
    caused an unconscious error in Jacob's version of Exod 28.30.
    Exod 28.38, which occurs close to the passage under discussion,
    has the phrase "Aaron shall bear the sins of the holy things"
    in both the Peshitta and Jacob's version of Exod, but the use
    of "sin-offerings" seems to
    exclude it as a possible influence.<ref target="#FNRef29">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef30">30</ref> At the bottom of folio 161 column a, in the
    middle of Exod 27.16, where the column has been left one line
    short to accommodate it.<ref target="#FNRef30">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef31">31</ref> At the bottom of folio 163 column a, where
    two lines have been left to accommodate it.<ref target="#FNRef31">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef32">32</ref> Towards the bottomof folio 165 column a,
    where the scholion has been inserted into the biblical
    text.<ref target="#FNRef32">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef33">33</ref> On folio 162, added in the bottom
    margin.<ref target="#FNRef33">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef34">34</ref> In the bottom margin of folio 169 column a
    (to Exod 30.13).<ref target="#FNRef34">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef35">35</ref> See A.G. Salvesen, "An edition of Jacob of
    Edessa's version of Samuel" in <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum
    VIIum</hi>, ed. R. Lavenant, S.J., OCA 256 (Rome: Pontificium
    Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1998),13-22.<ref target="#FNRef35">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef36">36</ref> M.H. Gottstein, "Neue Syrohexaplafragmente"
    <hi rend="italic">Biblica</hi> 37 (1956) 162-83, compared some texts in
    Samuel with the Syrohexapla, and in passing with the LXX and
    Peshitta. W. Baars, "Ein neugefundenes Bruchstück aus der
    syrischen Bibelrevision des Jakob von Edessa" <hi rend="italic">VT</hi> 56
    (1968) 548-554, compared the fragments of Jacob in Wisd with
    the Syrohexapla and the Peshitta. <ref target="#FNRef36">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef37">37</ref> Note that these findings are in line with
    those of S.P. Brock, <hi rend="italic">The Recensions of the Septuaginta
    Version of I Samuel</hi>. Quaderni di Henoch 9 (Turin: Silvio
    Zamorani, 1996), 26-27.<ref target="#FNRef37">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Salvesen6">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Abbeloos, J.B. and T.J. Lamy (eds.)
    <hi rend="italic">Gregorii Barhebraei Chronicon Ecclesiasticum</hi>. Tom. I.
    Louvain: Peeters, 1872.</p>
         <p>Baars, W. "Ein neugefundenes
    Bruchstück aus der syrischen Bibelrevision des Jakob von
    Edessa." <hi rend="italic">Vetus Testamentum</hi> 18 (1968): 548-54.</p>
         <p>Brock, S.P. "From Antagonism to
    Assimilation: Syriac Attitudes to Greek Learning." In <hi rend="italic">East
    of Byzantium: Syria and Armenia in the formative period.
    Dumbarton Oaks Symposium 1980</hi>, ed. Nina G. Garsoïan,
    Thomas F. Mathews, and Robert W. Thomson. Washington, D.C.:
    Dumbarton Oaks Center for Byzantine Studies, Trustees for
    Harvard University, 1982. 17-34.</p>
         <p>— "Towards a history of Syriac
    translation technique", <hi rend="italic">III Symposium Syriacum</hi>, ed. R.
    Lavenant. OCA 221. Rome: Pontificium Institutum Studiorum
    Orientalium, 1983. 1-14.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">The Bible in the Syriac
    Tradition</hi>. SEERI Correspondence Course (SCC) on Syrian
    Christian Heritage I. Kottayam, Kerala: SEERI, 1989.</p>
         <p>— "Mingana Syr. 628: A folio
    from a revision of the Peshitta Song of Songs." <hi rend="italic">JSS</hi> 40
    (1995): 39-56.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">The Recensions of the
    Septuaginta Version of I Samuel</hi>. Quaderni di Henoch 9.
    Turin: Silvio Zamorani, 1996.</p>
         <p>Bugati, C. <hi rend="italic">Daniel secundum
    editionem LXX. interpretum ex tetraplis desumptum</hi>. Milan:
    1788.</p>
         <p>Ceriani, A.M. <hi rend="italic">Monumenta sacra et
    profana</hi>, II/1. Milan: 1863.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Monumenta sacra et
    profana</hi>, V/1. Milan: 1868.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">Monumenta sacra et
    profana ex codicibus praesertim bibliothecae Ambrosianae</hi>
    tom. VII. Codex Syro-hexaplaris Ambrosianus, photolithographice
    editus. Milan: J.B. Pogliani, 1874.</p>
         <p>Eichhorn, J.B. <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine
    Bibliothek</hi> 2 (1789): 270-293.</p>
         <p>Fraenkel, D. "Die Quellen der
    asterisierten Zusätze im zweiten Tabernakelbericht Exod
    35-40," in <hi rend="italic">Studien zur Septuaginta-Robert Hanhart zu Ehren
    aus Anlaß seines 65. Geburtstages.</hi> eds. D. Fraenkel,
    U.Quast, and J.W. Wevers. MSU XX. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck
    &amp; Ruprecht, 1990. 140-86.</p>
         <p>Gottstein, M.H. "Neue
    Syrohexaplafragmente." <hi rend="italic">Biblica</hi> 37 (1956): 162-183.</p>
         <p>Hjelt, A. <hi rend="italic">Études sur
    l'Hexaméron de Jacques d'Edesse, notamment sur ses
    notions géographiques contenues dans le 3ième
    traité</hi>. Helsingfors: J.C. Frenckell, 1892.</p>
         <p>L'Abbé Martin,
    "L'Hexaméron de Jacques d'Édesse." <hi rend="italic">Journal
    Asiatique</hi>, 8ème sér., 11 (1888): 155-219;
    401-90.</p>
         <p>Michaelis, J.D. <hi rend="italic">Orientalische
    und exegetische Bibliothek</hi> 18 (1782): 180-183.</p>
         <p>O'Connell, K. G. <hi rend="italic">The
    Theodotionic Revision of the Book of Exodus : a contribution to
    the study of the early history of the transmission of the Old
    Testament in Greek.</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University
    Press, 1972.</p>
         <p>de Sacy, S. "Notice d'un Manuscrit
    syriaque, contenant les livres de Moïse." <hi rend="italic">Notices et
    extraits des manuscrits de la Bibliothèque
    Nationale</hi> IV (1798-99): 648-668.</p>
         <p>Saley, R.J. <hi rend="italic">The Samuel
    Manuscript of Jacob of Edessa. A Study in Its Underlying
    Textual Traditions</hi>. MPIL 9. Leiden: E.J. Brill, 1998.</p>
         <p>Salvesen, A.G. "Hexaplaric Sources
    in Isho'dad of Merv", in <hi rend="italic">The Book of Genesis in Jewish and
    Oriental Christian Interpretation</hi>, ed. J. Frishman and L.
    Van Rompay. TEG 5. Louvain: Peeters, 1997. 229-53.</p>
         <p>— "An edition of Jacob of
    Edessa's version of Samuel" in <hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum
    VIIum,</hi> ed. R. Lavenant, S.J., OCA 256. Rome: Pontificium
    Institutum Studiorum Orientalium, 1998. 13-22.</p>
         <p>— <hi rend="italic">The Books of Jacob in
    the Syriac Version of Jacob of Edessa.</hi> MPIL 10. Leiden:
    E.J. Brill, 1999.</p>
         <p>— "The Genesis Texts of Jacob
    of Edessa: a Study in Variety", forthcoming.</p>
         <p>Ugolini, M. "Il Ms. Vat. Sir. 5 e la
    recensione del V.T. di Giacomo d'Edessa." <hi rend="italic">OrChr</hi> 2
    (1902): 412-413.</p>
         <p>Wevers, J.W. <hi rend="italic">Text History of the
    Greek Exodus</hi> MSU XXI. Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp;
    Ruprecht, 1992.</p>
         <p>Wevers, J.W., with U. Quast,
    <hi rend="italic">Septuaginta. Vetus Testamentum Graecum auctoritate
    Academiae Scientiarum Gottingensis editum. Exodus</hi>.
    Göttingen: Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, 1991.</p>
         <p>Zotenberg, H. <hi rend="italic">Manuscrits
    orientaux. Catalogues des manscrits syriaques et sabéens
    (mandaïtes) de la Bibliothéque Nationale</hi>.
    Paris, 1874.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>