<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Dorushe Conference on Syriac Pedagogy at The Catholic University of America</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>February</forename>
                  <surname>2006</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/callForPapers/hv8n2fcdorushesyrconf</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>February 3-5, 2006</author>
                  <title level="a">Dorushe Conference on Syriac Pedagogy at The Catholic University of America</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Conference</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    Center for the Study of Early Christianity and the Semitics
    Department of the Catholic University of America in cooperation
    with the Dorushe graduate student association invite proposals
    for the 2006 Dorushe Syriac Studies Conference.  This
    year's conference will be held at the CUA campus in Washington,
    D.C., February 3-5, 2006. While all are welcome to give papers,
    the conference is especially designed to aid graduate students
    interested in integrating the field of Syriac studies with
    other academic disciplines for a teaching
    career. Proposals on any Syriac related topic are welcome,
    but discussion periods will especially focus on pedagogical
    aspects (how to incorporate our Syriac research into the
    classroom for a broader audience.) Papers will be
    pre-circulated to attendees and summarized at the conference.
    In addition, a list of resources to aid in the teaching of
    Syriac and related fields will be compiled and distributed at
    the conference. For further details see:<lb/>
            <ref target="http://csec.cua.edu/conference/Dorushe2006.cfm">http://csec.cua.edu/conference/Dorushe2006.cfm</ref>.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] E-mail
    proposals in the format outlined below by October 31, 2005 to
    56seville@cua.edu.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N2FCDorusheSyrConf1">Preparation of the Proposal</head>
         <head xml:id="HV8N2FCDorusheSyrConf2">Cover Sheet</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] On a
    separate cover sheet include name, address, any academic
    affiliation, phone and fax numbers, e-mail address, the
    paper’s title, and indication of any projection or other
    special facilities needed. Graduate students should indicate
    their current stage in their program and how they foresee using
    Syriac in their future academic work.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N2FCDorusheSyrConf3">Proposal</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Maximum
    word count: 300 words. Please submit your abstract as an e-mail
    attachment in RTF or MS Word Format. If your abstract includes
    Syriac or non-Roman characters please use a unicode font (such
    as the Meltho Fonts from <ref target="http://www.bethmardutho.org/">Beth Mardutho</ref>). For purposes
    of anonymous judging, please do <hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> include your name or
    other identification on the abstract. This information should
    be only on the cover sheet. Please be advised that the
    submission of an abstract and its acceptance represent a
    commitment from the contributor to summarize and discuss the
    paper in person at the conference.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
