<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">BYU-CUA Eastern Christian Research Library</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Kristian S.</forename>
                  <surname>Heal</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2005</date>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/projectReport/hv8n1prheal1</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Kristian S. Heal</author>
                  <title level="a">BYU-CUA Eastern Christian Research Library</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol8/HV8N1PRHeal1.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] A great
    number of essential Syriac texts are not readily available to
    scholars, even in some of the world's great research libraries.
    In order to remedy this situation, Brigham Young University has
    joined with The Catholic University of America to undertake a
    joint project to produce an on-line research collection for
    Syriac studies. What follows is a report of the work carried
    out so far. For further details please consult the project
    website (<ref target="http://cpart.byu.edu/ECRL/">http://cpart.byu.edu/ECRL</ref>).</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1PRHeal11">Scope of the Project</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] This
    project aims to build an Eastern Christian Research Library
    (the Library) of key editions and instruments de travail
    published before 1930. The Library is primarily intended to be
    a resource for scholars engaged in textual and manuscript
    research in the major Eastern Christian languages. The Syriac
    section of the Library will be populated first, under the
    editorship of Dr. David Taylor.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> Because of its focus, the
    Syriac section will include only a fraction of the literature
    published on Syriac studies before 1930. The Library is
    therefore intended to complement and support Beth Mardutho's
    more comprehensive eBethArké project
    (http://www.bethmardutho.org/ebetharke/).<ref target="#FN2">2</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1PRHeal12">Syriac Section-Phase 1</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Dr.
    Taylor has set the basic parameters of the Syriac section and
    drawn up a preliminary bibliography of volumes for inclusion
    (see project website). Renovations to CUA's Mullen Library
    created an opportunity in the summer of 2004 to begin
    populating the library with rare and important works. The
    richness of the Syriac holdings at CUA cannot be overestimated,
    nor can the kindness and competence of the collection's
    distinguished librarian, Dr. Monica Blanchard. Under her
    direction, and with the help of competent student workers, 157
    individual titles were scanned over a relatively brief
    period.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Images
    at CUA were captured on a <ref target="http://www.crowleymicrographics.com/images/New%2010000%20TT.pdf">Zeutschel Omniscan 10000 TT</ref> color book
    scanner tethered to a Windows PC, with a second PC used for
    proofing and data backup, which was done on DVD. The Zeutschel
    imaging system is the best of its kind, capable of producing
    very high resolution scans with high color accuracy, yet with a
    minimum of stress to the book or manuscript. Images were
    captured at 600dpi, resulting in (e.g.) a 70 megapixel image
    for a two-page capture of a 9"x11" book.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The next
    stage is to make the images accessible. Images are being
    cropped, rotated, and resized in post-processing and prepared
    for delivery as one of BYU library's online collections. The
    collection will be freely accessible to all. The books will be
    mounted on the web and made accessible through the ContentDM
    image delivery system. The unprocessed and processed images
    will also be archived by the library for future usage. The
    first phase of the Syriac collection will be made available
    over the course of the next year. Preference will be given to
    high demand items. The state of the collection will be recorded
    on the project website and announced periodically via the
    Hugoye mailing list. We hope this will be a useful resource and
    a benefit to scholars working in the field.</p>
         <p>
            <graphic url="HV8N1Heal1_01.jpg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg" width="700px" height="520px"/>
            <lb/>
    CUA technician scanning volume on Zeutschel 10000
    TT.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1PRHeal13">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> The Coptic section, under the editorship of Dr.
    Janet Timbie, is in its early stages. Pending available
    resources, it is hoped that the Library we expand to include
    Armenian, Christian Arabic, Ethiopic, and Georgian
    sections.<ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> BYU and CUA are library partners of
    eBethArké and are actively supporting this important
    initiative.<ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p> </p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
         <!-- InstanceEnd -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>