<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Christian Art and Identity in Medieval Syria. Qara, Dair Mar Yakub - The “Museum Fragments” Damascus, May 20-22, 2004</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Andrea</forename>
                  <surname>Schmidt</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/conferenceReport/hv8n1crschmidt</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Andrea Schmidt</author>
                  <title level="a">Christian Art and Identity in Medieval Syria. Qara, Dair Mar Yakub - The “Museum Fragments” Damascus, May 20-22, 2004</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Art</term>
               <term>Qara</term>
               <term>Dair Mar Yakub</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] An
    international conference on Syriac wall paintings was held from
    20 to 22 May 2004 in Damascus. It was organized by Mat
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Immerzeel</hi> (Paul
    van Moorsel Centre for Christian Art and Culture in the Middle
    East, University of Leiden), Andrea <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Schmidt</hi> (University of
    Louvain) and Stephan <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Westphalen</hi> (Deutsches
    Archäologisches Institut, Berlin-Damascus). The
    participants convened in the German Goethe-Institut in the
    Sharia Malki which is located in the same building as the
    German Archaeological Institute. The conference was supported
    by donations of the Gerda Henkel Stiftung (Germany), the German
    Archaeological Institute (Berlin), the Oriental Institute of
    the University of Louvain and the pioneer project on Syriac
    Christianity of the Leiden University.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The main
    interest of the symposium was focused on the newly restored
    Syriac-Melkite monastery of Saint James (Dair Mar Yakub) near
    the village Qara in the Qalamun Mountains. Together with
    Saydnaya, "up&gt;clula and Yabrud this village, situated of
    approx. 95 km to the northeast of Damascus, is among the most
    ancient Christian centres in the Qalamun. Since 1999 the German
    Archaeological Institute in Damascus under the directorship of
    St. Westphalen was engaged in the restoration of the wall
    paintings dating from the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    century which had been discovered in the church of the
    monastery. Twenty-two fragments of the church were already
    removed from the walls in 1970 and had been kept in the museums
    of Damascus and Dair <hi rend="sup">c</hi>
            <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Atiye. Except for
    two fragments, which are part of the exhibition in the National
    Museum in Damascus, the fragments of Dair <hi rend="sup">c</hi>Atiye
    have been now returned to Dair Mar Yakub which is inhabited by
    a newly founded convent of eight nuns. A. Schmidt cooperated
    with the restorers investigating the history of Qara from the
    5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. The results of
    these research studies carried out between 1999 and 2004 were
    discussed in a broader assessment of Christian wall paintings
    in Southern Syria (Dair Mar Musa, Ma<hi rend="sup">c</hi>arrat
    Saydnaya), Lebanon (Qadisha Valley) and Egypt (Dair al-Surian).
    Another subject of the conference was the cultural identity of
    the Christian minorities in Syria and its cultural and
    sociological background. The conference thus brought together
    the practical skills of restorers with the distinguished
    analysis of art historians and experts in Byzantine, Syriac and
    Arabic studies.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] The
    conference was opened the evening before with a reception in
    the courtyard of the Netherlands Institute for Academic Studies
    in Damascus situated in the old town of the city near Bab
    Sharqi. Mat <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Immerzeel</hi> (Leiden) delivered
    a lecture about a very popular subject in medieval church
    decoration in Lebanon and Syria—that of the equestrian
    saint (<hi rend="italic">Holy horsemen and templar’s banners</hi>.) He
    specially focused on the role of the crusader’s art in
    the contacts with indigenous christians. After him, Bas
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Snelders</hi> (Leiden)
    spoke about the origin and the unusual Asiatic style of a
    Syriac liturgical fan from the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century once
    belonging to the Syrian monastery in Wadi Natrun which is now
    preserved in the collection of the Musée Royal de
    Mariemont in Belgium (<hi rend="italic">The flabellum from Dair al-Surian, a
    unique liturgical object from the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
    century</hi>). He discussed arguments in favour of Mongolian
    influence in the iconographic representation of the Mother of
    God with child.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Next day
    the sessions were opened by the historical section of the
    symposium. Klaus-Peter <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Todt</hi> (Mainz) spoke about
    <hi rend="italic">Greek Orthodox Christians in Southern Syriac in the period
    of the crusaders.</hi> He focused on the reestablishment of the
    authority of the Orthodox Patriarchate of Antioch during the
    Byzantine reconquest of Southern Syria (969-1084) and the
    renewal of Melkite institutions during this period. The
    question of the use of liturgical languages in the patriarchate
    of Damascus—Greek or Syriac—was broached too.
    Dorothea <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Weltecke</hi>
    (Göttingen) explored the social conditions in medieval
    Syriac christianity (<hi rend="italic">Living during the so-called Syrian
    Renaissance—observations and questions</hi>). She pointed
    out conflicts between rich and poor, church dignitaries and lay
    elite or aspects of cross confessional relations in a
    multi-religious society. On the other hand she stressed that
    the common perception of “Renaissance”, as it was
    defined by A. Baumstark and P. Kawerau, must be redefined on
    the basis of a more comprehensive research. Baas <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">ter Haar Romeny</hi> (Leiden)
    discussed the complex terminology which is generally used to
    define the identity of Syriac christians and its sometimes
    inconsistent religious and ethnic implications (<hi rend="italic">From
    religious association to ethnic community—Identity
    formation among the Syrian Orthodox</hi>). He illustrated his
    theoretical approach with examples from Syriac historiography
    (John of Ephesus, Jacob of Edessa, Michael the Syrian),
    Biblical exegesis (Jacob of Serug, collection of Simeon,
    Dionysius bar Salibi) and art. The afternoon session was
    focused on Syriac wall paintings. Mat <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Immerzeel</hi> read a paper on the
    <hi rend="italic">Syrian wall paintings of Dair al-Surian</hi>. Erica
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Cruikshank Dodd</hi>
    (Victoria, BC) questioned in her paper the problem of what
    exactly the Syrian style is (<hi rend="italic">The Syrian Style at Dair Mar
    Musa</hi>). She explained her concepts in analysing frescos
    from Dair Mar Musa near Nebek and from the Qadisha Valley in
    the hinterland of Byblos und Tripoli. Together with the Wadi
    Qadisha, the Qalamun area is among the territories in which a
    local style marked the paintings of the twelfth and thirteenth
    centuries at most. On this occasion Andrea <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Schmidt</hi> (Louvain-la-Neuve)
    presented to the audience Dodd’s wonderful illustrated
    book which just came out from the printing press: <hi rend="italic">Medieval
    Painting in the Lebanon</hi> (Sprachen und Kulturen des
    Christlichen Orients. 8), Wiesbaden: Reichert Verlag 2004, X,
    450 pp. Nada <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Hélou</hi> (Antelias)
    presented a sample of her collection of slides concerning the
    symbolic meaning of church decorations in Lebanon (<hi rend="italic">Le
    décor des absides dans les églises du
    Liban</hi>). Then the third session of the day concentrated
    specifically on Qara. Aida <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Kaplan</hi> (Louvain-la-Neuve) who
    is working on a doctoral thesis about the nomenclature and
    development of Syriac writing systems, talked about the graphic
    character of a Syriac inscription which had been found on the
    southern wall of the church in Dair Mar Yakub; she placed it
    into the broader frame of palaeographic analysis (<hi rend="italic">Le
    graffito syriaque de Qara: analyse paléographique</hi>).
    Stephan <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Westphalen</hi> and Andrea
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Schmidt</hi>
    (Göttingen—Louvain-la-Neuve) presented the results
    of their recent research in the monastery Mar Yakub
    (<hi rend="italic">Historical evidences and wall paintings of Qara, Dair Mar
    Yakub</hi>). Originally known in antiquity as Goaria, Qara is
    mentioned as a Melkite Episcopal residence and Suffragan of the
    Metropolis of Damascus for the first time at the Council of
    Chalcedon in 451, where it is referred to as
    ‘Chonochora.’ Apart from that almost nothing is
    known about the bishopric in the first millennium. The most
    information—names of churches, bishops, scribes, and
    other persons in Qara—is furnished by colophons from the
    12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century on in Melkite liturgical manuscripts
    from the Qalamun. We also know that Qara was exclusively
    inhabited by Melkite Christians until the middle of the
    thirteenth century. St. <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Westphalen</hi> reconstructed the
    original location of the wall paintings preserved in the Syrian
    museums and the murals found <hi rend="italic">in situ</hi> in the church. He
    discussed the question of a local ‘Syrian Style’ in
    Qalamun comparing the paintings of Mar Musa (Syriac-orthodox
    monastery) with that in Mar Yakub (Syriac-melkite monastery);
    he came to the conclusion that the ‘Syrian Style’
    in the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century was not related
    to any specific confession. The medium of wall painting was not
    used to express theological differences. A complete catalogue
    of the murals in Dair Mar Yakub and the discovered Syriac and
    Greek inscriptions, as well as the history of the monastery are
    published in the forthcoming book: A. <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Schmidt</hi>—St.
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Westpahlen</hi>,
    Christliche Wandmalereien in Syrien. Qara und das Kloster Mar
    Yakub. Mit Beiträgen von S. Brock, M. Immerzeel und Ch.
    Strube, (Sprachen und Kulturen des Christlichen Orients. 13),
    Wiesbaden 2004 (in print). The paper of Mat <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Immerzeel</hi> (Leiden) related to
    the fragmentary <hi rend="italic">Wall paintings in the chapel of the Prophet
    Eliah at Ma<hi rend="sup">c</hi>arrat Saydnaya</hi> which have been
    recently discovered and restored by him. His investigations are
    included in the above mentioned book.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] The
    excursion next day brought all participants to Qara (the mosque
    of the village, formerly the St. Nicholas church; Mar Sarkis
    church; monastery Mar Yakub); to the monastery Mar Musa near
    Nebek and to the chapel of Eliah in Ma<hi rend="sup">c</hi>arrat
    Saydnaya in order to get acquainted with the specific
    conservation problems of the murals. The restorers explained
    the different methods of their work and emphasized the problems
    that last. In the evening there was a reception in the old
    damascene house of the Cultural Attaché of the German
    embassy which has a splendid view of the illuminated Umayyad
    mosque. Representatives of the Austrian, Belgian, Danish, Dutch
    and Swiss institutions and embassies in Damascus had been also
    invited.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] The
    third day of the conference was wholly dedicated to the
    practice of mural conservation. There was an interesting
    exchange of techniques and methods by the experts. Ewa
    <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Parandowska</hi>
    (Cairo-Warsaw) explored which kind of techniques had been used
    for restorations in Sudan and elsewhere (<hi rend="italic">Roman and
    Christian wall paintings from Syria, Egypt and
    Sudan Conservation solutions</hi>). Wolfgang <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Frey</hi> from the society of
    protections of monuments (Berlin) presented a paper on the
    possibilities and problems of relocating removed frescos on the
    walls. He illustrated his speech by examples of removed and
    re-installed wall paintings of the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century in
    the “Neues Museum” in Berlin. The conference
    concluded with a round table discussion on further conservation
    work which has to be done in the church of Dair Mar Yakub. The
    participants engaged in a keen debate on the 22 fragments which
    had been removed in 1970 from the walls and which are now in a
    very crumbled state. How to restore them and where to preserve
    them? Does it make sense to relocate them in the church or
    should they be given to a museum? Present at the discussion
    were also the superior of Mar Musa, Father Paolo
    dall’Oglio, the abbess of Mar Yakub, Soeur Agnes de la
    Croix, and the doyen of the faculty of art of the university of
    Damascus, Elias Zayat.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] In the
    afternoon all participants were honoured by a cheerful
    reception by the Syriac Orthodox patriarch Mar Ignatius Zakka
    Iwas in his new residence in Ma<hi rend="sup">c</hi>arrat Saydnaya. The
    director of the patriarchal library, Father Hazail <hi style="text-transform:titlecase">Soumi</hi> (Paris-Damascus), gave
    us a vivid report about the history and composition of the
    Syriac manuscript collection in the patriarchate (<hi rend="italic">Histoire
    du fond des manuscripts syriaques du patriarcat
    syriaque-orthodox à Damas</hi>). He is actually engaged
    in a systematic reorganisation of the manuscript collection and
    its cataloguing. Therefore the library with the manuscript
    collection was closed. But as a compensation he showed us
    digitized photos of some of the most interesting and beautiful
    manuscripts which attracted the attention of the scholars. At
    the end of the day H. Soumi gave the participants a tour of the
    new patriarchal library which has been well organised by
    him.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>