<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">J.P.M. van der Ploeg O.P. (1909-2004)</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Lucas</forename>
                  <surname>Rompay</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/obituary/hv8n1obvdploeg</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Lucas Van Rompay</author>
                  <title level="a">J.P.M. van der Ploeg O.P. (1909-2004)</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>J.P.M. van der Ploeg</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <hi style="float:right;margin:5px 0 5px 15px;background-color: #fff;padding:5px;border-top:1px solid #555;border-right:2px solid #999;border-bottom:2px solid #999;border-left:1px solid #555;">
            <graphic url="HV8N1OBvdPloeg_Img01.jpg"
                     rend="img"
                     mimeType="image/jpeg"
                     width="228px"
                     height="250px"/>
         </hi>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] On
    August 4, 2004, a few weeks after celebrating his ninety-fifth
    birthday, Father Johannes P.M. van der Ploeg passed away
    peacefully in Nijmegen, The Netherlands. Father van der Ploeg,
    a Dominican, was professor of Old Testament and Semitics at the
    Catholic University of Nijmegen (now Radboud University) from
    1951 until 1979; and, since his consecration by H.H. Patriarch
    Tappouni in 1963, a chorbishop of the Syrian-Catholic
    Church.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] In the
    field of the Hebrew Bible and the Dead Sea Scrolls Father van
    der Ploeg published a number of important studies and
    translations. With A.S. van der Woude and B. Jongeling he
    co-authored the <hi rend="italic">editio princeps</hi> of the Aramaic Job
    Targum from Qumran (1971), and in the Netherlands and Belgium
    his <hi rend="italic">Vondsten in de Woestijn van Juda</hi> served for
    decades as a reliable guide to the Dead Sea Scrolls. It was
    first published in Dutch in 1957 and was often revised and
    reprinted; it was translated into English in 1958 (<hi rend="italic">The
    Excavations at Qumran. A Survey of the Judaean Brotherhood and
    Its Ideas</hi>) and into German in 1959.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Syriac
    Christianity constituted a third important focus of Father van
    der Ploeg’s academic work. In his later life his many
    contacts with the Syrian Christians of Southern India gave him
    the opportunity to pursue his Syriac interests. This is
    expressed eloquently in the title of the <hi rend="italic">Festschrift</hi>
    that was offered to him for his seventieth birthday: <hi rend="italic">Von
    Kanaan bis Kerala</hi> (eds. W.C. Delsman, J.T. Nelis, J.R.T.M.
    Peters, W.H.Ph. Römer, and A.S. van der Woude; Alter
    Orient und Altes Testament 211; 1982).</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Father
    van der Ploeg’s Syriac work can be traced back, however,
    to a much earlier period in his life.  His interesting
    book on <hi rend="italic">Oud-Syrisch</hi> 
            <hi rend="italic">Monniksleven</hi>,
    “Old-Syriac Monastic Life” (Leiden, 1942), written
    and published during wartime, never received the attention it
    deserved. It was not meant to be a history of Syriac
    monasticism; the author intended merely to present “some
    critical observations and a short explanation of the origins of
    monastic life in Syria, along with a brief sketch of Syriac,
    more particularly East-Syriac, monasticism as it existed for
    centuries, following the reform introduced by Abraham of
    Kashkar” (<hi rend="italic">Preface</hi>, p. ix). While Thomas of
    Marga, Isaac of Niniveh, and Bar Hebraeus are the most
    prominent frequently quoted authors, several other texts,
    Syriac and Greek, are used and referred to as well. A number of
    important questions are dealt with in a clear and elegant
    style, enlivened with anecdotes and personal observations. A
    final section discusses monastic life of the present-day
    Syrians. The Syrian Orthodox, with their monasteries in Tur
    Abdin, Jerusalem (Mar Markos), and Iraq (Mar Mattay) are
    singled out as the only community to have preserved,
    uninterrupted, the tradition of early Syriac monasticism (p.
    97). An appendix contains the Dutch translation of Rabban
    Gabriel’s address to the monks of the Monastery of Rabban
    Cyprian (from Thomas of Marga’s <hi rend="italic">Book of
    Governors</hi>, ed. E.A. Wallis Budge, I, 376-379). Although
    this book is much more limited than Jules Leroy’s
    <hi rend="italic">Moines et monastères du Proche-Orient</hi> (1958;
    published in English as <hi rend="italic">Monks and Monasteries of the Near
    East</hi>, 1963 – Gorgias Press reprint, 2004) or A.
    Vööbus’ <hi rend="italic">History of Asceticism in the Syrian
    Orient</hi> (1958-1960), it can still serve nowadays as a
    useful introduction for interested laypeople and students.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] Widely
    used and well-known among Syriac scholars is Father van der
    Ploeg’s book on <hi rend="italic">The Christians of St. Thomas in South
    India and their Syriac manuscripts</hi> (Placid Lecture Series
    3; Bangalore, 1983), which is the product of many years of work
    in Kerala and in Europe. While the focus is on the preserved
    manuscripts—many of which are analyzed or briefly
    described, often for the first time—the author’s
    interest extends to the religious, literary, and cultural
    history of the various Christian communities. The first chapter
    provides a historical survey, followed by an overview of the
    various categories of manuscripts (chapter 2). Chapter 3 lists
    a number of important libraries in Kerala and provides
    descriptions of the main manuscripts. Chapter 4 is devoted to
    manuscripts copied in Kerala, but presently held in European
    libraries (Rome, Cambridge, Oxford, Paris, Leiden, and
    Amsterdam). In spite of its limitations (and the tantalizing
    incompleteness of many a description!), this book, carrying the
    clear mark of the author’s personal approach and
    dedication, is a unique contribution to the uncovering and
    study of Kerala’s rich manuscript treasures. Following
    Van der Ploeg’s publication, the work was picked up by
    various other scholars, but another publication of similar
    breadth and erudition has not yet appeared.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] One of
    the texts briefly described in his 1983 book became the subject
    of an independent publication, which appeared eight years
    later: <hi rend="italic">The Book of Judith (Daughter of Merari)</hi>
    (Môrân ’Ethô Series 3; Baker Hill,
    Kottayam, 1991). It includes a facsimile edition, with English
    translation and notes, of the text of the deuterocanonical (or
    apocryphal) book of Judith as found in an 18th c. manuscript,
    preserved in the library of the Malankara Catholic archbishop
    at Trivandrum (see <hi rend="italic">The Christians</hi>, 87-88). The text is
    neither Peshitta nor Syro-Hexapla. Father van der Ploeg
    recognized its importance and with his publication made it
    available for further research.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Even if
    Syriac was not always at the center of Father van der
    Ploeg’s academic work, Syriac scholars should be grateful
    for his distinctive contributions to the field and for his
    strong commitment to Syriac Christian culture in the Middle
    East and in India. May he rest in peace!</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1OBvdPloeg1">Acknowledgement</head>
         <p>The photograph was kindly provided by the editorial board of
    the Dutch-Flemish periodical 'Catholica'.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
