<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">FROM THE GENERAL EDITOR</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>George A.</forename>
                  <surname>Kiraz</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2005</date>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv8n1issuededication</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>George A. Kiraz</author>
                  <title level="a">FROM THE GENERAL EDITOR</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol8/HV8N1IssueDedication.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term/>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] Just a
    few weeks back, the community of Syriac scholarship heard about
    the untimely death of one of its foremost scholars, David John
    Lane. David had arrived in India on January 5 on a routine
    visit to the St. Ephrem Ecumenical Research Institute (SEERI).
    On January 10, he had a cardiac arrest and was admitted to the
    hospital; he passed away at 9:50 PM. David Lane's
    autobiography, which he prepared for SEERI, is published in
    this issue. He will be remembered by all of us for his
    scholarship, but also for his interest in Syriac not only as an
    academic subject, but as a living heritage.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] The
    funeral service took place at 2:30 pm on Friday, January 14, at
    the church situated in the SEERI campus and the burial followed
    at the cemetery of the Malankara Catholic Church at Kalathipady
    near Kottayam. The service was presided over by Mar Cleemis of
    Tiruvalla (Syro-Malankara Catholic Church, and SEERI's
    President), Thomas Mor Themotheos (Syrian Orthodox Church), and
    Thomas Mar Koorilose (Syro-Malankara Catholic Church). Fr. M.P.
    George of the Malankara Orthodox Seminary led the chanting in
    Syriac and in Malayalam. Other priests, mostly David's
    students, from the various other traditions took part. The
    service was attended by ca. 200 people.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] It is
    only fitting that Fr. David received burial rites according to
    the West Syriac rite of the Order of Burial of Priests. His
    body was vested with the priestly garments. The service
    concluded with the traditional <hi rend="italic">zuyo<hi rend="u">h</hi>o</hi>, a farewell ceremony exclusive to deacons
    and priests. The body was carried by priests to the altar and
    placed facing East. A priest represented Fr. David in chanting
    "<hi rend="italic">Phush bashlom</hi>—Farewell, O holy altar." The rest
    of the priests responded, "<hi rend="italic">zel bashlom</hi>, Depart in
    peace, O honorable priest." The farewell continued,<lb/>
    - Farewell, O holy Church.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O modest priest.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O holy bishops.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O pious priest.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O heads of the churches.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, our beloved father.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O heads of the monasteries.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, our blessed father.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O noble priests.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O venerable priest.</p>
         <p>The priests then carried Fr. David to the entrance of the
    church where his body was placed facing West. The priest
    representing Fr. David chanted,<lb/>
    - Farewell, O modest deacons.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O faithful priest.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O clergy.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, our just father.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O beloved ones and friends.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, our righteous father.</p>
         <p>Fr. David's body was then taken to the North side of the
    church to say his farewell to all dwellers.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O monastery and its dwellers.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O teacher of truth.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O city and its inhabitants.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O eminent priest.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O fellow mortals.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O ascetic father.</p>
         <p>Finally, Fr. David's body was taken to the South side of the
    church for his final farewell.<lb/>
    - Farewell, O Church and its children.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O preacher of truth.<lb/>
    - Give me peace and may you live in peace. This peace [that you
    give me] is henceforth forever.<lb/>
    - Depart in peace, O brother and beloved one. May our Lord
    receive you in the blessed mansions. May Christ, Who took you
    away, make us worthy to see you in the new life that will shine
    forth from heaven. Glory to you, O Jesus our Savior, in Whose
    hands is death and Whose will is life.</p>
         <p>The Syriac text of this moving ritual follows (taken from
    Book of the Order for the Burial of the Clergy According to the
    Ancient Rite of the Syrian Orthodox Church of Antioch, tr. by
    Archdeacon Murad Saliba Barsom, 2003, pp. 121-124).<lb/>
            <graphic url="HV8N1IssueDedication01.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] David
    left many unfinished works behind. His <hi rend="italic">opus magnum</hi>,
    the edition and translation of Shubkhalmaran's <hi rend="italic">Book of
    Gifts</hi>, which will be published in CSCO, is not yet at the
    proof stage. The proofs will be corrected by Andrea Schmidt.
    David had also almost finished writing an introduction to a
    forthcoming facsimile edition of the East Syriac
    <hi rend="italic">
               <hi rend="u">H</hi>udra</hi> based on the Thrissur
    manuscript of 1598. It is hoped that his writings can be
    recovered.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] It is
    our obligation to dedicate this issue of <hi rend="italic">Hugoye</hi> in
    memory of David John Lane, scholar, <hi rend="italic">malphono</hi>, mentor,
    and friend to many of us. It only remains for us to say,
    <hi rend="italic">zel bashlom, malphono <hi rend="u">t</hi>arqo</hi>.</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
         <!-- InstanceEnd -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>