<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Methods of Instructing Syriac-Speaking Christians to Care for the Poor: A Brief Comparison of the Eighth Mēmrā of the Book of Steps and the Story of the Man of God of Edessa.</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Nancy A.</forename>
                  <surname>Khalek</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2005</date>
            <idno>Vol. 8, No. 1</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/article/hv8n1khalek</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Nancy A. Khalek</author>
                  <title level="a">Methods of Instructing Syriac-Speaking Christians to Care for the Poor: A Brief Comparison of the Eighth Mēmrā of the Book of Steps and the Story of the Man of God of Edessa.</title>
                        <idno type="PDF">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/pdf/vol8/HV8N1Khalek.pdf</idno>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="8">8</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="1">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Book of Steps</term>
               <term>Man of God of Edessa</term>
               <term>homily</term>
               <term>hagiography</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract">
            <p>This essay is a brief comparison of the
    renunciation of material possessions in the eighth
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> of the fourth-century Book of Steps
    <hi rend="italic">(Liber Graduum</hi>) and the sixth-century <hi rend="italic">Story of the
    Man of God of Edessa</hi>. The figures of the Upright and the
    Perfect in the anonymous Book of Steps exhibit striking
    correlations with the characters presented in the <hi rend="italic">Story of
    the Man of God</hi>. Analysis of this homily and hagiography
    provide insight as to the pedagogical mechanisms within, and
    instructional usefulness of each text.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->

         <lb/>

         <lb/>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1]
    Instructing Christians to care for the poor is a common theme
    in the Syriac tradition.<ref target="#FN1">1</ref> Texts in the form of homilies,
    poems, or hagiographies employ various pedagogical strategies
    for the purpose of preaching, expounding upon, or demonstrating
    the value of charity. Two sources which represent the didactic
    qualities of such instruction are the sixth-century <hi rend="italic">Story
    of the Man of God of Edessa</hi> and the eighth
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> of fourth-century Book of Steps
    (<hi rend="italic">Liber Graduum</hi>), which is titled “On One Who
    Feeds all of His Possessions to the Poor.” The former is
    a hagiographical text while the latter is one short portion of
    the well-known anonymous collection of thirty
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi>.<ref target="#FN2">2</ref> By comparing these ostensibly
    disparate sources, it is possible to find striking correlations
    in their instructions to care for the poor.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] I have
    chosen to compare these two texts for simple and
    straightforward reasons. First, it is well known that the
    anonymous author of the Book of Steps divides the Christian
    community into two main groups, the Upright
    (<hi rend="italic">kēnē</hi>) and the Perfect
    (<hi rend="italic">gmīrē</hi>).<ref target="#FN3">3</ref> Collectively, the
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrē</hi> in the Book of Steps enumerate the
    duties and character of these groups with respect to many
    issues, among them poverty and charity.
    <hi rend="italic">Mēmrā</hi> eight is one homily which exclusively
    addresses Christians who renounce material wealth to varying
    degrees. It also lays emphasis on the <hi rend="italic">voluntary</hi> aspect
    of giving away material possessions for the sake of the Lord.
    Our second text, <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Man of God of
    Edessa</hi>, is a parable enjoining Christians to care for the
    poor and glorifying the example of a saint whose most
    significant deed was the fact that <hi rend="italic">his</hi> severe poverty
    was voluntary. Set in the late fourth and early fifth century,
    this hagiography likewise conveys the import of maintaining the
    needs of the poor and indigent, this time in the form of a
    moral lesson. Searching these sources for common motifs,
    especially in relation to poverty and charity, yields useful
    information for increasing our understanding of each text.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Khalek3">The Book of Steps, Mēmrā Eight</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3]
    According to the Book of Steps, how a community member
    functions depends upon whether or not one is Upright or
    Perfect. Put simply, the Perfect are characterized by a
    total renunciation of material wealth and a complete reliance
    upon the charity of others for material sustenance. Charity in
    the Book of Steps thus has two dimensions: it is favorable to
    give charity as an act of benevolence (which simultaneously
    constitutes a renunciation of a portion of one’s wealth),
    and it is favorable to <hi rend="italic">receive</hi> charity if the
    condition under which one receives it is the pursuit of
    Perfection. Provision of such charity is, in turn, the
    obligation of the Upright.<ref target="#FN4">4</ref> In return for giving the Perfect
    their sustenance, the Upright benefit from the teaching and
    prayers of the Perfect, who comprise a valuable spiritual asset
    for the community as a whole. References to this symbiotic
    relationship are numerous in the Book of Steps.<ref target="#FN5">5</ref> The eighth
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, which is short and seemingly
    non-descript, provides a simple formula for activities
    incumbent upon the Upright on the basis of Matthew 25:35-36;
    feeding the hungry, clothing the naked, giving drink to the
    thirsty, healing the sick and visiting the imprisoned. Wealth
    is permitted for the Upright only if they use it for the
    welfare of others.  Put simply, the Upright maintain the
    social needs of others.<ref target="#FN6">6</ref> That the Perfect are in need of support is
    a theme throughout the Book of Steps. 
    <hi rend="italic">Mēmrā</hi> eight concisely summarizes the
    circumstances under which the Perfect retains no possessions,
    and “has no place on earth to lay his
    head.”<ref target="#FN7">7</ref> Instead he “contemplates what is in the
    heavenly Jerusalem, and is focused there on the
    Lord.”<ref target="#FN8">8</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] Daniel
    Caner’s recent work illustrates that the instruction to
    care for the masses of the poor which is directed towards the
    Upright in the Book of Steps also refers to assisting the
    impoverished Perfect. A system of reciprocity between Upright
    and Perfect, whereby material support is exchanged for the
    spiritual assets conferred upon the community by the Perfect is
    clear elsewhere in the Book of Steps.<ref target="#FN9">9</ref> That the Perfect could
    resemble the everyday poor is a theme in
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> twenty, where one such Christian is
    described as “begging food and clothing like a poor
    person.”<ref target="#FN10">[10</ref> The relation between Upright and Perfect as
    one of giving and receiving <hi rend="italic">charity</hi> is explicit in
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> three, which reports that the Upright
    must also support “those who have no possessions or
    profession, who apply themselves wholly to the teaching of our
    Lord.”<ref target="#_ftn11">11</ref> Thus, when we read the term “the
    poor” in the Book of Steps, we should bear in mind both
    types of recipients of charity. Corresponding to each category
    of recipient, charity in the Book of Steps thereby has both an
    inherent and a potentially reciprocal value.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P5"/>[5] In
    keeping with this hypothesis and therefore in <hi rend="italic">spite</hi> of
    its title, the actual masses of the poor make no substantive
    appearance in this <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, which primarily
    communicates the difference between the Upright and the Perfect
    while assuring the Upright of their salvation and encouraging
    the pursuit of perfection through daily spiritual advancement.
    In this sense the eighth <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> is both a
    presentation of a scheme and an exhortation. While the station
    of the perfect is stressed as vastly superior to that of the
    Upright, the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> contains numerous
    reminders of the dignity of the Upright, who are always assured
    of their status, their eventual salvation and impending reward.
    In the first section of <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> eight we read:
    “If you know the Truth, that Truth will set you
    free”; even though the free are not perfect, as soon as
    they know the truth they are liberated from lying and
    enslavement to sin and they shall become Upright, and they
    shall not come into judgment.”<ref target="#FN12">12</ref> The first section
    also outlines what was noted above as characteristic of the
    active ministry of the Upright: feeding the hungry, giving
    drink to the thirsty, welcoming the stranger, clothing the
    naked, and visiting the sick and the imprisoned. This is the
    only mention of society’s have-nots in the entire
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>. They serve only to illustrate the
    basic duties of the majority of the members of the community.
    The relative status of the Upright is noted at the end of this
    section, where the author notes that the Upright are on a path
    to salvation and that through daily persistence they may attain
    the Perfection that is beyond acts of charity.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P6"/>[6] In this
    opening section of the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, we are also
    confronted by an apparent contradiction.  The Apostle Paul
    claims that giving up all worldly possession is of no benefit
    if one does not possess love, yet Jesus tells his apostles that
    the reward of one who gives even a cup of water to another
    shall not be lost. The entire homily serves to reconcile these
    two views by imposing the scheme of “Upright versus
    Perfect” onto the text. Paul was referring to the formula
    for Perfection, while Jesus was expounding on the active
    aspects of Christian ministry performed by the Upright. The
    author reconciles this contradiction in the following excerpt
    from section two:</p>
         <quote>
      But how did the Apostle say that these things are
      nothing?<ref target="#FN13">13</ref> He also said, “If I should give
      my body to be burned and love is not in me, I am
      nothing.”<ref target="#FN14">14</ref> For what indeed is that thing which is
      better than all things for which the Apostle longs? The Lord
      said “Whoever gives his cheek to the one who strikes
      him and is patient, he shall come to Perfection, if he loves
      and prays for whoever strikes him.” Is it that the
      Apostle negates the words of our Lord? God forbid! No, he
      does not negate them. Rather, he builds upon them.  The
      Apostle does not say that the words are not fitting, rather,
      something great he puts there.<ref target="#FN15">15</ref>  Namely [the Apostle
      is talking about]<ref target="#FN16">16</ref> one who feeds all he has to the poor
      for the sake of God, and is emptied out as He commanded him,
      and he renounces all things <hi rend="italic">but</hi> that humble love is
      not in him, who is compassionate to his murderers and who
      washes the feet of his enemies and who considers all people
      as if they are greater than he,<ref target="#FN17">17</ref> and who gazes upon the
      heavens and not the earth, and in his mind contemplates what
      is in the heavenly Jerusalem, and is focused there on the
      Lord.<ref target="#FN18">18</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P7"/>[7] Thus the
    explanation of this apparent paradox is that “the thing
    for which the Apostle longs” is to attain a state of
    spiritual advancement whereby one loves and prays for
    one’s enemies. It is in this section that we first
    encounter the term
    “<hi rend="italic">msārrqūţā</hi>”,
    ‘emptying out.’ This is designated as a great
    commandment, and indicates the complete renunciation of wealth,
    stability, and family life. In order to perfectly fulfill the
    great commandment, <hi rend="italic">msārrqūţā</hi> must
    be accompanied by <hi rend="italic">makkīkūţā</hi>,
    ‘humility.’  Without “humble
    love”, renunciation is not meaningless, but it is
    insignificant when compared to the fulfillment of the great
    commandment as performed by the Perfect Christian.
    Interestingly, Perfect love is personified in the remainder of
    this section, in an elaborate description of what a Perfect
    should embody.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P8"/>[8] The
    disparity between Upright and Perfect is reiterated in the
    beginning of section three, which is also the section that best
    highlights the difference between material renunciation and
    interior spiritual advancement.  The author notes that it
    is possible to renounce all possessions on behalf of the Lord
    and still not achieve perfect humility:</p>
         <quote>
      For it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> possible that men give all they possess
      and become needy on earth for the sake of the Lord, yet not
      arrive at that humility. For they love as much as they
      are loved, and they are humble to some men and they are not
      humble to everyone. And on account of that they are much less
      than one who comes to complete love. For he who does not
      become humble, is not being perfected, and he who is not
      humbled is much less than the Perfect ones.<ref target="#FN19">19</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P9"/>[9] Thus
    this sermon summarizes, in a simplified form, the Book of
    Step’s schematic for levels of spiritual advancement as
    effected by gradations of the renunciation of wealth. The
    Upright do charitable works, and the Upright who are advancing
    towards Perfection renounce possessions, but with varying
    degrees of humility and love for others. Once those degrees are
    surpassed, the Upright achieves Perfection, and is humbled to
    all. Overcoming obstacles to perfect humility is the process by
    which one is perfected.  In section five, we read a
    summation of the relative worthiness of the Upright and the
    Perfect:</p>
         <quote>
      And also there are those men who left behind all they
      possessed for the sake of the Lord and who love Him, and are
      compassionate towards Him, but there is not in them that love
      that loves God and Human Beings. And because they loved the
      Lord, He reveals to them the mysteries that are in the
      heavens, and all knowledge of faith, yet they do not
      understand the height and the depth and the latitude and the
      longitude that (perfect) love comprehends. Rather, they
      understand the mysteries and all the knowledge that is in
      faith.<ref target="#FN20">20</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P10"/>[10] In
    the passages presented thus far, the key issue is the voluntary
    nature of the renunciation of wealth. In the proto-monastic
    world of the Book of Steps, neediness alone could not comprise
    Uprightness. The volition with which one became needy and the
    degree of his accompanying humility determined the status of
    the believer. Caner aptly observes that “the Book of
    Steps describes not so much a monastic community or even a
    single, unified ascetic elite as a reciprocal relationship that
    loosely binds spiritually advanced ascetics to other
    Christians.”<ref target="#FN21">21</ref> The excerpt above elucidates an aspect of
    such spiritual advancement in a manner typical of the Book of
    Steps: while it points towards those who “left
    everything,” that is who renounced wealth for the sake of
    the poor, it is nonetheless a reference to the Upright and
    <hi rend="italic">not</hi> to the Perfect, as the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>
    goes on to clarify that Perfection is characterized by complete
    humility and abasement in addition to the renunciation of
    wealth.<ref target="#FN22">22</ref> The lines cited above, which open the
    concluding section of the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>,
    simultaneously reassure and encourage the Upright.<ref target="#FN23">23</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P11"/>[11] The
    fifth and final section of this <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>
    reiterates the theme of having knowledge of faith without
    comprehending perfect love. It exhorts the Upright to seek
    perfection by emphasizing the vast superiority of that station
    to all others, but likewise continues to stress that the life
    of the Upright is not without its reward.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P12"/>[12] In
    this short, at first non-descript homily, some essential themes
    of this unique strand of earliest Syriac asceticism are
    encapsulated. It is above all an instructional text, reminding
    the community of its obligations, its character, and its
    impending salvation. It is aimed primarily at the Upright who
    are involved in an active, practical ministry aimed at serving
    the needs of the indigent Perfect, while it idealizes the
    Perfect whose inner life and spiritual advancement surpass the
    ordinary world of giving and taking. It remains to see the
    Upright Christian who ministers to the poor in action, as a
    character in an inspiring and motivational story. <hi rend="italic">The Story
    of the Man of God of Edessa</hi> provides precisely that sort
    of motivational parable.</p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Khalek4">The Man of God of Edessa</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P13"/>[13] The
    history of this hagiographical text is complicated and somewhat
    convoluted. <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Man of God</hi>, a
    sixth-century anonymous saint’s life became conflated
    with the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Saint Alexis in the early Middle
    Ages.<ref target="#FN24">24</ref> In 1889, Arthur Amiaud published his research
    on Syriac manuscripts relating to Saint Alexis, whereupon the
    <hi rend="italic">Man of God</hi> narrative was shown to be an earlier story
    to which the material relating to Saint Alexis was
    added. My hypothesis is that the story of <hi rend="italic">The Man of
    God</hi> is a parable aimed at encouraging devotional behavior
    in a manner which is thematically consonant with the Upright
    Christian’s as outlined in the Book of Steps. It is not a
    typical hagiography, however, in that it is sparing in its use
    of miracles to embellish the narrative, and is essentially
    unadorned by extensive biblical quotation, even in cases where
    obvious references virtually spring to mind. As such, the story
    is a clear and simple pedagogical tool, which must have
    resonated in its function as a parable for those to whom it was
    read. <ref target="#FN25">25</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P14"/>[14] The
    Syriac version of the narrative of the Man of God is set during
    the lifetime of the Bishop Rabbula, who presided over the
    Church in Edessa from 412-436 CE.  The manuscript dates to
    the sixth century, whereas the story itself bespeaks an earlier
    milieu. The basic plot of the <hi rend="italic">Story of the Man of God</hi>
    is that the son of wealthy parents rejects the ostentatious
    life, and <hi rend="italic">wife</hi>, that his noble birth afford him. He
    leaves home on his wedding day and boards a ship headed for
    Edessa where he proceeds to live as an anonymous and pious poor
    person, devoted to nearly constant prayer and refusing to
    reveal his identity until compelled to do so by an oath made by
    a church custodian.<ref target="#FN26">26</ref> This kind of uprooting and dislocation is
    an essential aspect of the story, in that it is the main cause
    of the deep fissure between the Man of God’s past and his
    ascetic life. Upon discovering the worldly nobility of the Man
    of God, the custodian wishes to reveal the secret, and promises
    not to only at the urgent request of the Man of God. The
    protagonist then falls ill and passes away in a hospital for
    the poor. After his death, the custodian notifies Bishop
    Rabbula and divulges the Man of God’s true identity.
    Seeking his remains in a cemetery for the poor, the Bishop and
    the custodian are only able to find the rags worn by the old
    man.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P15"/>[15] In
    remorse mixed with inspiration, the Syriac version of the story
    relates Rabbula’s resolution to care for the poor, with
    the added warning that one could never be sure that precisely
    such a holy person was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> in their midst. Rabbula
    asks, “Who knows whether there are many like this saint,
    who delight in abasement, nobles to God in their souls, but not
    recognized by humans because of their physical
    abasement?”<ref target="#FN27">27</ref> Rabbula thus demonstrates a particular
    response to the presence of the poor and indigent. It is noted
    that he subsequently suspended all other activities and
    building projects to devote himself completely to the care of
    the needy.  The potential presence of such hidden treasure
    troves of spiritual excellence is explicitly acknowledged by
    Bishop Rabbula. As such, poor people like the Man of God
    provided the community, which in turn is represented in the
    story by the figures of the Bishop and the custodian, with a
    clear mechanism for Christian action in the form of
    charity.<ref target="#FN28">28</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P16"/>[16] Thus
    the <hi rend="italic">Story of the Man of God</hi> is both a parable and a
    story about tests, and as a pedagogical tool it thereby serves
    two instructional purposes. First, those who hear the
    story should be inspired by the hero’s bravery, devotion
    and pious behavior. Second, like Rabbula, they should be
    inspired to modify their own behavior towards the
    poor. The performance of such charitable acts is,
    according to <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Man of God</hi>, informed by
    the two sentiments expressed by Bishop Rabbula: a desire to
    help the poor and indigent, and a suspicion that a holy man in
    the guise of a beggar was always in one’s midst. This
    theme obviously alludes to the words of Christ in Matthew
    25:35-36, the same verses that open our
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Book of Steps</hi>.<ref target="#FN29">29</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P17"/>[17]
    Parallels between the Perfect and the Man of God are also
    evident. For example, the Man on God was an heir to great
    wealth, but rejected it. He was “joyfully separated from
    his country, for he yearned and was pressing in his position to
    be enrolled and recognized in the Jerusalem which is
    above.”<ref target="#FN30">30</ref> The Perfect likewise “contemplates what
    is in the heavenly Jerusalem, and is focused there on the
    Lord.”<ref target="#FN31">31</ref> Both opt for a life of severe poverty, and
    rely upon others for material support. Both represent a
    spiritual asset for the Christian community, as the Book of
    Steps makes clear and as Rabbula explicitly states at the end
    of <hi rend="italic">The Story of the Man of God.<ref target="#FN32">[32]</ref>
            </hi> The similarity
    between the Perfect and the Book of and the Man of God is
    ultimately bolstered by the similitude of both figures as
    pedagogical characters. We should remember that perfection is
    an ideal to which Upright Christians aspire. When Bishop
    Rabbula and the custodian marvel at the remarkable sacrifices
    made by the Saint in his life of voluntary poverty we have two
    parallels for Upright Christians on the path to perfection. For
    example, our author tells us:</p>
         <quote>
      From then on, that custodian, although he had been doing his
      work, improved himself through severe practices. He trained
      his body more than previously until even his appearance bore
      witness to his practices, as he told himself, “If that
      one who lived in great luxury does these things, what should
      we wretches do to receive our redemption?”<ref target="#FN33">33</ref>
         </quote>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P18"/>[18] The
    custodian and Bishop Rabbula are as impressed by the austerity
    of the life of the Man of God as they are by the voluntary
    renunciation of wealth and physical abasement undertaken by the
    Man of God. If we wish to round out our understanding of
    Upright Christians aspiring towards or transitioning into a
    life of Perfection, the examples of Rabbula and the custodian,
    on account of their reflection and reactions, are useful
    models.<ref target="#FN34">34</ref>
         </p>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Khalek5">Conclusion</head>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P19"/>[19]
    Throughout the Book of Steps, and in capsule form, in the
    eighth <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> of that collection, the
    position of the Upright with respect to the Perfect is clear.
    They are to support the efforts of the elect who in turn
    provide a spiritual asset for the community. A key aspect of
    perfection in the Book of Steps is the combination of voluntary
    poverty with extreme physical and social abasement. This
    renders the Perfect identical to the masses of the poor, to
    beggars, to precisely the persona we see adopted by the Man of
    God. The <hi rend="italic">Story of the Man of God</hi> is a hagiographical
    manifestation of the intended message of this
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi>, with the Man of God in the role of
    the Perfect Christian who voluntarily renounces all worldly
    goods and who also resembles an anonymous poor person in spite
    of his high spiritual and social status. In this hagiographical
    text, through the figures of the custodian and Bishop Rabbula,
    listeners were reminded that providing for the poor was
    incumbent upon them in part because of the inherent value of
    giving, and in part because of the potential greatness of the
    recipient.<ref target="#FN35">35</ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P20"/>[20] The
    Man of God himself was every man’s Christian hero. He
    presented a challenge in that he represented the potentially
    hidden member of the spiritual elect in the guise of a poor
    person to whom someone like the Upright Christian should
    minister. As a pedagogical tool, the figure of Man of God was,
    in short, a benevolent boogeyman; ever-present in the back of
    one’s mind, and lurking, as a test for those around him,
    in every crowd of beggars huddled on the street. In these two
    short, disparate and somewhat elusive texts, a comparison of
    common motifs serves to flesh out and broaden our potential
    understanding of each.</p>_______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Khalek6">Notes</head>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef1">1</ref> An extended version of this essay was written for a
    seminar on Poverty and Charity in Late Antiquity instructed by
    Peter Brown at Princeton University. Credit and special thanks
    are also due to Professor Robert Doran of Amherst University
    for all of his extremely helpful comments on many aspects of
    this paper. <ref target="#FNRef1">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef2">2</ref> It is worth mentioning at the outset that while I
    shall not address the issue here, discussions of the Book of
    Steps usually include analysis of the debate over whether there
    is a Messalian affiliation with the text. For a concise summary
    of this debate, see Columba A. Stewart, <hi rend="italic">Working the Earth
    of the Heart: The Messalian Controversy in History, texts and
    Language to AD 431</hi>, (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991). 
    References to the eighth <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> of the Book
    of Steps in this essay are to the M. Kmosko 1926 critical
    edition in PS III. For the sake of convenience, I shall also
    use Kmosko’s system for division of the text of
    <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> 8 into five sections. All references
    will cite the <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> number, followed by the
    column number and line numbers.  A complete English
    translation of and introduction to the Book of Steps by R.A.
    Kitchen ad M.F.G. Parmentier is forthcoming from Cistercian
    Publications.  For the purposes of excerpts cited here, I
    use my own working translation. <ref target="#FNRef2">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef3">3</ref> On the division of the Christian community into
    these categories, see R.A. Kitchen, “Conflict on the
    Stairway to Heaven: The Anonymity of Perfection in the Syriac
    <hi rend="italic">Liber Graduum</hi>,” (Symposium Syriacum VII, Uppsala
    1996; <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Analecta</hi> 256, 1998)
    211-220. See also Daniel Caner, <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging Monks:
    The Promotion of Monasticism in Late Antiquity,</hi> (The
    Transformation of Classical Heritage 33; Berkeley: University
    of California Press, 2002) esp. 106-112 and finally, Antoine
    Guillaumont, ‘Situation et signification du
    « Liber Graduum » dans la
    spiritualité syriaque’ in <hi rend="italic">Symposium
    Syriacum</hi> 1972, 311-322. <ref target="#FNRef3">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef4">4</ref> D. Caner, <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging Monks,</hi>
    108-109, n 111. <ref target="#FNRef4">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef5">5</ref> For another discussion of the exchange of actual
    for spiritual merchandise, see Adam Becker, “Anti-Judaism
    and Care for the Poor in Aphrahat’s Demonstration
    20,” <hi rend="italic">Journal of Early Christian Studies,</hi> 10
    (2002) esp. 311-12. <ref target="#FNRef5">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef6">6</ref> A. Guillaumont, ‘Situation et
    signification’ 311-322. <ref target="#FNRef6">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef7">7</ref> 8: 193, 20-21. <ref target="#FNRef7">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef8">8</ref> 8: 193, 6-7. <ref target="#FNRef8">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef9">9</ref> Caner, <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging Monks</hi>, 109. On
    the parallels between the relationship of the Upright and the
    Perfect and that of the Manichaean “Elect” and
    “Auditor” see Jason Beduhn’s <hi rend="italic">The
    Manichaean Body</hi>, (The Johns Hopkins University Press,
    2000) especially pp. 27ff. Beduhn cites the Latin <hi rend="italic">Tebessa
    Codex</hi> which expounds upon these categories in Manichaean
    doctrine and states: “These two grades…support
    each other and whoever has abundance of anything shares it with
    the other; the Elect with the Auditors from their heavenly
    store... and the Auditors with the Elect [from their
    terrestrial wealth].” <ref target="#FNRef9">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef10">10</ref> ibid. 110, n 120. <ref target="#FNRef10">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef11">11</ref> ibid. 111, n 129. <ref target="#FNRef11">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef12">12</ref> 8:192, 7-12, cf. John 8:32. <ref target="#FNRef12">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef13">13</ref> Here “these things” refers to
    charitable deeds. <ref target="#FNRef13">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef14">14</ref> 1Cor13:3. <ref target="#FNRef14">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef15">15</ref> Meaning, he gives the words a greater
    meaning. <ref target="#FNRef15">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef16">16</ref> I have inserted this phrase in square
    brackets, as it is my best rendering of the meaning of this
    section where we see a continuation of the theme of differences
    between the Upright and the Perfect. What follows is a long
    list of attributes of the one who possesses “humble
    love”, (the Perfect) which in turn is personified, adding
    a degree of vagueness to the description. <ref target="#FNRef16">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef17">17</ref> Cf. Phil 2:3. In general, this excerpt
    recalls themes in Phil. 2:5-8, where Christ humbled Himself as
    he took on the “form of a servant, and was made in the
    likeness of men.” <ref target="#FNRef17">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef18">18</ref> 8: 192, 15-8:193, 9. <ref target="#FNRef18">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef19">19</ref> 8:196, 1-10. <ref target="#FNRef19">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef20">20</ref> 8:197, 18-8:200, 1. <ref target="#FNRef20">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef21">21</ref> Caner, <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging Monks</hi>,
    111. <ref target="#FNRef21">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef22">22</ref> In this <hi rend="italic">mēmrā</hi> we read
    that the Perfect “reckons sinners greater than he, while
    he is not anxious all day, and does not have a place to prop
    his head on the earth.” See 8: 193, 19-21. <ref target="#FNRef22">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef23">23</ref> For a discussion of the possibility of an
    Upright attaining Perfection with respect to those stations in
    terms of Adam and the Fall, see Aleksander Kowalksi,
    <hi rend="italic">Perfezione e Giustizia di Adamo nel Liber Graduum</hi>
    (Rome: Orientala Chrsitiana Analecta 232, 1989). <ref target="#FNRef23">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef24">24</ref> See Arthur Amiaud. <hi rend="italic">La légende
    syriaque de saint Alexis, l’homme de Dieu</hi>, (Paris:
    Bibliothèque de l'Ecole des hautes etudes, 1889) and
    forthcoming  from Cistercian Publications, a comparison
    of  the Syriac and Greek versions of the story of the Man
    of God in an essay by R. Doran. <ref target="#FNRef24">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef25">25</ref> Dr. Doran has kindly provided me with a
    manuscript of his upcoming publication on the issue of the life
    of The Man of God as a parable, where he explores some of these
    issues in greater detail. <ref target="#FNRef25">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef26">26</ref> In his forthcoming publication, cited above,
    Robert Doran also notes similarities between the <hi rend="italic">Man of
    God</hi> narrative and the life of John Calybite. <ref target="#FNRef26">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef27">27</ref> Amiaud, <hi rend="italic">La légende syriaque</hi>,
    appendix, 9. <ref target="#FNRef27">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef28">28</ref> It is well worth remembering that the
    <hi rend="italic">Life of Alexander Akoimetos</hi> tells us that before he
    was a Bishop, Rabbula gave up all material possessions and
    devoted himself to a life of severe asceticism. See
    Caner’s appendix in <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging Monks,</hi>
    261-263. <ref target="#FNRef28">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef29">29</ref> On the relationship between the Man of God
    legend and the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Rabbula, see Hans Drijvers,
    “The Man of God of Edessa, Bishop Rabbula, and the Urban
    Poor, Church and Society in the Fifth Century,”
    <hi rend="italic">JECS</hi> 4 (1996) 235-248. The argument put forth by
    Drijvers asserts that both texts are propaganda tracts aimed
    against Rabbula’s rival and successor, Hiba. <ref target="#FNRef29">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef30">30</ref> Amiaud, <hi rend="italic">La légende syriaque</hi>,
    appendix, 2. <ref target="#FNRef30">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef31">31</ref> 8: 193, 8-9. <ref target="#FNRef31">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef32">32</ref> Whether this asset is exploited for
    political purposes is another matter, see Drijvers, <hi rend="italic">op.
    cit.</hi> 248. <ref target="#FNRef32">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef33">33</ref> Amiaud, <hi rend="italic">La légende syriaque</hi>,
    appendix, 7. <ref target="#FNRef33">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef34">34</ref> On the figure of Rabbula as a
    “paradigm of action” see Susan A. Harvey,
    “The Holy and the Poor: Models from Early Syriac
    Christianity,” in <hi rend="italic">The Eye of a Needle:
    Judeo-Christian Roots of Social Welfare</hi>, ed. Emily Albu
     Hanawalt and Carter Lindberg (Clarksville: Thomas
    Jefferson University Press, 1994) 43-66. <ref target="#FNRef34">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <p>
            <ref target="#FNRef35">35</ref> The author of the Liber Graduum makes
    another reference to just such a possibility in 25.6, col. 745.
    <ref target="#FNRef35">
               <graphic url="../site/RetArrow.gif" rend="img" mimeType="image/gif"/>
            </ref>
         </p>
         <lb/>
    _______<lb/>
         <head xml:id="HV8N1Khalek7">Bibliography</head>
         <p>Amiaud, A., <hi rend="italic">La légende
    syriaque de saint Alexis, l'homme de Dieu,</hi> (Paris:
    Bibliothèque de l'Ecole des hautes etudes, 1889).</p>
         <p>Beduhn, Jason, <hi rend="italic">The Manichaean
    Body,</hi> (The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2000)</p>
         <p>Becker, Adam, "Anti-Judaism and Care
    for the Poor in Aphrahat's Demonstration 20," <hi rend="italic">Journal of
    Early Christian Studies</hi>, 10 (2002) 305-327.</p>
         <p>Caner, D., <hi rend="italic">Wandering, Begging
    Monks: The Promotion of Monasticism in Late Antiquity,</hi>
    (The Transformation of Classical Heritage 33; Berkeley:
    University of California Press, 2002).</p>
         <p>Drijvers, Hans, "The Man of God of
    Edessa, Bishop Rabbula, and the Urban Poor, Church and Society
    in the Fifth Century," <hi rend="italic">JECS</hi> 4 (1996) 235-248.</p>
         <p>Guillaumont, A., 'Situation et
    signification du « Liber Graduum » dans la
    spiritualité syriaque' (<hi rend="italic">Symposium Syriacum</hi>
    1972) 311-322.</p>
         <p>Harvey, Susan A, "The Holy and the
    Poor: Models from Early Syriac Christianity," in <hi rend="italic">The Eye of
    a Needle: Judeo-Christian Roots of Social Welfare,</hi> ed.
    Emily Albu Hanawalt and Carter Lindberg, (Clarksville: Thomas
    Jefferson University Press, 1994) 43-66.</p>
         <p>Kmosko, M., ed., <hi rend="italic">Liber
    Graduum</hi> (Patrologia Syriaca 3; Paris, 1926).</p>
         <p>Kowalksi, Aleksander, <hi rend="italic">Perfezione
    e Giustizia di Adamo nel Liber Graduum,</hi> (Rome: Orientala
    Chrsitiana Analecta 232, 1989).</p>
         <p>Kitchen, R.A. "Conflict on the
    Stairway to Heaven: The Anonymity of Perfection in the Syriac
    <hi rend="italic">Liber Graduum</hi>," (Symposium Syriacum VII, Uppsala 1996;
    <hi rend="italic">Orientalia Christiana Analecta</hi> 256, (1998)
    211-220.</p>
         <p>Stewart, C.A., <hi rend="italic">Working the Earth
    of the Heart: The Messalian Controversy in History, texts and
    Language to AD 431,</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1991).</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>