<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Helga Anschütz (April 19, 1928 - May 13, 2006)</title>
            <author>
               <name>
                  <forename>Andreas</forename>
                  <surname>Juckel</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>
                  <orgName/>
               </affiliation>
            </author>
            <sponsor>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</sponsor>
            <editor role="general">George A. Kiraz</editor>
            <editor role="associate">James E. Walters</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI XML encoding by </resp>
               <name type="script">html2TEI.xsl</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="0.1"/>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
            <date>2006</date>
            <idno>Vol. 9, No. 2</idno>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication, a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                license has been granted by the author(s), who retain full
                                copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno type="URI">https://hugoye.bethmardutho.org/obituary/hv9n2obanschutz</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <analytic>
                  <author>Andreas Juckel</author>
                  <title level="a">Helga Anschütz (April 19, 1928 - May 13, 2006)</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j">Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Beth Mardutho: The Syriac Institute</publisher>
                     <date/>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="vol" n="9">9</biblScope>
                  <biblScope type="issue" n="2">2</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Hugoye: Journal of Syriac Studies is an electronic journal dedicated to the study
                        of the Syriac tradition, published semi-annually (in January and July) by Beth
                        Mardutho: The Syriac Institute. Published since 1998, Hugoye seeks to offer the
                        best scholarship available in the field of Syriac studies.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>Syriac Studies</term>
               <term>Obituary</term>
               <term>Helga Anschütz</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="uncorrectedTransformation">
         <change when="2018-06-28-04:00">File created by XSLT transformation of original HTML encoded article.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <lb/>
         <lb/>
    
    
    
    
         <!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Content" -->
         <hi style="float:right;margin:5px 0 5px 15px;background-color: #fff;padding:5px;border-top:1px solid #555;border-right:2px solid #999;border-bottom:2px solid #999;border-left:1px solid #555;">
            <graphic url="HV9N2OBAnschutz_Img01.jpg" rend="img" mimeType="image/jpeg" width="122px" height="150px"/>
         </hi>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P1"/>[1] The
    renowned German scholar and esteemed friend of the Syriac
    Churches Dr. Helga Anschütz died on the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of
    May at the age of 78, and was buried among the Suryoye in the
    cemetery of the Mor Ephrem Monastery in Glane/NL. Although her
    health suffered several setbacks during the last few years, her
    death was unexpected and met with deep mourning. By her
    scholarship and personal acquaintance with the oriental
    Christians and their homelands, she was an indefatigable
    advocate of the Suryoyo cause in their German (and European)
    exile. She served the Suryoye to preserve their identity; at
    the same time she promoted their integration by numerous
    activities of the two associations she founded. Her knowledge
    of the Tur Abdin, its history and its people was unique. She
    met the Metropolitan Philoxenus Dolabani of Mardin and Bishop
    Afrem Bilgic of Tur ‘Abdin.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P2"/>[2] Dr.
    Anschütz was born in Hamburg in 1928. Between 1948 and
    1956, she studied history, philosophy, pedagogy, and journalism
    at the University of Hamburg. In 1956 she received her Ph.D. in
    (early) history and economic geography, then taught German
    language at the Goethe-Institutes in Teheran (Iran) and Rabat
    (Morocco) as well as in several institutions in Germany
    between  1960 and 1989. Since 1965, she travelled
    regularly in the Middle East and the Maghreb, and centred her
    research on the present-day life of Oriental Christians. In
    1968, she received a special grant for research in the Tur
    ‘Abdin which resulted in her famous book <hi rend="italic">Die Syrischen
    Christen vom Tur ‘Abdin</hi> (1985). In 1990,
    Anschütz founded (together with her husband Dr. Boulos
    Harb) the German-Lebanese Association, and in 1992 the Mar
    Gabriel Association to support the Syrian Christians.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P3"/>[3] Scholars
    <hi rend="italic">and</hi> Suryoye will miss her.</p>
         <p>
            <anchor corresp="P4"/>[4] [The
    information is based on an obituary published by the Mar
    Gabriel Association in Germany (<ref target="http://www.margabrielverein.de">www.margabrielverein.de</ref>.)]</p>
         <!-- InstanceEndEditable -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>